Can you hear me? Can you hear me? Okay. The last session of today is on identity. And
the participants for that are counterclockwise. No, clockwise. Clockwise, Charles Melman.
It's your Whitbrook. I'm sorry, White Book. Then it is Anvido. Then...
I will... I will... You are not on the list. And then it is Jean-Michel Gabbat, and then
Marie Lyasens. Charles Melman is cheering the group, so he will be going.
Putting on a metal room. It's how it moves. It's all the pain. It's so much weight.
This is everything.dden up space. Or 16,000 meters, all the way around.
I think I would rather speak in English.
So, when I started to tackle the question of identity, of course identity is very linked
to the question of education, because to be educated and to get a training in any sense
to be trained, to be educated means that you need to have your own identity.
But if not, then you are not educated, you become a clone.
So how to tackle the question of identity, I chose three points, mainly subjectivity,
secondly, what is the ability to say no, the ability to rebel and the ability to think.
And the title of my paper is the very well-known sentence by Descartes, the past anniversary,
I think that's identity.
We were speaking of the terrorist attacks.
When I started to think about this paper, what came to my mind was a book by a friend
journalist whose name is Jean-Apsfeld.
The book is translated in English and it's called A Season of Machate.
And the book relates Jean-Apsfeld was very moved by the massacre of the two Tsis in Rwanda.
So he wrote a first book and his second book, A Season of Machate.
His book where he went for nearly six months and interviewed the killers.
He interviewed those people who were good people, they were peasants, they had absolutely no
hostility.
But one day they were given orders that they had to kill their neighbors and friends from
the morning, half past nine to four o'clock they had to take Machate and to kill.
Fifty thousand Tsis were killed like that out of a population of 60,000, which is quite
amazing, that took place in five weeks.
So Jean-Apsfeld went to interview those killers and he is not a psycho analyst, he's a very
good journalist.
And he was struck himself by the fact that the discourse was absolutely concrete.
There were no emotions, no affects.
And he said a language without images, which for a analyst is very interesting because
it's what we would call a language which is no more rooted in the drives and there's
no formal regression possible, no images.
No representations.
And about from this book I went to, what came to my mind are two other books.
One is Anna Arent, the banality of the evil, where she relates the trial of Aitman in Jerusalem.
And he's also, it's not an emotive discourse.
If you see the minutes of the trial, it's quite amazing.
He relates and he said that he never imagined and he simply, he didn't seem guilty because
he didn't want the shore to take place but he was just obeying orders.
From that point, one can think what is exactly, there are people who don't want to think.
So in the previous panel, somebody was, we were speaking of the love or the obedience
to the leader, which is for me, it's not really love.
It is, I love him, yes, but I stopped to think because he thinks for me and not thinking
can be comfortable.
Sometimes thinking is painful and not to have to think can be felt as comfortable.
And that was one very crucial question when we think of terrorism, of attacks, of any
kind, of those terrible social problems.
The third thing is you all know, I imagine, the book of Stanley Milgram.
Stanley Milgram is this professor of psychology who did this experiment.
Maybe, if you don't know it, I can stop, I think everybody knows the experiment of
Milgram.
So I won't go.
Just made a movie.
Yes, yes, yes.
So this shows that it's absolutely incredible how people who are intelligent, who are good
people, who even can be smart, facing authority and even a totally vague authority can obey,
that means stop thinking by your absence.
They act, they simply act.
So that put me to the conclusion and I will stop at that point that identity is based
on the capacity of continue to think and to want to think, and specially, that means
also the capacity to say no.
Because if you think at one point you cannot always obey authority.
So I think that Freud has two main papers on that question.
One is the negation, of course.
And the other one is the splitting of the ego in the defense process, where he shows very
well that there are some, I forget the word, secretrés, scarves, there are some scars in
the ego which will never, never heal.
And this scarves in the ego is the part of the unconscious ego which will always be open
at this scarves which will never heal.
And that means that only working through constantly and trying to keep our thinking process alive
is the only way to continue and not to be blind to what we are doing or not to do things
that we wouldn't like to do but that we have the tendency.
Because as it was said, evil is not outside, evil is in all of us and sadism is in all
of us and we could all become killers.
Thank you, thank you, Marina.
Thanks a lot.
Good evening.
we afternoon
The
second morning I
Read
Is
No
It's
Not
commodity, sequ
and support we set substitution.
I am a philosopher who is a philosopher who is a remarkable.
I am a former dezer of the law, a former dezer.
I am a former dezer of the law, a former dezer of the law,
a former dezer of the law, a former dezer of the law.
Thank you very much for entering Dune.
Let me say, in interaction, that it will trademarks his law as
a progress IN this story,
so that we don't even feel aiy
exist, and flee from GET DOZ
It is a very difficult proposition.
It is a very crucial proposition.
It can seem surprising that identity is regularly linked to a presentification sign of virility,
whether it is manifested or it is the scar of this sacrifice.
On the earlier day, the presence of virility,
whether we are human, is calling out your spreads?
One
This is the
1000 Mines
for people in Ghana
Congratulations on a Little Mac
Islamic
ARD
Our teachings
The text is sacred.
It's not a secret.
It's a secret.
The man who is here.
The people who are here,
the people who are here,
the people who are here.
It's a completely different.
They refer to the purpose to peaceful collaboration,
and as planet,
after a few months of
AP sandal Javelina de la
enisher daseter,
de BLINale de'
vivIP
That's how she believed the person,
who was the Bible,
who said,
a realistic road movie.
A road movie.
Road movie, road movie.
Huh? Road movie, road movie.
Road movie.
A realistic road movie.
She said,
she said,
for me now.
Hmm?
Lise von Rheelen.
He said,
two total shows.
the lesson,
to the one who's
a true
and
a message of energy.
He said,
the compliment of the film,
he said,
for the man,
who knows the religion.
Me okeun,
the religion only brought
in a catholic.
And the pretense of text
is the reference.
I think it's a big thing,
but it's a real thing.
He said,
the question is,
how do you think
of the consequences?
Could some resale resort or
to suburbia?
Shall we try to translate?
I didn't expect to translate.
That would be difficult.
Look,
I will sum up because
Schalman mostly a lot of very
interesting things.
Well, he started saying that
we are all driven by an object,
the object of our
unconscious fantasy.
And that, of course,
that is unconscious
and we are full of it without
even knowing exactly where we
are going and what we are
thinking.
I think this is very important.
Now, he raises the question,
when does that start?
When do we start, finally,
to really construct an identity,
even if a huge part of our
identity will always remain
driven by something that we don't
know?
I couldn't answer to this question.
I would rather say that I would
put it around the adiabus complex
or between three and four.
I mean, around the construction
of the superego.
And a superego, which, of course,
is rooted deeply into the
id.
I would put it like that.
And finally,
Schal, talk about the
three monotheistic religions
saying that what is very different
is that choral is considered to be
directly written or dictated by God.
And what I understand is the
difference because if it's dictated
by God, it has not to be
interpreted.
And the two others monotheistic
are interpretations and lead to
more and more and more
interpretations.
Yes?
You agree with that?
Sure.
Thank you.
Merci beaucoup sommes.
Meruis.
Les l'édour les jons.
A precedent.
Nous s'spadeurs.
L'iréin a travais de exegez.
Eres sur desinés and gémété
amine.
Yes, interpretation, which will
never end.
Because one interpretation
leads to another, one and so on
and so on.
So it's an ongoing work.
I would suggest that we should
make a distinction between
interpretation and critique.
And what I'm going to say,
before I have to preface what I'm
going to say with a statement.
I in no way want to endorse the
whole idea about class of
civilizations or celebrate the
west or deny the history of
western imperialism and colonialism.
Nevertheless, and I will probably
be accused of Islamophobia and
Eurocentrism, but nevertheless
what I want to say is this.
Well, I don't know what it's like
in France at this point.
But here, especially Columbia
where I teach, thinkers who have
been influenced by deconstruction
and post-colonial theorists are
constantly making the point that
identity isn't unitary.
Identity is always heterogeneous,
not unified, not solidified,
not final.
But they fail to apply their
point to the west.
The identity of the west isn't
unified either.
And as Kesteriadis argued, the
social formation of the west is
made up by two competing projects.
What he called the project of
autonomy and the project of
domination.
The latter is the history of
imperialism, colonialism,
domination of the globe,
domination of the nation, and so
on and so forth.
But there is something else that
happened in the west which makes
critique possible in a way that
it isn't another culture.
I mean, if you look to the
Greeks, for example, and I don't
think that's a way to celebrate
the Greek miracle.
But the unoxford classicist and
philosopher, Loy, G.E.R. and Loy,
has done extensive research,
comparative research between
Greek science, Chinese science,
and Indian science.
And he is intimately familiar with
all the text and sometimes it
makes it impossible to read.
But I mean, he's no
one, that's what I'm trying to say.
And his question is, why did
inquiry go further in Greece than
it did in either of these other
places?
And his answer is that the
structure, there was a certain
anti-authoritarianism in Greece.
As opposed to certain
structures of authority in China
and India which allowed inquiry
to go beyond a certain point in
Greece, whereas the
authoritarianism, the
perseverance of inquiry to power
prevented it from going that far
in China and India.
And then, I mean, I'll probably
be accused of being a
defender of the Enlightenment.
And I don't want to defend it in
its 18th century mode, but I do
want to defend it.
But then, contact,
they're all, so ours is the age
of critique.
And he enunciated the principle
that we shouldn't accept any
idea, any norm, any value, in the
name of traditional authority.
Simply because it's been passed
on and simply because the
authorities say it so.
And that, in principle, I mean,
it doesn't happen, it's violated
all the time, but in principle,
every important idea has to
stand before the test of
critical reason.
And I think these two
sediment and historical
experiences mean that they're
something sedimented in our
history, which needs to be
defended and needs to be
asserted against the other
strand of our history, which is
the project of domination.
Would you agree that that's
very near what you said is
quite near?
When I say the capacity to say
no, it's very important.
To say no to the idols of the
tribe.
Exactly.
And to acknowledge, no, this
is not mine.
I don't feel this and I don't
want to feel it.
Lloyd even makes the point in the
ilea that the other soldiers
stand up and say no to a
minna, which is almost unheard of.
They had the right to speak up
and to challenge their king
general in a way that was
uncharacteristic.
Also, something you said, one of
your earlier panels, that we see
the death drive in thinking
because the capacity to say no
and separate is the same.
That's true.
But at the same time thinking
goes against the death drive
because insofar as the death
drive wants to seek the
release attention, this version
of tension, thinking requires
the increase in tension, the
buildup in tension.
That's true.
Both are true.
Both are totally true and that's
why what is destructive.
It's not the death drive only
because it's the individual.
It's the unabiding.
I might slightly disagree in
terms of what has already been
discussed earlier today.
The question of the death drive
and teaching and identification
and the recent problems and
attacks in California and
connected and I think what we see
here is that education and
identity or identification are
somehow linked.
I would just begin by going back
to the sentence that has often
been quoted today.
Freud said that education is
impossible.
Educate, govern, psychoanalyze,
impossible professions.
Just to say that this is where
we are now, but precisely I think
our discussion is impossible.
This evening.
Nobody will come out of here with
a good sense of what we're doing
or saying to languages.
We won't understand each other.
That is clear.
Yet this impossible is what can
be used and I think we need to
think through the impossible.
And I think this is where La
Conne or De Rida or Bataille can
help us.
Why?
Because precisely the impossible
is a certain paradoxical mode
of thinking and you know like
what De Rida often does in his
text to bring us to an aporia.
We don't know.
We are stuck and so on.
Which in a way interrupts a
certain common discourse and I
think we should go back to Freud's
idea of what is this
impossibility here.
How is it connected with the
task of educating?
Is it possible to educate while
it is impossible to do so
normally?
On the other hand we have the
question and you started by
quoting the card.
I think therefore I am.
La Conne as we know
refrised it as I think Colin
quote therefore I am.
We can think it like I think
it's a good question.
Therefore I am.
I think therefore I am like a
whole phrase.
What I mean is that in terms of
the institutions that have to do
with identification or
education we can think of the
two parallel institutions that
have been so cooperative in
France recently.
On the one hand it's a high
schools, universities and elite
institutions and on the other
hand the jails where most of the
radical militants have learned
to identify with an ideal.
Which I think is also why we
had that question earlier.
Why are we maybe more moved by
the Uldurahoke and Betacron attacks
in Paris and they are playing
in Beirut and so on.
Why is it because it's just
normal kids having fun.
Any sense what we always aspire
to that our children can go out
on a cafe at night and enjoy
life.
And so that looks like very
different from with the
Ozzier 20 years ago when the
Goldenberg was attacked.
Okay, use religion as the city
and so on.
Today is just sort of everyday
style of life with which everybody
here in this room can identify
as something we think is good.
It may not be that good.
But if we think of the
rapidity of the identification we
have all those accounts of
marginalized disenfranchised
kids from the suburbs of
Paris who go to jail because
they first drug, they do deep
drugs, they are dealing, they
get called by the police, they
go to jail and then they
identify with an absolute faith.
And so this is the function of
identification.
Against this a certain
impossibility of the institution
of learning and teaching is a
good counter poison, I would
say.
I would put it as a particular
position I'd say in the
race, that only
make sense, not just upper
offensive
perspective but rooted in
important actions,
as people who make restrictions
foraina's
and other SI,
colleague Paul
And I think that the
discussion is very important,
and I think that the
discussion is very important.
And is wondering if the humanities
can address the question of identity
and the civilization and its
discontent.
The question of the
discussion is
that the
very important.
And when you are looking at
the question of the
discussion, the question of
the discussion is
very important.
And I think that the
discussion is very important,
and if the question is
very important,
is very important.
After Freud and Lacon,
which was in her text,
she's wondering if
we can understand
that the
discussion is very important.
So the question is
why is the question
very important.
The question of the
contemporary subject.
I think that the
discussion is
very important.
The question is
how do you
look at the
discussion of the
discussion and
all of its
things and
those who Jamie
nodding and
thinking that
be Veilow
The
How they do the
introduce
teachers and students.
And also, you, as an example, a particular character,
a philosopher, a philosopher,
and a philosopher, a person,
a person who has a mission to make a difference.
And the actuality.
On a second term,
she will interrogate the humanistic study,
which are philology, rhetoric, interpretation,
which open to the plurality of the unconscious meaning.
And then the whole characters who take the
the
dimensions women,
they take values that often
be
an
guides
...and then we got to the very beginning of the French.
This is another question by Jan beauty teacher
that we have found in the l
tv political
level as much as other people should
in case the
cast
Something like that
we are recording
...
nice
Ko
to protect the people of the country,
and to defend the people of the country.
And to protect the people of the country.
She will use the writings of a French rapper
to illustrate the system of reading
that she wants to expose.
Her name is Milani Diyana.
Milani spew his memory from the end of March
in 2004 Align gn skies
activity calculated like unfinished
forms of the
definition and implement it carefully.
Our
court
gh
oration
know
And I want to thank you for your time.
I want to thank you for your time.
Thank you for your time.
The signifier discontent runs in the contemporary zeitgeist.
And what interests her is to the fact that she calls herself
a suburbanite.
I want to thank you for your time.
In French, a happy with two Rs means to be abrasive.
If you take the role of
medical people back in depressing
then he always cares on the poor and wont do anything because his blaster was with a
dirty relic.
A Frenchragpe also means fear.
She wants to insist on her stage name, which is written
in the AIM apostrophe S.
The AIM is the abbreviation of diamond, which is from the Greek.
The AIM is the name of the Greek.
The Greek language is the name of the Greek.
It's the name of the Greek language.
The AIM is the name of the Greek language, and the name of the Greek language is the name of the Greek.
The AIM is the name of the Greek.
The AIM is the name of the Greek language.
She uses an anagramatic strategy coupled with a substantial and substitution to change her patronime by translating into Greek, which is...
The AIM is the name of the Greek.
This prefigurates the cleavage between D and AIM.
The AIM is the name of the Greek language, which is the name of the Greek.
The AIM is the name of the Greek language, which is the name of the Greek language.
The AIM is the name of the Greek language.
The AIM has a name of the Greek language, which is the name of the Greek language.
In her analysis, the two signifiers black and white appear by analyzing the world lucosia,
which is lab launch, and melancholia, which is lab noir.
She also says,boy, let's follow Z
and I'm happy to talk to you later.
I'm going to go to the room.
At this time, she announced a very naively done identification
to women, to her mother and to her friends.
At this time, she announced a very good identification
to her mother, to her mother.
to her mother, to her mother, to her family,
to her mother, to her mother, to her mother.
Through the failure of the identical operation,
she chose to conform to the right, the ritual.
She's great, yes.
In the summer, the men were not able to deliver
to the women of the exterior.
The men of the apartment were not able to do it.
They were not able to do it.
Her father, which she describes as a convinced atheist.
She was a very good atheist.
Her daughter, the Orthodox, Christian Orthodox,
were long veils in churches.
She was a very good atheist.
She was a very good musician.
What comes to mind is that Nicosy, the Capriella Cyprus,
is cut into Greek versus Turkish.
The duality has its origin in her father's origin,
which are never mentioned in her book.
It's about my family drinking"?
After years since the fortteals were dated,
our pianist was gathered in Europe des
The second identification is made through the veil that she adopts from the Greek tradition.
I think it is an corresponds to the
international version of co- vascular manufacturing in the world at length five days when the
legeating
You have to clear up.
In several independent differentoes
we can translate to whether
or not to play with any element
that you might like it in your future.
Sometimes Roberg
The
autobiography is emblematic of the history of a manic depressive woman which is out of
bounds without limit. The trajectory of the group is reversed to
virilization that she describes by saying that when she was younger she was
masculine and very hard with herself and others.
Thank you.
which did shake loss in black.
I am here
in libraries
of 6x5x Barnum
to require a pressures between Nietzsche
and in visa
left by
There are some necessary blinded sculptures,
from lamp greage.
Currently, all are
Room
because, as we urge people to have a committed campaign
around Speciallovors,
they don't have any
support,
to radically
reproductive hurts.
I would like to vote for the
Mortales Solo
Institute of Vikings
&GE
shoot
tattoo
constants
CLINIC
They can do
multiple
people
in lasts the year…"
elo
SE spun
my
complexity is pattern and limitations,
perhaps I saw this one last year
I'll give you aiding
not showing that specific
or non- degre Lepreye
the w
arma.
A
I am not a person who has been a reason to be a
and to be a
And to be a
My dear first good dearcap
I wantarest first
I want to physicist
decide sometimes are spent in Europe long-termm
and
from
first and foremost moment
Fiscal
to suspend
C brace
ik
...
motherboard
dis HQ Karen Stone dessert
her
strut
you know
and
you you you
you
What do you think?
Yes.
That's what born me.
That was for me.
Socka.
Socka too.
Okay.
Right.
American.
Baseball.
Sitoff in a man.
Trezet Hos.
Porque.
Pascuse us on the board.
De giène.
Contulation.
And he's so organized.
De façon purmo artificile.
La idantite.
Paro elixion.
De clabe.
E pas de l'aut.
Eis se suporte.
Sont capab de fere agai.
O suporte de l'autre clabe.
E en francilia u de mo.
De con t'ilia de rancón.
De football.
Pascuse.
Eis d'uéabour bocoure police.
E en ou ace perre.
Eis suporte are agai.
De l'autre cote d'ustard.
Eis a la sorti ou seek.
Eis paupercizament de butei.
De zam de m'esture.
Paupercizur.
C'est fen.
Eis que le sefina men.
Piscunu paron de identification.
C'est fen.
Eis fen.
Eis féc du gién.
Un vadir normo.
Eis un normo.
Como se fétil que segén.
Pisc.
Eis.
Sont gage nous un ino tificacien trefort.
Pisculabouti en sont patriartis.
Eis l'autre vous.
Eis nous el medallétrange.
Amon amon amon sonts.
C'est la ne pous siebe.
Que?
Piscul?
Froy?
Et inure parlaculte.
C'est vu d'irque.
C'est la meus yurunato que l'autre quilti.
O'ofoul.
C'est que féd aaportes vous le problem de nautificacien.
Eis l'inorma aque un zien segén.
C'est la ne félame.
Eis l'autre que nous evocón.
Faucément.
L'e mertre de paris.
Udu sain Bernadino.
Bernadino.
C'est la ne féd direct amon sonts.
D'efec la quilti.
N'appas aat agris que froy?
Aaportes yurcéchestion.
L'autre de ursicien.
C'est la neux t'aller.
Nous aaplic a froy de t'aller nous de cabine.
Eis trabagé avec se pascien.
Eis crèses aurcum.
C'ecolos aicolecate.
Y'an a l'istum wa ula vinier d'unrojigion.
Uto t'emetabou.
Umoiz el monotereiz.
C'est aet des excursions.
De vuéars aiè.
Eis crèèèè.
N'allotreiz ai.
A férse vuéars ais excursions.
Eis crèèèèè.
Ais crèèèèè.
Eis annaliz d'unroj.
Aumíne d'unrojigion.
C'est aiè.
Rommemau.
Un ail mai.
Aaparas aiè.
Promis sien.
Un ais.
Eis crèèèè.
Eis que t'aller nous vars.
F'omidar.
Promis sien.
Ais d'unmoiz trèc.
Le l'ir de l'un cominote.
Ais que pétougeau la posissions.
Ais crèèèè.
C'est aiè.
R'féron t'red d'un le m'amour sambre.
Ais crèèèèè.
Ais crèèèè.
Ais crèèèè, ais crèèèè.
Ais crèèèèè.
Ais crèèèèèèè.
Ais struggling.
from the Cantor groups
we received
rose lessons
there are no
radical
praising
they are
at our
times
covid
?!"
aded
An
egg
Freud
Bible
mad
Are you looking at this?
I really love this brand.
It's like my mom and girl.
At other places in the market without the same range,
they have both been possible and such.
So this couples anDirou litreing
Thisack, we would like to thank you to the director of resistance
on the
We can trace in our work whom many people,
there are Agricultural
In the interview, I just prefer to call myself a Jew.
It's a very good thing.
I'm a Jew.
Maybe I should say this in English.
That Freud was interviewed by this protonatsy writer, very famous man, who had been born in Germany, wrote in English, Yarek.
Interviewed everybody at that time.
And he went, Freud said, look, I want to call myself a Jew, not a German.
Yarek, oh, I was hoping, here I said, that you were more a universalist.
But I can understand the anger of Freud indeed, certain things happen and so on.
But in that debate, what interested me in, so it's a debate that was published in a collection, very interesting, in 1957, on the future of psychoanalysis.
It makes you want to laugh or to cry, I don't know exactly which, when you see what the imagined psychoanalysis would be like in, let's say, half a century earlier.
But there are many, many issues about education, identification, science and so on.
But fundamentally, what you can see is that Freud, first, we talked about the critique of American ideas and denounces,
as he always does, the superficiality of American cultural life and the medicalization of psychoanalysis.
But then he says, you don't know your own classics, he says to an Whitman, because Whitman, if sex were lacking or were lacking.
So Freud still believes that what is shocking in, let's say, American ideology of the common man is the sexual idea.
What he then discovers talking with Virac is that the most shocking thing is the death drive, to return to what we were saying earlier.
And he really goes on on on about the death drive, because Virac is ready to accept the idea, I think you were saying this, this morning very well.
But, and I think Freud's anti-CP may have anticipated, you know, the culture of Hollywood and the certain soft form, diffuse eroticism and publicity,
and everywhere today on any screen we can open and so on. That has been completely absorbed by mainstream American culture and Western culture,
whereas the idea of the death drive, that is still something that, surprisingly, somebody like Virac who loved the Nazis couldn't take.
But you know, the story is even more complicated, because everything most of us find obnoxious about American culture and consumerism and how I would,
was introduced by Freud's nephew, Bernays, I don't remember. And he took his uncles ideas and invented what they call it.
And he was hired by the big corporation, blah, blah, blah, and he was the agent of all of this.
But I think it took to conclude maybe on this and something that I owe to Charles Merman, because I can say that I started learning about LACON in a seminar you taught in Paris in 1969,
so that's a long time ago at the economic superior. In LACON you have this awareness that in the text I quote, there is a pedagogy of the death drive,
which is a little paradoxical to think today, because you were suggesting that what can we learn from the death drive, basically to avoid it, no. To understand what it means.
And so for LACON it has to do with language and perhaps with literature. This is I think why when we teach literature we also have to work with the death drive, which is I think more difficult than to work with the fact that students may fall in love with us and so on.
We know how to deal with that, but we don't know how to deal with their death drive.
You've been part of their transverse is also the negative transverse of the death drive.
The transverse isn't just euros.
Can you go to the microphone please?
You did.
Well, you also saw that it might be a cool thing, but some things are just barely as good as much, but obviously the better.
When people experience, those are great
and midsettle, people have come
and LOT of music and then they himself
have posterity.
Nah fullfloor is being used
Basically, she does the fifth
Oh 3-4
At first she history support
belly meditation
if al
free
Nah hezac
piring
aggravating
enthal
Yeah
Hehe
She converses
He comes to me
This is to Maria.
The identity is based on the capacity to say no.
Philosophically, I do agree with you.
But from a psychoanalytical point of view, I'm not sure that identity exists as such.
It's like the baby for Winnicott.
You see, it does not exist as such.
Freud's thought of identity as a social relationship.
Identity was social.
And you refer to the London genocide.
There is another book which I recommend, Scott Strauss, who analyzed different villages, different regions.
And I remember the conclusion that the same type of people sometimes did resist other participating in the killing.
In other words, the environment and the political environment was this system in the commitment of the crimes.
So the question is, what does it mean, identity as such?
I agree, thank you.
I don't think identity is one entity.
Identity is a long and fluctuating process, which has to do with recognition by the other two.
You have your identity, but you are also identified by the look of the other.
Perhaps if I can add something to your remark.
What Charles Melman was discussing with the example of the supporters is a little more than identity.
It's this mixture of results and identity that Clampera, for instance, analyzed very well in the language of the Third Reich.
And I know that book showed exactly what Mussolini did in Italy.
Not just an identity to being Italian or Nazi or German or Aryan as non-drew, but the resource that was allowed to happen.
And I think this is what a good club and my city of Philadelphia is very known for having really very rowdy supporters of the Phillies and so on.
You know, if you join that you will be able to kick out people's heads and bash them and so on.
That will be part of the little premium.
And so this is the kind of excessive enjoyment I think, in Italy as kinetic.
Try to describe this very well in what has been translated in English as my crowds and massed in German.
It really about the unleashing of enjoyment in a crowd, in massed.
It's I think different from just identity, we all need a certain identity, but that's special kind of identity.
A one line from Avid, I think that fits especially this country very well in our discussion is,
if you are afraid to fall in love, go into business.
BlackSupp IntrInformation has had a powerful issue that StarCraft had since.
It feels Exhibitionist type Curij, exposition, humour, propaganda, incarceration,
but it doesn't ever actually go in
to a Reich with men in saber
There were a lot of struggle foraged money.
Maybe I'm perfect and the question
And, like right now, it wants to be context
It's a very well addressed
But the money's going a bituxed
If this funeral doesn't hold
And it'll be favorable for' Westminster
So we start
in this nature the RanchWerect of some information.
Here are the text for native
which Garcia andcontrol still ask his authors
The
closest to grow, it's a Tessette
David
a lot of people who actually likes to do some
And if it will equal those Catherine'sbc
in 2019?
of translation as a deal against
Rashidq in summary
SES
ipping
as a change
Al
mini
context
oligarchy.
Goes in with hurts
may suffer so
William
I am very grateful to you for your
dedication.
I am very grateful to you.
I am very grateful to you for your
commitment.
No, just to conclude, just something which is
quite rather an anecdote, but came to my mind,
I don't know if you all know that the one who
always fight against the idea of nationalism was
Sasha Mazor.
And in the same time, he was also the one who
fight to have the first ladies admitted in
university, which is quite interesting because we
evoked the problem of the women identification, women
representing the otherness, and of course, the danger of
nationalism and unique identity when identity becomes
something totally restrictive and not an ongoing process.
Thank you all for coming tomorrow morning.
The meeting will start at 10 o'clock.
At 10.
Messier, Vichy, Vittian, Tu.
Messi Allen to
Excuse me for not being in the sun, but you the right way to show it.