I'm Ed Nurse-Assyan, Director of the Helix Center.
Welcome to the program of this afternoon on biology of the mind.
Just two announcements.
Next week, the roundtable is on Nationalism, Phonaticism, and Identity.
And on April 12th, we can get this up.
And on April 12th, we have a roundtable on synchronicity.
Today's roundtable is Biology of the Mind, and I will briefly present you the participants.
I won't read everything that is on this paper, which I think some of you have, just the highlights.
When I read your name, if you raise your hands, that would be helpful.
So John Kraakauer is Professor of Neurology and Neuroscience at Johns Hopkins University
of School of Medicine, Director of the BLAM Lab and Co-Founder of the KATA project.
Gary Marcus is Director of the NYU Center for Language and Music and Professor of Psychology
at New York University.
Ken Miller, who has been here before, is Professor Department of Neuroscience, Department of Neuroscience,
Department of Physiology, and Director Center for Theoretical Neurobiology, Columbia University.
David Rosenthal is Professor of Philosophy and Coordinator of the Interdisciplinary Concentration
in Cognitive Science at the Graduate Center of the University of New York.
So Matthew, you want to...
Associate Professor of Computer Science and a member of the Center for Cognitive Science
at Rutgers in New Brunswick, New Jersey.
Thank you.
Okay, well, my main work used to be on the mind-body problem.
Now I mainly work on consciousness.
When I worked on the mind-body problem, it seemed to me very clear that all mental gongs
on are simply physical gongs on in the brain.
And maybe I won't say very much more about that right now, waiting to see what other people
say about that.
That seems to me unproblematic.
One of the things that was listed that we might talk about is how far down mental functioning
goes in the phylogenetic scale.
And I assume it goes pretty far down.
I don't know.
I don't know very much about fish.
I'm pretty sure...
Way lower than that.
Well I'm just saying I don't know very much about fish.
So you can...
I'm suspicious.
You're suspicious that fish have mental functioning?
I don't know very much about fish.
Fish may have mental functioning.
Fish certainly have complicated biological functioning.
But it seems to me...
Well they certainly make choices about what they should do in a given context.
So what behavioral evidence I'm not a fish expert, but they make decisions about mates.
They battle over mates.
They decide about obstacles and whether to go this way or that way.
To me that certainly counts as mental functioning.
You could...
I suppose have a definition of mental functioning that would have a higher bar.
You could say well you only have mental functioning if you can reflect on yourself.
But I would call that...
Oh no.
It's not mental functioning.
No, I don't...
They share lots of neurotransmitters and brain organization with us.
You can use the same kinds of instruments and even better instruments to look at their
neural processes.
To me it doesn't seem controversial to say that a fish has mental functioning.
It's just a question of deciding what is the mental function.
Or a fly or a spider.
I mean if you're an animal with a nervous system you have mental functioning at some
level or so.
I go down to jellyfish and maybe even take the argument to bacteria.
I don't think that you need to set the bar anywhere near consciousness in the sense of
self-awareness or self-reflection.
It seems to me some plants do various things that are beneficial to the plants.
And it doesn't seem to me we want to say that's mental functioning.
So if a fish does something that's beneficial to the fish like choose a nice mate or get
some food or go away from an environment that isn't conducive, that doesn't seem automatically
to be mental functioning.
It seems to me there must be some difference between biological functioning and mental
functioning.
Well what's this?
Now we get to what we really need to respond to.
Well I don't...
One of you would define what you mean by mental functioning.
Well it's his term and I want to define it but the last point that he said is even more
provocative I suppose, which is I take it and I thought you did that all mental functioning
is biological functioning.
Oh I take it.
And the functioning is a subset of biological functioning.
Absolutely but it's a subset.
I just agree with that.
You want to disagree with that part?
Well certainly it would be non-biological mental functioning.
Oh I agree with that.
I don't let's hear that argument.
In principle if you think that when you take a functional approach to the mind and you
want to describe either making decisions, pursuing goals, acting in ways that seem intelligent
in the context, that functional behavior as best we can tell is something that we can
understand at the level of what we usually call information processing in the sense that
there is represented information about the world in some physical form that's then controlling
the behavior of the system.
And we know that one way that that can happen is in neurons but as best we can tell that
can happen in silicon or really any other physical system.
That's a different kind of distinction.
I'm willing to, here I'll give you a revised version if we're opening the window to silicon
which would be that when biological creatures have mental functions they do it using biology.
For them it's a subset of biology but you could use silicon and then we don't really
apply the word biology to silicon.
There'd probably be mergers in the next 20 or 30 years we could talk about where it would
be more complicated to draw those dividing lines.
But if the argument you want to make is it's possible to have mental functioning and some
other kind of substrate say silicon I think that's a reasonable argument but I wouldn't
want to make the argument that there's any mental functioning that we humans do for example
that doesn't have a biological basis.
We can't ultimately trace down to these things like actions of neurons and so forth.
I don't know if anybody wants to challenge that view.
So I'm agreed with all of that.
I guess I would challenge another tiny aspect of what you said.
You said and I agree that mental functioning is a subset of biological functioning.
Which subset?
Well, I mean I think there are many things that go into that subset.
I think we can start exclusionarily maybe and we can say although it gets problematic quickly
so we can say we're mostly not talking about things like metabolism but the truth is that
they do matter.
So a lot of the machinery that goes into the biology of thought goes into the biology in
general.
So if you take away the Krebs cycle that gives us metabolism in individual cells you take
away thought you take a lot of other things away too.
But the way that evolution works is it builds new things on top of old things and mental
life is built on biological life so neurons are specialized cells.
A lot of the machinery we expect in a cell in general we find tweaked in some particular
way in a neuron.
So I understand all of that but I would have thought that the distinction between the mental
as a smaller subset of the biological was going to be in some way or another functional.
That is to say we would say well there's all this biological stuff going on and some
of it some of the biology serves mental functioning.
So liver is absorbing or dealing with toxins for example.
It's probably biological but it's not mental function.
I don't know what we're talking about.
I have to say the same thing.
I don't quite know.
Everyone must be completely bewildered.
I mean what are we arguing about?
In other words how do you know when you want to describe something?
I think it's you know it comes from philosophy and David there's our representative philosopher.
You want to be able to say what counts as mental what counts as physical and what is
the relation between the two.
If we don't give the audience an answer to this question that's been bandied about for
twenty five hundred years then they're right to ask for their money back.
So we should try to answer this question about what is the relation between them.
But there's I mean you're starting with the dualism which you know I think most of us
at bottom maybe all of us reject.
But I think we have a.
I think we have a.
But the question is what is the revised view?
How do you articulate the revised view?
I think there are no dualists I think.
But these are the tests you finish your song.
Thank you.
You know what we think of as mental functioning I think is where you sense what's going on
in the world and you decide how to behave toward the world based on that sensing.
And I guess and I would talk about I mean so some of that could be metabolic you sense
that there's some glucose in the environment or something.
So okay I'll grant it needs a little bit more distinction but in essence but maybe not maybe
that's even the beginning of mental functioning but it's basically what animals have to do
that plants don't have to do which is they've got to get their food by going after it and
they in order to do that and they've got to find their mates by going after them.
You know just to spur your seeds to the wind and all the apparatus that let's just do that
and let's just see you know sense what's going on out in the world and then develop a behavior
to deal with the world based on that that allows us to reproduce that's mental functioning
as far as I understand.
Well don't plants up the roots go after water or light or light.
It's a I mean I think this is the wrong level I mean I think what everyone I mean my guess
is that what people are intrigued by as you go up to a phylogenetic scale and I'm allowed
to say that people in evolutionary biology hate that value judgement about going up or
down is I'll give an example maybe this will help you know the lobster has its claws and
it's at the bottom of the ocean and its own tail gets into its line of sight and it suddenly
lunges for its tail is that because it doesn't realize that that tail belongs to me and is
that because it doesn't have such a conception I think people who care about consciousness
and some philosophers like Daniel Dannett will only speak about humans because of this notion
of I but on the other hand there are ways that the nervous system can actually give you
a sense of self through E. Fringe copy and proprioception so the lobster probably won't
start feasting on its own tail without actually having to conceive of the lobster saying I'm
not going to eat my own tail because it's mine and anyone who has a cat sometimes a
cat starts chasing its own tail you get the funny sense that it's forgotten that it's
actually something attached to itself okay now there's an entire neuroscience of this
notion of sense of your own body versus the external world and some philosophers and neuro
scientists have said that consciousness is just some kind of evolutionary adaptation
on that system that can distinguish self from non-self so there's certainly an argument that
can be made using neuro-sci-free principles for how you might be able to iteratively reach
something that phenomenologically is consciousness and I think what everyone in the room including
probably us is it doesn't feel comfortable intuitively that consciousness is just going
to be one more phenomenon generated by the nervous system that has all these as Nicholas
Humphrey puts it magical feeling and qualities to them therefore we have to invoke something
qualitatively different to explain it that we don't demand of any other manifestation
of another system now I frankly I don't want the other speakers think think that's an illusion
I take the Dennett view that because it feels qualitatively different therefore the mechanism
has to be qualitatively different and I think that is something that we need to basically
get rid of because what it really is if you say that is dualism in its modern guys right
that and I dismissed that actually and I think Ken does probably as well I'm not sure I followed
all of that I mean there can be simpler and more complicated neural mechanisms and so
there's no reason to suppose immediately that we know what mechanisms are going to
correspond what mechanisms are going to sub serve more or less advanced psychological or
mental functioning but my thought about this wasn't that there was anything magical I don't
think that there is anything magical I started out by saying it's all biological and I think
it's all neural so far as we know it is but it does seem to me that it's a subset of the
neural reflex arcs aren't going to count as something that is psychological or mental
I think even though they're neural and so we have to be able to give a little bit of
thought to what it is that constitutes the subset oh and there's wonderful work on that
and you're totally right in other words there's work on binocular rivalry there's work on
other phenomena where it does seem that it's a subset of regions that seem to be responsible
for this you know if you can extrapolate from perception for example V1 you know primary
visual cortex doesn't seem to have this property extra strike cortex may have this property
when it comes to motor cortex it doesn't seem to have this property prefrontal singular
inferior parietal cortex seems to have it so I absolutely the property of this extra
property of the mental of the kind that I was mentioning we should be careful here I don't
think it's a property yeah I think we're talking about two different things and we
need to keep them separate before we make decisions about them one one is about whether
something's mental or not and the other is about whether something is a part of awareness
and what I heard in your neuro anatomy there was an inventory of the things that participate
in awareness but I would argue that you don't need any of those things to have a mental
property so men reflexes are actually worth arguing about and or grounding our terms whether
a reflex is a mental property so I would say that a rock doesn't have a mental property
of being able to make anything like a decision and when I bang your knees not exactly a decision
but it is to me it seems like a cognitive system there's an input there's an output there's
information processing and so for me I would actually count that as mental not awareness
I mean almost by definition that particular reflex is not the word mental for you just
become anything that a nervous system does it well I mean basically that's making mental
synonymous with what a nervous system can do well just no work up to Matthew's point about
functionalism and maybe machines could do mental things too so if a machine does calculation
you know it depends on how you want to find the terms it goes back to do airplanes fly
or not well it depends on how you want to find fly and this is why I wanted us to ground
these definitions early before we get into the stratosphere of like what do we count
as mental or not I'm perfectly comfortable attributing mental to a reflex because I think
that's what biological creatures do in response to certain kinds of stimuli and all the grounds
for excluding it but we can we can make a different definition I just want to be firm about it
so if the stimulus is the sun and the plant goes towards the stimulus that's mental I'd
like to know more about plant biology there was a pretty interesting article in the Yorker
which I did not yet read I confess not too long ago there are lots of neurotransmitters
can might know this literature better than I do but you find in plants that there's you
know there's some relation between the neurotransmitters we have and some set of signaling molecules
that are in the plant so there's signaling and somebody could say that signaling is you
know at least the first step towards mentality so so well and maybe this is this is partly
the divide between the empirical scientists and the philosophy just how we think about
things but what we're talking about is not the world and what's out there what we're
talking about is our our concepts and where we want to draw the lines on them you know
and and we start with I mean I think our real interest from about the mind comes from the
fact that we have one and we experience one and so a lot of our real interest is in self
is in all the stuff we're aware of but then of course we're aware there's a lot of stuff
we're not aware of and so we're interested in that too and then you start trying to generalize
and look at other animals and try to see how much of it like us and how much of it different
from us and but it's a concept mind is not a thing that that God created or Plato put
out there in the world it's a concept we're just you can draw your lines where you like
I wouldn't be uncomfortable with with calling you know plants doing active things in the
world mind and I wouldn't be uncomfortable with not calling a mind I don't know that
it's a really critical thing to work out I mean I agree with you and I think it depends
on where you want to go from there if we're going to start as a ground assumption and
ask a question like what is the relation between consciousness and the mental we need to know
what we mean by the mental but I agree with you that these are things that don't have
an absolute truth we're we make some cut definitionally and then we can go from there and try to
build something based on that initial cut so suppose we just think about let's forget
about plants and we think about what nervous systems do as our as our grounding for mental
functioning and then maybe this some subset to that that we're particularly interested
in I would I would vote for you know let's just start there in order to focus the conversation
let me throw out a concrete example that I think is interesting to think about which
is the worm the CL again's worm which is one of these model organisms that we know a lot
about including the connective of all of its 302 neurons and there are some interesting
neurons in there like I think it's the AIB intern neuron one thing that it does is it
seems to correlate with hunger and with a kind of state where the worm can do one thing
or another thing depending on hunger I got this example from Corey Bergman who's who's
on the NIH panel among other things for the brain initiative and she's she described having
a picnic at her house and she said you know there was all this wonderful fresh meat that
all of her graduate students were gravitating to but she had a nora virus at that moment
and so she was repulsed by the same smell and the point is that you can be in different
states which were split back to an external stimulus in the worm I think is in this case
so there are there are input neurons that respond to particular smells there are motor
neurons that engage particular actions mostly turning around that's what worms do and then
there are these intern neurons that mediate so the worm can be basically be in a hunger
state or not for me and people can argue with it and it is partly definitional but for me
that seems like a rudimentary example of a kind of awareness and in this state or I'm
in that state I'm not any longer driven purely by reflex I'm driven by which state I'm in
for me that that act already puts it over the edge and then everything else is complexity
everything else is more complicated states I don't think you have to accept that view
but that's the view that I've been sort of gravitating towards like what state you're
in digestively you've had a big meal you've had a small meal you're starving whatever
it is you'll behave differently it doesn't seem to me that the digestive system is part
of what subserves psychology yeah well Gary I'm puzzled by you by using the word awareness
there I mean you can be a different state but you don't know you're not necessarily aware
of any of them well I mean I think the self-awareness is reflective awareness which I think is a different
thing so I would not argue that the worm has any self-awareness but I would say that it
has an awareness of its environment that those states it has an awareness of an internal
state it may not be able to reflect on it and speak about it but that internal state mediates
its input output relations that's true but that's true we've known about state dependent
reflexes for half a century I didn't say it was new I just thought it was a nice example
stretch reflex stretch reflex is state dependent tell me you know depending on where you are
in the gate cycle for example will completely determine what your 1A afferent neurons and
spindles will do so even I mean even the notion of a reflex itself is problematic because
reflexes can be remarkably intelligent they can have state dependent reversals they can
be context dependent so I think that I agree with you that you can take something that
seems so simple and rudimentary like a reflex and begin to show that they can have intelligence
and the view I would take about reflexes if they are simply primitives that we incorporate
into more complex behaviors and what you've described you know in C. elegans is simply
the stretch reflex in another dies well there's actually a second question in that neighborhood
that I've been thinking about lately which is I call it the subsumption issue so it seems
like consciousness is unified you have one conscious state and we could talk about split
brains as a possible counter example and so forth but in general it seems like you're
aware of one state and there's all kinds of details modulating that but it seems at least
logically possible that if you're let's say a low order creature and I know about the
evolutionary biology cautions on that you are already looting to but if you're a low
order creature that maybe your only state is hunger or not and if you're a high order
creature there are many things that enter into your awareness but maybe some of the principles
are the same.
Just one other point I mean awareness and consciousness in the incognative neuroscience
and not synonyms so they can dissociate so for example Anton syndrome where people have
occipital strokes and they're blind will be unaware that they're blind but they are
blind and they're having the problems are blindness experiencing them but they're not
unaware of other things but that but so in other words there's they're different so
I and also again I do think for the sake of myself and the audience we have to sort of
be clear where we're going one is what are what are the you know is there a hierarchy
of behaviors that only nervous systems are capable of and do they have to be implemented
by biological tissue or by silicon and I think we've agreed that you could probably imagine
processes being done by other materials we can have our clue as to what we're interested
in by behaviors and then have a hierarchy and I think what's being implied here is that
at the top of the hierarchy of behaviors that can be implemented by circuits whether biological
or not is consciousness right that's what we're really talking about here is we start
with reflexes can we go with the the approaches and experiments and concepts that we use to
explain reflexes and can we extrapolate to consciousness that's what we're really talking
about here and I think again that we probably can right that we it may seem counterintuitive
and there may be a dualist urge but I think we can go from reflexes which are surprisingly
complex which is good because they've already got characteristics that may make them worthy
of study and I'll be very blunt I study the motor system and visual motor transformations
which I think lie just in that intermediate space between reflexes and consciousness with
the hope that by studying this intermediate kind of behavior we're going to be able to
generalize up and down and actually get to where we're going rather than jumping in
and studying consciousness and I don't know what the psychologists say about that but
I do think it's important to realize that we can use the same armamentarium and the same
concepts to ultimately I think explain something even as seemingly mysterious as consciousness
but I think that's what we're talking about here can we get there right.
So I would let me let me throw out my thought on that which then people can shoot down that
well first of all we've got nobody's debating that it all just is something the mind the
brain does is the nervous system does and there's nothing else magical going on so if
we can all grant that but the question is you know what can we say scientifically about
consciousness important to what does it mean to explain it and my own thoughts are that
in principle we can we will be able to say you know with absolute clarity this kind of
structure of neural activity and through consciousness and this kind of structure of neural activity
does not enter consciousness and these aspects of this piece of mental of neural structure
and through consciousness will will be able in principle there's no reason why we can't
completely correlate every aspect of consciousness to every aspect of neural functioning but
to explain why we're not zombies we'll still have a question to explain why we actually
are aware of anything when all this happens I don't understand how science could possibly
approach that the whole nature of science is that we I mean the world as we encounter
it has subjectivity and objectivity the whole nature of science is to extract the objective
and the reproducible out of this mess of subjectivity and objectivity and now we want science to
tell us why some set of mental constructions leads to an internal awareness I don't even
know what why would mean I just don't see how you pose that as a scientific question we
could say everything about when it happens but why are we not zombies I don't see how
I don't know what to do with that question so by subjectivity you mean what well everything
that our internal experience our internal awareness so could you derive from first principles
just to make this concrete what it feels like to be in pain to experience an orgasm or what
it's like to perceive the color red so there's one piece of the problem that seems very straight
forward if not easy which is which which information source are you aware of it at any given point
neuroscience is making a lot of progress on that so we John Davis a rundown before these
areas seem to be part of that awareness circuitry and these aren't you can say that this particular
thing is enters into v1 but doesn't go beyond there and so forth we can characterize this
this is this is Ned Bloch's access consciousness versus phenomenal consciousness but can we
explain these other things could you explain to an alien what it's like to experience an
orgasm given the facts that we know about how the brain works or could you only say for
example it's represented in this way in the prefrontal cortex and there's this other
representation in the brainstem and these are the patterns of activity that we see during
the orgasm but not actually be able to explain yeah I mean I think this is the core question
would we ever be able to explain to an alien what it's like to see red and I think this
is the most I mean again I take the denit and Humphrey view this is such a pseudo question
I mean there's no denying that there's such a thing as qualia and experience but I think
what the fallacy of it is to think that the explanation is going to feel like the thing
it's explaining now why do we think that explanations when it comes to consciousness have to feel
like consciousness itself in other words it's the same fallacy I think anybody's saying
that well that I think that is what's actually happening is it okay you've explained memory
with synaptic changes but it doesn't have the memoryness of memory when you explain it that
way well but John take the question of the questions take take the question of why you
have an awareness of something and you're not a zombie that's the thing I think we can't
address but you think we can address that when you say why I want to know what you mean
by why so let me just you know take the denit Humphrey line right where they and there are
two questions that come to the bottom of consciousness well three right one is could you detect it
in another person doesn't mean you know what it feels like but couldn't alien come down
as Nicholas Humphrey has written about and do enough recordings and observations to say
this is a conscious being not a zombie a b what are the neural bases for consciousness
we don't know right he comes up you'll be interested with the idea of you piggyback on
E. France copy and forward models you develop a reverberating attractor and that itself
leads to a endogenous feeling that's called consciousness but there's there's all the
magic leads to no no no but I could say that about anything else so when when I say I want
to pick up this cup the commands that I need to generate to reach that cup we don't know
what they look like they certainly don't look like the movement itself in other words there's
no obvious mapping if you have a windscreen wipe of switch on your car right and you see
the windscreen wipe is going like that the one thing you don't need to do with the switch
on the cars it doesn't have to look anything like it I think you're attacking a strong
man optical illusions are the same thing it's never the explanations just going to be that
is the necessary and sufficient conditions in the brain to cause the phenomenal other
of all phenomenon and to say that the explanation has to feel like the phenomenon will never
happen well no no but this is this is my question I can say this is this is the you know this
is the correlate oh I mean we can't say cause we can say correlate in if you lesion it any
of you had a measure of consciousness go it goes I mean correlation and cause can be fused
if you do necessary sufficient conditions so you're you're not telling us what this subjectivity
is you're speaking of it is something other than you're speaking out of it is something
that gets caused or gets led to or something of that sort I think what probably an alien
isn't going to find out is an alien isn't going to have your experiences so if the demand
is to have your experiences then not going to happen but the alien isn't going to have
your stomach or your food or anything else you isn't going to have your home or your
car right that's different so I'm not I'm still puzzled by what this thing is you're calling
subjectivity so it does seem to me it does seem to me that you can give a pretty good
explanation not in neurological terms but in psychological terms as to what's going on
when you see red I won't for today hazard a guess as to how to describe orgasm but seeing
red is a lot closer for example to seeing orange than it is to seeing blue and you can
get a kind of quality space which people have mapped and you can give a description of what
it's like to see red in those terms and you and I assume that if neither of us colorblind
and colorblindness is perfectly testable empirically we assume that more or less my
do love the difference of cone distributions in our eyes this is going to be the same for
you and the same for me right but I'm not going to have your experiences and you're not going
to have my experiences so if that's the mystery of subjectivity it doesn't seem to be a mystery
at all my two degree well look we can build everybody agrees we can build a robot that
has some interesting behavior not nearly as interesting as ours but has some interesting
behavior I think we would also all agree that the robots we can build right now don't have
any self-awareness don't have any consciousness don't know if we know that in advance there
are this guy named Scott's a lady at Yale who's been building robots that have a swarm of self-awareness
so they can recognize themselves maybe in a mirror and they can plan around their own
bodies and so forth so that's actually not as obvious as as you're presuming it do you
I think that they have subjective awareness like you and I do well I mean I go back and
forth on this there are days in which I think this is a pseudo problem as these gentlemen
have been saying and that there's no way to answer that question so we don't have a meter
that can evaluate this person has a subject subjective awareness or not and I think the
reason why I think it's not a pseudo problem is because I can absolutely imagine a world
where we do all the things we do for all the reasons that we do them and we have no subjective
experience about it well I don't know what you're imagining when you imagine that there
these people like the Chalmers who say that they can imagine this and they can imagine
that and I think this is wonderful I can't and so I would like to know from you what it
is you're imagining that is to say what I'm imagining the robot for a good thing behavior
but I'm quite confident does not have anything like my experience so I'm taking you to be
a generous fellow and therefore to accord me experiences of Brown and so forth and so
on but on what basis just just by analogy to my own experience and then but what's the analogy
I mean you can't if it's the right I can never say for experience but I you know I take it
for granted but I can't prove it no no no no no not I'm not asking for proof proof is
for mathematicians that's what he is a little bit okay so in that field I defer to you with
proof but we just want a good reason we want something to go with here there are always
people in this room why do you think any of them has experiences of anything why aren't
they all like the robot that you were imagining what is the reason for this is it just an analogy
to one person it's good when I talk with them they exchange you know when we talk we exchange
we think that that that that tell me that that they make me believe that what goes on
inside you is pretty much like what goes on inside me I'm sure that they're going to
get robots that are really good at that kind of thing well at some point there may be a
question about the robots right now there isn't see what you're asking I'm not going to agree
with you some the second question I mean the neural basis of consciousness is very difficult
right and some the neural basis of it is very difficult some people may never agree maybe you
won't are you saying mental and I'm talking about consciousness now whatever this awareness
self-reflection the non the anti-zombie right that's what I'm talking about mental and
not interested just nervous system stuff okay but then the second question is why do we have
consciousness at all and my problem and I agree with you about this robot world where everyone
is it wouldn't look like our world I mean consciousness was presumably selected for it was
presumably piggybacked on some previous function and it probably has some benefits otherwise we
wouldn't have it and what those better than you're saying there is such an it and there'd be a
possibility of not having it I'm saying yes that's subjectivity I thought a minute ago you said that there
wasn't really any hit there no no no I said that there's no problem with I don't I don't just
agree that there's subjectivity in consciousness and I also agree there's more of it in humans than
other animals what I was saying is not sure that the Nagel the Nagel view of what it liked to be
a bat is not a scientific question in my view all we need to know I don't think it's a question of
any sort yes agreed but people get hung up on saying what's it like to be me and think that
scientists are going to come up with an explanation that's what I'm pointing to a question when I'm
asking about the what I'm saying about the robot point is that consciousness is probably what makes
everyone in this room sit and listen to us blather on right they actually come here and go I want to
learn about the mysteries of life I'm interested that when your dog is panting and can't wait to go
for a walk right take me for a walk give it were a robot it would just you know presumably you can
go robot to do that no but then what you're doing is your mimicking your mimicking these funny
features of joy and exuberance and curiosity and those might be useful actually for evolutionary
purposes and that may be what we're talking about but hold on there's evolutionary purpose in having
a motivational system and having a selective attention system and so forth and consciousness is a
uber version of that well that's the question is so what is it what is it adding beyond the
selection attention the motivation and so forth think why not just have an organism that had those
is there some extra thing that we're trying to explain and what is that extra well I'm gonna I'm
going to study for the next through four years to be a doctor because then I'll be able to make money
and help people think about that that's a motivational system an animal there's no animal that can
see four years ahead we have different motivational systems and other animals I don't doubt that all
I'm saying is that perhaps consciousness is the prerequisite for that much more complicated form
of motivation that's what I'm saying I think that there's reason to think that that's not the case
because look thinking thinking can occur without being conscious what is that mean how how how
oh easy oh so all the stuff that happened before you're aware what you think it's nothing but I'm
thinking just becomes again like mental a synonym for anything your nervous system can process and
do no it doesn't but it's quite specific you have a problem you don't know how to solve it you say
oh to heck with it I'm going to bed and the next morning you wake up and by gosh there's the solution
and so what's this what this is complicated enough that it's going to have mental content it's going
to have what people in philosophy call a propositional or intentional content expressable by that
causes I think that such and such I think so and so and it's going to be describable in the same way
that we describe conscious thought except for the bit about you're not aware of it taking place so
it's thinking but it is unconscious and the question is what is the being conscious add to it because
to get an animal to do what's good for the animal right it needs to think and it needs to have
selective attention it needs to have all of these things but none of those processes need to occur
consciously well I just want to just to clarify again for the audience no one's denying that
there are quite complex implicit cognitive processes a whole wonderful field your Tim
shallis is written beautifully on this that you can have processes that look analogous to
processes that you're conscious of without consciousness on them and you want to deny that those are
thinking no well okay so if you grant that those are thinking that I don't know how to make sense
of what I'm saying I'm going to say no right because then thinking stops doing useful work as a
concept so let's take me overnight well no it doesn't stop doing that useful work what you can do
with thinking is for one thing infer so you have this thought and that thought leads to this thought
which leads to that thought and you wake up in the morning with the solution well okay let me just
say talk about that so we have no evidence right that qualitatively what you just described when
awake and conscious is what's going on overnight when you have your aha moment in fact consolidation
so just for those of you who aren't neuroscience it is true that you can have all sorts of
improvements overnight in many many tasks that you did the day before and come back better the next
day with no additional practice right so the question is something was going on in your brain
overnight that continued what you were doing and you wake up and you're better and you could
extrapolate to say maybe that's the aha moment because you were doing something overnight there
people and study hippocampal replay for example but what seems to be happening is you may be
tuning neurons better right and so that when you now use that same circuit to do the same thing
the next day it's better at it that tuning that went on overnight doesn't itself need to be called
thinking it certainly needs to be called learning but they're not so not are you going to not
sit I mean I always think learning to be a subset of thinking but you've got a different definition
I think we obviously we have another uh definitional issue here what what is your definition of thinking
that it excludes learning no I think thinking is another one of these dangerous vague terms that
people have a fuzzy colloquial notion about you seem confident in writing around and excluding
things I gave you a pretty tight I would say that thinking is another word we give to conscious
neural processing no more no less so all of Kahneman's system one things you would exclude from thought
then I mean all this kind of automatic intuitive stuff that's well I mean that's another you know
what we're going to call Kahneman's cached ideas I mean for those you know system one system two
what system one is and there are many other areas in neuroscience that look like system one
it where you have a cached repertoire of responses that are triggered right because it would be
incredibly annoying if you had to keep from first principles deriving your responses so yes the
nervous system has cached repertoires of responses and we're gonna let's be careful there because
there's interpolation there so you can you can without conscious effort do some kind of posture
for example or adapt to some unusual posture let's say you're carrying something I'd give you some
extra weight you don't have to think about it but you're changing your motor system that's because
you have a control policy a pre-established cached control policy and basically system one in the
culture domain is a control policy we should probably define these terms well I'm just saying
I think what's better for the audience is to realize that once one starts to get systematic
and one starts to be thick in one's descriptions of the phenomena one's interested in then you
realize that it's not really the terms we're getting hung up on it's the range of the phenomenology
we're trying to talk about like that we have like a coffee which over here so um I think that
it's helpful just to talk about the phenomena and how we're trying to describe them and study them
so that's interesting but I'm still stuck with your your word thinking because you're using it
in a very different way than I've heard before I would just want to clarify something you're
saying that anything that's cached is not thinking I look I'm not going to be I'm saying you know
I'm like the philosophers I don't believe that interesting discussions require rigid definitions
if you look at modern epistemology and philosophy where you talk about knowledge a lot of very
interesting working philosophies been done on knowledge without a definition that's rigid of
what knowledge is and I'm saying that I'm trying to make distinctions which have fuzzy boundaries I
admit but I'm saying that to talk about offline tuning of neurons in the brain during sleep as
equivalent to what we do when we're awake and thinking I was granting your sleeping case but I
was very interested in the the Kahneman system one stuff so it's a different way of construing
what thought is to say that thought only includes the deliberate conscious reflective kind of stuff
when we sit here and we take a long time I guess as most people here probably think that's what it
means to well I think some people might include like the intuition you decide when you're trying
to pick which apartment you've looked at a lot of apartments and you might buy them and everybody
is fighting over you know putting down down payment first you're integrating a lot of information
about the view and how close it is to the subway what are the schools like and so forth you don't
necessarily put it all in a spreadsheet I mean if you're neurotic like me maybe you do but you
don't have to you can do it off in a way that feels a little bit offline but is that not thinking
it's like what you do is that kind of synthesis is that thinking so it's localizing a sound in
this room thinking well I don't see why that follows there's actually this guy in the Netherlands
Dijkstra house who has done it's example I was alluding to it's I can go yeah who's done experimental
work with complicated consumer decisions it works much better if you don't work it out consciously
with simple consumer decisions it does work out better if you work it out consciously I don't know
why that is but one would think with the complicated consumer decisions like buying a house and so
forth and so on with that benefit of a spreadsheet then this is thinking and it doesn't seem to me
that when you speak of tuning of neurons that's really at all relevant and the reason that I don't
think it's at all relevant is we started out we all agreed that at least for the non-silicon cases
if you've got psychological goings on it's going to be brain function so you can tune up the brain
in one way or another and maybe it's thinking and maybe it isn't and you've got to have some other
way of deciding whether that particular tuning up of the brain is thinking when you wake up you
find out well look I wasn't offering a proof as I said before I was offering a good reason to think
that if you're absolutely puzzled when you go to sleep by something and then you're very clear
headed and you see all the connections clearly when you wake up something in the meantime has
happened and I don't see why that isn't thinking but I think we're back to debating definition
rather than phenomena and I mean we can define thinking one way or another exactly
absolutely not neuroscience and it's a psychology psychoanalysis
sorry so you have a situation where somebody whenever they are
regretful or feel bad about something they have done or said that they then respond to that
by attacking the next person it's a common occurrence if you're looking at people's behavior
now they have no awareness that the reason why they are attacking this other person
has to do with whatever feeling so how would you in terms of you're talking about there's no
unconscious thinking how would you explain this right so first of all this is so far for my
purview that I doubt what is with rats it's no no no it's it's true that it is it is far from your
purview and it's not since what we are talking about is the biology of the mind and so what I'm
telling you is this is what I see as the mind and I'm asking you you tell me what is the biology
of this mind so as I said there's a fascinating and other people here know very interesting literature
and cognitive neuroscience showing surprisingly complex cognitive processing going on absolutely
absence of conscious awareness right in other words everyone wants to say that a certain
threshold of complexity of the cognitive process even if unconscious we're going to call it thinking
and I have no problem you can call it leading to behavior right yes I mean I have you know
cattleman from the from the behavioral economic side or whether it's all the work being done you
know by people like Tim Shales and Adrian Owen and all these people there's no question that
surprisingly public complex cognitive operations occur that have impact on behavior when people
are processing but when you ask them are they aware that they're doing so to the stimulus
they'll say no there won't be above chance so your example fits beautifully into these
vast range of phenomena where complex processing is going on and people don't realize they're
doing it so neuroscience is in complete agreement with the kind of thing that you just described
yours might be more subtle and more complicated and harder to do in a lab and more difficult to
control all the variables and to show systematic effects across many subjects so it might be difficult
to do classic cognitive science on your phenomenon so the real question but it can be done yeah the
real question is given how much can be done in that way that I would want to call unconscious
why we have a consciousness at all exactly right and so that's the question that I posed before
we got on to this terminological issue is if you had a motivational system and a selective
intentional system wouldn't that be enough why why do you need more well as I said the person
has written a whole book on this topic in Nicholas Humphrey and it's it's not my idea at all but
he's the most interesting so far in trying to answer exactly your excellent question which is
that consciousness really is a souped up qualitatively better way to do motivation and attention if you
want to be an organism in a common now look to me that almost seems like a category error if you
say that what you've got is motivation and attention and then there could be something else we'll
call that consciousness and it turns out that that consciousness is just better versions of the
first things that we don't actually need to evoke consciousness we just need to talk about how you
make a better selective attention system a better motivation system we don't need a third a lot of
empirical evidence that you get selective attention is really very fine grained which in the absence
of awareness there's just been a lot of work in the last time here yeah because another no problem
let me ask Matthew what you think of all this well I don't know so I don't actually I'm sort of more
you know also kind of sympathetic to zombie arguments I don't actually think that there's
anything that I could conscious that I could explicitly choose to program into a system that
would make it conscious in the sense of having a kind of first-person life even if we like had a
whole brain situation understood it's not I'm not I'm not I'm not saying that I would deny that it
would happen I'm just saying I can't say that I don't think it's a functional thing so I don't
actually think that by programming some capacities rather than others I'd be able to titrate what was
what it was like to be a robot so the awareness that we have of ourselves is things like I think
I'm sitting I think I'm talking to some people about the biology of mind I think there are various
things like that so if you can figure out how to get a gadget a machine to have thoughts and then
you can figure out how to get the gadget to have thoughts with this content and that content and
so forth then you're home free and you can have a gadget that thinks I'm doing this I'm doing that
I have the experience of bread again like you have you have a system whose representations have
have that content yeah something else from saying that like it's like anything to be that system
right so what I want to know is what the other thing is it's as far as I'm concerned it's just
this is the universe that we live in well I would I would add ours it's like no no no but I want
you to articulate what being with shallmurs amounts okay so what's the difference between
so you've got these guys who think that there's this subjectivity and it's mysterious and it
defies you know scientific treatment and Nagel's argument is subjectivity is where we start and
objectivity is getting away from subjectivity so objectivity can't give an account of subjectivity
it seems to me this is all word mongering and unless one can say what it is that's missing well
so so what's what's the difference between all this non-aware sophisticated cognitive processing
and aware sophisticated so I was saying that what the difference was was that when you've got
conscious seeing as opposed to subliminal seeing then you have an additional awareness so if I
subliminally see the table and I have an awareness of the table let's not worry about what the content
is but I have there's the table I have an awareness of it's subliminal it's not conscious if the
awareness of the table is conscious if it's conscious awareness then I have another awareness
of the first order awareness of the table so so so it's a popular robot that that can that can
enter into its memory banks you know the thought there is a table and the thought I just noticed
there was a table then is that that robot becomes well I thought we didn't know whether robots
were could be like us well but but suppose I just programmed a robot the way we know robots are now
where we know they're not like us and I programmed it to be able to say you know not only there's a
table but I just said there's a table I know there's a table so it's not conscious but just because
it has that in its memory right that's the soul sort of argument but I see you have to just look at
the world I mean let's take play I mean it's amazing how little neuroscience of play there's been okay
but playing people are beginning to look at it now not every animal plays so these animals that
have attention and motivation like a nute or a locust no one has seen play behavior right then
you get to crows and mammals and I'm not going to talk exactly whether you start to see this extra
behavior right and we call it play now all I'm saying is that there are these qualitatively
different extra behaviors that nervous system start to manifest that seem extraneous you know
and whether we want to go to the aesthetic to the planned to playful what some people are saying is
that those are the benefits that consciousness mechanisms might start to give you and now again
I'm in no position to say whether you can't play if not conscious or whether the beginnings of play
suggest a little bit of awareness of self and fun but the I think again quoting from Humphrey and
Dennett that the arguments for consciousness independent of the neural bases for it are going
to have to take this are we going to have a robot zombie writing a poem is it going to open the window
and go what a wonderful world it is today right now that's what I'm saying consciousness probably
you need to have it okay well so look not I would I would agree with you that there's evolutionary
reasons for this system which this part of the neural system that is the thing that enters our
awareness the only I I agree that it was selected for I agree that it has a function the only thing
I don't agree with is why I couldn't do exactly the same things without having any subjective
awareness of it because I'm saying it wouldn't lead to play forward planning well that's that's
the point it's not all the same your processing and behaviors happen why do you know what is
they they wouldn't be they wouldn't be triggered I mean that is a good question but I'm just saying
I believe purely intuitively that what I it's going to have to go in the direction that I'm
saying we're going to have to look at the phenomenology of conscious behavior to get clues as to what
it does extra rather than constantly falling back on these zombie arguments and I completely agree
with you they just they're negative pointing it to the limitation you know in other words a boy
it can a computer a robot do everything except be self-aware but you do everything
it could even be self-aware but it might not be aware that it's self-aware right now
it may not have any subjective experience
so I don't actually think I mean again I don't I don't think about consciousness that much because
like I said I don't think that there's any difference in from the point of view of the system
you know what's interesting from the point of view of
the programming as we're able to you know succeed in building more knowledge into systems in using
learning in new ways and in like having architectures that exhibit more flexible behavior is that we
understand more and more of the sophistication that goes into our unconscious processing in ways that
help us I think to reflect on the kind of engagement that we have with the world
and sort of why it is that mental explanations are such effective explanations of people
so one thing that's different between you know computer systems are very good at
solving classification problems so they'll be able to make a really good good prediction about
whether you're going to pay your credit card on time or whether you know whether you want to buy
a particular product based on your web surfing history but what they don't do is that they don't
kind of critique the representations that they have in the world so that they don't sort of use
their what they learn as sort of hypotheses going forward they don't have kind of they don't
pose questions to the world and they don't sort of have feedback and that sort of seems to be one
of the things that's really important when we attribute to each other beliefs about the world to say
like you know when I think that that's water on the table there that's making a complex set of
predictions about well I'm going to drink it if it doesn't taste good I'm going to try to figure
out what it is instead there's a kind of system-aticity to the way that our representations inform our
engagement with the world and that kind of functional structure allows us to appreciate why
it's so much easier to explain what somebody does in terms of what they believe
than to explain in terms of what's happening in their cortex or even to draw correlations
between what they've done before and what they're likely to do again.
Right now. I totally agree with your take on the difference between AI and human cognition.
I might say though that that's really about what intelligence is and we have a different kind
of intelligence than machines do of course different machines have different intelligence from one
another. I don't know that that's actually informative about what consciousness is so in one theory would
be in order to be conscious you have to have a certain kind of intelligence another theory would
be that our kind of intelligence is just one route to having consciousness and maybe machines could
have consciousness by taking a different route and again some of its different needs have
consciousness without having this. I mean I'm certainly willing to entertain that I'm not willing to
entertain that new to self-awareness I don't see any evidence of that but some level of awareness
that's prior to self-awareness I think it's probably do have.
Yeah the lobster that knows it's where its body ends and where the world begins.
So what's troubling for so might be troubling for some people is that iPhones have some sense
of awareness of where they are right they're GPS systems you know in fact where they are.
To me those kind of arguments are pseudo cleverness right they don't actually get to what we're
talking about I mean okay yes programmers made GPS systems in phones but if we're going to be
talking about evolution and how we go from certain forms of all awareness.
From you today is that it's a better motivational system and a better
I have I'm not somebody I can program an iPhone with a better awareness system and a better
motivational system. I'm not sure it's going to get me there I'm not sure it won't either but
iPhone having motivational awareness is just absurd.
Well certainly an iPhone has awareness.
iPhones have awareness they have accelerometers they have GPS systems they have microphones
they have information cameras they can sense things about the world they can sense a lot of
things about and and they can selectively filter it so they can focus right now on part of the
image rather than the whole image they can turn on one sensor rather than turn off.
They can turn on an iPhone where but you said a nuke wasn't and a reflex wasn't.
Why I said an iPhone you're giving iPhone awareness but you denied that
reflex is added. You denied that reflex is added.
Denied that reflex is had awareness. You said that at the very beginning.
I'm willing to exclude reflexes.
But not an iPhone.
iPhones I have not adjudicated one way or another.
I'm simply trying to pinpoint the distinction you're sort of rudely shaking your head but we're
trying to figure out where the distinction might go right so it doesn't seem to be at the level
of sensation it doesn't seem to be at the level of selective awareness unless we really have
two logical choices we're making some definitions here and one of our logical choices is to say
we're just going to attribute consciousness to iPhones. Most people in the room are comfortable
with that but some might we haven't really given a principled argument if we're going to go down
the line that says we're not going to attribute consciousness to iPhones then we can't do it because
iPhones lack sensation because they have them. We can't do it because they lack selective sensory
apparatus because they have them and even motivational system we could at least have an argument.
So if we want to say the iPhone doesn't have consciousness which I think is a respectable
position then we want to say why we are holding that position. I have not heard a good answer
to it yet today. Well I mean we're going back to the idea that I agree with you that reflexes
are based on simple after input output okay and that the arguments from evolutionally
standpoint are you start with sensation then you move to E-france copy and forward models
what does this mean by the way it's sort of internal representations of the external world that
simulate sensations and there's a lot of evidence for that that you can begin to predict the
sensory consequences of what you're going to do based on internal simulations without actually
having the sensations and so the argument might be that you go from sensations to these internal
simulations of sensations and then maybe that was piggyback to Pong for consciousness being
some extra feeling to this internal simulation of sensation and that one can construct that
kind of argument. Now that use of circuitry to go along that spectrum is a completely different
universe to talking about the fact that an iPhone could be programmed to have a GPS or an accelerometer
which you know of course but there's no way that the iPhone is now going to say thank you for giving
me a sensory system I'm now going to evolve to have internal copies and then I'm going to evolve
evolve to being conscious if it's true that an iPhone could evolve right in front of us in its
little lifetime and that's news to me. It seems to me that everything rests on the part that you
called the extra. So in terms of having internal models again computers have lots of internal
models there's a lot of it's worth noting that most voice interfaces only work because the system
is able to subtract its own expected sound from its input to detect what you're saying.
Right so so I'm saying that we understand from engineering computing the benefit of Ford models
and we've made them in nervous system and it's an interesting phenomenon and could one go with that
if we believe in evolution or I'm saying. Now a computer you give an internal model it's not going
to evolve right. Well that's not true either I mean you can you can make computers that have
evolved evolution systems there's some very nice work for example by Kenneth Stanley where
there's evolution over time the internal models of those computer systems evolve over time they get
better at learning all kinds of things so maybe they're limited still in the ways to maybe point
out but but they are I mean there it seems to me like just a technological question so there's
there's a whole field of genetic programming of evolutionary programming and it's made some
progress it hasn't made as much progress as I would like I mean I don't think that the systems are
that sophisticated but they're capable of learning some kind of new representation of building some
kind of new model and it seems like you know 25 years or 50 years that that field will be further
along like most fields my intuition is that still won't give us that something extra if there is
something extra but part of my intuition is maybe we are it's a it's a red herring looking for this
something extra well that I think I think we're not talking about the phenomenon is real the question
is whether the that's for nation for the phenomenon has to be qualitatively different I think I
did you all agree that quanera real the first person perspective is real that they are then I
would say we haven't today certainly offered any understanding of even how you would figure out
what that I think is a pseudo question okay question from the audience stand up and microphone please
it seems to me that one really simple epistemic can you go slightly closer to the mic or one is
very simple delineation that can be made perhaps is that consciousness can't be a discrete unit
it seems to me the consciousness how long phrase this consciousness is something that is shared
among us we all laugh at the same time I sort of share a consciousness with my pets they share some
of mine I know this is a little silly to to phrase it so simplistically but um
um a phenomenon like quorum sensing or the to describe an organization like the United
States of America we could describe this we could use the same descriptions of consciousness
to describe groups it seems to me that the descriptions break down when you try to
identify one discrete unit of consciousness I think the one place where neuroscience has
actually made some progress is on replacing this idea of pure localization one spot in the brain
that does this with the notion that there are networks and circuits and I think once you have
that realization that there are networks and circuits then at least a little bit of what you're
asking about gets gets a little bit easier so if you understand that what any computation
whether we're talking about language or walking or whether we're talking about consciousness
is a network and that these different networks overlap with one another then you're not quite
stuck I think in the puzzle of saying well it's it's not a discrete thing well most
most cognitive capacities aren't really discrete things there there are constellations of neural
processes that are in flux they may vary from one moment to the next even in one particular
individual and certainly across individuals and I think we're starting to have some understanding
of the network dynamics of the brain because they're not even figured it all out but I think
that's a place to make progress on that question. I'm Chris Kenzel I'm a psychiatrist and psychoanalyst
and I like to offer a new paradigm of just take me a minute. Ten years I'm sitting behind the couch
patients over over that time I have the distinct impression that the mind is consciousness and
unconsciousness. Don't ask me all the details of how I got there but that in fact is what the mind is
so what's the so the next question is well what is it it's it has to be a form of matter
but it does it's not like any other form of matter you can't see it you can't measure it you can't
weigh it you can't what is it is it up is it an abstraction then of matter is it a special form
of matter so I came across in Scientific American the notion that all matter is waves
I began to think well maybe consciousness and unconsciousness are indeed matter ways themselves
that is maybe the reason we can't break them down or get their components and so on is because
they're primary fundamental matter ways just like energy and time and substance so on that
they're fundamental matter ways I don't know if I can get the the theory of the hypothesis is that
at a certain point in the evolution of the universe that consciousness and unconsciousness matter
waves emerged that they then made life think about the cell without a survival drive and without a
survival implementation implementation how could a cell possibly survive without drive and without
a means to do it a procedure so unconsciousness became the drive the survival drive consciousness
became the procedure you have survival drive survival procedure you have adaptive drive
and animals adaptive procedure and you have a whole person evolution thing in human in human beings
so there's two parts in what you're saying one is is that drives are really important and I think
there's room to argue about what counts as a drive whether whether you find a drive in a single cell
and that's a definitional thing and we could talk about that on the other part of what you're saying
I would say that the waves aren't going to help us here but what we're looking for is an
organization of matter that's what's proven to be helpful in understanding life itself so people
were looking for this vitalist force which they never really found what we found instead was that
the right way to understand life is in terms of particular arrangements of matter that have
particular properties such that they reproduce such that they have metabolism and so forth
and that's how we understand life now is if you have the right arrangement of matter that gives
you those properties what I would say in consciousness is whatever the answer is it's going to start
with information processing that you're going to have arrangements of matter that allow you to
do information processing there may be some other requirement but I would say that's a beginning
necessary requirement that probably nobody here would disagree with can you will go and say something
yeah I mean I agree with that I just the a couple of things one is that the
the connection between you know the fact that matter is wave which is basically quantum mechanics
and and the mind or consciousness is that they're both not they're both mysterious
and and therefore there's a tendency to say this this is mysterious and that is mysterious so
this must explain that and they have nothing to do with each other exactly totally agree yeah and
the we know quantum mechanics is mysterious in certain special ways which typically go under the
name of entanglement when these special things happen it's very foreign to our experience and
it makes it mysterious it's it's very clear that there's entanglement is not playing a role in the
brain the brain is operating out of temperature under conditions where this is just not playing
any role so it's just it's just divorced what what is the other thing that I want to say is just
I mean we we all agreed on this issue and so therefore we didn't discuss it which is that
you know consciousness is and mind are just are just manifestations of the brain but
just to give an experience just to make I mean we live with this weird internal awareness which
is our mind and it's seen so mysterious like it must you know be connected to the cosmos or the
universe or something but when you start doing when you do surgery on on animals or on people
you know everyone has got a piece of meat called the heart and that pumps their blood
and everyone has got a piece of meat called you know a kidney and that filters their blood
and everyone inside their skull has got this brain thing and it's it more fat excuse me more
fat than meat yeah but it's me it's a piece of meat that evolved biologically to do a function
and it's no more mysterious or dependent on quantum mechanics than the kidney or the heart
I agree I agree okay next question please
first I want to say there are a few iPhones in here that don't seem to have intelligence
they just want a 10-cent second I have two I have two short questions that are sort of contradictory
one is we don't know what strength is in particular we know that it's an emergent
quality of certain objects so why can't consciousness be considered an emergent quality of the brain
and then the second question maybe I'll just let it go with it actually
I'll start on that one and other people can disagree if the analogy I was just making with life is
right well life is an emergent property but there are different kinds of emergent properties so
life is a kind of emergent property that we can well understand why the functions of particular
molecules lead to the configurations that give you the reproduction the metabolism and so forth so
life is different from the constituent molecules but it emerges in a lawful and predictable kind of
way so that's one kind of emergence it's conceivable that there's another kind of emergence that is not
sort of doesn't follow in the same reductionist or inverse reductionist fashion so I would argue
that if you understand the right information processing properties that that then consciousness
emerges I mean we I don't think we have a proof of that but at least with the rest of of mental
function that seems to me to be the right way to go as we say these mental functions emerge
if you have the right configurations of matter and I would just say I mean yes it is an emergent
property of the brain but it's not as sort of nonspecific as that I mean the brain has a lot
of detailed structure and different pieces of that structure are involved in different kinds
of cognitive processes and there are some detailed set of structures that we don't understand that
you know and or some some cons or some constellations of activity in all these detailed structures
that emerges consciousness but it's not just kind of you know a soup out of which continents
emerges it's a very specific thing that's involved it's not magic it's emergence from high degree of
structure yeah very briefly at what point would you all be willing to seed to an either an alien or
a robot the property of consciousness very good I have a hard enough time with other human beings
I don't think there's an easy answer to that because there are different ways that we
try to answer that question one is the thing that Kim said earlier there's a kind of an analogy
right we all look roughly alike and we seem to function in similar ways and so forth and so on
we can exchange things by way of language in non-linguistic ways so I assume that you're
kind of like me and you assume I'm kind of like you that's one thing but we know well we think we know
I guess the first point of contention was I said fish and all I said was I didn't know much about
fish and everybody jumped and they weren't mental they didn't have I said I didn't know
but everybody jumped on me but you know one thing about fishes I don't feel like a fish is very
much like me just looking at it off hand so when you look at its genome and its brain organization
that that's very different so the question is how do you do it right and what I'm saying is
we have different ways of doing it and one answer isn't going to fit all cases
I would say that you know I don't work in consciousness you know but people who do in neuroscience
and people who do in philosophy do come up with criteria behavioral criteria and we've
ultimately if we believe what we all do which if it's have a physical basis there will be neural
criteria which an alien would potentially then be able to say these conditions are necessary
insufficient to produce the behavioral phenomenon of consciousness so even though I'm not somebody
who's writing down the behavioral and neural requirements people to have it's not totally
impossible to do so I think we could do it but if you took Matthew's point from the very
beginning seriously and at least allowed the in principle possibility that machines could have
consciousness and you won't come up with necessary and sufficient neural conditions you might come
up with necessary sufficient computational I mean processes I mean component processes components
and processes I'm a functionalist I'm not an internal here I think David Mars levels in terms
of describing things in terms of algorithms and implementation we might be looking for
something that's algorithmic I'm not sure we can find it at all but if we can I would think it would
be I'm just saying that you got to figure out what the machinery is doing not what the machinery is
actually far as I'm a hootian neuro-conversity liberal liberal studies philosophy background so
this is going to be a little bit philosophy going on really enjoyed everything the contention was
great kind of heated up their own so these would be that first comment that might be helpful is
Immanuel Kant made a distinction regarding what science is because part of the discussion was
what science was that was maybe implied constitutive versus regulative principles
regulative principles helps sort of guide where science is going what's worth doing etc
constitutive principles are which atom which molecule under what conditions will do what for you
and it seemed like the something extra the magic that was banished immediately from the room which
is still here I think has to do with regular to print principles because the regulative principles
for Kant you can never get these you can't find them under microscope and yet you should try to
find them anyway for instance the beginning of time that kind of thing is the example he uses
so I think part of the discussion goes to that consciousness as a regulative principle helps to
guide the research whether it's functional research or other kinds of research about neurons and
connect homes and so forth because it's kind of why we're doing this on the other hand another
question that I have I guess at first a comment on the emergence thing if you do have all the
conditions I don't think it's predictable as Professor Marcus said you have conditions that
would give rise to life but you can't predict what kind of life it's going to be otherwise we could
predict evolution which we can't I think no one's going to say that the entire scenario was predictable
given the right to no one so with that I will then ask you a real question and the question is
basically we have the motivational thing the kind of constituency we're saying if we had these on
the iPhone would be conscious perhaps there's one thing missing that would be helpful I get this
from Whitehead it's the self intensification of experience something that has experience
will try to intensify its experience and it's that in that that Whitehead finds consciousness and life
and it finds it in the respect that it diverts from or diverges from routine it diverges from
reflex every time it does that things get intense if experience craves intensity then experience would
logically do that at some point and improve itself thereby so it kind of fits part of what you're
saying but I was wondering if there's any correlate to the effort to intensify one's experience at
whether one is a fish or a sea elegance or human I could take the first part of that there's something
that didn't come up today but always comes up and it should come up which is there are kind of a
few logical possibilities here one is the consciousness is like life that it's an emerging property if
we have the right definitions we understand the right molecular processes we can understand it
another possibility is that we can never understand it that we're not smart enough and that the
tools that we have won't get us there Colin McGinn has made this argument I've never been impressed
by it but it's it's out there it's a logical possibility and the third possibility is that
we're trying to find the answer to a question that is a non-problem that it doesn't really have an
answer so sometimes historically scientists have looked for things that don't exist and they were
just asking the wrong question I would say that today we have made no progress towards giving an
answer to what consciousness is because what I would count as an answer would be if we say what
that something extra is so that I can then go out and figure out whether I can program it into my
phone or not and until I have an answer about what it is such that I can decide whether it's
programable or not we haven't made progress so that just leaves those other two either we're too
stupid or it's not a good question in terms of the intensification I I can always tell you my
reaction to it is is that it we're taking ourselves as humans and our experience a little bit too
seriously as the explanation of of all of you know mental functioning or consciousness or awareness
that you know that that I don't have to just add a fly in the end it's an empirical question you
know we're gonna have to look the only creatures that we can be sure you know are fairly sure
our conscious are creatures that can report it to us which right now is just humans and you know
eventually maybe we'll be able to say in humans what neural processes lead to consciousness and
then maybe we'll be able to look for analogs that in animals and try to cross including
the imperative we don't know what it is and and I I guess the point is we're not going to get there
any more than we could understand quantum mechanics just by thinking about experience we're not
going to understand how the brain works just by thinking about experience it's it's going to be
a deeply empirical question and the answers are going to be you know completely surprising and
not at all what we imagined well that's something else we didn't really talk about today much is
what kinds of neural tools for example might help us so there's a lot of things on the table with
the brain initiative people are trying to figure out better ways of imaging circuits of neurons
rather than just individual neurons or large clusters of neurons I don't personally see how
that's going to lead us to an answer to consciousness but it's a it's a very interesting question is
there some circuit level property that if we understood that we would be in a better position
to understand consciousness or can we even be more articulate than that and say this is the kind
of circuit level property so there's been some efforts to look at the circuits that control the
flow of information on the notion that part of what consciousness is about is what I was calling
selective attention so there are many things you could attend to at any moment but you select
from those possibilities and I think we're on a good track to understand that at the neural level
but if consciousness is this extra thing that goes beyond selective attention then it's not
it's not so clear that getting more information about how the circuitry works is really going
to answer the question I would say I would say we're five or ten levels away of understanding
away from being able to talk maybe 50 or 100 from being able to talk about that I mean at
right now we just we need to understand how the pieces of the brain work to do small bits of
computation which is what we're going to understand from these studies looking at many more neurons
at once and then we're going to have to build up multiple levels of understanding of the brain
before we can never really get to this place we all want to get to now because it's what interests
us so much which is to say you know well what is it about neural processing that is a recent
conscious that's that's it isn't to say that by adding lots of neurons now we're going to solve
that by adding lots of neurons now we're going to help build the next level to the next level of the
next level and I don't know how many levels that before we finally get asking those questions
I think we need to go to the next question otherwise people there's quite a few people waiting so let's
we've reached two hours so we're out of time technically no we started at two-thirds it's not
four o'clock yet so go ahead hi there my name is Joe Russo I'm a web developer and just yeah we're
at the one and a half curious person what we're at the 90 minute mark we were just given incorrect
information very good I was wondering your thoughts on when there are people having near
death experiences and there are basically a lot of things shut down in their body and then they
they come and they're brought back some some who happen to be brought back claim to have
experiences of of certain kinds of things and it makes me wonder if perhaps the the biological
armor that we're sort of equipped with now is just simply one potential place where
the experience of consciousness and interaction and all that other individuality and all that
stuff occurs but it isn't necessarily recorded what are your thoughts on that the movie flatliners
talks about that a little bit too it's great so I didn't understand the question the question is
that we don't just say it again I was wondering your thoughts on the idea of them maybe consciousness
doesn't even require a body per se it may be something that actually can can have a persistence
without having biological home to live in one thing that comes to mind is like you know ducks
flying and they're kind of communicating and they have this real this really elegant harmonious
kind of interaction that goes on and granted yes they have little duck brains that hold their
little thoughts and everything but there is also this interaction that seems to happen between them
in the air and makes me think that this idea of consciousness of thinking of self-awareness
all these things that many of the things that we've been talking about you've been talking about today
may be piggybacking as it were off of biology but not even necessarily be necessary so there is hope
for the iPhone still well I think all of us would categorically reject that but we could we could
talk about why as well I mean there is some some interesting work about modules in the brain you
know stonice love to hane for example has this blackboard view that it's sort of like a working
memory buffer analog and sort of like your ducks that certain basic modules like s1 m1 v1
aren't conscious but there's a place where you can put their information into a buffer and this
buffer has the property of consciousness so we wouldn't be totally rejecting if we were to say
that maybe these network models that suggest that there's a way of bringing modules online
and this is the one theoretical model this blackboard model that's quite interesting with some
empirical data with it but not embodiment which if I think what you were getting at I don't think
we we've got I mean the idea that you can just leave the brain and the body behind I mean it's
about it's about what it feels like to us it feels like our our mind is disembodied it feels like
our mind floats free of any material substrate we would all agree that's a new one but yeah I mean
the fact is you know any any piece of your mind can be destroyed by destroying some
appropriate piece of your brain your mind can be split up in so many completely non-intuitive
surprising ways by losing bits and pieces of your brain yes you know and don't depress us
do they don't depress us and all of us up here are physicalists so we're we're arguing a little bit
about whether iPhones might possibly be conscious we don't really have the definitions and so forth
but all of us think that whatever consciousness is as a physical basis so we all agree that as a
biological basis in us a physical biological basis in us and we hold open the question
depending on how you define things for whether it might have a different kind of physical basis in
some other kind of creature as Matthew pointed out in the beginning but we all think that has a
physical basis I'll say one sentence about near-death experiences the only sentence I'm going to say
which is there's some very interesting work by Philip Lieberman who's a linguist and a mountain
climber about what happens when you lack oxygen and your your brain gets distorted not surprisingly
near-death experiences fall from my mind in the same category what happens when you don't have
enough oxygen doesn't tell us anything about consciousness and I can I just say that the brain
look everything you're seeing and experiencing now it's not like a camera opening its lens it's a
computation your brain is computing this whole scene from the sensory information it's receiving
brains sometimes compute hallucinations sometimes compute distortion they compute you can experience
all kinds of things it doesn't mean they're out there it means that's what your brain is doing right
now okay there's an additional thing that should we throw in I think all of us are physicalists not
only with respect in mind and consciousness but with respect everything that is everything has a
physical basis yeah I wanted to say I'm as interesting and make one comment and then
quit comments and then ask the question the quick comment is just my opinion the early on
the issue of definitions came up and I for one think that it is not just important to define
things clearly that it's essential to define them precisely and because if you don't as many
scientists agree and it seems would seem to be logically obvious if you don't define your terms
you do not know what you are talking about so that's the point I wanted to make
then the question I have has to do with all the talk about the rights room let's say I have a
million questions on the subject but derives from the issue of motivation there are certain
presumptions and assumptions that underlie that if you're talking about motivation as how it
affects the brain and its development of consciousness well let me just step back one second I won't
take it on the issue of definitions I think the example of it is how we in the discussion today
there was a great deal of confusion and imprecision in the terms consciousness awareness thinking
and so on there was talk about senses I didn't hear anyone say anything about conceptual
consciousness which I think is specifically what was referred to by consciousness sometimes
other times it was used in a general way then it went this is whisked like all kinds of
confusion you know this perceptual consciousness sensual consciousness there's all kinds there's all
you're sent an awareness let's say and thinking and the difference between that and thinking what is
thinking I didn't hear a definition of thinking so and it's a simple thing to do I would say but
let's back it into that now because it will become a more story my question is this on the motivation
if you're going to get into motivation you have to get into free will because something has to cause
it and what I'm thinking of I know that logically or philosophically to take the position of determinism
is self-contradiction but when you think about what happens when you make a choice when a consciousness
makes a choice that requires action and sends a message to pick up the glass of water or whatever
it was then there's a change of state somewhere in the brain and you get an infinite regress if you
try to explain it because according to the laws of physics physical you're all physical guides here
the laws governing motion are pretty well determined for everything you have electrons you have molecules
and so on and then you make the decision to do something the instant before that in order to send
that message down a neuron something physical has to initiate it and I think that's where the real
real serious mystery lies because what is what is the cause of that change when you make a decision
how can you translate your decision into motion if you say well because this atom moved over this
electron moved over there well how did it move what's physically what moved in and then you give
that answer you say well oh okay because the electric potential change well then what changed
it well because this or then what changed it and you get into an infinite regress and it seems
incapable of solution that's the mystery to me and that's what I want to ask you if you have
any comments so I don't accept the infinite regress argument I think people are actually
making progress on cases like that so first of all I do accept your criticism that our definitions
are really shoddy and I think our definitions are really shoddy because for the most part the things
we're talking about don't have facts of the matter in the world so my example on this point was about
whether airplanes fly there is no fact in the matter world about whether airplanes fly it's
definitional you can choose to make that definition with respect to some other problem but there is
no fact in the matter in the world and so it's hard to make those definitions I'm not going to let
you take another question because there are other people waiting on the infinite regress part however
what I will say is that people like 10 people who do molecular computational neuroscience
so that people working in those two domains have made some real progress at looking at things
like signal transduction where they look at the individual molecules that are just involved in
very very low to sit low level decision making where we have a little bit of a cognition on one side
and we have molecular events that we can actually identify and manipulate and so forth so I think
there's real progress there I don't know that we've made any progress at all in understanding
consciousness but in decision making we really have I really can't we really
just another question just really give me a answer my question because my question is
where does the free will or the conscious consciousness where is the point at which it enters that first
pause that makes the physical thing process I think it's a mistake to think of keep it
a finite physical process where is the entry point of your free will okay Matthew so so I tend to think
of identity as a content so to say to say that I did something is to say that that action is
responsible to my values and my beliefs at a point in time that is to say that I can take ownership
of the action is expressing who I am well but what I think is that who I am the values and beliefs
are represented their physical patterns of activation and so to say at what point does the physical
pattern of activation well actually there we know how to implement inferences and and to like
translate from you know statements of values and statements of beliefs to inferences that say
certain actions are the best actions that respond to those things and it's it's completely mechanical
the mistake is to think that the your identity the meaningful what's meaningful about who you are
is separate from the physical instantiation that's making it all possible it's a way of looking at
the physical instantiation that's making it all possible and so that's why you can make decisions
because your brain makes you and it makes the decisions and it makes them match two two two
answers your point about definitions and I absolutely agree the kind of science that I do
and it kind of operational definition to essential on the other hand when we have quite
nebulous things like thinking and consciousness operational definitions are possible and I agree
with you but they're going to be fuzzy just like there's going to be a discussion potentially about
art here one day no one's going to come up with the fundamental definition of art it doesn't mean
you kind of interesting conversations about it beauty is another term so I would say that we are at
the intersection between philosophy and science where strict operational definitions are not
available yet but I agree with you and the second point about the the start point I think you're
right that to talk about where did it start an infinite regress is to say that we have a t zero
but we don't really have a t zero right in other words I'm in this room right now I'm biased towards
being in this room there's a cup in front of me so there's a little bit of a biasing towards my
language reach back up I'm in a context where I met at some point reach fit although now it's empty
but um do I know exactly why I chose at this time point to go for it versus plus or minus five
seconds on either side no okay but I definitely know that I'm in the context biasing me towards
certain behaviors so there's no real t zero you see that's the mistake I think is that we're
in this ever lengthening context with many different shells of time to it which all bias you towards
certain behaviors because you're in it and so no I know and that might see a little bit indeterminate
but being in a room in front of a cup was something that I decided to do so in other words I think
that by t zeroing it the way you are it causes a slightly false infinite regress thank you okay
next you can always approach the participants' labels
so just a couple quick observations leading to the question about the the role that hasn't really
been addressed of ecological context in which brains operate number one and the role in
computational neurobiology of local minimum and maxima so in terms of ducks for example and fish
birds flocking behavior we actually do know it's not ephemeral that it is the relationship of keeping
the fish or bird next to you in front of you at a certain average distance at all times so it's
simple but it is a social ecological context in which neural processing is occurring so that's my
entry point to this I wanted to follow up on the first question about quorum sensing because I
think the response took it wrongly I think it was more about again the social context not about one
portion of a brain but one brain in an ecological context of other brains quorum sensing is ubiquitous
it occurs in bacteria we can simulate it very nicely so I'm asking the question if consciousness
is an emergent phenomena that is somewhat proportional to the degree of neuro complexity in a social
species cats have a neuro cortex but it's smooth but the neocortices of more highly insephalized
complex and sephalization in social mammals they tend to we tend to look at them and see more of
our behavior and sensitivity elephants are looked at as quite emotionally sensitive for example
we are very similar the question is not whether we are similar to champion
champions champions ease for example a lot of behaviors they do everything from deception
to certain social aggressions and the rest of it so my question is how would you address the again
the ecological context of neurobiology and how that interaction might affect the local minimum
maxima that can lead to a decision point that's it I mean I don't think any of us would challenge
the notion that the social component is important there's a interesting new book which I have not
finished yet by Michael Graziano that tries to give an account of consciousness evolutionarily
in terms of social function you know whether you buy that argument partly depends on how you
ground the definitions of consciousness in the first place so if you accepted my example of
the worm you'd say well the worms got some modicum of awareness but it's not social or maybe it is
socially you could probably argue that part too so me again there's a there's a grounding issue but
I think Graziano has has some interesting arguments there and I don't think any one of us would want
to deny that the social component is really important certainly to our subjective experience of the
world I think we might make the argument that in order to understand that ultimately we need to
catch that out in terms of my brain internal experiences how they cope with the information
that comes from the outside world we don't want to say that you know information from the ecological
and environment or the social environment isn't really crucial to the kind of experience that we
have some of what we were trying to grapple with here is why does the experience have that we have
have the flavor that it does so why does pain seal the way that it does and presumably social
things should enter into an answer for that we just haven't figured out what would count as an
answer but when we get there that should be part of it I just want to say that I'm saying
that's the inverse I'm very concerned but I want to make sure the question is taken properly
in my view it's not that we're coping with the social ecological context of others in our species
it's that we need that my my small hypothesis is that consciousness emerges in our species because
we even have the facial frequencies of one gyrus which is about to focus precisely on details in
the facial facial musculature and motion of others in our species so that's my question
the only look I can't say much about the social except obviously we're very social creatures and
that was involved in our brains evolving but I just want to caution against taking familiar
familiarity as humans with something essential about consciousness or about minds or about
intelligence I mean the creatures whose behavior seems most familiar to us by and large are the
creatures that were more closely related to and and so you know we have more mental structures
in common with them but it doesn't mean that you know some very distant creatures I mean certainly
crows and parrots and ravens are pretty distant but they're they independently evolved you know
quite a quite a high intelligence but they don't write symposia well neither the dogs are cats or
I just have one point tangential point about your question about the
flocks of birds with these complex structures that's a great analogy and then you said
correctly that the rule that leads to this so-called complex structure is actually quite
simple it's about keeping an average so in other words there are many there are many examples of
this where the phenomenon looks incredibly complex but the rule that leads to this so-called
complexity from our viewpoint is unbelievably simple I'll give you another example a colleague
of mine in california modeled little mice pups that you could film from above and these little
mice pups when they're put in a box make quite complex pinwheel shapes okay and it looks quite
complex and so he said he was going to make some robotic rap pups and he was going to then do
you have to do a sort of like rat touring test you'd watch the film of the digitized real rap
pups and the robot rap pups and he got the rap pups to do the same kind of thing what do you think
the rule was anyone something random simony it was entirely random it was just that the shape
to get to your point of the rap pups plus random behavior led to so-called complexity so I would
say that's the same as consciousness it seems so mysterious and complex to us that we think the rules
that lead to it in the nervous system have to also be very complex to us and what I'm saying
is just like the flock of birds just like the rap pups the rules will turn out to be surprisingly
simple and surprise us and we're going to be entirely wrong it's our incense hubris because
we think it's so mysterious the explanation has going to have to live up to our sense of its
mysterious it does and so I should be happy and keep my mouth checked but okay no no wait we have
to have we have only 10 minutes left and we have still hi uh thematically that's exactly what I
want to ask about it's not I don't really have a question I just wanted you guys to talk a little
bit more about that inflection point and if it's the biology of the mind what's your question point
towards having consciousness would yeah with the worm sorry I looked at you and assembly
knew we were talking about the worm uh that that how biology evolved past that point and if we
stepped forward in time maybe that's the best foil to look at where something more complex emerged
but you know I think it's sobering to realize that you know life was kicking around on this
particular planet for you know three and a half billion years before primates emerged and primates
were kicking around for what 20 million years before 50 uh human or 15 50 million years before
hominids emerged and hominids were kicking around for four or five million years before humans emerged
and you know it there's a whole lot of life and a whole lot of intelligence a whole lot of brains
a whole lot of minds that were happening before human beings happened to pop into the world and
and and speak so uh I I'm worried about the idea that there's some magic you know there's some
inflection point where we where life crosses it and then we're there you know life has gone in lots of
ways and places and intelligence has evolved all over the place I mean octopus octopi are
extremely intelligent by many measures I don't know if they have consciousness but they're they're
smart just that it simplifies the problem a little bit more and I honestly just wanted to hear
knowledgeable people talk about why they think what were the the evolutionary conditions in the
selection why did that the brain take that power reaction I had to your question was to think about
so there has been an inflection point clearly in uh human evolution so we're very different than
our ancestors were 200,000 years ago people kind of slice at 50,000 or 200 they argue about that but
certainly we're pretty different from 200,000 years ago a lot of things have changed since here's a
question that's very app-proposed what we're talking about is was the evolution of some change in
the system of consciousness really important to that so it could be that what really made all
that change was language let's say and maybe that affected consciousness and maybe it didn't and
of course again we don't have a machine we go around and say well our dogs conscious are
bonobos conscious and then we could you know we could look at our ancestors if we had a time
machine too right if we had a time machine and a consciousness meter we would you know be much
better positioned to resolve these arguments but as we don't have either all we can do is
these kind of thought experiments it seems to me like just having language and maybe the ability
to represent hierarchical structures and to care about the intuitive theories or beliefs of others
might be enough and maybe you wouldn't need consciousness but we don't really know so I thought it was
actually a provocative question that was very difficult to answer but I think your point is
well taken that we have to that you know I'll give an example of dexterity right some monkeys cannot
individually their digits and we can't right it's a remarkable change in dexterity and then you
ask well is it a biomechanical or is it neural and we think it's neural and then you start looking
for what is the neural basis for this quite phenomenal leap from being able to really just do this
to be able to do that and you know it's a few connections to the ventral horn a change but it's
not a giant change in the neural mechanisms and yet you get behaviorally a very big change right
so in other words I think what's going to turn out is that there's going there is an inflection
point we're all talking about something that humans have an abundance we haven't defined it but
consciousness and self-awareness we have it nevertheless we have to agree with Ken that it had to be
piggybacking in some incremental way on a nervous system that's been around a very long time so we
have this mismatch between an incremental work on the substrate and what seems to be a very non-linear
change in behavior on the outside but that happens with non-linear systems right so evolution is the
way to get at this and we will answer this how do we get this apparent behavioral leap with a
fairly nondescript change relatively speaking in the brain it wasn't like a whole new lobe suddenly
occurred right so that's the way we're going to have to go if this question is the right one and
the inflection point is something we're going to have to look for and I think we will reverse
engineer it frankly eventually thank you my question is like we say that the mind gets distracted
the drones it it wanders and and like how how is it related to the underlying conscience like
this the the mind being wandering or distracting or running how how does it relate to the underlying
consciousness or subconsciousness and then how does that relate to the firing of the neurons and
like how does this kind of like interlink and which way does it go meaning like does it go from the
mind to the neurons or does it go from the neurons to the mind or like well the second part is the
easier part to answer which is the mind is what the brain does Marvin Minsky said that originally
so it's bi-directional they are they're just descriptions at a different level of the same thing
the way that you can have physics and chemistry they're both true it's not that one is true and
then makes the other one happen they're both simultaneously true and so we're really talking
about different languages to describe the same phenomena we're talking about using psychological
terms versus using neural terms in terms of the mind wandering stuff that you started with well
that's about how the brain decides which information to follow at a given moment so for example we are
distractible if there was suddenly a loud noise you'd stop paying attention to what i'm doing and
if you stop paying attention to what i was talking about you might at that point start thinking about
your laundry and this is a risky avenue for me to talk about because you might start thinking
about your laundry don't think about pink elephants anyone please um but so we have some machinery
that govern basically our train of thought i mean i think that that Freud and James and so forth
thinking about stream of consciousness had something to it there there's filtering that we use to
decide which stimulus should i pay attention to at a particular moment and account so it was mind
wandering if your brain says i should pay attention to this thing they'd say of immediate importance
even though i had decided i should be paying attention to my class and there's kind of very
there's i mean there are different neural structures responsible for doing parts of
attention but there's a there's an area which in monkeys is called lip lateral interpridal
which is involved in in aspects of monitoring visual salience as to what you get the attention
and there's an experiment that was done by micky golberg and jane beasley at columbia where
they record from lip and the monkey is fixating and then it um it gets shown a target that says
when the fixation light goes off sicada move your eyes over there and you'll get a reward and then
while it's still fixed so then during that time lip is really representing that area quite a lot
it's saying oh that's very important i'm going to tend to that and then something completely irrelevant
flashes over here well lip represents that briefly uh but it goes away again because it's irrelevant
and it turns out the attention you can also measure where the animal's attention is by various
tricks and the animal's attention goes to the distractor precisely when the lip activity for
the distractor is higher than the lip activity for the target and when it comes down again when the
when the hill crosses that's when the attention switches back so that's a neural correlate of
there's something there that where you know you there's something there that you're not
attending to but it's still represented and then you come back to it when it gets to the the
the biggest hill that's that's one example of some correlate between neurons and what you're
asking about thank you um my question is one of the problems that you have in discussing consciousness
is that we talk about it as a unitary phenomenon but it's really there are levels of consciousness
even within the same individual so you can go from coma to acute awareness to meditation and
then the other levels in between so um greenfield who's like a neurobiologist has studied
different neural populations that she found that very small groups she calls them neural
assemblies very small units are very briefly um activated and then disappear and she would link
that more with a transient awareness maybe something like children have maybe animals other species
but as consciousness as we call it like really attending builds up you find connections between
the different neural assemblies and they're more long lasting and then out of that even
of experience of self emerges from you know but it what it's really dealing with is going from
let's say a coma state where almost nothing is happening where maybe um you can activate someone
who's deeply unaware am I saying imagine yourself playing tennis you know they've done that experiment
and they see on an fMRI the that area of the brain lights up so that brain of a deeply comatose
person is indistinguishable from an aware person but obviously that person is not conscious um but
in a conscious person you see many more areas activate so what we would call consciousness is
more like a global long lasting level of activity and the experience of the individual as to whether
or not they're really present in the moment or they're just um you know being activated bombarded
with stimuli has to do with how much of the brain is functioning at the same time then the other
um caveat is that the right and left sides of the brain have different styles of functioning and
the right hemisphere processes in a more global very quick way and we call that unconscious it
doesn't have language and when it gives some kind of message when you sleep on what you get when
you wake up in the morning it then transfers to a more conscious of verbal which it pay we pay a
price for the consciousness because it takes time you have to think about each detail and then come
up with a decision like you're fed that information from your global intuitive side thank you i just
don't want us to clarify the age of an experience very grief yeah the adrena experiment i mean i
think to the audience it's very important to distinguish what neurologists mean by the word
unconscious and conscious when it comes to coma versus what we mean by consciousness that's
totally different things and to adren o n when they did that experiment on the tennis those
patients were not in coma in fact the whole argument was these were the people who were being
deemed to be in coma the bedside by neurologists but in fact what was called minimally conscious
state so in fact it it's they're not in coma with a fragment of consciousness they're not in coma
okay next briefly yes move be brief i'm going to toss this at uh professor morkers first
i want the comments of the other members of the panel there's been a lot of discussion about
definition and i'd like to ask you to comment on the valid solid definition that general
element offers for consciousness self-awareness the ability to project into the future reflect
on the past language use uh whether you might comment on his very concrete definition of consciousness
which rises out of biological levels what i would say is that all of those things are well two
points all those things are not a few points you have two other people away the one point
can do all of those but it doesn't get at whether there's something extra thanks for
i'm missing two things first is the female presence on the panel i think that would have
added something secondly i'm always too easy to get to you
mate um secondly that is an old problem that is the ambiguous ends of the day
secondly i uh you're speaking a language it's very different from my language i come back from a
psychoanalytic background and the unconscious is so important to this institution and i feel like
i'm missing something today i feel like i'm missing you using the word unconscious i haven't heard
it much and i uh to be brief i would be interested in who given your expertise in the research lab
who who is uh approaching uh your terminology from a psychoanalytic perspective who's doing
critical research today on brain functioning and the unconscious as it's used in the psychoanalytic
community and as most people are aware of uh psychoanalysis was more or less uh left out of the
academic community as our civilization has evolved because of its lack of research and ability to
have control groups so my last question is what is the hope for psychoanalysis to be included in
academia again in this world of research well there's a lot of work being done okay implicit bias
a lot of work being done in that which you could argue the psychoanalytic you about before um
all the unconscious processing work that i discussed that people like Tim Shallis are doing
huge amount of fascinating neuroscience who's doing so Tim Shallis for example has written very well
about this there's a lot of work on cognitive processes that are below the level of awareness
so implicit bias that kind of work priming right i mean you could argue that what goes on the
psychoanalytic is just a higher level version of of being primed in some way by your experiences so
it may not look to you like it's in the domain of the phenomenology you like but at the level of
proteins that beneath the level of awareness huge amount of neuroscience the problem is that most
of the research done in neuroscience does not have to do with what you are saying what he said is
not really the same unconscious you are talking about you are talking about what Freud called the
dynamic unconscious and uh to my knowledge there is very little work on the dynamic unconscious
and in my own personal view is that psychoanalysts first need to define that better than they have
uh starting with Freud's original work i also just say that most neuroscience is not
at the high cognitive level at all it's it's at levels of just understanding how basic little
pieces of neural circuit to work and do very small things that are very far from cognitive
processing little unconsciousness um so you know we we're just a long way from that level of understanding
in the brain okay thank you one more question i have two very different questions the first one is
assuming based on very poor science i know that it was true how do you integrate healing at a distance
and sending messages that a distance into the biology of mind that's my first question my second
question is related to basically what was stimulated by our uh Cambridge speaker uh when we have a
slalom at the olympics and they're going down and we know that they're using a long term i'm using
his words long-term motor skill learning and its relationship to higher cognitive processes
such as decision making how much is body language that is learned does that put you at a lower or a
higher level of mind and consciousness in terms of the first this is the last this was the last
question so in turn to the first one the the mind's talking to each other to distance or healing at
a distance i think i you know at least for myself i would say i don't believe in it and um until
somebody can scientifically demonstrate that it happens i'm not going to try to explain it because
i don't think it happens yeah so um just one general point i think i i think what Ken said is something
that for us who do psychology neuroscience is very important we talked about consciousness today but
we're far from being in a position scientifically i mean understanding that explanation in other
words even now when it says looking at little circuits and they explain behavior we do a very
poor job with even that right in other words it's the unspoken elephant in the room that we're not
really that good at extrapolating from the behavior of neurons to behaviors we can correlate
but the understanding is very poor so we have to be super super modest we do a really bad job
even the low level stuff and here we are talking about consciousness that's why philosophy is
a very important and psychologist before we get to the neurons okay to the skill thing
um i don't quite get your question in other words what are you saying being good at something
physical makes you less cognitive is that what you say no i'm saying that they spend a long time
long time learning uh how to move their bodies but they make decisions at the same time that
they're going down that slalom there is conscious thinking too so i'm just asking where do you put
the learned body language is this now back to more a reflex response or are you dealing with a very
advanced response yes it's a great question it's about the role of the motor the role of the motor
system that is connected to consciousness yeah well yeah i control powers about that yeah okay
thank you very much