Good afternoon, everyone.
I'm Gerald Horowitz. I'm the Associate Director of Helix Center and I apologize for the delay
in our getting started. One of our participants due to a family emergency is unable to make
this talk on misinformation, coding and misinformation, and the birth of NFTs. And I'll say a word
or two about what we're thinking this topic will be about, but the participants are going
to be the ones who really help decide, and you'll decide among yourselves whether they're
telling you the truth or not. Let me say something first about Laura Edelson, who's not here,
unfortunately, but I'll give a brief description. She is a post-doc researcher at NYU with
the Cybersecurity for Democracy Project, which she co-directs with Damon McCoy. There she
leads the observatory and the ob-observer projects, which aim to increase public transparency
of digital advertising, particularly during elections.
We have here with us today, Susanna Martinez-Khande. Is that the way to say it? Isn't that good?
She is an award-winning neuroscientist, author and a professor at the State University of
New York, Downstate Health Sciences University. She is the founder and executive director
of the annual Best Illusion of the Year contest, which inspired her most recent book, Champions
of Illusion, published by Ferro Strauss and Jerome. Her first book, The International Best
Seller, Sleight of Hands, Sleight of Mind, What the Neuroscience of Magic reveals about
our everyday deceptions was published by Holt and won the Prisma Prize for Best Science
Book of the Year. Martinez-Khande is one of the premier science communicators in the United
States and has made television appearances on the National Geographic's channels, redesigned
my brain, discovery channels, head games, the daily planet, PBS' Nova, Star Talk, CBS,
Sunday Morning and the World According to Jeff Goldblum.
Sidney Gess is an assistant professor of politics and public affairs at Princeton University.
His research and teaching interests lie at the intersection of political communication,
public opinion and political behavior. Via a combination of experimental methods, large
datasets, machine learning and innovative measurement, he studies how people choose,
process, spread and respond to information about politics. Recent work investigates the
extent to which online Americans, news habits are polarized. The popular echo chamber hypothesis
patterns in the consumption and spread of online misinformation and the effectiveness
of efforts to counteract misperceptions encountered on social media.
Yotem up here. Is that, did I get to? Yeah, good. He's saying good enough. Thank you.
He's an assistant professor of communication at the University of Buffalo. His work combines
computational methods for text mining, network analysis, experiments and surveys to study
media content and effects in the areas of political science and health communication.
Dr. O'Pyr authored and co-authored more than 300 peer reviewed academic papers published
in journals such as the American Journal of Public Health, Health Security, Tobacco Regulatory
Science, Risk Analysis, plus one Journal of Communication, Communication Research, Public
Understanding of Science, Journal of Public Health at Health Communication, Communications
Methods and Measures and more. So with that, we're going to get started. I'll after I
take my seat. Okay, so I'm interested in getting things underway and I invite any of
the three of you to jump in and express at least some sort of ideas about what you're
seeing, what everyone of us, I think, is seeing in our culture about misinformation, polarization,
etc. And obviously because the conference is on coding, we're interested in sort of how
digitalization of information may be playing a role in this. So who wants to start?
Okay, I'll offer a sort of starting idea and you'll feel free to sort of revise that
or throw it away later, but just to get things started. I think part of what's happening
or what has been happening is that we have incredible digital communication technologies
that have enabled many people who previously were not able to express themselves at the
sort of ease and scale that they can now. And this created a lot of opportunities for
different people, different perspectives in different groups to express themselves in
society and also to engage with society and participate in society in new ways that I
think have sort of cut against the usual kinds of inequalities. However, what that also means,
another way of saying that is that sort of traditional gatekeepers, including gatekeepers
of information, have lost their kind of received power. And so kind of a flip side of that
potentially is that gatekeepers who exist to kind of maintain hierarchies but also to
vet information for better or for worse, have lost some other additional power. And so one
of the big questions today is sort of who or what, including technologies, is replacing
these kind of standard gatekeepers that have been in place for, let's say, 100 years.
And how do we as society sort of adapt to this new reality?
And I can add to that from a neuroscientific perspective, our brains are not wired to
multitask. It's the opposite. We're wired to pay attention to one thing and one thing
only and suppress everything else. What happens is that when we are pulled in all directions,
we cannot really pay attention to more than one thing at once and arrive to any type of
quality judgment or performance. This is something that happens in magic shows, actually magicians
get us to multitask in a magic show, they split our attention, and that's how they get
away with magical murder. What happens this day is that with all this digital content
and social media, this is really pushing our capabilities to pay attention to the limit.
And so we are, it's very taxing to be able to determine what actual data, what's misinformation,
because everything seems to have the same priority and we are not focusing and analyzing
in any depth for any length of time.
I mean one of the big questions that I think are on my mind recently, is are we really in
a new era of post truth? I mean, because you hear it everywhere, right? That we move to
a different time in human history, but it's not clear to me based on the empirical work
that we've been conducting and based on reviews of previous eras that really crossed a rubric
on to a different time in terms of relationship between humans and truth or humans and information.
I'm wondering in recent years why is everybody so preoccupied with misinformation now? It
wasn't like that 10 years ago, right? When I started, I'm relatively, this guy is new
in the area, but when I started in 2010 to look into misinformation was kind of a niche
topic in social sciences. I wonder if something really changed in the way we communicate with
one another or some external events happen that kind of pushed us to look for explanations.
In other words, are we sitting here because something really changed in how we use media
or are we sitting here because we're still trying to explain to ourselves the 2016 election?
Yeah, what is going on? Well, this reminds me of, I think there's sort of two general
classes of commentators on what's going on with us. So the one class says, oh my God,
this is completely different. We're really in trouble. And then I'm sure you've all seen
other articles that suggested, oh no, back in 1820, there was just as much politicization.
Maybe there was more people were fist fighting in the Capitol building, et cetera. If it's
true that there was an earlier period where there was more of this sort of fermentation
of politicization, can we see anything in common then from now? Is it possible to draw a line
between those two processes? Yeah, I mean, yeah, I know it could please go ahead.
I think they work fundamentally the same people that we were a couple of hundred years ago
and even much earlier. And we are, actually we have the capability and even you could
save the drive to lie and to deceive the brain is the great story better. And we try to make
sense of reality by telling stories about what's happening to others as well as to ourselves
and that we make incorrect connections between cause and effect that has always happened.
And even if something as easy as trying to trick somebody into thinking that we're interested
in something that we're not or the other way around, we are able as primates, we are able
to pay attention to something that we're not looking at for will intend to deceive for
the primates to do this as well. But not every species is able to do it to dissociate what
they're looking at from the place that they're actually paying attention to. So we have these
mechanisms that are inherent to our brains that we have always lied to one another. I
think what's different now is the tools that we have accessible to us. And I think that
it used to be much easier if you don't know is this true or is this a false hood and you
go and you try different sources and you can arrive to the veracity or particular issue,
I think much more in a much more reliable way. I mean, even today you see an image, you see
a video or an audio record. You cannot really tell if this is manipulated or not. This did
not used to be the case.
And I guess misinformation has always been there. It's not a new phenomenon. The only
thing that seems to me is new is more people have access to internet and so on, which allows
them to express their opinions, which before they had no access. So if, let's say, you
were organizing a coup in a foreign country, you gave a story about what was happening
that was in the papers and everybody accepted and nobody said, and if you knew information
that countered the motives that were expressed, you couldn't make it public because there
was no outlet. Now you have questions about, I don't know, whatever political issue, you
immediately put it on the internet and you have an opinion and then other people follow
you. And of course, part of the problem is the more you claim to have some kind of conspiracy
behind it, the more excited you make people get and the more you have tension.
Yeah, I think, I mean, one way of kind of restating a part of what you said is that
propaganda has always been with us. It's traditionally been the domain of elites and
today, the ability to produce propaganda, like a lot of things, has been democratized.
So now anyone can sort of make up their own stories and they can have it disseminated
instantaneously at great and unprecedented scale. So that's one thing that has changed.
Right. And there are positive aspects to it because, like you said, there used to be
like a one version of the truth and there was no questioning and that I'm thinking,
well, something that I'm afraid about is the flu of 1918, what we call the Spanish flu,
when it turns out it did not originate in Spain, actually it's still debated, were it
actually? China, right. Sorry. Start a new rumor. Exactly. So, but the point is that
apparently it is the case that the Spanish newspapers were the ones that were not lying
about the numbers, other places were suppressing that information. So that's how it became
to be known as the Spanish flu. But so that was like, I kind of like a worldwide misinformation
back then, 100 years ago. Right. There may have been this sort of also this movement
going back to their early 19th century where one of the pieces of propaganda was that our
elected officials were dependable, reliable, they were reliable elitists and they were
going to tell you the truth. And that was a useful bit of propaganda to a degree. I mean,
you know, I don't want to sound too cynical about it, but that was a story and narrative
that many people in the United States accepted true or false, but they accepted it, but it
may have done some good because people said, well, I can look to this authority to establish
the truth or falseness. Now we have politicians in this article this morning in New York Times
that shows the number of Republican candidates who deny the results of the 2020 election.
The majority of them deny the results. We're, it's interesting, fake news was is the claim
of the people who've been creating a lot of the fake news, right? So they're not only
producing fake news, but they're undermining everyone's faith in any authority to set
the strength. The term fake news has come to me in something different that it used to
mean some years ago, but it is true. I mean, something that it is not just trusting politicians
and trusting governments, but I believe in trusting in scientists actually, we just published
a paper in which we found in an international sample that the willingness to be vaccinated
for COVID-19, the parameter that was mostly related to with one's willingness to be vaccinated
was trust in scientists. And when this trust in scientists is not there anymore, then you
have people who are thinking, well, why should I be vaccinated? I can do my own research.
And I think that that's what we're seeing also that anybody can do their own research.
And everybody can be an expert. There is no separation between expert opinion and the
opinion that basically anybody could have in any field.
I think if there's one thing, political scientists in my field of political science,
it's the one thing that we have found time and time again is that trust is this core
ingredient in making democracy work. And it's trust in institutions, trust in scientists.
I would add maybe trust in the news media, trust in some basic quality sources of information
about society, just trust is the thing that makes things run more smoothly. And when you
lose that, things can come apart. And so this conversation is making me ask, on the one
hand, trust is good. It has a lot of beneficial properties. But does trust also come with a
cost? So what are we giving up in order to maintain high levels of trust? I think you
suggested one, which is that if we sit on one extreme blind trust, you could blindly
trust the government, you could blindly trust what the news tells you. And we've just seen
through history that that too can have its pitfalls. And so maybe just I don't really
have an answer to this, just to pose it as a dilemma. But I might suggest that there
are perhaps different sort of equilibria that might work. So you could have a high trust
equilibrium where there are perhaps more established gatekeepers, there are more transparent institutions
and people understand how that works. And then we're in the process of moving to another
equilibrium and we haven't quite figured out what that looks like, but it's a destabilizing
period.
And I think that perhaps, I mean, we're trying, I feel like the conversation that we're having
is that it's top down. What can we do to achieve a balance or what should we do that so that
society has a diversity of sources of information, but maybe not too much diversity or maybe
another everybody's opinion should be way the same. I think that perhaps it's a, I don't
have an answer, but maybe we can, there are certainly positives in having accessibility,
having access to all of these kinds of forms of information, even fake news. But what we
are lacking is education. And I think that what we, some of the things that we need to
as a society is to empower individuals and that in the educational systems, I feel like
even today children are not giving the tools to develop critical thinking to be able to
face and evaluate all of these alternative and competing sources of information. So that's
a serious lack.
I want to build on something that Andy said, I think it's a healthy thing to be skeptical.
We are scientists. That's what we do. That's our job, right? I mean, our job is to be skeptical
to a healthy degree to question knowledge even after it's been established and so on. But
what we've, what we're seeing in recent years is kind of a shift that I see as dangerous
from skepticism to cynicism. And I think it has a lot to do with this erosion interest
in institutions of knowledge that's actually predates the internet and social media. I
mean, you can choose a lot of random points to kind of start the discussion of it, but
I'll choose for now the early 90s where conservative talk radio shows like Rush Limbaugh and a
few years later Fox News were launching these campaigns against the institution of knowledge
if it's the mainstream media, if it's the scientific community, basically a populist
argument that elites are lying to you and they're not working for you. I think this
is where you start to see the beginning of the process that we're in the middle of right
now. In the last six years or so, I believe that the Trump presidency pushed it even
farther by not so much spreading specific lies, but challenging the epistemology of
knowledge. I mean, what does it even mean to know something? Who should we trust and
who shouldn't we trust? If you look at Trump's making arguments, for example, and I'm sorry
that I'm making it about Trump a bit too tempting, but all those, all those sayings
that people are saying, right? I mean, Trump says people are saying that the elections
were stolen and now we should accept that as a source of knowledge. The whole perception
that there is no reliable source of knowledge, that everything is subjective and everything
is an attempt to push in the agenda of sorts, is I think kind of the cause of where we are
right now.
In our first panel this morning, Jorgi Bizaki was mentioning how so many of the facts that
we think we know that we ascribe to, we don't know firsthand. We get them from our parents
or from other authorities and we don't have the time to go and validate everyone, every
one of them. If the world's in a state of chaos and it's making everyone anxious and
I think rightfully it's making many people anxious, one thing to say is, well, one thing
to hope for is that you have a great leader who's going to help communicate to you why
you need to stay calm and carry on. And the other thing that can happen is leaders could
say, no, you're right to be anxious, the elites are screwing you and there's a conspiracy
going on. And weirdly enough, that conspiracy thinking, I think puts some of their minds
partially at ease because I think, well, now I have an explanation for why this is going
on rather than having anything more meaningful. I just want to say one other thing, I'm a
physician and I treat a lot of, I'm a psychiatrist and many patients will come to me and complain
about their doctors, their non psychiatric doctors, their primary care doctor or their
cardiologist, whatever. Can you believe he didn't do this or say this or do this test
or she didn't do this or? And I'm skeptical about the quality that some of these patients
may get from time to time. Some of it's excellent, but some of it's not so good. But I always
say to these patients, like, listen, if you want to go with the numbers, go toward the
doctor and do what they tell you, okay, because, you know, it's not perfect, but it's better
than you staying away and thinking you're going to figure this out on your own, right?
So maybe that's a weak argument in favor of trusting authority. You say, look, you're
better off of just imagining them to be honest and fair to you. It's pretty difficult with
what's being advertised these days, right?
And it's true that we need to develop some sort of algorithms for what you should trust
and what you should. Because nobody has the time or the resources to question everything.
And it seems that from regular skepticism about the particular sense of claims, we have a
right-to-situation in which everything is set for questioning. It is different to question.
I believe two vaccines cause autism, right? That has been debunked many times. But from
there, we shouldn't, you know, go on and question whether the Earth maybe is flat and that there's
actually a flat Earth society. I don't know how serious they are. But yeah, I think that
goes again, I think, to the issue of like the expertise. Do we even rely or do we even trust
to recognize that there is an actual thing as an expertise and who gets to be an expert
and who gets to have an opinion that should be valued?
There was this movement that's going on now for many years now. I think it's a high-frequency
trading in the stock market, right? Where these transactions are occurring way faster than
human beings can involve. And I mention that because apparently it does have an impact
that the speed of these transactions has an impact on the dynamics of the market. So I'm
wondering about, because this is a talk after all about coding and digitalization and such,
we are getting a much faster feedback by the social media outlets that are tailoring the
news items we get in a much higher rate. I wonder what you all think about that as a
phenomenon.
I mean, I think you're absolutely right that the velocity, the sheer velocity of information
is increasing. And, you know, I think the most common response to this that I've seen
is that people become overwhelmed and just tune out. So news avoidance is now like a
term for it. There's a phenomenon of news avoidance. People just turn it off. They pay
less attention. The flip side of that is people who actually do want to inject the information
into their veins can do so at the most extreme rate that was never before possible. And so
you have super engaged people who want to consume every little bit of content and are
sort of mainlining like Twitter or TikTok or whatever it is. And then you have everyone
else who's sort of not as engaged. And, you know, that creates a whole set of new problems
for itself, because then you have, imagine the feedback, you have, you know, you have
content producers, you have information sources that are now catering, whether they're fully
aware of it or not to these like most hyper engaged consumers whose interests may or may
not reflect those of the rest of society. And we don't consume all information equally
because we are all subjective to cognitive biases, you know, confirmation bias. We hear
what we want to hear and that this piece of information that is supporting my prior view,
I'm going to really go deep into it and I'm going to process it in high detail with high
focus and that this other piece of information that goes against my views, I'm just going
to ignore, keep scrolling. So, and I think that the fact that we have so many source
information coming at us with high speed and high amount, this only serves to exacerbate
the cognitive biases that we already have because we're overwhelmed all the time and
just defaulting to these ingrained ways of thinking. So, I think it is harder to change
minds today than it used to be.
I know in magic, one of the things they'll do is they'll get you to look here and you
look there and they're getting you to confirm some false belief quickly, right? One, two,
three, and then the trick goes, that takes place, right? And that's a little bit of what's
going on with this, I think, right? There's all this sort of false and it's at least emotionally
stirs you up.
Yeah, absolutely. There's probably a paper about what the psychology and neuroscience
of magic tell us about misinformation because there are so many parallels.
I think the word emotional is key here because when you talk about polarization and the way
the algorithms are maybe pushing us towards our own views, it's important to remember
that most people don't care about politics or don't understand politics at all. I feel
like what we do see right now is a lot of emotionality, a lot of affective polarization,
right? I mean, I hate conservatives or I hate liberals. I mean, I just can't stand them
and what they represent, this kind of sentiment is more driving people than actual understanding
of policy or, you know, deep ideological views. Most people don't care about politics at all
or I understand very little about it. But it seems like more and more we are occupied
with feeling about the other side. That's what I see. I don't think we are more politically
sophisticated now than 10 years ago.
More and more we are.
Say again, sorry?
You said it's not so much that we are actually interested but we are more and more kind of
preoccupied by it.
I think we are more and more identifying emotionally with one side of the cultural divide that
we have in this country and the more we see ourselves as part of one group and not the
other, the more we seem to hate the other group more than we care about the actual policies
that they are trying to promote.
I think one example of how it's not always just about politics either. I mean, the way
we might or might not be manipulated. One is I'm an infrequent user of Instagram and
I don't use TikTok but I understand Instagram says hey, we have to get more of what TikTok
is doing. So we are going to show little videos.
So they show those ridiculously appealing videos of dogs and cats.
And the next thing I'm going with, before I'm able to break away and that's just plucking
in my emotions. There's nothing typically political. It was the one with the bulldog
with the Trump hat on but aside from that it was just emotionally engaging and they are
very good at it. I was like Doritos. You want to have another one and another one and you
keep going.
But the other topic which is again not really political, maybe it is a little bit, but it's
this article today in the paper about this new finding about Chaucer. I mentioned this
earlier today. So Chaucer has been accused by certain literary experts of having raped
somebody. And in any way being a misogynist and a lot of feminist literary scholars have
been applying feminist analysis to Chaucer as the father of English literature so to speak.
Anyway, someone came up with this wonderful, it seemed to be wonderful and it may not be
because we have to be checked. But the interpretation of these legal documents may mean that it
wasn't the word, it wasn't rape. Anyways, this is a special term they use. They seem
to demonstrate that this was basically, the woman was basically defending herself against
the accusations she left her previous employer too quickly and was taking to Chaucer's and
both of them were in defense of this lawsuit. Anyway, I'm sorry if this is confusing to
her. My point is it may have changed the worldview of many of these people. So I'm thinking,
gee, I wonder how some of these feminist scholars are going to react. And I was really pleased
to see that the ones that were quoted in the New York Times anyway had a really good and
measured response to it. You know, like, well, this doesn't mean that everything we do about
feminist scholarship is now invalidated whether or not this is, whatever this, however this
gets determined. But I knew I was thinking to myself, people are invested in a particular
view, you know, and they almost resist the idea of changing. Like, they will disbelieve
they're a little bit more skeptical of the new finding, let's say, because they want
to hold on to their view of the way things are. And I think that's fascinating because
that's, again, it's not exactly a political case.
Isn't that rational that what you just described?
How do you mean? I mean, like, I've lived, you know, I've lived a number of years, like,
I've educated myself about a topic and I've like developed what I consider to be informed
views about things. Find counter a piece of information that like, maybe challenges some
part of my existing belief structure, like, sure, like, you know, I might be skeptical
of it because it contradicts, like, it contradicts my worldview, which I've rationally, you know,
constructed, of course. But like, it would be very strange from a rational perspective
I were doing counter one piece of information that contradicts what I think and then so totally
changed my opinion, right?
But wouldn't you take pride in thinking that you're open-minded to changing your point
of view? And whether I've changed it, you might say, oh, good.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, but I think open-mindedness doesn't necessarily mean that you are just
like, your opinions are being swayed by every piece of information that you encounter.
And I think sometimes that's the idea that people have when the term sort of open-minded
is used. And I think I actually think that would be irrational and totally unworkable
if people went around the world just totally changing their views based on the last piece
of information that they encounter. I'm caricaturing what you just said, but we have people here
with more expertise who could probably speak to what I'm trying to say. But I guess, you
know, often these kinds of patterns where people say, like, oh, you're resisting this
information. Well, yeah, I mean, of course, people are resisting information that like
challenges their worldview. Like, why would we expect anything otherwise? Scientists do
that all the time.
I guess I'm thinking there's a value in believing in your intellectual indifference to the outcome.
I'm not saying you are going to do that. You're a human being and that's natural, it is natural.
But if you say about people, oh, it's only natural, you're going to be in a camp. That's
the camp you're in. And if you say, well, there's a real value in ascribing to some impartiality.
And I think that we've lost a little bit of that, that there's... Trump made some comments
some time ago that, oh, of course, someone made that decision because they're a democratic
judge. And Justice Roberts said, nothing like democratic judges and Republican judges.
Well, I think this is fascinating because I have to say, I don't know anyone in my circle
who, most of those people do not like Trump whatsoever. I think they all go, yeah, he's
right. Okay. Now, see, to me, that comment of Roberts was prescriptive, not so much descriptive.
Like, it's sort of, yes, we should be able to believe in the indifference of our jurists
because that's really the ideal. You say, well, in a real world, it doesn't work that way.
You're being a fool. You're being naive. But you see, instead of saying, oh, good for
you for supporting the idea of impartiality, you're sort of looked at like you're some
kind of knife, right? I think that's unfortunate. I mean, why not believe impartiality as an
ideal?
Well, I think as long as it's clear that this is aspirational rather than descriptive.
I think impartiality is good, but it depends on what it is about. There are certain things
that you can't be impartial about. So if they told you the best treatment for depression
is to hang yourself, you can't be impartial about such a thing. But I think part of the
issue is to be somewhat somewhat, it's said that skeptical and have a certain more balanced
view is that it helps with anxiety. You can see that in your office, if you have a couple
and one of them doesn't trust the other one, the lack of trust becomes a major preoccupation
going around and around. Next thing you know, they're checking each other's cell phones,
they're doing this. So trust is very important and I think what's happening with all this
misinformation is that you end up diminishing people's trust and therefore you get the kind
of agitation that we've seen, especially in this country a couple years ago where everybody
is so agitated, you have patients who are waking up at two o'clock, three o'clock, four o'clock
in the morning. I say patience because that's my sorts of information, but I'm sure some
of my friends were doing that to check the news. And so that kind of thing is psychologically
damaging. So there is a limit to how much misinformation can actually affect people's
mental health and I think it does and to develop skepticism about all the information is a
positive look. I think you're both getting on something important in terms of you mentioned
something about presenting a balanced view and what is a balanced view because hanging
yourself is not a good treatment for depression and you shouldn't be given the same way as
some actual forms of therapy. But this is something that the news media has struggled
with and that leading to the Trump election used to be in a newspaper recording that a
new person two sides of an issue and that's supposed to be balanced. But I think that
reports today they have come to still struggling with this but they're coming to the realization
that I just giving equal time and equal work come to two issues. That's not necessarily
a balanced view or if you're talking about having a TV show with interviews about a panel
about climate change and you have a climate scientist and a climate denier that's not
a balanced view because in one case you have the exception view of a specific issue and
the other case you have somebody who represents thousands of climate scientists so it's not
that's not balanced that would be in balance but I do not think that we have arrived to
the right formula or 100% different size of an issue with appropriate weight.
Well you and Tim you mentioned the cynicism before and you know for me the issue of cynicism
as I was saying in my thesis just a moment ago that if people are considered to be somehow
stupid or naive to be open to some you know consensus opinion or some authority and that
or if they're made fun of for thinking or believing in impartiality that doesn't breed
that doesn't breed trust it just won't you know you're wrong for being for having any
trust in an impartial decision you're just a fool and I'm afraid that's a meme in our
society right now it's keeping us away from forming establishing some kind of legitimate
sources of authority for many of these topics and there seem to be a change in how we react
to evidence I think evidence is maybe a key word here on one hand we have more and more
segments of the population who just reject evidence as irrelevant and on the other let
me take for example you know what the the January 6 hearings right now there is a I
think kind of a feeling that no matter how much evidence the committee will accumulate
some people will not be persuaded by it right maybe because they distrust the source of
the evidence or maybe because they just don't it doesn't change our mind at the same time
where evidence is losing its meaning for many people you now have a new kind of brand of
conspiracies and that doesn't rely on any of it and it's at all I mean I take the they
QAnon conspiracy for example people are willing to believe in in outrageous arguments based
on very little it's it's different even from the conspiracy theories of let's say 2001
where truther is around the 9 11 attacks were trying to collect every bead of information
they could you know they would try to I mean it was of course inaccurate and wrong but
at least it wasn't attempt to kind of find some information that can support their side
I remember all the you know attempts to calculate the heat levels of the metal and what not
these days the new conspiracies are just arguments being thrown around people are willing to
at least spread them without any support whatsoever and at the same time they're willing to reject
the scientific community that that is working around around facts and evidence right and
I think that part of the problem and one of the reasons not necessarily the main reason
but one of the reasons that we don't have trust and that misinformation continues and
impeded is that we have a lack of accountability I don't think that we can have trust without
accountability and I think that perhaps there are some there's a there's a sea change or
the beginnings of a sea change I mean we just had the Alex Jones trial for spreading this
misinformation with the with the with the families of the Sunday Sunday hook victims but
for for a very long time for over a decade he was able to spread this misinformation and
making a lot of money out of it without without any consequence.
I mean just to throw out one other ingredient in this yeah I'm I thought your take on the
sort of objectivity and you know the extent to which sort of whether something is truly
objective say in journalism has been challenged you know I think the you know what's going
up part of what's going on here is that we have claims by kind of established players
so like journalists like judges who are you know they're claiming some sort of objectivity
or neutrality but people you know have they're taking some other evidence like whether it's
their experience or they're feeling that there's no accountability or being able to point to
outcomes that contradict this this assertion of objectivity and they're saying what you're
saying isn't true or you know I don't believe what you're telling us because we have this
other evidence that you know you're obviously biased towards this outcome and it's easier
than ever to obtain that independent evidence that at least challenges these traditional
claims to objectivity and lack of bias and you know one thing that's making that easier
is transparency or just you know the ability to actually collect your own your own data
and make that available for other people traditionally you know most information that people would
use to make these kinds of assessments was channeled through these kinds of gatekeepers
but but today you know whether it's through literally laws that allow people to just request
documents from from government authorities or social media which can take very obscure
pieces of information and suddenly put them in before millions of people suddenly you
know there is other evidence that people can use to challenge these claims to authority
which are based on you know neutrality or objectivity and that can't withstand that kind of scrutiny
you know if people are willing to believe that that the claims are not fully fully based
on yeah like on a solid foundation.
Even the efforts have been to try to police or regulate the messages in social media
and then that that's a fraud to some degree fraud right.
I think people don't understand how unregulated social media is part of it is intentional
I mean we decided to put social media under section 230 which means that we read them
as the technology industry and not a media industry right.
I don't think people understand how arbitrary the process of moderating information on social
media is it's basically still you know based on on those companies making decisions based
on their on their financial kind of benefit they are not legally bound to remove misinformation
there are no clear rules about what's considered misinformation or not this is the wild west
of information.
Why is misinformation bothering us more than that because we have more access to it.
Because what sorry.
Because we have more of it or more access to misinformation why are we so bothered about
it.
I mean we knew it was always there.
I think that what's new about misinformation in the digital era is that we are communicating
now in an environment that prioritized the algorithms that you talked about earlier.
I think for a long time we were worried that the algorithms are pushing us toward information
we already believe in.
So there was a lot of discussion of filter bubbles and echo chambers and all those ideas
but I think these days it seems more evident that the environment that we communicate in
prioritizes engagement I mean at the end of the day it's a financial decision the social
media companies like Facebook and TikTok and YouTube are free meaning they need to make
money somehow when they do that by keeping us engaged for as long as possible collecting
our data and tailoring advertisements to us right.
In order to do that they need to give us information that that's going to keep us interested.
This information just fits the bill better than facts.
I think the information environment that we are working in and almost living in these
days just prioritizes misinformation more than before more than the mass media or mainstream
media era that was more bound to some objective norms of objectivity.
It's something that I think should bother us is about the access and vulnerability that
young people have to misinformation.
This is no and I have three children there 11, 12 and 15 and I noticed especially during
the pandemic during Zoom school and my two all this kids were a couple of years older
at the time I guess 13 and 11 and I learned a little bit too late and that we've better
best to remedy it but they have been subjected to a vast amount of misinformation online
and we have a number of conversations and I have not even been aware of this and that
even with misinformation being kind of like my field in a sense but this was basically
happening in front of me and I wasn't seeing it and young people they have access but they
don't have the tools it's difficult to have the tools as even as informing as informed
adults but in some of these misinformation is specifically targeting children and young
people and yeah I think it's a big problem and it's a no problem.
Well if it's true that it's way less regulated and never in the past would that mean how
would it be regulated now is that something you're in favor of?
I mean it's I mean if you're talking about things that are targeted to children I mean
that seems like a pretty ripe area for regulation that seems like yeah that seems like that's
a pretty pretty uncontroversial statement so let's start there.
Yeah are we skipping a right are we going to regulation now?
I mean I was interested in actually peaking off something else that you said so I mean
you've been talking a little bit about sort of learning basically like training and teaching
people how to basically sift through the information that they encounter and there's been a lot
of talk about you know trying to improve educational efforts both you know in children and even
later in life so I've been very interested for example in things like digital data.
Media literacy you know trying to come up with ways of improving people's digital literacy
skills as a potential solution for people's susceptibility to misinformation and so I'm
curious if you've like you know ever kind of thought about that or if you've encountered
these kinds of issues if you are optimistic about these kinds of approaches for helping
to solve this problem.
Well optimistic I don't think this is the only solution but I think it's an integral
part of the solution and because I mean to be able to sift through all of this information
and decide what to keep what to discard you first need to be aware of your own vulnerability
so you have to be aware that there are all of these various sources of information.
I think also there's lack of awareness of our own just neurological susceptibility
such as human beings with the nervous systems that we have how we can folkry to all sorts
of perceptual cognitive biases.
I don't think that this is really well understood or accepted you think okay I'm going to be
able to I know that there is misinformation out there but I know myself I know that I
can make a good decision and you can convince yourself that you can be a good judge and
but fundamentally you have to realize that you have to keep questioning yourself because
you are vulnerable in ways that are not going to be apparent to you.
I want to go back to regulation for a second it's a really tough topic and all of us are
struggling to answer those questions.
I think there are two parts or two components that we need to consider.
First is what do we regulate and the second is who is supposed to do that.
So the first one is hard I mean both of them are hard but the first one is really really
hard because the amount of misinformation right now is so big that we cannot regulate
all of it right so we need to make a decision on where to draw the line in the sand.
For me for example I mean it's still vague but my kind of border line will be where people
live or well being are put at risk right so maybe we wouldn't regulate any misstated
argument on the internet but if something is for example the conspiracy is putting a
complete full racial group at risk for example maybe that's the place where you want to intervene.
So first of all we need to decide what to regulate and what not I mean what kind of
lies to take down and what not.
The second problem of course is who's going to do it and both options are pretty bad.
One option is to let the government do that and we know that in the past governments
had abused this power.
The Chinese government for example right now is regulating TikTok in a way that removes
let's say information that's favorable to the Hong Kong and Taiwanese side right.
We can think of other examples from the history when governments use their power to regulate
information to detrimental effects.
The other option is to let the companies themselves do that and that once again is problematic.
Do we trust Twitter to decide what's truth and what's false.
Do we trust YouTube to be the arbitrators of truth.
The answer is of course not.
They are first and foremost business people.
Their concern is with the bottom line of their companies and they don't have a motivation
really to keep the information environment clean.
Now between these two if I had to choose I would still go with the government because
at least the government is being elected by the people.
I mean nobody elected Mark Zuckerberg to have so much power over information.
Politicians are not perfect.
But at least as citizens we have some authority over selecting them or monitoring their behaviors.
So no solution is perfect but I think we need to start talking about government regulation.
It happens in other countries.
I mean in the United States it sounds like a big deal to ask the government to interfere
with information but take Germany or Austria for example where it is illegal to deny the
Holocaust.
I mean there are laws in place and again how do you decide what to make into a law where
something is becoming an existential threat to people's safety.
So maybe it's time to start seriously thinking about regulation.
I wasn't actually necessary.
I didn't want you to get the idea that I was in favor of regulation although I know there
aren't that many obvious solutions to it.
I also agree with the idea of educating people more to try to become more skeptical.
I'm a little bit pessimistic about educating people basically because of what your original
premises which is we're really prone to these sorts of trickery.
We just are as human beings.
And then there's this sort of general idea that there's a, you know it's interesting
that there's so much skepticism about truth started on the left.
There's a lot of critics of skepticism and the relativism of truth started on the left
and then it's sort of really been appropriated by the right now.
And so we have both camps have become relativist which is difficult.
Right, as people say well I don't think the government on the one hand should be the ones
who decide what's true or what's not true.
And then the other people say we should be free to say whatever we want.
We want the First Amendment rights.
Everything's turned upside down.
But maybe the idea might be also, you know, first of all I think when folks say well for
example Holocaust denying is illegal in Germany I don't think about their legal system around
that but I imagine if you've been cited for claiming the Holocaust wasn't real you might
have some ways to address that legally to try to, no I didn't do it or was it work of
art or whatever, you know something of that nature.
I would think maybe that would be something that would happen here.
The other is you can get together these businesses and say look you have to come together with
to some consensus of what's legitimate.
Let the companies do it as a group and let them know that otherwise it's going to be
the government's going to step in.
It's interesting that a lot of, I mean you were mentioning where the groups being oppressed
because of false information I think Alex Jones was a good example but one of the things
that came up with Alex Jones and I know we've all heard about this in other context is that
there are people getting threatening phone calls and you can imagine that that's something
you could keep a record of and it could be something used as a trigger point for there's
something has to be done about this.
This is leading to a lot of threats.
I don't know what you all think of that as a possible.
Yeah I mean that's something that would probably be illegal you know offline with a telephone
so why would that be legal if you're doing it through Twitter or through Facebook.
I will say I thought the way you framed that was very good.
You know personally in terms of regulation I feel like we actually had a pretty good workable
solution for a while.
This section 230 idea which is we're going to let there be a flourishing of different
platforms.
They can all figure out their rules and people can sort of go to the platform whose rules
that they like.
Problem is that was not designed for a world in which we have like two or three huge platforms
that have come to somehow dominate our kind of public sphere or that's what it seems
like anyway.
It was for a world in which there was like AOL and copy serve and all these little dial
up services and the stakes just don't seem so high.
And so you know the question to me is is there a way to sort of adapt this kind of like middle
path to our present day reality which just does not reflect the reality in which the
original regulations were drawn.
So I did included.
I'll just say the idea bearing section 230 was that if you're a technology company that
produces let's say a phone you can't be held responsible for what people say on the phone.
But with Facebook and Twitter that's not the case anymore.
Their algorithms are determining which information will be more permanent which information will
be more obscure.
Meaning they are beginning to hold not beginning they are holding editorial role of what's
being said on their platforms and maybe they're not a technology company anymore.
Maybe they are media companies at this point and if they are we need to regulate them just
like we did for cable TV and newspapers and all the media that came before.
Yeah I think the question really does come down to the extent to which there is some
sort of editorial discretion.
It's like literally this is literally what some of the court cases now are hinging on.
So it actually isn't the case that there aren't regulations or laws.
There actually are regulations or laws.
They're going to be made by one actor or another whether it's a court right or some sort of
de facto rule by a company and so I think what we should try to figure out is whether
the public can sort of play a role in determining what the rules are going to look like because
the rules are going to be set one way or another.
I included the reference NFTs which are a little bit have receded a little bit in the
media coverage of LA but I saw it as a being an effort.
I mentioned this to you earlier, Rotem, it's like an effort to reestablish authenticity
in some way because these are ways in which these things are supposedly indelible and
not open to dispute and similarly Bitcoin which have a relationship in the cryptocurrencies
the idea that okay we don't want to trust the Fed anymore with the way our money is being
managed we're going to find this sort of democratized way of making sure our money is
transactions are I don't want to ledger that's indelible how quickly that sort of what do
you think about the fact that how quickly this is sort of it was like a little bit of
a fat and it seems to be I don't know if it's going to receive forever but it has receded
a little bit.
One thing that interests me about NFTs is that we perceive them as less authentic as
you said than money but for me it's kind of ironic because money was always.
Fictional.
I mean right, I mean what is money?
What does it mean that I give you a piece of grain paper that has no value at all you
cannot wear it you cannot turn it into a tent or anything you know.
It depends on trust.
It depends on trust right I mean the only reason money works is that I can give you this piece
of paper and both of us know that you can take this piece of paper to a genet by the
share with it right.
I think the NFTs are just another iteration of the same old idea of imagining a financial
system and making up rules to play by but yeah it seems like these days it's kind of
collapsing I don't know.
I'm not an expert on NFT but it seems that the.
In the NFTs there is no country behind the NFT it's between the buyer and the seller
but with the let's say the owner you have the United States treasured guaranteed that
what's guaranteed the NFTs was.
Just trust in the other or in the market.
In a way it connects to the previous point you started talking a little bit about kind
of libertarian models of communication what if we just let people be and hope that they
are going to do the best with it.
We seem to put a lot of hopes into that and it's true for NFTs but it's also true for
social media and discussion.
We built this utopian perception of media environments like the internet where if we
just let people be themselves if we don't tell them what to you know what to read or
what to think or what to say the best content will always prevail and it doesn't seem to
hold water.
When push comes to shove it seems like we're not always looking for the best content.
We're not always trying to spread the most accurate information.
It's nice to kind of dream about the libertarian world where you can just leave people through
their own devices and they're going to do the best.
It doesn't seem to work.
Do you think this concern about misinformation is going to diminish over the years since
there's so much of it and people will then start thinking well I'm reading all this but
it's misinformation so that they develop a sense of skepticism of a degree that unless
they find real evidence in something they just dismiss it.
I think arguably it's already diminishing.
I think it's being replaced with other concerns.
For example you hear a lot about other kinds of consequences of social media like harassment,
hate speech, even things like incidility, things that just also make things unpleasant,
have a lot of harmful effects but don't necessarily hinge on the question of whether something
is factually accurate or not.
I guess my prediction would be the next time that there's a new big technological shift
in mass communication that raises worries about whether people will be manipulated in some
way we'll hear again about misinformation.
Now I think the conversation has sort of moved on a little bit and misinformation is I think
a potential harmful effect of social media but there are lots of others and I think it's
perhaps healthy that we're kind of making some room for some of these other things as
well.
And I think it will be unlikely that people will just, anything that I read, anything
that I see on the web I'm going to discharge.
I think it's going to keep, it's being curated currently it's going to be even more so that
it links to the polarization issue but I think that people will always have some particular
sources of information that they trust implicitly and they'll be seeking that kind of content
that they already predisposed to trust.
So I don't think that there will be like a widespread skepticism about any sort of
information but perhaps more polarization, heaven.
I think the idea behind NFTs and cryptocurrencies was an effort to sort of codify a form of
authenticity and it fails.
It does fails because what people need is more trust.
And you know you like to think well if I codify it I make it absolutely unassailable yes
or no that that's not replacing trust between human beings.
It's really an interesting, right?
That isn't a good point.
I agree that that's potentially a cautionary tale but I'm not sure, I guess I don't know
if that's universally the case.
So here we have a situation in kind of financial markets, right?
So maybe like we really need trust to sustain a healthy market.
But I see some more things going on with our previous discussion about how do you know
which sources of information to trust.
Can we replace that kind of trust with authenticity?
Well I think that's happening too, right?
If you look at where, I mean when I just talk to my students, you know, they don't even
think about information in terms of trust.
They think about influences that they follow.
They think about broadcasters who they find authentic or real.
So people are already using authenticity as a sort of a metric for where they should
get information.
And so it is a question to me as to whether that sort of replacing trust with authenticity.
But is that cause or effect like do you trust some influencer because they're authentic
or they seem authentic, will you trust?
Really, I know it's a good question.
It's a good question.
Yeah, yeah.
But I guess like one way that you could think about this, I don't know if this is accurate
but you know as trust is sort of declined across the board in a number of spaces.
People still need something that can just simply solve the problem of like where do
I turn to?
People will always find shortcuts.
Yeah.
What shortcuts do I use?
And maybe I'm just using these words interchangeably or something but it's like there is something
about the authenticity of the messenger now that seems different than this kind of traditional
notion of the problem.
But I don't...
The apparent of this.
The apparent, yes, exactly.
I'm all in favor of authenticity and I agree with everything you said.
And I'm just saying that thinking you're going to find it by having it digitalized that
the other thing, this is going to be vouch safe by the digital, the code is not going
to happen.
If Bitcoin and other cryptocurrencies ever take off, it's not going to be because they
have...
Because of the tech, their blockchain technology, it's going to be because people start to put
trust into it.
It's not going to be because of the technology is what I'm saying.
Well, it's like something that inherently can't be hard coded.
Like, well, at the point where you have to sign a contract with someone, it's like,
well, you're not relying on trust anymore.
Like, you know, right?
So...
Well, should we open up the floor to some questions?
Does anyone...
Does anyone here have any questions?
Why don't you come over here?
No, please, because one of them...
Pick up a demike.
So I'm curious, with so many different views of reality and everything you guys have been
talking about, how will history be written about our time?
Will it be in parallel tracks?
Will there be a history that is true history of what was real?
What was fact-based?
We never had true history.
Yeah.
Well, maybe, but it seems like it's more at risk now than possibly it's been.
I mean, there's a book by Vargas Losa that came out last year about the events in Guatemala
and the U.S. role in whatever it was that happened in Guatemala.
Well, that only is something that came up in a more consistent and coherent way with Vargas
Losa's book.
So what is the accurate history of what happened in Guatemala until that point?
No, I know what's the problem.
History's written through the eyes of the historians.
But this seems even more fraught with conflict about what reason did that.
I think I'm not that I'm an historian, but I have a little bit more faith.
There's going to be a consensus that will be built over time.
Right now, historians just agree about the way things went and they reinterpret parts
of history still to this day and not always in a highly polarized Democrat versus Republican
way, but just because they're honest disagreements among historians about how things go.
I mentioned a story about Chaucer today is a good example.
That may be debated.
I think among academic historians, there will be enough of a consensus about what's...
Actually, I am more optimistic about the future historians than I am, but what's happening
today.
Because I do think that the access to information and to spreading information, there are so
many people today, like anybody has a voice.
And so future historians will have access not just to establish experts, governments,
borders, but we don't know how the everyday person used to think about in the Middle Ages.
They didn't have a voice that we have been able to recover today.
So I think that future historians will have to shift through content, but they will have
a lot more to work with than we have today about the arrest passed.
But that itself is going to pose...
It's going to be this challenge of abundance versus...
What is the scientist that I will say?
Do you have too much data?
I agree.
Which is like a practical matter.
I've tried to reconstruct what people have said on Twitter last week.
And you should try it sometime.
It's really hard because people are responding to other people directly and indirectly.
People are making vague references to things that are not always obvious after the fact.
Reconstructing the context, I think is going to be increasingly difficult because it's
told through memes and references that are constantly evolving.
And it's going to be trying to decipher hieroglyphics in a way.
Perhaps so.
And will that information be preserved in forms that are accessible?
Well, yeah, just because it's digital doesn't mean it doesn't decay.
Exactly.
Yeah.
Well, hopefully there will be people who are academics who are motivated to do that work
on the hieroglyphics.
I like to think there is.
A lot of people who have written about history, books about historical developments are not
always exactly historians either.
And we can think of economists who have written pretty divergent views, Hayek and Keynes,
and pretty divergent views about how history is going to economic history, but also general
history.
And we've survived with that.
So I'm reasonably hopeful about that.
Anybody else?
Oh, please step up to the mic.
Okay.
So since we have some political scientists here, the first thing I want to ask this concept
is a little tangential, but it comes back political science.
My understanding is science is you observe the world, you make theories, you test those
theories through experiment, and then you see if your theories were correct.
Now, if we want to guide this in the context of today's topic, misinformation and algorithms,
would a political scientist be able to conduct an experiment on this topic and make predictions
in theories?
And is that something they would do, or even more generally would do, political scientists
just make predictions but don't run experiments?
Can you comment on that a little bit?
That's a great question.
Yeah, you're right.
And as sort of social scientists, we want to be able to make and test hypotheses, which
often means you're testing predictions.
So certainly, speaking for myself and my own research, everything that I try to do fits
the framework that you just described.
When you're talking about misinformation, things become difficult because there are ethical
issues involved.
So if I could think of the ideal experiment that I would like to run, it would involve
exposing people to a ton of misinformation and see what happens.
Well, that doesn't seem ethical to me.
And so I can't run that.
You can't rat.
Sorry?
You can rat.
Exactly.
So you can do it in rats.
And so part of the creative challenge of doing this kind of research is trying to explore
ways of studying these questions in ways that don't require you to be a mad scientist,
basically.
It involves natural experiments, so have platforms changed the way that they've operated.
And so does this speak to this particular hypothesis about, say, the effects of misinformation?
The other thing is that a lot of the most interesting research that's happening right
now, both by political scientists but also people in psychology and other fields, and
in communication, is trying to test the effectiveness of different kinds of solutions for misinformation.
So take it as a given.
How can we do to reduce people's belief in misinformation in ways that don't infringe
on other kinds of values, like free expression?
So I think this is all a very active area of research.
But I agree that we want to take this sort of scientific empiricist path to understanding
these questions.
Can you give a performance for us to give some sort of experience with, well, not on a sometimes
sort of misinformation, we have the number of experiments with misdirection, as you might
have, in a magic show.
We actually study magic tricks directly to investigate various kinds of cognitive biases.
So you can do these kinds of things.
It's a bit less of an ethical concern where you're investigating magic tricks, but you
can get similar kinds of issues.
I'll just add, oh, I'm so sorry.
I'll just add that, first of all, there ain't one approach to scientific inquiry of political
science.
Both Andy and me are more quantitative and, I guess, post-postivistic in nature, but some
people don't accept that as the only way to understand the world.
In the area of misinformation, specifically, I think that in both your field of political
science and in my field of communication, we are getting very good at building microtheories
of misinformation, which can be tested experimentally in the lab or in controlled environments.
What we are not able to do is to use scientific methods to answer those big questions.
Like, how does misinformation influence our society?
That's something you cannot put into a lab or you cannot create two societies that are
equal on everything except for the presence of misinformation.
So I think we're spending a lot of our time on the micro level of just understanding the
psychological processes.
And in their regard, we are taking a very, an approach that's very similar to the hard
science as much as possible within the creation of movements.
That's such.
Well, first of all, thank you for this wonderful discussion.
And a few years ago, a study made at MIT Media Lab.
The question was, do fake news spread faster and more than real news or truthful news?
And the answer was yes.
So the problem is why and one may think well because of bots and new technology that can
multiply the diffusion.
But the result of the study tells something different.
Apparently, fake news spread faster because of human beings, because of the emotional
reaction they evoke.
So my question is, when we are discussing the impact of new technologies, the temptation
to be apocalyptic is already at hand.
But shouldn't we go back to the human factor?
Because as you said, we are basically the same.
So confirmation bias, you said that reassurance, conformism, the feeling of being part of a
community of people who share the same belief are always the same.
So I think the human factor probably has to be more investigative than interface.
There's too much emphasis.
Don't you think there's too much emphasis on the technology?
Thank you.
I do think that emotions are a critical component.
And we know from a neuroscientific perspective and that in studies of attention, that emotions
prioritize attention.
That's actually a lot of the reasons that magicians take advantage of this.
Magicians actually make us laugh at critical points where they need to misdirect us.
So you can use emotion almost surgically in a magic show, also in social media and in
the spread of fake news.
And we used to think, I mean, many years ago, the thinking in science communication was
that, well, you need to put out the correct information out there and you need to give
more detail and you need to communicate it more.
And so people are going to extract the right conclusion.
It's just they are arriving to the wrong conclusion because they don't have all the information.
So let's give more information.
Let's make it more accessible.
That doesn't fix the problem because you're ignoring the emotional components.
Can I add something?
I thought that was a great question too.
I also, as a social scientist too, I think humans are always going to be at the center
of what I think is important.
But as a political scientist, I think human behavior is structured by institutions.
And so kind of another way of saying that, how that applies to this topic is that I think
social media platforms have different affordances or different features which can bring out or
suppress tendencies that exist in humans.
And so that's the thing that's really important.
There's nothing inherent to, I think there's nothing inherent to social media in the abstract
that means that it's going to incentivize engagement with misinformation.
But it is baked into some platforms today and that the way that they set up the incentives
within the platform.
And so I think that redesigning social media, how they're designed, the kinds of behaviors
that they facilitate for people, the kinds of behavior that they encourage from people
is something that we should be thinking very seriously about.
Because yeah, it's true.
Humans have a tendency to think of ourselves as part of a group.
But that can be emphasized or de-emphasized.
And what the group is, right, that's not hardwired either.
And so these are things that can be brought out through features of social media, including
things like algorithms or not.
There's been a movement I know and I'll know much about it, but I do know that some groups,
organizations will have people go out together and live camp out or solve problems.
And the whole idea is here they're identifying with each other, yeah, they're cooperating
with each other towards certain goals which is different just saying, well, I'm a liberal
or I'm a conservative, right?
They're actually targeting some goals and that seems to foster a little bit more of
a sense of community.
Yes.
Thank you very much for a very stimulating discussion.
I cannot help but remember that it goes to time in human history where the heliocentric
system was considered misinformation.
And the geocentric system was considered human to be the truth.
And people were actually tried, they were put on the fire for challenging the so-called
truth by spreading misinformation.
Okay, so my question is, is there such a thing as information?
Because if there is misinformation, it means that the information is what's true and the
misinformation is what's wrong.
Now is there such a thing as information?
And even if there is, what's wrong with challenging it?
And so the last thing I'm going to say is science is very limited in what objective,
let's say, is like physics, I mean, more than 95% of medical, biomedical published research,
which we consider science, cannot be replicated.
That tells you how hard establishing what information is at least in the scientific context where
you can have objective methodology let alone in the social sciences.
That's what the problem is.
So should we err on the side of allowing misinformation because that makes the dialectic process which
allows us to filter and synthesize and refuse and accept that should we allow misinformation?
Should we err on the side of allowing misinformation?
Or should we err on the side of imposing quote-unquote information which actually may turn out in
maybe the next decade or the next century to be false?
Thank you.
My feeling, I think that these are different issues I've played here.
And I think one issue pertains to the science enterprise itself and that it is true that
we do have a replicability crisis or problem more in some areas than in others.
But and I think that there's a lot of fundamental problems with the structure of science, how
it's done this day, the kinds of science that gets incentivized, the pressure to publish.
There are a lot of problematic issues and certainly sometimes we're playing it a bit
too safe in the sense of the research that gets resources to be performed.
I think that's a different problem from misinformation itself and in the spirit of misinformation,
I think that by individuals, not necessarily scientists, I think that's a different domain
from a science than the best way it could be done.
So to me, those are different issues and yes, in terms of the science, the other thing
I think that's important to keep in mind in terms of the science because it was mentioned
something about truth.
And I would say that scientists don't try to get at the truth or they should not try
to get at the truth.
The truth in science is always aspirational and that's why we talk about validating hypothesis,
not verifying a hypothesis and the hypothesis is correct until it's proven otherwise.
So as scientists, at least the way that I was taught to the science and the way that
I teach my trainees is that you try to eliminate hypothesis that are incorrect and hopefully
you get to narrow down more and more the actual answer.
But as a scientist, you have to be always in the mind frame that you need to be questioning
your own results and there's also others of course, but all the time you're supposed
to be revising your framework in light of no evidence.
Yeah I absolutely love this question.
We can spend two more hours just answering this, right?
You asked what is information, forget about misinformation, what is information and that
bothered every thinker since we learned how to put our mind into words, right?
I mean that's Greek philosophy that's played out thinking about the people in the cave
trying to figure out if they are really seeing the world or not.
I'll kind of get inspiration from all the statues of someone Freud in this building and
go to another Austrian philosopher of science which is Karl Popper, right?
And I'm a very strong, a very strong, a properian person and I think he reminded us that science
is about, as you said, science is not the search for information.
It's the systematic rejection of misinformation.
We would never be able to prove with certainty that anything that we see in studies is true,
right?
The best we can do is to reject hypotheses that are wrong.
We are able logically to reject some ideas and then at any given moment we need to take
the actions that are most suitable to the current state of knowledge that we have at
that point.
Take vaccines, for example, that you talked about before.
Can we say for certain that vaccines have no negative impact?
Of course not.
We can't.
Certainly we can't.
We can just reject the hypothesis that people who take the vaccines are more likely than
others to have autism, for example.
We can reject this hypothesis but we cannot say for sure that vaccines will never have
a negative influence.
So yes, science is kind of, as if it's working in this regard, we will never get to the truth
but I think we are able to gather enough consensus on what's wrong to direct policy and behavior
that's more educated.
I wanted to make a real quick response to this too.
There are different sorts of misinformation and when the consequence of misinformation
could be dangerous, of course, we want to figure out a way to get around that.
A famous director now, sort of infamous director had this wonderful little bit where he was
his neurotic child version of himself was being reprimanded by his mother who said,
what's at your business if the universe is expanding?
So the idea is, okay, you know what, if the universe is expanding or not, we don't need
to get to the bottom of that.
It's okay with us if you don't accept authority on that.
But if you go to your doctor and you have a, God forbid you have a cancer and the treatment
that's going to be offered for you and oftentimes if they're experimental treatments, they'll
even tell you in advance.
I can't even say this is going to be good or safe for you but you have to make a decision.
You know, that's where the rubber meets the road.
You then, I think, you're best off putting your trust into the doctor and in return,
the doctor has to have in his or her mind the idea that I don't want to let my patient
down because this is almost like a sacred trust that's being placed on me.
So that means we have to go back and make sure that this treatment is good and valid.
Sometimes you don't know in any particular point in time but trust is another, again,
comes up as another important feature separating information from misinformation.
And not always making a clear demarcation, right?
Then there cannot be, which is part of, I think, what your question entails.
Yeah, thank you.
Yes, please.
Actually, that response was very closely related to the question I wanted to ask because, so,
there's an implication to certain kinds of misinformation.
And so, we touched on regulation before.
My question's about are there other kinds of regulatory capacity in sort of societies
that exist today or that we can build into our societies?
Because if certain kinds of misinformation might imply certain kinds of harm to specific
people and they're endowed with certain kinds of voices.
So my question is, is it possible to think of how can that create the potential harm
of misinformation, how can that create feedback loops to like a repair capacity?
Is it possible?
I mean, I think this raises, I mean, I think this is an interesting question that raises
the challenge as to how we sort of build sort of responsive mechanisms of accountability
for any kind of regulatory regime that we end up wanting to have.
So what are the rules of the road for content moderation and platform governance?
And who gets the decide, who gets a voice and how these rules are determined?
I think there's a strong case to be made that whether this is being channeled through
like legislatures or some other citizens' bodies, those bodies should be representative
of the diversity of interest in society.
Very much including people who are the victims of, I mean, not only misinformation, but harassment
and hateful speech that can deal legitimized people, deal with legitimized groups and make
it more difficult to participate as citizens.
When we say regulation, we usually think of content moderation, right?
Having information that is wrong or adding some disclaimers and so on.
But recently some scholars raised some more creative approaches to regulation.
And one that I found really interesting is the one suggested by Victor Picard from the
University of Pennsylvania.
He says, instead of focusing on moderation of content, let's take taxes from social media
companies.
There's a lot of money from that misinformation, right?
Let's take some taxes back and use it to fund high quality journalism.
You can create a fund that kind of builds on the money that being made from our misinformation
and build more reliable institutions of knowledge with it.
So maybe there are more solutions that we're not thinking about, but they're more creative
than just running after the next mistake and trying to correct it all the time.
I think that's wonderful.
It's a great point to high point to end on.
It's not my idea.
But it's a great comment.
And I'm really pleased to hear all the different efforts to sort of come up with some, you
know, handle some solution on this issue.
And I want to thank you all three of you for contributing the way you did.
Thank you.
Great.
I appreciate that.
Congratulations.
A lot of talk sharing.
Thank you.
That's all we're going to do, right?