My current as well is something. My voltage is about the safety.
The voltage is less because the average is less.
It sucks. Yeah, no, he's saying the whole puncher is bad.
He's saying that us people down here have...
No, too few. You're right. You're right. I need more holes.
We're going to start. We normally have about 50 people in the audience,
but since this is our first live meeting,
I think we haven't been able yet to publicize it enough so that the people who usually come are here.
The idea for... I'm the director of the Center at Nursassian.
The idea for these...
Between the way also separates our second decade,
and something in 2012, and then we accepted
to have five programs together. It was a pay because
it didn't have anything live for the Nurs
and the other Nurs and something that we sent to the center.
We came to us by more than one of our friends.
And...
Elias Dockwarch. And then that coding
was an important subject and had many angles to it,
and maybe we should have round tables on that. And Jerry Horowitz,
who is the associate director of the Center, then took this and developed
amazingly five round tables.
And so today, this morning, we have the first of those,
and then we have four more, two more this afternoon, and two
tomorrow. I want to thank all the participants
who volunteered to come here and have a conversation,
and I leave it to Jerry to introduce everybody, and who we take on from this.
Thank you, Ed. It's a real pleasure to be back here live
at the Helix Center.
Let me take a moment to introduce our
esteemed panelists today. I'll try to make this quick,
but it's certainly interesting to thought,
maybe I can introduce the idea behind this talk, which I think is a little bit
unusual. So the theme of the conference is
overcoding.
I thought, when did the interesting start off?
What did we all come to the idea of what codes are,
and what coding might be? I find that,
and this I'm sure is true, a lot of ideas
are sort of being concretized now. That means one thing,
which is sort of programming and coding, but codes have a long history,
and what their meaning is, I think, is fascinating.
So we'll take that up. So first,
Jorgi Bzaki identified a hierarchical
organization of brain oscillations and proposed how these rhythms
support a brain syntax, a physiological basis of cognitive
operations. His work changed how we think about information
encoding in the healthy and diseased brain, such as epilepsy and
psychiatric disease. Several laboratories worldwide
have adopted his framework and provided supporting evidence for the two stage
model of memory in both experimental animals and human subjects.
Bzaki is a big professor of neuroscience at
NYU. He is among the top 0.1% most cited
neuroscientist, member of the National Academy of Sciences,
USA, member of the academia,
European, and the Hungarian Academy of Sciences.
Michael Novichak is a curator and professor of paleontology
at the American Museum of Natural History and senior advisor
to the museum's president. From 1994 to
2021, he served as the museum's senior vice president
on Provost of Science. Awarded a doctoral degree
at the University of California, Berkeley, Dr. Novichak studies concern
patterns of evolution and relationships among extinct
and extant organisms. His interests have range from the fossil
record to data on DNA sequences.
He has led a participation, I'm sorry, he has led or participated
in paleontological expeditions in the North American
Rocky Mountain region, Baja California, the Andes Mountains
of Chile, the Yemen Arab Republic, Argentina,
Sahara, and Africa, Morocco, and the Gobi Deserts of Mongolia.
Karen B. Stern is a professor of history at Brooklyn College
of the City University of New York. Her research is deeply interdisciplinary.
She studied classics with honors at Dartmouth College, her name,
her MA and PhD in religious studies from Brown University,
and has excavated and conducted field research
in different areas of the Mediterranean, including Jordan, Greece,
Tunisia, Morocco, and Israel. Several grants,
fellowships and residencies from the National Endowment of the Humanities,
Council of the American Overseas Research Center, and the Getty Villa
have supported her research which deeply deploys
methods from the fields of archaeology, anthropology,
epigraphy, history, and religion, and religion to investigate
the daily lives and mature culture of Jews and Christians
in antiquity who inhabited areas around the Mediterranean
through Arabia and Mesopotamia.
David Salter is a professor of psychiatry, neurology,
pharmacology, and at the School of the Arts
at Columbia University and New York State Psychiatric Institute.
He received a PhD in biology from Columbia University.
The lab has published over 250 studies on synaptic function,
particularly of the basal ganglia and dopamine systems, and
neuroimmunology in normal and disease states that are cited over 50,000
times. He is founder of the Dopamine Society,
the Gordon Conference on Parkinson's Disease, and the journal Nature
Parkinson's Disease. He has received awards from
the McKnight, Simon's, Helmsley, Narsad, Huntington's,
and Aaron Diamond Foundations and the Universities of Jerusalem,
Minnesota, University College of London, and National Science
Foundations of Israel, Austria, Portugal, and given name
lectureships at the National Institute of Health, Harvard, Yale, UCSF,
Emory, UC Irvine, Irvine, and the Vatican.
Mark Vandemir Koop, oh sorry, Mark Vandemirup
is a historian of the ancient near East and
Egypt from the beginning of writing to the age of Alexander of Macedon.
Besides teaching at Columbia University, he has taught at the University
of Oxford and at Yale University. He directs Columbia Center
for the Ancient Mediterranean. He has published numerous books and
articles on various aspects of the
ancient near Eastern history, Egyptian history, and world history
with interest ranging from socioeconomic and
political history to intellectual history. He has written extensively on historical
methodology as it applies to his field of study.
In these writings, he aims both to present the materials of these fascinating
ancient cultures to a broader audience and to explore new paths of research.
Okay. I think we're done.
So, thank you very much.
So, I guess I'd like to get started with my
premise of the talk, which is
if one of you or several of you want to discuss your ideas
of what coding and decoding means very
generally. Because each of you has a certain area of expertise
that goes into specific examples of decoding or coding.
I'd like us to start with hieroglyphs, the Rosetta Stone
anniversary stuff like that. So, that sounds good to me.
Actually, the ancient
languages and scripts that I may deal with are not the hieroglyphic ones from
Egypt, but those from the Near Eastern, especially the first
system of writing every invented in world history, the Kine Forum
writing system. And there we see in
the right 30000 BCE, the invention of a writing system
that's quite different from what we currently use, the
alphabetic writing system, but a system that mixes together
science, multiple signs that indicate words for parts of
words. One of my things that I'm very interested in
is actually what that did to the people's
perception of the universe in which they lived. Because
in the way the conceit of the writing system,
the way they conceived of the elements of the writing system,
it was not in order to reproduce speech, but it was
in order to reproduce reality and
reality expressed in writing.
And because it's very different from the way we perceive writing
or alphabetic script, where let's say each character has
one particular value or has only a value within the
context of the other characters, but it's always
the say a letter B, as always something to do with the
maybe all impronunciation in speech, each character has
multiple values, values that can sound entirely different
from one another, but also that can have
different meanings altogether. And what you see happening
in this Knif form script is actually that
they play around with a written form of
anything, a name, or sentence, or something like that,
and they reinterpret it using various
meanings of the various elements. Obviously this is not the case
for basic writings, but this is when you talk about scholarly
text, ritual text, that type of thing.
So you can take actually a particular sequence of signs
and give them one meaning, and actually if you
give each of these signs a different, you know, different play around
with it, you can actually come up with exactly the opposite.
So you get this, but seems to be, to us, extremely
confusing, but actually the depth there is a coherent system
that enables you to interpret things, and then
get an understanding of anything in the
universe through its written form.
Well, would you say that there's more of an emphasis?
It's slightly less abstract in more material,
let's say the material nature of the image
of these... No, it's actually nothing.
So it's a very visual system of writing.
The basic, and the most difficult thing to understand is that
actually each element within this system has multiple values,
and if you, obviously there's an apparent
and immediate understanding when you read something,
but if you really want to discover the full truth,
the full value of something that is expressed in writing,
you have to consider these other options.
And so you can take a particular name
and you can then interpret that name.
I mean, when I said you can interpret it entirely in the opposite
that's, that it does happen, but that's perhaps too extreme.
But you can actually see in the name of an individual,
let's say, of a God, you can find within that God's name
all aspects of the powers that God has
in the universe if you read that name properly.
How did you feel
decoded, you can inform? How much a decoded?
Yeah, how did you understand what these various meanings
that each of these can ask? Well, sometimes they give us this information,
I mean, we have, I mean, they have scholarly material where they
it's not back upon their own writings and give
interpretations of their own writings. There's a long
textual tradition that goes on some 3000 years.
And so we benefit from the fact that, especially in the
late appearance of this history, there are people who looking at
texts that have been produced in the past and who
make commentaries on these texts. And so there,
within these commentaries, we can see how they could take
certain passages and look at these passages and
give them various interpretations. So you're saying that there's
an unbroken tradition in Mesopotamia, which is very different
than the broken tradition in Egypt.
Well, no, this doesn't go into the modern era actually, the
interesting thing. So this system, you have to rediscover how to
rediscover it in the 19th century of the common
area it was rediscovered. And it wasn't, I mean, it was
already an accomplishment that said to be able to read its
kind of form text because it wasn't as easy as with Egyptian hieroglyphs where you have the
Rosetta Stone, which gave you an ability to
understand this hieroglyphic science. But it was accomplished
that once we, you know, people were able to read this
text also, they became able to, scholars became able to read more
complicated text and figured out that they
themselves indicated sometimes, well, although you have
this particular passage, that passage actually can
have multiple meanings, or we can explain the meanings that that
passage has, by looking at how it is written out, not
by how it is pronounced.
So, let's start with the basics.
Coding is an agreement between the sender and the receiver.
It requires a cipher. Without the cipher,
there is nothing. So information is not out there,
it's not in the sender, it's not in the receiver, it's a relationship.
The information should be packaged and anybody who learns the
Morse code knows that packaging is very important because the stop
science, or you compute the language, or you can, in human languages,
you have to have methods to say, this is the
beginning, this is the end of the message, and this is the asset
which we call cipher. Without a cipher, you can never
break the code. Shampaleon,
Shampaleon could decode
the hieroglyphs because he was given
the cipher, the Rosetta store, and that grounded
an unknown language to two known languages that he spoke, he spoke like
ten languages, he was equipped with the
way to discover things, all my credit is for him, but without
Rosetta Storne, he would have no clue. Let's see another example, he wanted
to have examples. Alan Turing is well known, he is
the core, the core breaker, in fact he didn't break the code. He couldn't.
The core, that is the cipher, was given to him
by the Polish intelligence service in 1939
by the Polish post office because they already had an enigma machine.
Actually, he got two enigma machines. The enigma machines
contain the key elements
of which you have to reiterate, reiterate, reiterate,
the same method for Shampaleon, and many other
breakers used. Now, in the brain,
we usually read every single cognitive
science paper that the brain covers information. This is
nonsense because there is no information out there.
Information is always a relationship between what's out there
and what is inside here. So, actually, without humans,
I challenge you and say, there is no information.
We make things out there and
keep it as information because we know and we create
the ciphers. Now, this is very general. You get the fantastic
particular examples. I'm interested in this
possibility though that this modern understanding of decoding,
let's say where there's a key.
The key, yeah, thank you.
The definition of coding then gets to be, well,
if you know the code, you know how to proceed to try
to unpack a certain sort of information.
Decipher. Right. But we, I think
now have this idea that it's a way to be able to know how to speak the words
to just say them out loud. But I think earlier on,
it wasn't just simply a matter of turning it into an oral
format. Right. Does that fair to say that that wasn't exclusively
what it was about? That's exactly what you need to call.
So, when I let, like to send a message, I can do it various ways. Anyways, can do it.
By the way, you know, our obsession with about the human mind is just a very narrow
kind of an approach because
when you generate an artifact, it is a
message to somebody else. And the advantage of an artifact that it will survive you
and it can be given to many, many. So, it's a one to many communication
and forever. And it's very easy to identify human artifacts
where you go in the desert or anywhere you find anything
you say, this is natural or this is a human mind. Because we are sensitive
to those things that are required, the human mind's, and it's
ability to construct it. So, that kind of message
is what was, I'm sending messages
all the time with my eyes and my gestures and so on. Land beach
was an extraordinary human invention.
And of course, when land beach occurred, then
some of these guys around the table, including me, were very valuable
because they are the people who were the ones who accumulated all that knowledge
and carried the information. But when writing was invented,
that was huge. And then books were invented, that was huge.
And so on. But it's basically an externalization of brain function
is sending messages to very signals.
There is something that irritates me a lot. There are a lot of people
in my field to study. So, the origins of writing
and it seemed to, it would say it actually explicitly
it was not a big deal. Because as you're saying, there's a system
of communication pre-written or even in parallel
with writing a system of communication through visual images
etc or through objects and so on. And they're saying, well
writing is just a similar thing parallel and it doesn't really
affect the brain to, to, beyond
that's what you've been saying. In my opinion, it seems that
the invention of writing had a very radical impact on the
functioning of the human brain. And that it made the human brain
function differently. But I'm not, of course, I'm not like you are
specialist in this, that it made the human brain function differently.
And what about people that don't read? Yeah, thank you. Please.
No, just because I, I walk the materials that I work on from
antiquity are not necessarily sort of look at texts but I also look at
images because in antiquity as well as in modernity, not everybody
could read them right. So the fact that you have these
amazing, uniform texts, whether they're just like receipts of
things or more extended ones, it still requires specialization
to be able to, to be able to carve those
figures in those particular ways and to have that vast information
at hand and to be able to read it and process it. But sure,
we're not ever aware that simultaneous could do that. So for those who were able to engage
in the very specialized elite activities of the
production of these texts, surely it changed how they thought
and it sort of had a ripple effect on how society is organized.
But for many people who couldn't engage in those things, right, it took
until literacy, however broadly we describe it, becomes more widespread.
I think it, it probably, it's true. I mean
the way bring function might have developed would be different in accordance with
the relationship to those systems, by imagine. There are actually experiments
in India that are more illiterate
than needed and the people who were enrolled
in a two year school, they were monitored with fMRI
and they showed changes all over the brain almost. It's hard to point, you know,
this is not a verne kind, it broke areas everywhere. But the remarkable
thing, I think this is what we have to realize that our
communication or cypher system is based on a generative
grammar. That is of course part of the, this, this vocal language, but
one was written, the key thing is that
how humans figured out in all cultures, 20 to
35 elements, letters, to describe
the entire knowledge of humankind. That's an extraordinary
achievement and of course it was not designed, I remember no smart people,
just the general smart people, and they devolved.
And that's something that you can call human emotion
because no other species achieved.
I think what your saying is very provocative. But I'm thinking
that if Homer couldn't read and write and Muhammad
famously could not read or write, do you think their brains are working differently?
Yeah. I do think so. You think,
Muhammad who essentially wrote
or Homer that wrote all this wonderful material
that survives for thousands of years. He loved to be here. But he didn't, right? Yeah, but he didn't.
Me too. But he didn't, and it was all sung, right?
And the Quran rhymes, and no wonder people, remember it.
But still, I mean, it became written, but it wasn't
written by them. Christ didn't
write his stuff down. And yet, so you're saying that there was this
big transition in a way from
Muhammad to whatever, I forgot the
name of the person that described that started writing the Quran down.
They would have two different kinds of brains.
Okay, all right. You're focusing, I mean, unfortunate.
You're focusing too much on the alphabetic writing system.
And there, this is the issue of the relationship between
oral and the written. And the purpose of the alphabet is to represent
the oral. Therefore Socrates thought that writing
was actually a bad thing because it took you
one step further back from truth. Okay. But
I'm saying, or arguing, is that
the kiniform right is system and a hierarchical right is system for that matter.
They're not alphabetic. And so in the kiniform, which I know very well,
it's not, the intention is not to render speech.
The intention is to render something
reality in writing. Yes, you can make a connection
to speech, but actually perhaps initially it was not even connected
to speech. Initially, it may be just, I mean, the earliest
text we have, there is no clear connection to speech.
It is not a rendering of speech. It is rendering of reality
in a written form. That then
adjusts itself that when it comes to people who, with different
languages, who use this script to start including more and more
connections. Well, then I think what you're saying is the big jump isn't to writing.
I mean, I know, I mean, well, facetious, but it's not to writing.
It's to doing a form of writing that does reflect speech because the reason
we remember the Iliad or the Quran or
whatever is because they weren't done in written
speech with rhyme and meter so that people could retain it.
So, otherwise they would have forgotten. I want to kind of get back to this idea
that at the origins of spoken oratory,
but then I think especially writing,
there was a little bit of a, it meant something to people who were not
good at oratory for starts. They thought these folks who could
do this, they were performers, they were special.
And certainly once writing began, those who were illiterate
formed this gigantic sort of penumbra around the illiterate,
the literate folks, they saw a lot of these texts as being magical
but even though they couldn't penetrate it, they realized it was magical. It was something
magical about because there were experts who could derive things from it. So,
it's wrong to think that it didn't have any impact at all on the illiterate.
It was this group that was carried along with that.
I want to say one other thing before I forget it about the brain function and that is
there are these interesting neurological conditions like
Alexia where people cannot read from stroke and other sort of
brain knows a graphia where they cannot write. They often go together. They always go together.
We know their brains are the same as brains of people before
there was writing primarily. Something happened
there was some transformation in their brain but it's the same brain and it's an interesting
sort of mystery. For me, the
perhaps fundamental distinction early languages and clearly writings is that
the speech is storytelling. It's mostly about what we call
episodic memory or episodic information. That is, I'm part of the
agent who is communicating. Whereas the
early Cunay for writings were very abstract. They were all about semantics.
The semantics is of starting with counting
the number of bushels, the number of bags of
wheat and the number of sheep and so on. This is how the numbers
emerged as an abstracting because it was a practical
reflection of the activity of the humans who said
I counted sheep. Now, two years ago I was counting
doing something and the way I counted one, two, three, this is how the decimal system
was did I, and things like that. Then all of a sudden it occurred to the person
that in Cunay forms, early Cunay forms, the
ten bags of wheat has different ten
than the ten sheep because they specifically referred to the
referred thing. Later on, somebody said, maybe ten is
something I can use in counting anything. That was
an explicit semantic information. Later on
when the landages became more complicated or complicated but
more useful, then the storytelling came back also in
written languages.
One has narrative text relatively soon. It's relative
to the first, you know, written, you're talking about administrative
text and indeed they're the primary, they're the first things found
but we have narrative texts. Okay, 600 years later
admittedly, it's a long time on this. The one thing that
is very important in this, so indeed the administrative
documents are the primary documents found in the earliest writing
and this to me is very important. Alongside, there are lists of
words, lexical texts, or dictionaries
but they are actually in my reading of them, their study
of the written word. So it sees it
as it's not just making, well, what type of
sign, cuneiform signs do we have that we can use in administrative text
which actually takes, because they're visual signs and it takes
it and it plays around with them and come up with nonsensical
signs. You know, somehow they see that
there is an ability to create something, a reality
that is not connected to physical reality and that's purely
a written reality. Michael, what do you think?
Well, I am. My interest come way before
language, I should say, and the work but I'm very
familiar with the need and the concept is
cipher. On one hand, I've been working for years, trying
to what we call reconstruct the tree of life and the tree of life
is an evolutionary pattern that now is
an extraordinary time, at least in the last decade
and a half, that DNA sequences and the genetic
code is part of that evidence to reconstruct the tree. But DNA
has certain limitations. 99% of all life that ever
existed on this planet is extinct. And so
for those fossils, except with some very few, and my
friend Sponté Pablo, just won the Nobel Prize, his
work, you know, except for those exceptional
circumstances where the code has actually been recovered in
human fossils or things that are mammoth
skin and so forth, things that are very quite young, that
fossil record is really, really out of the
scope for DNA. So we have to rely on what actually
happen, the fossils that we find, and that
as Darwin recognizes, is an incredibly inconsistent
and spotty record. But you mentioned cipher and I think
what we have are cipher,
what happens in the advance of recovering this history
is the discovery of a cipher. So, and indeed
almost, it's almost a platitude you see occasionally
where someone will proclaim, oh I have this early hominid
fossil, it's the Rosetta Stone for human evolution, you know?
Everything is a Rosetta. But the reality is there are
ciphers, once in a while a fossil is an extraordinary cipher.
For example, Archaeopteryx, their earliest bird,
shows the definitive characters of both dinosaurs and birds.
And it's only in the last five or six, well
the last decade that we've come to recognize that
birds are not only related to dinosaurs, they are dinosaurs, they're just
a branch of dinosaurs. In fact, they're a branch of theropods
that are related to Tyrannosaurus, an overrafter, and a lot of things
that we've collected in the Gobi. So, you know, that's our cipher.
It was a combination of characters which was recognized by Richard
Owen in the early 20th century. He said, hey look, this thing
has some dinosaur-like characters. You didn't go much farther than that
than a John Ostermet Yale went a little further and then
people like Jacques Cotea and Mark, my colleague, really
you know, expanded on that. And so
it's, I think, we're always searching for ciphers, you know,
in the fossil record. And there aren't too many.
You know, it's a very rare event. That's why
there's so much attention paid to it. I think speaking for
the audience, can you say a little bit more about why birds are dinosaurs? That's really
pretty intriguing. Well, the
skeletal structure of a, if you, as
Richard Owen observed, if you strip that arkyoptic skeleton
of, you know, it's preserved in this incredible
way in the gerolimestone with impressions of feathers. And if you
strip that off this
animal, it looks like a small theropod dinosaur.
And it's hip structure, the orientation of the
pubis, the lower limb and the
very, very characteristic of a subgroup of dinosaurs, the
peripod dinosaurs, with the long claws and the extended
digits on the foot, and
a whole variety of other characters. So, and
of course, we discovered in 1993
with this very incredibly rich sight in the Gobion, and away
this sight, which we named Uka-To-God, the whole sight is a
cipher because it's preserved
hundreds of skeletons of dinosaurs, little mammals and lizards.
And compared to what we have
and what we found in Mongolia, in
North America, a lot of those animals, especially the smaller ones,
are represented only by isolated teeth and jaws.
We knew nothing about what they look like as whole animals.
We called those fossil spare parts because, you know, you have to
put everything together. Well, we discovered that
these overrafters were nesting.
We discovered the first nesting dinosaurs, and they were on a clutch of eggs,
and the eggs were always in an architectural
arrangement. And these dinosaurs
were capable, just like birds, of parental
care of their nests. So, there was once in
place, there was a window open to dinosaur behavior that
we never expected to find, once again, that kind of
and once again reinforcing the relationship between these
dinosaurs and living birds.
Just to amplify this point, how important this to have
a key or a cipher, the
ciphers lead to game-changing ways,
and the framework through which we see the world. As an example,
our effects on the philosopher introduced
a term called Alan Vitale. Nobody knows the young people
I'm talking about. Alan Vitale was the most
critical thing in the two centuries ago, because
it was impossible to explain
or conceive how from a seed you can make a tree
or a woman sperm you can make a human.
That must be a driving saw. Alan Vitale is a
drive of life. And it led
nowhere. All of a sudden DNA came around, it was a game changer.
Nobody talks about Alan Vitale anymore. Everything is explained, because
we shifted to a different framework from where things are
explained in a self-explanatory manner. Well, precisely, Darwin had
his theory of natural selection as solid,
but his mechanism for it is completely wrong, because he didn't have
that cipher. But I want to make a point about ciphers, because the
cipher you referred to earlier, Jorgi, about
the Rosetta Stone, was an explicit like this equals this,
that equals that. There has been the
ciphering that's going on here, clearly there's no key. There's no explicit
key in what you're doing in paleontology.
There are other methods that people have that try to make some sense
of decoding what is going on. So there's frequency,
the chronology, things of that nature. And also, am I wrong
about this, so linear B also was decoded
without an explicit key. Yeah, it is the code in the right.
The frequency of the appearance of certain units, elements
in the language, is used as a kind of a way to build up a key.
How often in the information being imparted
does what we think which would be, the letter E appears much more
than other letters, the letter Z, not very much, except in your name.
And mine is this part of it because everything
in nature is log normally distributed. The edges are the right end of this
q distribution. Exactly. No, but those sort of frequency
analyses and chronologies do help to build up
a sort of a key which doesn't necessarily, well, which is the best we can do.
But in order to do so, don't you need to have an understanding
of the general structure because indeed the letter E is
more common than the letter Z within the structure
of language. And those are the three words that are frequently used,
but not really changing or changing much slower
over the time of humankind. So they give you a language
when you are looking for common words in
Finoyuri for example, then we have a bunch of words
that are very basic and frequently used over centuries
such as blood, fingers and so on. And the rare
words are changing meaning a lot. Many Greek words
are used today in a totally different connotation, like
empathy. Everybody knows what empathy is. The real use in Greek is called
disgust. So all these
transformations happen because of the way how we
use language in everyday life. And these numbers or the
frequency distributions are very important tools to dig out
what are the common and what are the unique elements of changing
language. Also I think you need a context for interpreting
the key to recognize that key. So just thinking
back, forgive me about the fossil record,
there had to be, someone had to present
the idea that these things took place
over enormous amounts of time and that was a huge controversy. There was
an evidence directly for the age. We didn't have radiometric
dating or anything like that. There was basically
a concept of time with
being in this enormous expanse. And it
was rejected by most intellectuals of the time
until it finally took hold. So you needed some kind of
context to interpret even those
fossils, those cypress people were finding fossils during that time.
And thinking that maybe they were
casualties that didn't make it on the arc. So
you had to have some kind of context for interpreting the cypress
in the beginning and then first place.
I appreciate to imagine it as a type of patterning
to the types of materials that I work on
and the way that I work on them. There is no cipher because I'm
approaching it from sort of a cultural angle. So some of these
things resemble letters and some of these things resemble pictures. This really
just paying attention to the precise spatial context and sort of
broader practical context. And looking at patterns in the distribution that
enabled us to sort of create some sort of framework but interpreting them
because otherwise there is no interpretation. It's not, you know, they're not
words to represent something necessarily. What are those texts that you're referring to?
A lot of my research is on graffiti in Aramaic
or Greek in Syria and
the antiquity or the Middle East. And ways in which, I mean
to sort of park them back to us. You described it these
ways that people produce artifacts. We just don't know necessarily what
they're trying to communicate sometime except the patterns
and their distribution can be helpful. If they're graffiti and burial caves or
in places of prayer or worship or something like that. But
these are humans who might not have been able to
write a record of how many sheep or how many, well maybe
if it was a very limited vocabulary they could, but they're trying to express something.
I mean they're trying to commemorate a moment, an idea
and it's sort of trying to get a sense of what, why they're creating this sort of
artifact of presence or ideation or something.
How do you know you are writing? I don't. So because that's the, without
the cipher you have a consensus approach.
That was a wonderful expression of burning man that I often use.
That reality or the truth is what we all dream about together.
That's a wonderful expression except it's useless
because everything that we would like to define
has to be grounded one way or another. I have to communicate that
grounding to other cultures because other, no, your classic
or any classification can happen only from a point of view
from a classifier's point of view. Now we have, it can be classified in millions
where it's, you know, you have a beard, you have short hairs and so on.
That's really nice. So that kind of
classification is useful and then somebody comes in a different
framework and said, for sure. But then
you could say, well Ben what do we do? Do we just need to laugh?
I absolutely, I think that's why it's important to
create a sort of record your own framework of interpretation.
As long as we know that we are in a temporary
particular mindset, then it's, then it's okay.
This shouldn't bring us to time because you just
mentioned that people don't have, didn't have the concept of
very long time because human perception and
animals perception is based on this cute rule that
10,000 years for me is the same as the million years.
There is no way I can.
When I was a boy, as a kid, I was
obsessed by this issue. I just didn't understand
how you could understand time. And my parents took me to the
Grand Canyon. And I said, oh wow, I think I finally
got it because this is this immense place.
And it starts the bottom of the canyon. It's pre-cambrian
rockets, goes back billions of years. And then it goes to the top.
And then I realized the youngest rocks in the canyon were 200
billion years old. The stuff at the top. So there was even more.
I just, I can't wrap my head around that. And I still think,
even though we can date those rocks and even though we can
recover these lost communities and so forth from
eons ago, I still think
we don't quite perceive what that means.
We don't know what that means.
As a young boy, was somebody like humans
200,000 years ago. We had a vague concept
of space and time which meant that we are, nobody is in this universe.
Just tiny little things. And there is this huge thing.
Science approached it, well,
space and time became scientific concepts as
editing us when we started measuring them. So space was
replaced with distance, time was replaced with duration,
and then we came to an agreement with measuring instruments
such as the rod and clocks. Without such externalization of brain function and
a universal agreement on things, space and time
is nothing. If you continue discussion, I will explain you that there is no space
at no time. But, and indeed, once you
started to look at those stratifications, those are concrete.
Those could be looked at. And then you look at the physical
process, or not you, but geologists have said, the evolution
of this is this long, according to
biometric, then you have an agreement. Well, while
you know, looked at those rocks, and then
it went down to a beach or a river,
and it's, well, wait, I can see in these rocks these pebbles
are streaming out. I can see these things forming. Now,
let's see how long that takes. And it went out in the beach and nothing happened.
You could sit there for a month. And then you saw a little bit of sand
being deposited on a sandbag.
And so he said, hey, this takes a huge amount of time
to create what you see here in this rock record. Yeah, I want to
go back to something Karen just said earlier, you challenged a little bit,
and I'm just going to talk a little bit about how do you know,
how could you confirm what you're seeing when you look at these
archaeological things, and you said, well, it's true.
A consensus gets built. And you tell your story,
your account, the best you can, and then you wait to hear what sort of other
colleagues and experts in the field think, and you slowly build it up. Okay, to me, that's what
language is also to, isn't language a consent, or we think
language itself forms as some sort of social thing. Everyone agrees
that we're going to use the word red, whatever the original
wrote, whatever the original red was, that we all kind of get into
this consensus. And interestingly, that seems to give the
semantics to meaning, right? So you can say, well,
what you're doing right now seems to be a little
in co-ed maybe, at worst. I don't think it is, but you know,
it may be it'll come closer and closer as consensus, and it might go down the wrong path.
The consensus may be this in a long direction, and that's
just what you're dealing with. But I think there's something lost in that, because
the next topic I'm interested in talking about is, well,
is there anything lost in changing to the thinking of things being
all a coed? Like, do you miss something? Because it's
reductionistic to a degree, right? You know? You only miss tons of things, because
again, we are human and landmen
chauvinistic. But we can look at the same problems with a different direction.
So semantics or explicit knowledge can be derived in
all animals one particular way, which is my own experience.
So one, I have one experience, I have another experience, another experience.
And from those interactions or intersections of those experiences,
something becomes explicit. That is
the events are stripped off from this
spatial temporal conditions, and it may become
explicit. When I've seen a first dog in my life, I said, it's an
episode, it's an experience. I see another dog and another dog, and then I created
the explicit knowledge of darkness,
and I know what it is. Now, this is fantastic.
Humans with landage have another way
of producing semantics, which is, ticks are given to you
by an authoring, such as your parents, such as your teachers, and so on.
They said, this is a USB. This is an iPhone.
And I can use it because I was told about the utility
of that thing, and it goes along for a long time, and I
have no reason to go into it, even though I don't know what's in USB. I don't even know what
USB stands for. I just know what this is. So humans
can give, there's a little
funnel here, and then pouring a lot of knowledge into the
head of a newborn, a child, because we can
do, and people who cannot generate episodes in their lives that are people
without people can pull systems, they still
can get around because they have this enormous freely
given semantic information. The catch is this,
because it's not your experience. You don't go through the verification
process. You don't ground those things. And then I start believing that
I'm a good Democrat because this is my framework.
Or I'm a good Republican because this is my framework, and I never
questioned my framework because that was given to me. I never questioned those words
that were given to my teacher, my priest, or if I have one, or
or authoricists. So that's an interesting
thing, and that's why I say that when we
split things to
it's, or carve nature by its
joints, and we are trying to go, this is the only time when you have to think about that
seriously. Where everyday violence is not a big deal. You know, culture is not a big deal when we are
classifying this and that, but when we are going to the roots of things,
then this is the key to think about, and this is the
key to think about it. Absolutely. It needed the approach for space and time as well.
I'm going to go back with this issue of language because
we have to get to exact term that he uses, but now I'm Trump's
case, idea of other linguistics is totally different from what you're saying.
It's not something that is taught to us, language is not taught to us, but
language is somewhat inherent into the human being
as a species. I'm afraid I can't. I mean, I hope
I'm not talking about something that is totally
alien to you. I thought you all thought you'd say. No, no, you just brought up a can of worms.
It's going to go way longer than two hours.
I should have not. Yeah, not a lot. I mean, happy to get into that, but
maybe briefly. Really briefly? I mean,
for me personally, in my own work, I sort of dismiss all of that.
There are all forms of animal communication
that have nothing to do with those roles.
And then it becomes, for me, very, very arbitrary
about what we call language friendly. I mean,
the Consul Batcha Cup studies, have you ever read these things?
These are fantastic. This is a spell he just retired, but
anyway, he studies prairie dog communities in
Arizona, and the different communities have different
communities. To us, they just sound, they're 100 milliseconds, right?
And so to us, they all sound the same. But if you simply record them
and slow them down, you find out that they have
different meanings. One of them will mean
the coyotes coming from that direction. He even
did experiments with graduate students wearing different color
t-shirts, and they were able to assign
a call to each of the colors that the graduate students used to.
And they were able to distinguish one of the graduate students in a different
way, even if she was shorter than all the other ones.
Those useful graduate students. Yeah, yeah. And then he would do things like
shoot a rifle. He'd shoot a rifle off on the side, and then they would develop a new
vocabulary for that. So, yeah, no, it's fantastic. It's great work.
Is it language? But in this case, wait, isn't
that analysis based on looking at
a stimulus and then the frequency of the response?
Like, it's a little bit of a syntactical analysis, because you're talking about the
formal aspects of those sounds. And that's exactly what we do when you
try to decode a script that we don't know, right?
I don't think it's inconsistent with, I'm not a Chomsky fan either, but I happen to think
that's not inconsistent. You could say, well Chomsky would say, yes, but in humans,
the way language forms, the formal aspects, syntactical
aspects, have a certain form, and we can rely on that to do an analysis
of the difference. So he would exclude that as a language,
and I just frankly stay out there. Yeah, yeah.
And use the word language, like when you're referring to
prairie dogs or dolphin. He would use the language. Well, I would use communication,
mostly because I don't want to get down that road of defining
languages, because to me, okay, this is what I really think.
I think that a lot of academics like to use
languages a way to differentiate our species
from all other species. Right. And so I just don't want it.
I don't want to have to do it for them. I think it's a waste. For me personally, it's a waste of time.
I don't think anybody has that. There are very few landmages
that landmages completely human. Yeah, but no M does.
He still says it now. No, you're he still says it now.
I know, but then he has a lot of followers
in different departments. It's like you were saying
some, the what
Vita, it's like if we were still arguing about
getting the homunculus from the semen into the
egg. I mean, it's just something I want to put aside.
I agree this as a prominent person, but I think any linguist would agree that
communication is a better, perhaps more general word and
I can communicate with my dogs by cats and
there's no question that we communicate or they communicate with each other.
Do they have syntactic arrows? Yes, they have.
Do they have the same land with Gs? And we know that birds have also
some of the most complicated things like questions.
The French dogs communicate differently than American dogs.
Different language? So, let's say interesting
thing that brings me back to my
my,
my, what says it funnel that
we put a lot of stuff into our brains is because, interestingly, there is a
big
key for humans or big discrepancy between
knowledge of humankind and the
individuals share. My share of human Christ knowledge is extremely ridiculous.
And it's getting worse and worse and worse obviously every day.
Now dogs, they are not going to be
very good today. Now dogs, from anywhere
they have pretty much the same knowledge of
the kind, anyway, in the world. Do they have
cultural differences?
There might be localities. Are there
cultural inheritances in animals? Yes, there are. There are no monkey groups
in Okinawa. These are rizous monkeys. They wash potatoes.
And once that, that tradition is
gone, then perhaps it's gone forever.
There are many cultures that, like the
Tasmanian cultures, like the Icelandic
cultures and Greenland, that cultures, they all disappeared because
the people who had the knowledge died and
then they couldn't make new canoes. They didn't make arrows
and things like that, all of a sudden, that civilization
just disappeared because of the lack of this knowledge.
I have to tell this story, mostly because it's amusing, and I want to
move away from having this roundtable devolve into a talk about animal consciousness
which we love to do here at Helix but we're good at.
The story which may be a good segue is, there was a study about
cats looking into whether cats understood their names.
I think this is just a wonderful story.
As opposed to other words, they might hear. So they do an MRI of the cat
and they call the cat's name. And sure enough, the researchers found, yes,
cats can distinguish their name from other words, spoken to them.
They just don't care. Yeah, that's right.
So, it's really funny, but it does say something about
what then do you do?
It's really, the cat's decoded tabby.
It's decoded it. Some part of his brain, anyway, seems to evidence
that it's been decoded. But then what does the cat do with that code?
Is that creates a meaning for the cat, right?
No, I love that story because they really don't give a damn and it's very interesting to me
to be around people that are trying to decode, for instance,
the SETI group, which you probably read about this, trying to decode
the whale song by doing deep learning and the fellow running
that says, well, we just need more data. That's all we need. And it's
nonsense, frankly. I mean, God bless them for doing that and I'm glad somebody
else is doing it. But Roger
Payne, the fellow who discovered whale song, he tried to
you know, he's done over 50 years
of following the whales and interacting with them as well as we can.
And he was trying to imagine what the conversation would be and the conversation would essentially be,
okay, where's the food now?
And I'm tired of smelt.
Give me octopus. I'm tired of smelt. And that's the kind of,
and this also reminded me of
conversations with Oprah Chernofsky, who you probably know is a bird scientist.
And he says, you know, he spent his life around these
songbirds and he says, you know, they really think
we are very slow. I mean, we can't possibly catch them,
and we're very stupid. And the stuff that we worry about is just
nonsense. And I think that's right. I think we're going to put a little bit...
He's absolutely right. And you're right with yourself. In our field,
COVID-19 neuroscience, neuroscience, we made this mistake all the time because of our inheritance.
That is, we are giving the world
to the brain. We are recording from the brain something, such as firing
or fMRI singles, and then we find a relationship.
And we think we are decoding the brain, and you
have only been New York Times. The fact is that their message
is message only for outside observers, because only the
outside observer has the luxury of seeing the outside world and what's happening in the brain.
Neurons in the brain have no clue. They don't know if there is
anything outside. The only thing they have is the activity there.
So what comes into the world, there has to be grounded. It has to be
connected to something that something has.
You have to have a second dominion. The only thing that's available for the
brain, that is for us as humans, also is through our
actions and our verification of things.
Others, those are... Our things are verified independently.
Everything is just a consensus.
That doesn't really help us at all.
So, you know, when it comes to
communication, so brains work some... We use a lot of imagination,
but that has to be looked at. And I can give you many, many examples that
we have tons and tons of misunderstanding. Once you start recording from the brain
and you ask whether those patterns that we thought were
going to be authentic, these things, actually means something to the brain.
If you don't have that grounding knowledge,
you know nothing. Well, a good way to think about that would be, in this
goes, returns to Shannon's discussions about information.
You know, and he made a very strong effort to say, look, this is
not information in the sense of like knowledge. It's not meaning.
It's just how you get the code. There's a code for the information,
right? And it's just imagine
a signal comes across a wire or the airwaves and it's the word
dog, right? Okay, dog. Now, that's wonderful.
I heard it. It's the word dog. Now, why is it then, then, if I
want, I can go to the library or I can think of myself. I can write an essay
on dogs about all of my experiences and thoughts about dogs. I can
write a poem. I can make a song. I can write a song about dogs, right?
And so, and those individual expressions of mine will be,
I hope, rich and elaborate. And it goes well beyond just the
single word dog that the information came along, but it doesn't have the
full richness of dogness for me, right?
And I think that's an important... But it doesn't. It's just a few. Yeah.
Because you represent... Right, but the code
only provides a key to triggering that sort of,
you're saying there's a context into which these codes
find themselves and then the rest has to do with the way the
humans respond to it. That's why I was saying earlier, if a
illiterate looks at writing, especially I think back
in the ancient times, it would have a very strong
meaning to them, although it was not the explicit meaning that the code
seemed to be trying to convey, right?
So, back to the notion of the cipher, you know, to my mind,
I think what ciphers are, they are
the means of falsifying consensus.
And there's so many classic examples of that. I mean, plate tectonics,
everybody thought continents didn't move. And even though
there was a concept for moving continents,
it wasn't really... It didn't really falsify consensus until
as examples of real science brought up here,
paleomagnetic reversals,
patterns on the ocean floor showed
actually that the ocean seafloor was spreading and these continents
moved. So that happened almost a century
after the concept of continental drift.
So the cipher, the key was
paleomagnetics and it falsified
what most scientists believed at the time. And the Russians still,
some of the Russians still believe that continents still move, but
it's an exceptional community.
There are these paradigm shifts, okay?
And we should, I mean, I think we shouldn't be too arrogant
into believing that now we have found that. So, it was a
century or next year, you will find some, you know,
some other revelation that will create
a different type of idea. I'm in a field with violent arguments
about this because I keep encountering and
in combat with, say, genomics people
who say, now we have the true tree. We know exactly
what was related to what. And I'm in a
school or a group of people who say, we don't. We may never
have the true tree. I'd be very much like in technology.
She were describing. Have you read
Integral Tree? No. This is exactly about
the darkest tree and today's different branching and how you
classified all ocean in different ways. It's an extraordinary
good, you know, time vessel, this thing.
It's still very good. I think one of the reasons
I was interested in coding is I feel, in many ways,
we were in this sort of paradigm of computers being the answer to everything
we're going to apply, a computer model to understand every
phenomenon we come across. And I thought, well, I'm interested in coding
and I think it's not all a bad thing, but I feel there's some
a little overreach. Well, isn't it because
in medicine, it's everything's genetic.
Oh, I wouldn't say that. But there's a lot that's genetic.
Yeah, but then you see I have identical twins, which are except for
T cell receptors and antibodies are genetically
identical and they're obviously not identical. So now I wouldn't say that.
And some of them develop, we have ones with plenty cases of somebody develops a disease
and the identical twin never develops it. This is the biggest problem we have
in neuroscience that we've got inbred that is identical
twins and these are 50 to 100 generations.
Yeah, so embarrassing that you take 10 animals and
two of them are outliers all the time. Yeah, yeah, still.
So yeah, I would say, okay, maybe sometimes people
pretend that everything's genetic. But it is a paradigm.
It's a powerful paradigm. Well, the discovery was so exciting.
People are dead or you can identify
genes. Oh, absolutely. I mean, there are plenty of
you if you have the Tysock's gene, if you have sickle
cell, you might develop the disease at different ages, but
eventually you will develop the diseases. But there are plenty of others where
you will never have. But like in paleontology
that's the thing too now. Are you talking about
genome? So we're all looking at these
particular questions with a new lens that is say that
we think enable us to create these
genealogical trees and things like that. That might
mean, in my understanding, the whole issue of
human evolution has radically changed in whatever. The 80s
or something like that? Yeah, well, and now, but there's still
a lot of arguments even with all this new genetic information,
genomic information. There's still a lot of arguments
about the mobility of
homo sapiens and the relationship to homo erectus
and whether or not there was one exit from Africa or
25 exits or it's not a field that I'm really
deeply involved in. But even with the
arrival, and in the areas where I work, I work primarily in
evolution. And there's still some big
uncertainties and controversies in that area even with all
this genomic information. Some of it's working
extraordinarily unbelievably well. And as you can tell, I'm skeptical, but still
the fact that you're saliva can find your second cousin
in other countries is pretty astonishing. And the fact that Google
Translate is doing so well, even though it kind of cheated in some ways in the way
but it's working immensely well, right? You just said
probably everybody's using it. I wanted to ask the neuroscientists
here just say a few words about how you go about
to the degree the word decoding applies to what you're doing. How do you go about it?
Because you don't necessarily have a key.
So we do have a key. At least I'd like to let me have a
few. And the interesting thing you said, you're interested in mammalian evolution, so am I,
but from a different aspect of you. Part of the most fascinating thing, but
the brain for me is that in every
memo what remains constant
over the evolution time is timing.
That is the brain reasons you might heard about alpha, beta,
gamma oscillations and delta and so on. These are
not only individual ones, but they form a hierarchical system
in such a way that slow oscillations are
modulating the amplitude of the faster ones and the phase
of the faster one modulate the amplitude of the even faster ones.
So it's like the tie
is changing and then upon the changes the
amplitude of the
beta is changing. Now this is good because
when you ask how come that you scale up a
system 50,000 fold from the small brain to the
size of the brain of a wave,
what is the rule of this evolutionly scaling? What should remain
constant and what remains constant is timing through
this oscillation because they are preserved. It would take
the turn 30 seconds. Why is that? Because this is
what they call the neural syntax. This is the
time packages which allow that you said
information if you want those piking activity from one area
of the brain to another area of the brain because the other area of the brain is already
given the cipher which is the time window. If you don't have
that framework, this neural syntax, then brain areas
cannot communicate with each other. We cannot communicate with each other. The reason why you
understand me is because even though I have an
accent and I have made so many mistakes is because I have a
particular tempo which is about 4 Hertz which is
characteristic of every single human language which is also not only the
utterances but also the perception. And the reason for that is because both the utterances
as well as the perception of these events are based on
brain rhythms. So again we have to go inside
and train in order to have the grounding and that's the grounding for me
the grounding of the origin of language and classification
and cipher. How much of this
formal appreciation of these constant
relationships? How much of it is
a purely sort of mathematical
1 over F distribution? How much is it divergent
that? Does that help you? Because
if it's very generic, it's very simple.
It's not only generic, but you already know the content
of these patterns. And if something is short
it means that in a system which has
constraints on the speed of communication, the brain is a very
slow system. You know the conduction velocities of the
neurons is on the order of 0.2 to
several meters per second. Very, very slow. So given
that if you have a short amount of time available it means that only your
immediate partners can be involved. That is
short means small number of neurons. More time
means larger number of neurons. And then the
cool goal of this communication is that whatever happens locally can be
broadcasted globally as well as the global brain
state. You know what the activity
pattern in the brain is constraints how local communication or local
cipher can be generated.
If you take away the cipher, if you take away the
voltage, if you take away all of these brain latins, the end of the day
is that every single psychiatric disease is
associated with one or other type of timing problems.
It's difficult to differentiate diseases from
each other because those are all arbitrary. But it's very
easy to look at the brain even
at a depressed patient with its depressed state or non-depressed state
that is very different. So the timing, the communication
is absolutely matters and that's what I'm
pushing for that we have a sittactical system.
I'm thinking as a very general level this idea of extracting
some understanding of meaning from either brain activity or
artifact assumes a certain sort of background
either it could be in the various mathematical descriptions of it. It could be noise.
It could be a 1 over F frequency. These are background
mathematically defined substrate
and we think we find meaning when
something diverges from that, something you give a stimulus is no longer
it doesn't have that baseline anymore.
That's a way of building a key. Isn't that in a way when you
don't have the literal, you set it up so you're right
but then there is a deviation. This is when many brain structures kick
in and it happens to what's called phase receptor
and all of a sudden the timing changes
and that timing change is detected elsewhere. If that is not detected
as happens in schizophrenia and then other diseases that's a big problem.
Okay, great. Wow.
Time went fast. All right. I guess the question is do we have
any folks want to ask questions of our panel?
Thank you.
Thank you all so much.
Sorry everyone is sitting down
so I'm going to sit down too. Hi everyone thank you that was really
fascinating. My name is Celia Emery. I'm a museum architect
and my concern relates to I guess
for the politics of coding, the psychology of coding
and where agency fits in. So in museum design we have
two aspects of time space. One of them is the path
of the visitor in the spaces of the institution
and people enter into a building with a pre-existing idea of how they're going to use it
because they're adults, they're free agents and they've already learned how to use buildings.
So on museum institutions
set up what that time space
experience is going to be and yet there's a conflict, there's a schism
within any use of any building which is that we as
individual agents want to be able to act in our own way we want to be able
to affirm. So your reference to the graffiti was so interesting I'm about to go to
Alula to visit the Hegra tombs and there's a lot of graffiti
we'll talk. But apparently it was
speculated that that graffiti was just journeyers writing down
that they had arrived, in other words I am here, Joe was here
and in fact that isn't, that is what much of the graffiti is. So that
kind of need for us to kind of the ego to kind of exist
somewhere and market somehow within a coding
system. So the other schism that we have is that
in a museum you have a relationship between a
person and that artifact which was created in a different point of time. So it's in a different
space, it's in a different time. So how do we, so there's two different aspects of this, I'm going to
get to this point. In epigraphic and cuneiform
the who was control, my question for the group is really
who has the control of these forms of ideology?
Who is creating, who is benefiting from the
cuneiform methods, why? And who was
benefiting from written language and why? How come that
didn't continue to exist? And then how do we as individual agents
kind of fit in? Like aren't we, are we just obeying
the ideological precepts that have been handed down to us?
Or do we have any agency within coding?
Sorry, can we do so long?
Well let me start with the specific question of who benefited
from cuneiform. You can have a very materialistic
interpretation and that's the usual interpretation. It's a
way of dealing with a more complex system of especially
economic interaction, therefore you need some type of record keeping
that goes beyond time and space
that can travel from one
place to another place or is kept
for a specific period of time.
To take it to this greater
level of, you know, when the
writing system, what the writing system has a meaning beyond
a purely practical writing system. Well, I wouldn't call it an
ideology, it's a philosophy, it's an approach to reality.
It's an attempt at understanding
reality that yes, is shared by an intellectual elite just
as today philosophical discourse is shared by
intellectual elite but it frames a cultural
you know, it creates a cultural setting
that yes, the entire civilization
if you can use that term, you know, is part of even
a lot of the majority of people are not
consciously aware of the elements of this.
I'd just like to say that, you know, one of the
roles I have at the museum and I still have is I have oversight of exhibition.
So I really understand what you're saying about what the visitor
how does the visitor engage or how does the museum engage
with the visitor and the question you have and who has agency there
and there's always so the trend in recent
years of course has been interactivity, interactivity,
interactivity and they're generally many of them are experiments that fail
because you make assumptions about what visitors
really want and the problem is that's based on you
European, you're not the visitor, you know,
and it's fascinating just to think about
what's happening in a museum, what happens when a
visitor encounters an artifact or a fossil or
a piece of tapestry or whatever in that sense.
Well I think there are just many interesting
questions that you raise and I'm very jealous of your
that's true. I hope you'll open the university case.
But that said, I think it seems you're a
dependent in terms of proof benefits because it has to do with how
communication works in individual societies and today
in a global society working literally in code benefits
very different people than at least
geographically. It's sort of a more
sense of something much more diffuse than when you're talking about individual
ancient societies or medieval societies where certain practitioners
were sort of deputized of being the record keepers and they could derive
status from their roles as such or
proximity to different ranges of literacy would allow people to sort of
pen themselves accordingly in that order of status
or esteem. And to go back to a point that you made earlier,
I mean this is why we literally have tons of
whether we call them magical texts or texts of ritual power
a lot of times they're total gibberish. At least
us they seem to be and they don't seem to accord with any particular script
that we know of because it seemed like it
resembled writing to people who couldn't write they wouldn't know the difference.
And so there's a power to that and sometimes it was just something esoteric
deliberately esoteric but I think the ways in which we relate
to sort of dominant types of communication allows us to sort of
fit into broader constructs of status, cultural
economic and otherwise. But I think it's really sort of culture dependent
I think when we talk about antiquity again it's very different from
today when we talk about code and coding and who's benefiting from their
ability to be able to work with certain languages on computers
it's you know many more people than 20 years ago
but who are those people right and how do they use that information
it's something that I can't possibly triangulate
that others might but I think it's definitely indicative
it's a symptom of something that's shifting in our global society that I
can't interpret but because it's something
sort of different it'll be interesting to see work.
The key phrase you have is relate.
I think that's the most important thing in the museum and I'm looking for
creations that allow me to go to a place and I lose
my sense of time. All of a sudden I can devote
my entire mind to what's going on there. Once I do that
I all of a sudden have
first point of view rather than a third person, first person point of view
rather than the third person point of view of everything.
Now you ask about the agency that I become an agent
because somehow you transform me and I will be
part of the participants of those events even though I had
no knowledge about that if continents go together.
But I use my imagination, I use my existing knowledge, I use my existing belief
systems to relate myself to that situation.
Now the agency is not human
every animal has the desire
and everything to learn these boundaries
we know that we have boundaries and that's the
essence of even a mobile or every single creature that
knows that it has boundaries and relates into everything else.
That relatedness is the super important thing. If I go to a
museum where I have to interact, this is what kids when they
go to New Jersey, the science museum I see, it's the same thing as a physics class.
Plus maybe they can do more freely and the teacher is not watching.
This is a fascinating thing because yes we are always saying
the museum is important, it was important to reopen
after COVID because this is a place, this is it gives people a sense of place
but what's really interesting is for a lot of people this is their place
this is there and increasingly
and there might be a dichotomy in society maybe that will break down
as people die and younger and younger people come up but
you can see it in a daughter
or somebody close to you that you know intimately
what their reality is compared to
what you're trying to do with visitors coming to a museum.
So two examples that work for me very well, of course it requires
the relatedness, the Japanese shinto goddess.
It's simple but you lose the sense of the time immediately
because you are just looking at the rock. The other one is an extreme
other thing that Selena also knows about, you know, a marine abramovich
when she was sitting in the over there
there was nothing there except a pair of eyes and you were
looking to see yourself in those eyes and all of a sudden
you had a means of saying you can discover yourself
if your museums spaces can create that
thing that discover yourself you leave the museum with a better feeling
or recreation then there's the look.
The institution is really because the organization has telling you what's in the
information. Exactly, they want to convey information. I don't need information, I have enough.
My own personal experience which is
taken for what is worth I'm not a I have nothing to do with PCMs except as a
museum goer but you know a lot of what makes science interesting
are controversies and challenges within a paradigm
and the challenges within a paradigm can be small
and they can be in the verge of some cataclysmic change
and that's really I think interesting to people
I would think it's interesting to people. I think it's a mistake to use the word controversy
for a devol. I would stay away from that word because I think it makes people think
well there are experts and you're already distance from it. There are experts
and the word controversy personally for myself sort of is off putting
it makes it seem like this is a little bit good to be beyond me. I think it's really
useful to say here that just lay out the different ideas
side by side and don't refer to it as being some raging
controversy among experts.
I just want to express appreciation for
everyone who does this work and it partly relates to fun.
I found and this is also relating to what you asked before is there a difference
to humans between something that's a million years ago or 10,000 years ago
and I find that with my students anything that happened
before the year 2012
is ancient history. The time is completely compressed
and obviously my students are not as they're not working in the same capacity
if you were to look with graduate students in your field or
you with yours or you with yours because they're already very much aware
of the stretch of time. But to me
the ways that museums have the capacity to jar
people from the present reality and to
force them to confront chronology and
time whether it's I feel like it's activist work
these days and the power of losing yourself in those places
being jarred from your phone. It's different when you're talking
about academics or researchers or specialists in the
general public. I think it's one of the only places where
we can remind people that there's a world beyond themselves
chronologically, culturally and beyond the human
realm too and I think it's that is what I feel like is increasingly
lost in the world of coding and it's just such
important work. So anyway you can make people uncomfortable enough
to be present in their spaces and learn is a contribution
to everybody. Do you take your
students in the field? Do you notice the difference? Absolutely
I am so extraordinary now.
I teach in a history department so not all my
students expect to specialize in anything that relates to
antiquity but I tell them that I think the tradition
about museums is that you know it's from European tradition
these are places to appreciate art and being able to appreciate it in a particular
way. It's a status thing, it's an appreciation thing
so I tell them these are libraries
they're like visual libraries in a way not like not that that's such a
great advertisement for them either but rather than being something flat
and two dimensional it's something you get to enter and immerse yourself into
and when it's really effective I remember because I teach
in Brooklyn, I teach in Flatbush and some of my students have never been to
the Met and I remember the first time when I started teaching Maron I
brought a class in the Met and I remember the student who looked up the
grand staircase and he just was like well you know
because it's just a different environment, a different world
and when you don't approach it as art but you know objects that are
artifacts that can teach us about different places in times that these
you know that they can investigate it's totally transformative and it's something that a lot of
people take for granted in lots of different places but
I think it's again like a form of activism
to remind people they're not the center of the universe and their phones are not the center of the universe
but the world is not flat so
sorry that's the thank you.
Is there another question?
As I hear everyone talking about decoding it seems to me that there's a little bit of
sort of an incompatibility of some fundamental
assumptions that especially as I hear this coming out in the debate about consensus
so it seems to me that there are kind of two different approaches here
to what decoding actually is so
I've kind of like set out a number of binaries here trying to make sense of this for myself
seems on the one hand there's a sort of approach to denotation and on the other
an approach to connotation as it pertains to decoding meaning.
You know you could say that there's a kind of idea here of
this context or I guess thinking about
what you were saying about the brain in a sense that there's a synchrony
you called that synchrony a key but I don't think that that's a key to meaning that's just a
condition of possibility for interpretation of meaning.
So I guess I'm wondering in this discussion of coding one
whether you all would agree that there are two different approaches
to thinking about what meaning is and whether that's a
disciplinary problem or something else.
You ask an easy question please.
So
you said synchrony is not exactly the same
as brain waves but nevertheless I didn't make a claim
and nobody does that we can decide for the content
that say it's a you know grandma has a large
way of defining things but one of them
is you could call it the phonetics of that and
that's without content so that's what brain it was about.
Now the meaning is the essential thing of everything unless
my students show me that that relationship between
what the experiment that proposed to the brain and the responses there
has a message for the rest of the brain or to the animal
that's not there is no meaning. So meaning has to be
generated only through utility at least this is what the view
in evolution as well as in the animal world
is that if particular thing comes with a plus or minus
in the life of the animal that generates meaning. So
many ways the way how today's neuroscience is studied
we think that it's a like slate and then you just shovel
information into this your brain and so on and you can
with which means that the complexity of the brain whatever
we do is growing as you learn more and more and more
and that's exactly what happens in an AI system and it collapses
very soon because there are so much stuff interfering with each
other. Another way of thinking about this is that
brain comes already with an equipped
dictionary. Every single thing that exists in your future life
is already there and the parents that
we thought were generated in over in fact they
pre-exist. So what happens is that out of this realm of
possibilities you experience something that goes in
one way or another positive or negative and that pattern that was present
at the time when that experience happened becomes
meaningful. It will have a utility for now or the future of the organism
this is how we generate meaning. Now the linguist
or a human person who thinks about may have another way of
phrasing it but I think that would be just rephrasing the same kind of thing.
I'm going to drive you guys both of you crazy. I mean to me I'm not sure what meaning
means here but there are I mean
if it means something as simple as you know
when I talk about brain rhythms I mean if I if you stimulate
a synaptic input to a muscle
fiber that muscle fiber will twitch and if you do it over here
there's a couple of extra steps
but no this muscle will twitch and if you
go over here this muscle will twitch and if you just go
a few you know bottom millimeter on the
other side you will hear something or you will feel something
and in a particular part of your body. Is that meaning? Because if it is then it's
based in okay so rise it not meaning
because it has no relation to experience
but what if what
it's remapping?
So I'm going to press you on that it can change
so we can we can remap
this to hear instead of there and this happens
all the time when people have strokes for instance.
Now is it meaning?
I would say it would be meaningful in the context
that we understand how
I think we have to finish up. I always want both of you but
here it becomes so there are things that are not there but when you have a stroke
it becomes a meaning so when you touch your nose
with your toe
it feels it has a meaning for you because it feels at the same
now that meaning is acquired through experience
and because you feel at the same time I can show you that anybody can show you that
it's not at the same time it's a much longer time to go from here
or from my nose but that for me as a utility I don't care about the mechanism
I just know it's at the same time so that's a meaning for
me because I can use that information
anything that I can use utility determines meaning
That's a really unsatisfying discussion right
yeah that meaning is the most
difficult thing. Yeah we have to move on right it's interesting it's an interesting question.
So I've learned so much this morning and I'm very grateful
and it has led to many different questions but I'm just going to bring it down to one.
I wonder what happens in terms of when emotion enters
what happens to how people approach things and I'm thinking
now at the Morgan Museum right now there's an exhibit
on Erduana I'm sure you've already seen it you've probably been talking
to Sydney Bactog about it or
but it goes from agriculture being discussed in terms
of bushels which you were mentioning versus
handling of harvest through this highly
emotive charged poem by this priestess about plow my
fields plow my fields as an erotic
situation so I'd love to know what happens in terms of
the evolution of mind that brings that in
or the world where we are a man in his bassel in Egypt
you know where that's a whole other very highly
emotive interaction.
So are you asking within the context I mean
the fact that it becomes something that it's
written down? No that you
can approach the harvest through the number of bushels
or you can approach the harvest as a kind of analogy of becoming
together of sky and earth, male and female what happens
what's happened in the mind that opens it
up to that kind of approach. Well, metaphorical
language I don't know if that's, I assume it predates
writing, metaphorical language where we
connect something physical let's say
that's physical in one area of life and metaphorically
we connect it to another area of life I would imagine
that that pre-dates the origins
of writing one of the great things about poems like
the American Epics is rich, it is with metaphorical
language and what I find interesting about metaphorical
language you mentioned in the Ishidwana poem is
or metaphor or metaphors are contained within a
cultural structure in order to make sense so
abundance of fields makes sense in a particular type of society
actually I discussed metaphorical language with my students
only a couple of days ago living in New York City they have no connection
at all to the metaphors that are being used in ancient
poetry because they're mostly rural metaphors and so
but I do that I think is yeah there is a system there
of clothing as well you have to understand
you have to understand the cipher you have to understand the system
if I compare something to an
object, an entity, a natural phenomenon that none
of you have ever experienced you're not going to understand my metaphor
but just also in terms of
image making or expression and emotion I think that's more what I'm
wondering about especially now with all the talk about emotion and cognition
and what the interaction is between them and I just thought
how do you express emotions?
How do you render emotion
orally or in a written form?
You can only do so I think by using
comparison, I mean love is a feeling of
whatever fire etc etc.
I think we're also going to have the opportunity to reflect on some of this issue in her
fiction, fiction, meta-fiction talk later today because I think
really for me the answer and response in part to what you were asking is that
there's a dialectic that goes back and forth between metaphorical
poetic sort of meaning, phenomenological meaning and then
the way it gets encoded and then the codes create the opportunity for more
engagement with meaning because the codes themselves can have meaning
so I think it's a
very interesting dialectic did you ever know? Oh sorry
Hi, please. Hi. This last question
sort of prompts me to rise.
I have this thought I've been developing for a long time and it seems to
coordinate with a lot of the different themes that we've had this morning
Prior to the development of language
there was a great deal of intelligence in
early humans they survived and
so the way. The thought
just to make it very general is that
the evolutionary pressure which leads eventually to the most powerful
evolutionary movement which is the development of culture
really requires the development of language because we have to
express to larger groups over time
over generational time
the development of language seems to be
a cognitive way of thinking which is
pairs of opposites which is as you say positive
or negative and so on. The metaphorical thinking
is not it's more analog
the earliest need
for language I want to suggest or I think
is the communication of what we would call mythic
kinds of ideas it is what forms a
group it's what gives self-identity
to the group and the evolutionary pressure is in the direction
of groups that are more tightly bound more coherent
those are the successful ones.
So how does that happen? Evolutionarily
the thought that I have and I don't have your expertise to know
whether it makes sense to you which is why I guess I am saying this
is that we develop a
the brain develops a sensitivity to certain
kinds of narrative that we think of as mythic
we recognize mythic ideas mythic
narrative in a different way it's not about the content
there is something that we feel is mythic which would
require a physiological development
evolutionarily based in the brain
and so we end up with two kinds of minds a cognitive
which is all linguistics are cognitive
and the same intelligence that we had before we
developed language and those two different minds
are not being commensurate they cannot communicate with each other
you can't be thinking about metaphor in a cognitive
way and understand the power
and if you try to translate it into cognitive
forms you lose the power
and so we have these two different minds
just as a further development of that is the notion
that that which can communicate
is myth mythic stories mythic
ways of thinking is what gives us
a sense of wholeness where we can see the world
with the two incommentral intelligences
anyone?
We were talking downstairs over coffee before a little bit about
people have written books that are very similar to what you're saying
and I guess you had Peter Pessick here with the polyphonic minds idea so
you might want to check out his book he kind of thinks the way that you do
and we were also talking about the bicameral mind which is very
out of fashion but you know that book?
Yeah so it's very similar to what exactly
it's very very similar to what you're bringing up. Now I'm very skeptical
of both of them and I'm friendly with Peter
but still I'm very skeptical I think they take a lot of
impressionist to kind of stuff and try to come up with the whole theory but and just like I'm being a
little skeptical of what you said but that doesn't mean you don't have a lot of depth there and that there's a lot to examine
so we were talking about kind of the variation
of what you were saying just before we started the meeting this morning.
I take these two sides that you're describing as being
a non-incomensurate or at least they may be different but they're different ways
of looking at the same thing where they're on a developmental
historically on a developmental course and I think I mean the person
that comes to mind for me is Ernst Kasier who wrote a lot about
mythic way of looking at the world and has it became more
rationalizing scientific not to say that's always better
which is what people sometimes lament but that it's
a further development of mythic thinking.
I think you're saying there are two parts of the mind one of them is more modern
and it can't exactly coexist simultaneously with the other part.
I think we have them both at the same time.
Our problem today is our inability to see them both at the same time
to experience them both at the same time.
Myth functions by just it doesn't describe
it is a place from which you can experience
both ways of experiencing the world or seeing the world
and responding to it at the same time and gives us a sense of
home. Myth becomes religion at a certain point.
To me, myth plus politics equals religion.
I really had hoped in fact that's a very we have to finish and that's an interesting
end note because no it really was my hope that that this would be
just sort of two-sided this decoding and demeaning
connotation and denotation is something I was hoping we would be able
to bring out here and I think we did a really pretty good job.
I thank you all for your contributions.
Thank you.
Can I make a little correction?
So I kept wondering
if we could have this conversation two-thousand years ago
and many of the things that we discussed here were discussed two-thousand years ago
in the exact same way and your answer about myth and so on
was unanswered the same way.
So now it's impossible but I think if you
look at the grounding that is how you can make
a judgment
that there are two brains as you said, emotional and cognitive brains
and this has been going on in humankind for a long time
before DSM-5, DSM-4 actually had two axes
and one set of psychiatrists that with the cognitive problems that
have been with the emotional problems, now we know
there is no part of the brain that would be dedicated to emotions.
We know also there is no such a thing as fear center
because negative and positive is the luck, context,
the stomach, the heart, wherever something bad is called it next to it
or just to it is the good. This is how the relationships
are formed and that is just to show
there is no part in the brain that you can look at. MRI is
just like we can distinguish and separate cognition from emotion.
They evolve together. They are never separate.
They have the beliefs that we can separate them and those beliefs
can persevere and no amount of introspection can help.
That's why I throw it back. But if you look into the brain
the debate will become simpler.
There are times where you have an emotion and you have no cognition
onto you actually. Absolutely.
How do you have a condition without a motion?
No. Okay. So if I can't have a reaction to something
just through emotions, yes you can.
So that I call adaptive behavior and you can call it
cognition. So if I avoid something because it's unpleasant
that's a adaptive behavior and that's the definition of cognitive action also.
Now I'm going to have an out-p
to go. You say hotel, motel, town?
you