I'm Ed Nurse-Shesian Director of the Hill Excentation.
Before I introduce the participants, I'd like to say a few things about upcoming programs.
We're going to have a weekend on around December 1st, 2nd, 3rd,
devoted to the relationship between science and art.
So we will have scientists, artists working together
and we will also discuss what is called STEAM education.
So that's in December.
Prior to that, some of the round tables we are working on are illusion of knowledge,
sleep and memory, some round table on emotions,
mind hours and others, and a few other things that we are working on.
And we will put it up on our website and send you emails about it as we haven't planned.
Today's round table, complexity and emergence to visions of cosmic order from particles to people
was proposed to us by Tyler Volk, who is a professor of biology and environmental sciences at NYU.
The other participants next to Tyler is William Grassi.
He is an interdisciplinary scholar, academic entrepreneur and social activist and author.
Next to him is Tim Modlin, who's been here a couple of times before,
who is a professor of philosophy at NYU.
Next to him is David Grinspoon, astrobiologist senior scientist at the Planetary Science Institute.
And on the other side, it's Ilya Tampkin, professor of biology at NOVA and research associate at NM&H.
Thank you.
Well, we're supposed to each say a few words about our interests.
Do we get over here, maybe? David?
Sure.
So, as was mentioned, I'm an astrobiologist.
Astrobiology is inherently a multidisciplinary endeavor, as the name implies, astronomy and biology.
And now many other disciplines as well, trying to understand really the potential of the universe to produce life
and what environments that may occur in and how we might search for it.
And my own entree into that is as a planetary scientist, I actually do climate modeling of other planets
using similar tools to what we use to try to model the future climate on Earth.
And part of that is the search for extraterrestrial intelligence.
It's connected in interesting ways with astrobiology.
And recently, I've just completed a book that's been about a four-year project,
which is looking at the Anthropocene epoch, which is the name that some geologists and now other people have proposed
for our current time of Earth history, which is characterized by humans as a geological force.
Looking at that through the lens of astrobiology, in other words, for someone who thinks about planetary transitions
and the relationship between life and planets, what does this moment in Earth history
when this species, this arguably new kind of phenomena on the planet, has become a major factor in planetary evolution?
So that's what I've been focusing on recently, and it dovetails in interesting ways with this,
or the whole story of cosmic evolution.
What is happening on this planet now and what do human beings really represent as a factor in planetary evolution?
That's my entree to this subject.
Okay, Shriya, we go around forever.
So I'm sort of on a different...
My specialty is foundations of physics, so I mostly have been looking at trying to understand fundamental physical theories.
So the connection, I guess, to this particular topic would be in the connection between the base level physical laws
and emergent laws in the sense of patterns, fairly predictable patterns that appear at higher levels
that are predictable without knowing all the details of the micro-physics.
So far as I have much to contribute, it's just to appreciate what a mystery it is, why that should even happen.
There's no particular reason why law-governed micro-physics should give rise to any interesting macro-physical structures
that have both complexity and predictability.
So we take it for granted because we live in a world like that, but we don't appreciate how curious it is that we do live in such a world.
So maybe I can contribute something there.
So I got interested in the subject 30 years ago, writing an dissertation in a religion department
on what it would mean to treat the modern scientific cosmology as a mythopoetic creation story.
And I sort of fell into this rabbit hole at that point.
So I'd sort of been doing what we called then the Epic of Evolution or the new cosmology, what people today often call big history.
So I'm involved in the exegesis of big history. What does it mean?
And how do we interpret it?
So I'm sort of play with lots of different interpretations at different levels.
And of course part of that is to figure out the big questions.
But also I'm really interested in big history as a kind of pedagogical endeavor because we've learned so much about the universe in the last 50 years
and about ourselves and in origin and our psychology and of course all that has also fueled a tremendous change in the way we live, the anthropocene as you mentioned.
So for me putting it all together both as a sort of metaphysical question but also as a pedagogical endeavor is what's inspired my work over the years.
So I most of my bread and butter work has involved the global carbon cycle and climate over the years, energy systems, but the work in the global carbon cycle took me from the macro planet down into molecular levels
and I also had a strong interest in patterns, Tim referred to patterns, patterns of different scales and how one scale can influence another scale
and how sometimes similar patterns can reappear such as binary systems or certain shapes such as spheres.
And I was, this began because Ed invited me to a panel in April which I could not go to but I said I have this new book called Quarks to Culture
and Ed said that would seem like a good topic for panel on complexity and emergence in May so let's set that up.
And what I, this, this, and you have the handout in case some things get referred to that everybody could talk to because I think tonight physics is going to come up and biology is going to come up and culture is going to come up
and these figures are from, figures are from my book and what the basic idea was that you go down in the body into cells and into molecules
one can be going down back in time in terms of the origin of the types of these things so the cell had to come into existence before you can have a multicellular body such as an animal
and a molecule has to come into existence before you can have a cell that's made of molecules.
Now not the cells of our body, not the molecules of our body but as a type of system there had to be a buildup from something small to large
or there was a buildup, it doesn't have to be but science has not discovered this, a buildup from small to large and I said, oh I wonder if one could count
I wonder if one could use the idea of merge of combination into new systems from small things, one could use that sequentially as a number of steps
and distinguish fundamental levels of who we are and not just up to our body but then we are part of a social system too so I was just wondering can one do that
and then that led me into these 12 levels that I talk about that each have, the next question beat each must have had something special that came into existence or emerged
in order for the next level to happen that could not have happened at a prior level so there must have been something about the molecule that was different from what the atom was
that the molecules required to form a cell, a living cell, that the atoms by themselves could not have directly gone there
and the same with the fundamental particles of the standard model of physics, there was some paper in science years ago that somebody said, you don't model bulldozers with quarks, that there's these intervening levels
that's been well known that there's been, the physicists talk about the onion, the layers of the onion and the biologists have had their major transitions of evolution and what I was merely doing was saying, oh one could actually see them as part of a way to do big history in terms of certain levels
and it relates to things like emergence but that's the topic of the panel so I'll just leave it at that. I'm an evolutionary biologist and primarily interested in the general mechanisms that lead to the formation of the patterns we see reflected in the history of life
it is clear that evolutionary processes occur at multiple levels of biological organization from molecular to all the way to ecosystem, because of systemic levels and the patterns that observe in nature, they are the outcomes of the synergistic effect of different events that occur at all these different levels
So to me prior to even attempting to address the question of how these processes result in the patterns that we observe and describe as evolutionary biologists, we need to be very clear about the ontology of the structure of the organic world
and it's not a surprise that by itself the level structure has been long recognized, every single textbook in biology begins with the description of the hierarchy of the living world starting with molecules leading to the formation of subcellular structures that then make cells, so this makes up tissues and so on
until you get to the organisms, organisms make up populations that interact with each other in an economic way in the context of ecosystems, communities and so on up to the all encompassing biosphere
However, if you look very carefully at this stereotypical structure that everybody is familiar with, you begin to recognize that this hierarchy of scale where you simply order biological entities in the order of the smallest of the largest
It's probably a sufficient way to maybe describe different types of biological entities, but it doesn't provide an explanatory power to explain the processes because at the same level, there are entities that cannot be encompassed in a single uniform hierarchy
Evolutionary biologists like myself who try to look more seriously at these questions recognize that there are two types of biological individuals that fundamentally differ in their nature, some of which we refer to as systems
where the relationship between entities that comprise the system is based on the energy and matter of relationships
An example of that would be, for instance, a cell where different organelles interact with one another in some kind of economic way to make the largest system, or they're basically part of the whole system
On the other side of the spectrum, there is a system of information transfer which recognizes the replicating entities where the relationships of them or the mode of incorporating into the larger entities is not the energy and matter relationship
But the matter of inclusion based on the ancestry is a geological entity which I better describe not as systems but as historical teenagers
And the evolution occurs as the interplay of between these two separate, however overlapping hierarchies
So an example of that would be, so within even our bodies, there is this duality of interactor and replicator systems, so our bodies composed of two fundamentally different units is a soma and the germline
The whole purpose of the germline, or our cells responsible for reproduction, is only to transmit the information from one generation to the next
One can be perfectly happy organism, leaving any offspring behind, so it would be perfectly functioning as a system in the economic way without ever reproducing
So it's just the second aspect of our nature as well as any other biological system at every level to be able to replicate in a proliferated way
So the processes like selection of sorting can take place where the evolution results from, so to me this is the most fundamental question within evolutionary biologists
To see how you can understand the processes that impact the hierarchal systems at one level, so the so-called ecological, sometimes economic, hierarchy of life
And how it reflects, in a synergistic effect, at the different levels in the historical or geological hierarchy that we perceive as what we described in systematics and taxonomy
as a tree of life and the patterns that are being of that tree that are shaped throughout the history of life
One of the problems we're going to have talking about complexity, let alone an emergence is that we're dealing with all these different scientific disciplines
and there's no numeric measurement of complexity, it's not just the size of something, it's how diverse it is perhaps, or I'll focus later perhaps on how much energy it consumes
How much energy flows through the system, but I think it's really important, a lot of people don't understand, I don't know, be curious what you, I talk about the great matrix, we're talking about hierarchies or scales
And we do have some interesting scales, we have a scale of time, chronology, we have a scale of size, we have measurable scales of free energy flow through a system
And one of the electromagnetic spectrum is an amazing scale, which is very important in our level of reality
And a sound is a different type of scale, interestingly humans have a much broader many orders of magnitude auditory capacity
And we actually perceive visual light, it's very small range, and I think then we can go to inductive scales, or let's say there's a scale of information and ingenuity
Or there's a scale of sentience and consciousness, or of course the scale that we're talking about is emergence of complexity
Those are maybe there are others, I don't know, but those are kind of ways of orienting us to all phenomena that science describes
So we have, I think some interesting, it's not just anything goes, there's a lot of restrictions about what science can understand or feel
I call it the great matrix
By that you mean the system composed of all these different scales?
No, I think everything can be, everything can be, everything can be.
The great matrix.
Oh, the great matrix, time, space, energy, electromagnetism, sound, and those.
So would you, but some of those seem like subsets of others?
They are, for sure, electromagnetism is a form of energy, for sure, so is sound
So some might be more primary.
And we live in this amazing little thermodynamic eddy, eddy in the universe where complexity runs uphill
And so we have this, you know, if it weren't for that thermodynamic eddy
Where the Goldilocks conditions were just right, we wouldn't be here talking about it
And so how do you see that? So the thermodynamics run uphill, meaning you can have local reduction in entropy and increase complexity
As long as there's a global increase in entropy, and
Anytime energy flows through matter, it creates order, creates information
And so that's what the weather is, right? It's a way of dissipating energy.
That's what a hurricane is, or a tornado.
When it passes through solid matter, it can also have memory, and it can also compute, and can make, reproduce itself
And so the weather, the gas molecules, as soon as the energy flows stops, they just dissipate
But, you know, life has achieved this internal telos to, you know, survive, reproduce, and create life more abundant and extravagant
So, for me, the fundamental physics of the universe is that as long as there's energy flowing through matter
We have a possibility of increasing complexity
So that's key, the possibility of increasing complexity, but it might not be an inevitability
Absolutely not, and it says nothing about how that complexity is going to evolve or what it's going to be, but the possibilities
So that's kind of fundamental level, and most people don't get it, it's very counterintuitive
But Eric Chason at Harvard and Tufts, astronomers, it's really interesting, sort of back to the envelope calculations
About how much energy flows through a system, let me just put it out there really quickly
Like the Sun as a unit, of course, it's really big, and it's really put on an enormous amount of energy
But a photosynthesizing microorganism is about 500 times the energy density flow of the Sun
When you normalize for the mass and the time frame
A mammalian body is about 10,000 times the energy density flow of the Sun
Our brains are about 75,000 times the energy density flow of the Sun
And by the way, our brains only work on about 20, 25 watts of energy
So our body is working about 100 watts of energy
And if you take all the energy that we use outside of our bodies
As a result of first fire mastery, then agriculture, then fossil fuels
Where millions of times, the people in this room, are consuming energy millions of times that of the Sun
So it's very counter, again, when normalized for the mass of the system
So energy is part of the story of complexity
And most people focus on the information side of it, it's informationally driven
But you don't get the information without the energy flowing through matter
So that's a sort of fundamental physics point that Tim might want to say more about that
Yeah, I'm not sure, let me try and make a point about information in terms of entropy
And then maybe I can ask you because I'm not quite sure what you have in mind by energy flow
So one way to see the complexity, this is an example, I guess of Sean Carroll's, but it makes the point
Complexity is a really hard concept to get a good grip on
People often try and equate it with a concept that you have a better grip on like entropy or something like that
But if you think about the, there's a standard example of increase of entropy where you take coffee and cream
And start them out where the cream is just on top of the coffee
And then you wait and it slowly diffuses and, or you stir it, right?
Which would be introducing energy and, but even if you don't introduce any energy and it will slowly diffuse
If you stir it, it goes through a phase where you have this tremendous complexity
You have the tendrils of cream that have interesting shapes that are intermixed with the coffee
But then as time goes on, it eventually becomes bland again, right? It just becomes a mocha brown uniform mix
That's the maximal entropy state, right? It's not the maximal complexity state
So you started from a very uncomplex system and you go through a sort of complexity maximum
And then it tails off as time goes on into again a very uncomplex system
All the time entropy is going up
So the conditions for there even to be complexity or how you quantify it or what you mean by it
I think are very difficult. I'm not sure why you would need energy flow to get complexity
I mean, I'm not sure what you think of the connection there between energy flow and complex, and increasing complexity
What the one thing about biology, so I, so
And I'm not, and there's things I'm not comfortable about with the information
I mean, I understand, you know, that's a whole discussion
I tend to take a very almost architectural approach, but one thing about the origin of life is that now
And I'd be curious, the transition from physics and chemistry to the two
Once you have living cells, the way I see it, you now have systems that require the import of matter and energy into them
And export of waste, which you do not have with an atom, you do not have with a molecule
They can be relatively static structures
And so to have life you do need a field of either molecules that contain chemical energy in the environment
Or radiative energy with photosynthesis
And so it does have to flow, that does have to flow
That was something, of course you understand, I know you know that, but that was something what you were asking, then what that transition meant
Because once you have a system that requires inputs of matter and energy and exports waste
It seems to me then, then biological evolution almost follows logically from that
Because since these creatures are replicating themselves, they can't just grow forever, they split and they form two cells
Now they're in competition inherently, because if one is importing a nutrient
That's depleting the nutrient in the environment
So there's depletion of the energy from the environment if we talk about matter containing energy
But living things also need matter as matter, they need the carbon atom to structure other molecules
So it's not just energy, they actually need certain kinds of material building blocks
And once you have something that needs imports and exports, you get biological evolution
Because now there's the depletion in the environment from the nutrient import
And there's putting out toxins as waste, because the waste these creatures are getting rid of it
So they are causing detrimental changes to the environment setting up a competitive so to speak field
You can also have cooperation in there among organisms, of course, which is important for the evolution of the eukaryotic cell
But it sets up this field
Now, so I do have this overriding question
That's in a way a different kind of dynamics that have been born from the physical chemical dynamics
Now it's not just coming out of the sky coming down, but it seems like it's a fun...
It seems like it's different enough that biological evolution is different enough for us to really think about what that means
And now you can have a combination of biological structures
I think another important concept here is homeostasis
Because it's not just enough to have those energy flows
And as you say, the flows of matter that maintain them
I think Eric Chesson's observation that energy density seems to conform to this sort of hierarchy
It seems to be a characteristic of this hierarchy
It's very interesting, the hierarchy that you've kind of named in your introductory statement
Does seem to carry with it this also hierarchy of energy density
But I don't think Eric has answered the question of why that necessarily needs to be
It's sort of an observation
When you name this hierarchy that Tyra has very well described
And then you look at the characteristics of these different entities
One thing you can observe is this energy flow density is really markedly increased at every higher level
It's exponentially increasing at every higher level
But it's also a characteristic, some of that energy, some of what it needs to do
Some of the point of that is to create a homeostasis so that the flows of matter and energy
That allow that structure can persist
A disequilibria's homeostasis
Yes, so it's not a causal, it's not a causal factor
It's a necessary energy flowing through gas
Spontaneously creates or complexity
I'm going to try to make one step back because we have discussed so many concepts
And the relationship between which is not always clear
We started with notion of complexity, right?
So we wanted to maybe get back to that a little bit, discuss it in a little bit greater detail
Wouldn't be, let's just try to simplify things a little bit
So let's pretend that we're just looking at a system at one particular comparing two systems at the same organizational level
So it's made from comparable parts
So we have a very good mathematical language to describe structures in the form of dynamic networks
That interact with one another, where different parts interact with one another in some non-trivial way
We have, we can describe the topology, the strength of the relationships
We define as modularity, the overall topology
And by doing that we can compare to a system in terms of, in some numerical ways of assessing complexity at that level
The difficulty comes in when you start looking at hierarchical systems
Where an element of a system is in itself a complex system of a different level
Then, you would argue that the system is more complex, the more hierarchical levels you have
Because what you yet, I think overall
And you could just clarify it, when you say hierarchical, do you mean nested?
I mean nested composition
But there are sometimes people use hierarchical to mean like a tree structure
Yes, or not hierarchy of control
No, I meant specifically, physically nested
Nested, you can think in like a Dan Meche sense, because I know Meche talks about one way of one form of complexity
Is numbers of layers of nestedness
And I saw that he has a paper in your new book, for example
But that's what you're talking about when you say hierarchical
Specifically about one particular type of hierarchy when you have nestedness
Because I think that's a different in scale, something you referred to
Early on regarding that scale is important
Scale is important because the discontinuity in that scale
That's what creates the discreetness of levels
This way we can talk about the levels as ontologically sound real thing
Rather than just pure our conception of something being a little small or something being a little larger
Because I think nobody would argue that when two individuals interact
It would, like two humans would interact
It would be correct to say that cells of one interact with an individual person of another
Because these are not comparable entities with regard to this scale
Because the rates of processes at different levels are completely different
So that's why when we look at the dynamic system
It can be only composed of the elements of the same hierarchical level
Because they are, if you engage in the energy and matter relationship
It can be only among entities that are within the same structure
Yeah, I'm totally into that, where then these entities at these different scales
They have certain kinds of relationships that they're capable of
So we are capable of using light and sound, of using remote sensing
Which cells, biological cells, they can be responsive to light
But they're not actually, as far as we know, communicating through, like say, a linguistic modulation on light and sound
So the way I see it is that it's not only the birth, what's key is not only the birth of these new scales of size
These entities or systems have new kinds of abilities to relate
And I think what you're saying is that they tend to relate to entities on that same level
Yes, and you tell our effort with your approach of different agnices levels
These are the fundamentals jumps in this level of organization
Something that is sometimes referred to as major transitions
Major transitions in the bio-biologist, yeah
So it's not about how the system once it's already emerged, how it starts working with this having multiple levels structure
But you're focusing to be on the emergence of these levels in the first place
Right, so it's a different story
Obviously you have to have these levels emerging first
Because now we're looking at, we're faced with the already existing system of these levels
But have must have emerged sometimes through history
But it's a different question of how these levels have appeared in the first place
I'm just not sure I understand
I understand the notion of level, I can make sense of the notion of levels
I don't see why you would think that only things at the same level interact
So suppose I'm a biologist and I'm looking at, I don't know, otters
And otters are able, I think, to pick up rocks or somebody is able to pick up rocks and smash
So the rock is at a really low level of complexity, right?
But it interacts with this biological organism, it's important
So it would be a nice world if, as it were, the levels just sort of thin themselves out and only interact
But there's all kinds of inter-level interactions
This is a really important one, it's really important
It's really important for particles and atoms interact with mutations
But it's a different kind of interaction
Maybe there's a certain kind of constructive or engagement that only happens at the same level
Obviously, we get hit by high energy protons and it can damage ourselves
But that's different from communicating with another organism
Maybe otters pick up the rock to maintain its homeostasis
I don't think of rock and otter at a different level
In terms of their roles, maybe complex, different composition, yes, at a different level
But I'm not putting them at different levels because of their complexity
At the same level of interactions, they belong to the same level
Because at the same time, they fly as an organism, it's a level of an organism
It will interact with a human, because human is an organism
They're at the same level of an organism
But obviously, you can argue that the fly may be more simpler than a human
That doesn't make them, but it would be a role
So I would take them as multicellular or...
Yes, that's the level of multicellularity
But it would be wrong to say that an otter interacts with an ecosystem
An ecosystem that's a level that's encompassed not in all of the otter deals with
So otter would interact with other abiotic and biotic elements in its own environment
But not with the ecosystem, such as...
Or the fact that a human being is a multicellular organism
But now we know with the microbiome that we're not only interacting with unicellular organisms
But that, in fact, our nature is integrally composed of unicellular organisms
Which are themselves, integrally composed of things at smaller levels
So it gets complicated, doesn't it?
That's where it's complicated with the question of what leads to the origin of levels
Because if you look at a human organs composed of multiple cells
If you try to look at an individual cell as an independent organism
Which it is not because it usually does not live under natural conditions
Devode of being part of a body
It would not be, but in the early origin of multicellularity
That was the mode of emergence of that multiolegrinism level
The problem, you can talk more about this, that the emergence of multicellular deacet
It has to be a fundamental step where there was this next level emerged
But I think with regard to interaction with humans, with its microbiome
We are at the same level as this organism
They're organisms, they're multi-cell, maybe a multicellular and unicellular organs
They still can't interact, they can eat each other
It's, well, maybe not multicellular, unicellular organs will eat multicellular ones
But it's an organismal level
Complexity and level are not necessarily can be equated
I think you can only compare the complexity of entities that are at the same level
If you can compare between levels, then what do you mean by compare?
What do you mean by compare?
When you said you can only compare two entities at the same level
What do you mean by, what do you do?
You don't use parco-physics to do economics
Oh, okay
You need to have the discourse, I mean, you have the discourse to figure out the scientific relationships
But I think it's important to note that the adjacent levels often do have things to say for each other
And there's a difference between complicated and complex
So the example I like to use is that cars are a really complicated thing
But we sort of know how to build it and how all the pieces work together
And we're at a traffic jam on the morning commute where everybody's driving along
And a little variations in somebody's speed starts replicating and all of a sudden it stops, goes stop, go
That's a complex phenomena
And complexity is a whole science of its own
And all the most interesting things in the universe are complex adaptive systems
Where there are lots of different interacting parts
And some freedom or possibility of things happening differently
So complexity as a term of science is really different than complicated
And a lot of what science is is trying to make things that look complex turn into complicated problems
But now there's a whole bunch of phenomena that we study
Some of them are very simple like flocks of birds which some can be described mathematically
Some not that are complex and I think that's an important
But what he described as a relationship between the complexity of a car structure and the traffic
Which cannot be decomposed and explained in terms of the car parts
That's the exact example of comparison between different levels
I mean in some way the traffic jam is simpler because it can be mathematically
Mathematically sized by little units and people write equations for it and do modeling of it
Where a car, yes it can be understood but to me the multiple levels of a car
Of course the car jam is made of cars, so that's why it's a...
Yeah, but I think what you just said is going to be much more true in ten years
About traffic jams when there are no more...
When there are human drivers are no longer a part of the equation
Whereas now there's a complex neurological sensory reactive component to that
It's interesting to note that soon there will be traffic jams that are probably just as complex for different reasons
So here's to me, so we haven't gotten into culture yet
I'd be really curious about how you think about this idea, how you all think about it from different angles
And particularly from a general principle
So lots of people for years have been talking about cultural evolution
Which is like biological evolution, not by having a genome and not by having a phenotype, genotype
But by having properties of propagation, variation and selection
So the automobile manufacturer can make more cars
That's propagating, they're not self propagating yet
But then they put out variants
Scientific theories can do the same thing, put out variants
And then it's selected in a field either in one's mind or in society
Now there's certain pushback against that from some of the social scientists
No, no, no, you don't want to make the comparison to rigid
But there's really sort of a tidal wave of literature happening
In this culture evolution studies
Simply saying that there's been a way I would put it
A rediscovery of these triple processes of propagation, variation and selection of pattern
That occurred at the beginning of the origin of life at the prokaryotic cell
And occurred again at some point in human evolution
I'll take it to be definitely by the time of sex tools
And probably we think language
And I think there's also a similarity between the amino acids, 20 amino acids
Being able to build a complexity of proteins, almost an infinite complexity of proteins
And human phonemes, a few units of speech
Being able to build almost an infinite number of words
I think there's kind of a parallel between this sort of element
Going to complex, being within the cell
As the genetic and amino acid system
And simple elements being complex in the human language system
Corresponding to the beginning of a propagation variation, selection process in biology
With a propagation, selection process in culture
So I'm curious as if there's been a rediscovery
As these levels of organization have built up
If suddenly the prokaryotic cell, which is using biological evolution
So is the eukaryotic cell, so is the multicellular organism
And so is the animal social group
And then with the anthropologist called the metagroups
Where groups can be not visible to each other on different sides of the mountain
But they're still linked in a culture
If that began a propagation variation and selection process again
That means there was a rediscovery of the similar pattern
Kind of a principle
So there's a difference between biological evolution and cultural evolution
And that's because we learn
And we pass on what we learn more or less to the next generation
And that becomes an exponentially growing process
So individually, we're not all that smart
We have a person by limitation, if you will, about how much we can know
And how much we can knowledge and know how we can contain
But you put us together in this quote unquote superorganism
And we're just...
We're on this exponential...
Don't run as individuals down too much
Well not you
I'm not saying that before... I mean I do want to mark a difference here
Because I think the analogy...
The wonderful thing about the theory of evolution
The original biological theory of evolution wasn't just that it was replicators with variation and selection
But that it was random variation
That you didn't need a tealological, you didn't need a purpose, you didn't need an aim or a design
And this could all just be happening randomly
Now hopefully once you get people involved
They're honestly not the chefs really aren't just randomly throwing stuff in
And seeing what happens, they come to have some understanding of what they're aiming at
And you get intentional behavior
They might come back to the restaurant
Which is gonna make the whole thing much more efficient you hope
And much faster and much more powerful
So I would be a little leery of...
It seems to be, but leery of stretching the analogy too much
But I would like to say it's more than an analogy, it's some deep level
It's the rediscovery of some of these triple principles
But how they're manifesting, because even the chef can't determine whether those people are gonna like
Yes, use the term intentional behavior
And I think that's an important term as far as this difference you're trying to describe
But then we can also ask
What do we really mean by that?
And where does intentional behavior come from?
And one idea, and I don't think anybody really knows
But one idea I've heard about that
And this is above my pay grade, but some of you guys might know more about this
But for how the mind works and how ideas emerge
And how intention, whatever that is, comes out of this
Is that there is some sort of potential, sort of Darwinian type process
Or at least process that's sort of analogous to that going on inside the brain
Where different associations and ideas are kind of competing and emerging
From some sort of a process
And so it may be that some of these qualities that you're describing
As the sort of universal pattern emerging, our pattern emergence are going on
And contributing to this, but that it's really going on as far as idea formation
And indeed the formation of intentionality, however that works inside our brains
Well most of my brain was pretty empty when I was born
And of course it went through a prolonged period of childhood
Dependency grew three times from, right?
That's about how big the brain grows in childhood
And so everything that fills our brains is largely, including our language
It's largely acquired through the social and environmental network
And so for me the brain is a really interesting thing
But it does nothing without oppositional sums and environment
And a social environment in particular
So to me, the real miracles, how does this stuff, how does the environment imprint itself into our brains?
And how do we, how do we, so you could talk about all kinds of different emergence
There's evolutionary emergence, there's developmental emergence from a single cell to an adult body
Or there's functional emergence, like all the cells are working at the same time
So it's the physics, right? What is it, like 40 trillion cells in our body?
Half of them, as many bacteria
And then you could even talk about intelligence emergence
That can happen to an individual, it can happen to a species
And I think we...
Can it happen to a planet?
Well, you know, so that's the question, that's the Tejhardian, Pierre Tejhard de Chardin, the Jesuit priest, one of the patron saints of religion and science
To continue with, to go back to David and talk about it, and do what you said is that
Yes, we're born with these baby brains
And we suck up a lot from the environment
And one of the things we pull up is the ability to be intentional
Or at least use that language to people, oh, I thought that through
And I now decide this, that's in a way a propagation variation in selection
Well, there's a...
Let me again make a kind of analogy here in terms of even...
It's certainly true that you speed things up by, as it were, virtual processes in the brain
That make selections out of different...
I'm deciding what to do, and I think about five different possibilities
And I try and project out what will happen and make my choice on the basis of that
And those are only the ones you're consciously aware of, which is...
Right, but you do need a...
I think you...
Right, you need a distinction, and think about chess playing computers, right?
So originally, really the chess playing computers were sort of blind variation
And they just did massive searches of all possible move sequences,
Which because of combinatorial explosion, they could... had a horizon
But in some sense, in some sense they considered hundreds of millions of possible sequences of moves
And if you ask an expert chess player, he'll say, I considered four
You know, I looked at the board and I said, maybe it's this one, maybe it's this one, maybe it's that one
And then they focus down, right?
It's a different... it's really a different...
And we think they could not have it, and even unconsciously we think they could not have done hundreds of millions
That's right, because they don't know the unconscious question
That's right, so you know, it's... I mean...
That ability to... it's true there's a kind of variation there, at least they're looking at a variety of possibilities and selecting among them
But there's also a lot of interesting things going on that they can look at such a small variety of...
Things and apply their cognitive resources to them
But also to be really true to biology, the variation is also really not...
Also from biology we know it's not entirely a random
Also we know that some parts of the genome can mutate more readily than others
It's predictable, we know that some mutations are filtrated to the level of phenotype, not also through some random manifestation
But there are some constraints by the organism level, so it's not also entirely random
But I think in general the metaphor of relating cultural evolution to biological evolution
I think it's both a useful analogy and there is some truth to it in a very general sense
Because if we define evolution and it's simply even just basically there in terms...
You know, Darwin didn't use the word evolution at first, he just used descent with modification
Which simply in modern language we can translate it as a fate of information
So in that sense evolution can occur in any system whether information transfers from one generation to the next
As long as you have some sort of replicating system
So human culture, it adds to it, just adds to the new mechanism of information, transparent modification
Which is through our culture
And because that method is quite radically different, you can transfer information only to the next generation
But kind of laterally, almost like bacteria do with their lateral gene transfer
You can recover lost information from the past and there are old sorts of ways
How can fresh can be transferred in ways that are not found in biological systems
It certainly lends to some novelty and intentionality as part of it as well
Some creative intent of individuals, so we should not discount those as well
But at a higher level of maybe higher social structures within the human society
There is some element of maybe not necessarily selection because I don't want to draw analogy to like
Fitness in biological systems, I think it would be too
Maybe too untrue
But there is some sort of sorting, you have variance and they are being by some either random function or maybe not
They are being sorted and distributed where some persist some do not
In that sense it does hold
But would you say there is some kind of fitness maybe about a bottle or everything that we design
You are uncomfortable with using the word fitness
I am a little bit uncomfortable because you want to keep it to biology
Because if you are thinking of a very specific meaning, you use the ability to replicate itself more
Maybe having a better form in saying an element of human design shape
It might not necessarily translate into high rate of its reproduction
Right, but some...
Like in terms of manufacturers
Right, so the better way of having the typewriter in terms of ergonomics was not the way the typewriter worked
I just don't know what I said, I can be generalised, maybe it is true
I am actually one of the few people in the world who uses a Dvorak simplified keyboard
Which was designed in the 1930s by an efficiency expert
Based on the frequency of the letters and the two and three letter combinations
To minimise finger motion
But we are all locked into the QWERTY keyboard which was designed to make us type slowly
Because the machines would jam
And C-Mingigal has a lovely essay about this, in evolution
It doesn't have to be optimal, it just has to work and then it gets fixed and stuck
And so every time we look at your computer, you should think
My god, this is an icon of how brilliant we are and how stupid we are
Because the keyboard is literally pretty stupid
In biology, they talk about the... not optimising but satisfying
So anyway, that's...
And this is probably very true to human culture as well
Something that might persist for reasons other than being the best serving the needs
So for instance, some years ago I embarked on a project trying to apply biological methods
Maybe very naively trying to reconstruct the phylogeny kind of evolutionary tree of musical instruments
We discovered very unusual and interesting patterns that we had to do with looking at coordinates
From the late 19th century and up to the middle of the 20th century
And it turned out that some of the trumpet related musical instruments
And it turns out that some of the trans that we found had to do not specifically with a better design of vowels
And the way horn is structured overall
But there were some purely economic reasons for developing the industry in some ways
Because some people patented certain ways of making it
Preventing other people from doing it, there were other social forces
Had nothing to do with optimising a particular item
Obviously humanly designed in a very creative way
Item that was very consciously designed, but it could only develop in certain ways
Because higher level social structures like patent agencies
And maybe some individual players, some jazz players that used some of these instruments
They preferred something more artistic
And they designed purely for aesthetic and historical reasons
They didn't really care about maybe a better playability in some ways
So there are many more, I think, aspects to human ways of variations being sorted in human culture
That's why I didn't want to define it as a specific fitness function
Because fitness applies only to one thing
This is an interesting thing to bring into it
But when you start talking about fitness
It's very easy to say when you're talking about Darwinian evolution
And even neo-Darwinian evolution
What the sort of goal is, you don't really need a goal
It's just those entities that do a better job of propagating themselves
But when we get to cultural evolution
Then you do have to start saying, well, what is the goal?
What do we want? It's not necessarily true that the goal is for each of us to have as many offspring as we want
In fact, we're starting to realize that there's a whole other level of planetary fitness
In which that's actually bad
So you can't help but start to say, okay, so what really is the goal?
But when you get to aesthetics, it's very interesting because you could say, well, this is something that
Isn't really a part of biological evolution
Except it is because you get into sexual selection
And you get these ridiculous structures that are among the most useless
And the most beautiful parts of nature
Which have this whole other goal
But it's still the same goal, but it's attracting a mate
Not anything that's more useful for
And they agree with you, especially when they mentioned earlier that it all comes down there
So just the way human brain functions too, which I also don't have as much expertise to speculate about
But, Linus Frost has one interesting comment
When critiquing the purely biological transfer of the notions of evolution to the culture
But the X doesn't reproduce, doesn't make another X
So it happens to in the mind of its creator, conceiving the idea of it
And what happens to these ideas, how they manifested in the objects
So you can't necessarily even look at those coordinates and say, well, that's how they evolve
Now they just maybe imperfect reflection of the processes that occur in the human brain
And the evolution at that level
So I think just looking at the cultural artifacts as such
As divorced from the workings of the human mind
I don't think it's a very legitimate pursuit in that way to view cultural evolution like that
It's certainly just looking at organismal features
Can allow you to reconstruct phylogeny, maybe in quite a precise way
But it's not telling you the mechanism of how evolution further occurred through speciation variation
So in that way, you can also tell something about the way human culture works
By looking at some patterns of similarities between artifacts and different aspects of human culture
But do you really understand that you really need to look at the function of the mind?
I've been doing a lot of reading and research right now for a book I'm writing
On how this applies to finance and economics and investing
And one of the things that we all have these hunter-gatherer brains
And we live in this incredibly advanced civilization
But we're still on the psychological level, we have a lot in common with humans 10, 20, 30,000 years ago
100,000 years ago
And so our thinking is fast and slow, we're predictably irrational
And we're driven by all kinds of variable hormones in our body
And so there's another question, how did a complex global scientific civilization
Possibly emerge from such stupid primates, some of whom are president of the United States recently?
Well, I wonder, do you really think that we live in an incredibly advanced civilization?
I think we have the potential to form one, but I would say that as a basic prerequisite
To define an advanced civilization you would have to have the ability to imagine that
You're sort of a part of a sustainable civilization, and I'm not sure we're actually there yet
I mean, there's the normative moral side of it, and then there's just the fact of it
And I'm just talking about the fact that our world is so different than when people lived in 100 years ago or 1000 years ago
I agree with that, but I also think that it's possible that, I mean, trying to describe Manhattan to say one of the 100 gatherers who lived at a pinnacle point
One of the most important things that we have to do is to imagine that we have a 100,000 years ago
Which may have been among the first homo sapiens sapiens in southern tip of Africa would be very difficult
Humans have an amazing ability, capacity for reinvention, they were probably genetically pretty similar to us
But maybe that's more stuffed now, yeah, but maybe that difficulty of them imagining our world is as difficult as it is for us to imagine what an advanced civilization would be like
So, yeah, do you think that how long before we get there, I'd like to know?
Well, I want to see it, so when I hear you talk about speaking up and fasting
When I hear you talk about these levels, Adam's simple cells complex of...
One question that I can't help but wondering is, okay, what's next? The next level
I read something recently actually when I was just starting to write my book that I just finished by Isaac Asimov written in the 70s
Just a little short essay where he talked about this hierarchy of atoms to molecules to viruses to full-blown cells to multi-cellular
And then he talks about the multi-organismic and there's some examples of sort of full-blown superorganisms like insect colonies and so forth
And then he talked about we humans, we have leanings towards that superorganism
We have some identity with the tribe, with the group, but we're not quite there, we're still
And to me that was really powerful, like I thought, and I say the beginning of my life, yeah, well in a certain way we're stuck between the individual and the superorganism
In a way, that's one way of encapsulating our predicament here as human beings trying to have a sustainable society because there are ways in which we need to function as a superorganism
But we're not inherently good at that
So I found that powerful because it's just one way of trying to place our current cultural difficulties in the context of what we're talking about here
Where do we fit, and what's next in that? I'm really scared of that analogy
I don't want to be part of a superorganism
Cells, unicellular organisms were looking out for themselves, and in multi-cellular organisms the individual cells are easily expendable
They can be sacrificed quite regularly for the good of the... and I don't want to live in that in a society that's going to throw a bunch of us away
I don't think that's going to be progress, right? There's going to be progress when every person, nobody lives in poverty
When people have the resources are more or less spread much more equally than they are
And everybody has dignity and everybody has access to decent things
That doesn't look like a superorganism to me
It looks like a rationally designed system, right?
And again, rationality, it's kind of important when rationality gets in the game
It's rationality just isn't in the game of evolution, and we're aiming for something else
We're aiming for something we've thought through and that has moral principles underneath it and so on
Well, maybe, I mean, we're getting... I don't want to argue about semantics here, what we mean by superorganism
I'd certainly agree with what you just described as important goals
It's an interesting question, are the bacteria within us...
They're... they're... they're organelles within us that are pretty much the same as bacteria
But have found some way to live in harmony and organism that we identify as ourselves
Are they unhappy? Do they know that they're not bacteria?
And maybe the secret sauce to go from organism to healthy planetary superorganism is exactly some of what you said
Maybe...
Eliminating poverty...
I mean, this is why it's not strictly a biological step to go to the superorganism
If we're going to get into intentionality and rationality, maybe that's what's missing to...
to bring us to that next step
And evolution's just not predictive, and there's nothing strange about evolution leading a system into a complete disaster
But as you were saying, cultural evolution is different because we have these scenarios in our mind
And I think we're not thinking about the future enough as a...
Yes, making people smarter would be a really good idea
So one of the things that this little discussion brings to mind
The little discussion brings out is that we have all these values like human rights
And they're not written into nature
They're invented by humans
Or the traditional religious worldview is that they're dictated by a creator
That each human has innate value
And so the scientific and post-enlightenment world is trying to figure out how to ground concepts like human rights
Which is... it's a great invention, but it's a fiction
Just like money's a fiction, it's not really real
There's no other species, exchanges, matter, energy, and ingenuity based on symbolic systems about values
So one of the ways to ground...
Our intuitive sense of the innate value of human rights is in what Whitehead thought about, Alfred North Whitehead
The idea that emerging complexity creates at every stage a greater freedom, greater possibility
And there are kind of thresholds
And that the human is a particularly intense threshold
In which the complexity of the cells in our body, the social networks
We're kind of a nexus of a lot of freedom, a lot of choice, a lot of possibility
I don't think morality is really an issue for other primates
So it is for us
I think that the planetary scale that could be to overcome our fears
That being subsumed and being less free could be more free
Is that your personal hope or you think it could be even...
In this sort of Whiteheadian metaphysics, there is a telos to the universe
And that telos is a greater complexity, greater freedom, greater creativity
And greater beauty, for him beauty of aesthetics is an important point
So I think you can... it's not fully worked out
But I think you can start to define things that there is a real difference between killing bacteria versus killing humans
And there's a qualitative and quantitative difference
And you can't measure it, but it's not just a self-serving bias on my part
But otherwise human rights is... you have definite ideas about what they should be
Of course evolution doesn't care at all about our future and that level
No, biological evolution has no moral
I mean, I would just like to register my objection to this fictional...
I think there are standards of objective standards of morality that have to do with equity and fairness and so on
That by thinking hard, you can figure out at least some of them
I'm not saying that there's a rational resolution to every moral dilemma
But I think there are some moral principles that chattel slavery is just objectively wrong
But it wasn't for most of human history
No, it was wrong, all through human history
People were doing objectively morally horrible things through most of human
And we're still doing objectively morally horrible human things
I don't think these are inventions, I think they're discoveries
I think we've made moral progress by discovering or registering the fact that slavery was wrong
That discrimination was wrong, that discrimination against women was wrong
It was just unacceptable, morally
It wasn't right back when people thought it was okay
It's not they're thinking one thing or another that makes it okay
I would like to agree with you, actually, but I wish I could agree with you
So you're saying there is a moral evolution?
Yes, I think there is some more...
Certainly moral evolution, but I think it's directed
Our moral behavior has gotten in many ways better
Because it's through the recognition, coming through moral slays
When you think about the civil rights movement here
It was a matter of getting people, the majority of people to care about a minority on purely moral grounds
On saying, look, this system is just wrong, maybe I'm benefiting from it
So how do you think that might play out in the future as we have tendencies
You brought up that are frightening tendencies, maybe for the subsumption of the individual
Into the super organism, you know, anthill
Do you see that we are going to need to either invent or discover or still have to be doing that?
Like there's more to come?
Well, look, I think there are a lot of...
Just as people could live in a society with chattel slavery
And somehow avert their gaze and avert their mind from it
Even though they knew, I mean, Jefferson knew, these people knew they were doing something wrong at a deep level
But we have lots of self-rationalization, a lot of blocking, psychological blocking mechanisms
To keep us from recognizing how terrible certain things we are doing
You know, hopefully as time goes on, people will start to see...
They'll look back at our society and say, you were so primitive
Because they will have actually put into practice things that if we think about them in a calm way
We'll say, yeah, we're really our society
I mean, as I say, we live in a society where there's such a thing as the working poor
That if someone can be employed 40 hours a week
And still be hard and still be able...
There's just no moral principle that should allow that in any society
If you're a socialist, you think people shouldn't even have to work to live
And you can make that argument, that's going to be a harder argument around here
But even now, on both sides of the political spectrum
How could anybody say, yeah, somebody can be out there working 40 hours a week
And still not be above the poverty line
So I just want to point out again that animals and trees and plants don't have moral choices
We have moral choices
So now we need to talk about how did morality emerge in human evolution
And again, we have hunter-gatherer brains, we're all tribal creatures
We harmlessly divert that into sports or other things
We less so harmlessly divert that into ideologies and nationalism
And ethnic chauvinism and so on and so forth
And so there's two ways to approach our moral
One is what's functional, what's best for the individual for the group
And the other is principled
And so you're taking a principled position
And there's reasons why that's good too
We certainly both agree that there's moral evolution
But you almost sound like you'd like the God there
With the Ten Commandments
And somehow imprinting in our biology
Rules against slavery and fantasize
Like God, no, no, no, no, no, no, this is like you're merging the two things here
There was an old art, there's a...
If you go back to Plato in the youth of Fro, he gave the right argument about this
Creating morality isn't something even God could do
If you think God made up morality
Then you're saying, all right, I'll have Ten Commandments
Should it be thou shalt kill or thou shalt not kill?
Well, pretty much six and one and a half a dozen of the other
Because there's no moral principle
Then you think that's just an arbitrary choice
Then it wouldn't be a moral principle
But what about the fact that those societies that chose thou shalt kill?
Which, honey did, especially outsiders
Then they didn't survive as well
There's kind of a selection process in historical cultures
It's also true that the world evolves in ways
The reality of our situation evolves in ways that fundamentally change the moral landscape
There are moral challenges we have now that people didn't have a couple hundred years ago
There's a historian, an environmental historian named Francois Muho, a French guy
Who wrote an essay called Thomas Jefferson and Me a couple years ago
We talked about Thomas Jefferson and slavery and how, as you say, he knew that it was wrong
But he said that Jefferson and his contemporaries lived with what he called a moral deficit
Because even though their new slavery was wrong, they could not imagine
How they could live without it
And so they lived doing something they knew that it was wrong
And he goes further that slavery was a big part of how they got the energy to power their society
The way we get energy to power our society now, we know it's wrong and it's harming future generations
This was not something we had to confront a couple hundred years ago, or a couple thousand years ago
Certainly when the world was functionally infinite
Now the world is no longer functionally infinite for us
And we are confronted with new moral challenges
And it's very complicated because it's not enough to just say, well we have to change how we live
If you wrote your bicycle here, you're fine
Although I applaud it
I took the train out here, that wasn't too bad
But it's a global problem that we have to address globally
It's not enough to change our energy distribution because these issues of inequity
We are raising people in developing countries deserve a more high energy lifestyle than they have now
Because the, you know, rural electrification
Being able to cook their meals without having to gather wood and gun
That's going to cause them respiratory harm
There's a basic way in which they deserve and need more energy
And yet we all live in the same atmosphere, so it's our moral obligation
Not just to change the way we live, but to help them change the way they live
And this is an entirely new kind of moral conundrum that humanity has never had to face before
So there may be moral, I agree with you actually that there are moral absolutes that we can at least search for
But certainly the landscape has changed, so there are moral conundrums we face now
That people have not had to face before, and that may well be true again in the future, the landscape shifts
So have you thought of what that might mean for the individual psychology?
Well again, to me it's part of this trying to learn how to become a larger entity than ourselves
Work together in groups in a functional and sustainable way
You may not like the language of super organism, and that's fine with me
Because it's really more of a metaphor than anything else
But certainly I think we can agree that guided by compassion and principles of equity
And some of these principles we agree on
That we have to learn, we're faced now with a need to move into a mode where we can function well together in larger groups than we've had to before
And to me that reflects this kind of hierarchy that you've described in an interesting way
But even without departing from even the traditional biological hierarchy, human species is unique
In a way that it's the only species that exceeded the natural boundaries of its own ecosystem
We don't live within constraints or we give an ecosystem
So for us, due to a large extent to our capacity of culture, cultural exchange, we occupy the entire globe
And we can use the entire planet and I can't entirely agree with you that because of that, that's the unique challenge
Now all the species at any level have that maybe say moral obligation, but they kind of have a global role
In forming the future of its own environment
And that's why it's certainly unique, even irrespective of culture, and the culture is probably what is responsible for the global status of our species
There have been species, of course, in the past who have changed the planet and suffered the consequences of that
Going back to our friends, the cyanobacteria who poisoned the whole world
There's a one species that's right, there have been organisms in the past
And I think you can find examples of single species that have done major things to the globe
But at any rate, in that sense it's not a new conundrum
But yet it is a new conundrum, but what's new about it, we're aware of it
We feel this sense of responsibility, we are, whether you want to call it evolving or changing
Or whatever word you want to use, moving into the future as a changing entity through new mechanisms
And obviously we're not just doing that in some vacuum space, we're doing it against the backdrop of a planet
The evolution of which we have somehow suddenly found ourselves integral to
And so these are now, and this is my sort of fascination in the really subject of the book I've just written
We're not just talking about a change in biological evolution, we're talking about a change in planetary evolution
That is coming about through this new level of, if we can call it evolution, cultural change
There's one thing that intrigues me about that, then the world, so yes, cyanobacteria or what I like to call
Biochemical guilds have changed the world, but then it's now in our minds
The carbon dioxide level is above 400 parts per million, well not everybody's mind yet
But hopefully it will be because it's in the air and it's talked about
And so the world, in the way it's a problem, our minds have caused the problem, so now they're starting to appreciate that process
Strange feedback between our minds and the planet, it wasn't my mind, it wasn't your mind
I didn't invent fossil fuel consumption, I didn't invent computers
It was this distributed mind, and we're already involved in this larger collective, whatever you call it
And I think economic markets are kind of interesting in that respect
Because most economists and investors would agree that it's got a mind of its own
And if they could understand it and predict it, they'd be filthy rich until everybody else adapt their mind
And so we're already involved in culture and economics and discovery
And this whole economy of knowledge and know-how and language and everything else
And we're like the bacteria in our stomach trying to understand what is this thing I live in
I always notice, and I know nothing about economics, and I'm really glad you're addressing this on this level
I can't wait to read your book, but I always can't wait to write it
What are you doing here, go home and write it
I always notice when I venture to the business pages, which occasionally I do
The way the language that we use to describe the market
It has emotions, it has intentions
We talk about the market is spooked, or the market became afraid of this, or the market was worried about this
Or the market was buoyed, or happy because of this
The market has bipolar disorder
Is this just a metaphor, an easy way to describe something, or are we actually describing some sort of...
We talk about it like a conscious entity, and yet obviously it's some manifestation of our own individual choices
That's where my knowledge of this ends, it's just sort of being befuddled by that
We're on the same thing
It's the emergence part of it
I think, I'm sorry, I would be a little cautious about this emergence talk
And making it all sound so mysterious, because it seems to me we're missing
In the case of fossil fuels, there is just the blind greed of certain people
Who wanted to make a lot of money, and didn't care, just like the cigarette manufacturers and so on
They were doing something that for Sea of We was going to be horrible, they didn't care
Now you can talk about the emergence of this, but that's the problem, right?
Don't look at sound like it's the big one
But it's not interesting
The fossil fuel industry is making money, and they want to continue to make money
But that's not the whole story
You get no benefit from fossil fuels and the people who make money on it, you get no benefit
No, I didn't say that, I'm saying that
Well, I'm not the same, I mean fossil fuels
There's a conscious attempt which has succeeded to make people disbelieve scientific results
To question the entire scientific enterprise, to think this whole thing is a hoax
And that's having terrible political, making it impossible to address this politically
And that's the way we can do it
Whether I had benefited from fossil fuels or not, and at what point it became clear the damage
Of course, in the beginning, I can imagine people saying no matter what humans do
We're too puny, right? The stuff coming out of my tailpipe can't possibly mean that
There's going to be human change
Well, the greenhouse effect was not even understood
So there was time, it took time to figure that out
In a rational situation, once you figured it out, there would be steps taken to
Emeliorate it
So this being blocked by that, and it's not mysterious why we're being blocked by it, right?
So I think what you're describing is absolutely true, but it's not the whole story
I feel like this global mind we're talking about, which is actually kind of dumb and slow, is figuring it out
And fossil fuels have been this wonderful thing
They are a wonderful thing, I mean, we discovered that they replaced our slaves
They replaced whale oil, which seemed great for a while, and then we realized that we did that a little too long
It did some damage that we wish we hadn't done
200 years from now, that's how we look at fossil fuels
We did that a little bit too long, and we did damage that we wish hadn't been done
They've been an amazing source of energy, and if you look at the level of poverty
Over the last 200 years has gone down, down, down, down, down
There's been amazing progress, human infant mortality is half what it was 30 years ago
There are a lot of ways in which this is the best time to be a human being alive
And a lot of that has to do with fossil fuels
Now it's absolutely true that we need to change what we're doing
And a big part of the reason we're not fast enough has to do with the pandemic
And we're all about greed, and people denying that and delaying it
So I completely agree with you, but the long story is one of we did this thing that seemed great, it was great
And now we're realizing that we need to stop doing it as quickly as we can
And part of the reason we're having trouble realizing that we, this global human mind is because of this fact
That we're not on the same page, and in fact some people are profiting by keeping us all off the same page
I just want to say that the people who work in ExxonMobil or wherever do not think of themselves as evil
I'm sure they don't
And they have a very few people do
Exactly
Okay, we will stop here and go to the audience for their questions
for their questions. You have to go to the microphone if you have a question.
Yes, we also are talking once he says, okay, to ground this.
This is getting... Can you have a question? Yeah.
Hi, I'm Gio. I'm a neuroscientist by training and I stopped doing that because of my
new passion for psychocultural development. So emergence in culture is really the thing that
wakes me up in the morning and I was really enjoyed this really a rich conversation.
I have one question, essentially about cultural development. And you said something really interesting
about that I didn't get before, about that if you add energy to matter, you create complexity.
Right? You said something like that. And it's kind of interesting because then you bounce back
something that was said before about cultural development. I said there is a big difference
and it's a learning we learn. And I was sort of wondering if you could make a parallel between
matter and a flow of energy creating complexity as fueling emergence and complexity in the
biological physical world and having mental structures that of course you didn't talk about that but
they are mental structures and they change. And this flow of information which is really learning,
which is the information that's available and that a particular individual will also be sensitive
to able to read, would actually fuel emerging, I mean, complexity, creativity and the emergence
of new mental structure. I was wondering if you could, if you had like any ideas about what is
actually happening when we talk about cultural development or consciousness development.
It's too complicated. I can talk. I mean, so I think culture requires energy
as just like all biological things and for this great acceleration that we've been through in
the last century from three times as many people practically in my lifetime, much more consumption
of fossil fuels, so on and so forth. I think that all requires energy to happen. But I think I
want to also say two things. One in Chasan's work, Eric Chasan, he talks about optimal energy flows.
If all the energy that we use outside of our bodies was going through our bodies, we'd all
be burnt toast. So there are different ranges of optimal energy. They often, in big history,
they often use the term Goldilocks parameters and sometimes they're leaps or shifts from prokaryotes
to eukaryotes or whatever. But it's all the same process, whether it's single cells or human brains.
It's energy, matter, and ingenuity or information that contains ingenuity. So DNA is a way of coding
information and what's more important than the information is, it's information that does something.
And so our brains are also good at coding information and the stuff we remember,
information that does something useful. And then that information is exchanged between brains
and across generations. And that's what bacteria do it by lateral genes transfer. But when you get
into eukaryotic evolution and sexual reproduction and distinct lineages, then you have a different
type of selection process, a more Darwinian. And it's not that Darwinian selection doesn't
operate on our genes, it does. But we have this other way of evolving through collective learning,
through symbolic language. And maybe the most important thing we invent are fictions like money
or human rights or religions or cities. So I don't know if that answers your question, but there's
a question. Don't you think that there is a correlation or at least like a mirror image between
flow of energy in matter, fueling biological and physical evolution and flow of information
within mental structures, flowing the creativity and complexity in the emergence of new mental
structures? So you could talk about information density flow. Yeah, exactly. That would be a
term that I use. Information density flow. So humans are particularly amazing. And now of course
we're creating new information, we're drowning in data. So one of the really interesting things
to look at their trajectory of digital information and plot it out against the amount of energy
required to store that information. So I think right now about 10% of the electric grid in the
United States is devoted to maintaining computers and computer data banks and super data centers.
And that, you know, if like if the banking system goes to a blockchain, that will require a new
leap. If you look at the amount of genetic information that is generated or the amount of
information that they generated, it's CERN. So we're on this exponential leap of information,
but it's not, it's what matters is information that does something that has some ingenuity to it.
And that may be lost in the jungle as it were. Okay, I'm okay with his question just in terms of
we feed, so to speak, mentally on patterns of light and sound and to some degree smell,
but mostly in touch. But you know, so there is, we are requiring these inputs not just for the raw
energy of the light coming in. I mean, it's not really helping my body. It's way too little
that's coming from your, you're asking that question of as I'm getting patterns of light and sound.
So I know very literal sense of his, his question of I do see that there is an analogy there.
And then what we do with that, of course, is it's not just it's inherent that we have to do
something, it's not inherent, we have to do something with what he he spoke in English to us. So
we're already receptive to that. One last response and then we move to the next question.
I'm not a cultural anthropologist to really provide a full answer, but as far as understand,
the part of the development of the human brain was a part fueled by the change of human feeding
patterns and diets, especially with regard to cooking, which led to the extremely much of my
vision that for any other organism consumption of energy and probably at the level of individual
organism, even before you start talking about some communal responses to the collective consciousness.
So for at the level of individual with the development of the brain that will lead to the
greater capacity of thinking processes, there was a definitely influx of energy from the change
of truly biological structures. So it has to do with feeding strategies change in the feeding
apparatus, the ability to cook and related to that utilization of tools. So I think it's directly
involved. Okay, next question. Oh, there are more.
It's been a very interesting discussion, but one in particularly in terms of the
question of energy and ecology and so forth, but nobody mentioned an experiment that took place
about 75 years ago, which was an experiment conducted by a rather small group, maybe a thousand to
two thousand physicists who produced an atom bomb and the history of the science of this
really goes back to Einstein and Bohr and so on. So it was a long process and they were very
conscious of the ethical and moral possibilities about this event. We don't have to go into all
of the discussions that took place. Among the scientists, there were differences of opinion,
but generally those one of the argument who said that knowledge and information is more important
than a decision about what the result or the consequences of this would be. Of course, they were
under the pressure of feeling that the Nazis were developing an atom as well as we were,
and that the Nazis, if they got one, would be more horrible than if we exploded it. And they also
thought that this would have a great effect on the expense, expansiveness and availability of
energy because they thought atomic energy could be, we know all about this. But this wasn't
discussed and one of the reasons why I suppose it wasn't discussed is that they didn't know what
the effects would be in the long run. They thought they knew what the effects would be in the short
run, but not in the long run. We still don't know whether this atomic development,
what the effects in the long run are going to be. And so I think that nobody has been discussing
how we can find some way to be able to predict the future better, not only in the stock market,
which will make one of us a richer or not, because I think that's the real problem. We can't predict
the future. We don't know what's going to happen. And we are still living in the where I am anyway,
in the belief that the more we know and the more we understand about nature, our own nature is in
the nature around us, the better off we'll be. But that hasn't been proven yet.
Thank you. Well, you raised some excellent points. The Manhattan Project scientists, many of them were
aware of what was going to result and were terrified of it. But as you said, they were more terrified of
what would happen if they didn't do this and the Nazis did it. As far as I know, there was nobody
involved in the Manhattan Project. None of the scientists who said, we shouldn't do this. Let's
stop because of what were unleashed. There were a lot of them that are immediately afterwards became
leaders in the disarmament movement. People like Philip Morrison, and for the rest of their lives,
many of them, this was what they devoted themselves to, was nuclear disarmament, because they realized
immediately that they had helped create something that was not really a weapon in a meaningful way,
but was a global suicide machine, which it remains. And there was even, they were even faced with
the knowledge, the possibility that when they did the Trinity test, they might destroy the world.
There was a calculation that they weren't sure, depending on the cross sections of some of these
reactions that they might fuse the entire atmosphere. And at that moment, destroy all life on earth.
They thought it was very unlikely. And they decided to go ahead with it. So, I mean, I think they
were aware of these moral contradictions. They were choosing what they thought was the lesser
of evil. And then a lot of them spent the rest of their lives working to put the genie back in
the bottle that they had helped unleash. And we still live under that thread in a way that I think
people underestimate for reasons that have to do with your profession, probably more than mine.
Addressing the psychiatrist. But as far as predicting the future, let me just say one more thing.
Part of what I did, I was at the Library of Congress for a year, a couple years ago,
as the chair of astrobiology. And one of the projects I did that I wrote up as a part of this
book, Earth and Human Hands, was it was called a short history of the future, where I looked at
predictions of the future through a large swath of history, and particular predictions of now
that were written 100 years ago, 200 years ago. And one thing you realize when you do this exercise
is that nobody can predict the future well. Even really smart people, H2Ls, and, you know,
Sage, people who regard as Sage, who predicted certain aspects of it really well. But nobody
gets the game changers. And I think that that will always be true and that I'm not even sure
being able to predict the future well in total should be our goal. But there are certainly
aspects of that that have now become essential as far as those levers that we're pooling on the
Earth. Obviously climate modeling is important because that's a lever that we're pooling. So,
you know, we'll never be able to really predict the future well, but we'll be able to increase
our ability to break that down into some tangible goals, such as predicting the
effect on the climate of the doubling of CO2, things like that we'll get better at. But as far as,
I mean, the problem you're addressing really has to do with managing ourselves and our behavior,
collective behavior as we get more powerful tools. And that, I'm not sure, is even really a problem
of science so much as it is of spirituality and other realms we haven't entirely addressed yet
in this conversation. Can I say a word about the predictability problem? This actually,
at the very beginning, I said, well, here's an interesting thing that it's amazing that
above the micro-physical level where we think there are these strict laws,
that there's anything predictable at higher levels, right, that they should form enough structure
that and have enough stability and predictability. In the case of, say, atoms, you put a bunch of
atoms together and you get the ideal gas laws, which are very simple, right, and very, very
predictive. And it's really important for that that all the atoms are the same or they interact
in very much the same ways. The climate is more or less the same thing, but you get because of
the flows, it's a chaotic system, and so it's more complicated. But the kinds of predictions
we're worried about, which have to do with human beings, that's a whole different ball game,
because every single one of us is different. And every single one of us will respond differently
to our environment and differently to inputs. And you can't have a statistical mechanical
theory that's going to predict human behavior. Well, you never will have, because there's too
much idiosyncrasy in each individual brain. So there's not the kind of uniformity that's going
to allow for such a thing. So I think if you wanted to predict, who predicted the last election
correctly? And this is something that it's not far in the future, right? We were all living in this
society. It had to do with collective psychology, it had to do with all sorts of things that I think
are just not ever going to be amenable to strict prediction in any way. So I'm sorry to give you
that story. But I want to propose a major breakthrough in making progress in the way human beings think
together by sorting our different ways of being human, our different ways of thinking, our different
ways of making sense. And what I've devoted my last 50 years to is applying Freud's emphasis on
early experiences to that single most important item in all of life. It's people, can you name me
one most important item in all of life? And the answer is, I believe, pretty clearly, the sun.
And applying Freud to the sun, I would make this proposition that the flow of solar energy to us
here, let's say in the middle third of the upper half of the planet goes as a curve, one curve a
year, it's something like 200 calories per square centimeter at the low end Christmas time for a
whole day to 800, six months later. So we have a solar energy flow that is sort of sinusoidal shape.
But the point is this, your birthday turns out to be the phase with respect to that sine curve,
a fundamental dimension. And so we can make progress if we get rescue birthday away from
astrology and its nonsensical premises and approach it more in a Freudian way. We're talking about
light and dark, hot and cold. And we can sort humanity usefully so that we can learn how to think
together and make progress in a democracy. We can even solve the riddle of justice that it turns out
this is going to be too heavy. It turns out that in the Old Testament, and I'm an atheist,
but in the Old Testament there is a useful dividing of humanity by 12 in the 12 brothers, 12 sons of
Jacob. And in the fathers, goodbye to his 12 sons, he identifies a lot of traits that I think are
important. The kids who are born when it's cold and dark, and it gets colder and darker, he said,
you guys have too much murder in your heart. But in particular, one of the sons, the son, I
believe, is born midwinter. He said, you guys are the ones who have the talent for being judges.
And when we make you guys the judges will have justice. Voila. So can you imagine approaching
the puzzlement that we're facing here, the confounding variety of ways of being human,
if we could usefully sort them, if birthday indeed was a legitimate basis for profound
differences in human nature, could you imagine that as a basis for some progress?
Guess when I hear that, I think of like ant casts or something like that, you know, the 12 cast of
humans based on when they were born. I mean, I've wondered like whether I was born in November,
whether like, okay, I got like a month going down to the dark, but then started coming around soon.
I didn't get very far in my own head about that. I guess, I don't know, I think there was something
in nature years ago about astrological sorting. I know you're not saying it's the planets, but
I think it was pretty much debunked. I'm not saying that the light doesn't have some effect on people,
but so does birth order, parent personality, siblings, what kind of electronics you're using.
It's complex and complicated. It's complex and complicated. So, okay, next question.
The point that you made about the Manhattan Project and how these really smart people
came to the conclusion that they needed to be tribal because the Germans would do it
if they didn't do it is an example of even if we have really smart people, they're still going
to end up being tribal. So, is there any any example in nature where there are people or
organisms evolved from being tribal to being not tribal? So, there's a scaling that happens all
through human history from small hunter groups, Rob and Dunbar thinks there's actually a neurological
correlation that probably the largest group the humans would feel comfortable in based on our
brain and the complexity of social relations is about 150 people. And then at that point,
it would split and there are there's also sort of archetypal
teams like the archetypal team, the band of brothers. It's like the football team, it's 12
over 10 or 8 or you know, but never 20, never 30, right? So, the business units. So, there's
are kind of an inherited natural scale to human sociality. And one of the great mysteries is
how do we scale it up to millions of people? Like, you know, chimpanzees could not, you know,
this many chimpanzees could not sit in the same room together. I guarantee all hell would break
out, right? Especially strangers. So, right? So, you know, how we're not like a big herd animal,
we're intensely concerned about our social relationships. And if they get too complicated,
our brains can't deal with it. That's Dunbar's quote unquote number. So, one of the ways is
what part of the study, which is religion. And, you know, that's one of the ways that we scale up
society, right? And we go from pretty egalitarian hunter, gather troops to two hierarchical groups,
where there's a minority that steals the surplus production to sustain, you know, different hierarchies
or whatever. And one of the competitive drives, once agriculture comes into play, is that agriculture
is not a high growing productivity, economic activity. It gets established and then it's
pretty stationary. So, if you want to get rich quick, the logic is you go invade your neighbors,
you steal their livestock or animal, you kill the men, steal the women, make them slaves,
increase your labor, increase your land. And so, within agricultural civilization, not only do you
get things like patriarchy and, you also get an economic incentive to militarization. And that
militarization, that competition then drives the spread of all these ideas all around the world.
And for good and for bad. So, anyway, it's a mystery that seven billion of us are on this planet right
now. It's a mystery. And that we are, I think, the pinnacle of cooperation in evolution. That's how
I would frame it rather than the pinnacle of competition. But both have played an important
role in human history. And to answer your strict question, biologically, there are examples.
There's this whole counterpoint to, you know, sort of competition and survival of the fittest.
There's this whole field of biology, social biology, where there is cooperation at different
levels and group selection has led to remarkable examples of self-sacrifice in nature for the good
of the whole. And it then does come down in some level to propagating genes. Yeah, I mean,
the insects are the stars at this. But there are other examples as well. So, there are biological
factors that have pushed in that direction. But as just mentioned, human biological capacity
does seem to have a limit. Fortunately, we are not limited to our genetic skills. The one thing
that, in addition to being, you know, uniquely perhaps cooperative species, we're also uniquely
adaptable and reinvented species. And, you know, the world is changing in some ways that one can
imagine, increase our capacity to overcome tribal differences. Global communications, right now,
we're at a moment of possible fragmentation and trying to struggle with some of the effects of
connectivity. But that may just be a moment. But it seems as though the trend is for global
connection. And that combined with our innate sociality may sort of come to our rescue.
Tyler, do you want to respond also? I'm not trying to find what everyone said.
And I would also mention science as something that is a global cooperative.
And, in fact, almost anything where people come together to seek some goal that's bigger than
themselves. I've been a part of some spacecraft teams, you know, and very close to people. For
instance, on this New Horizons mission that just made it to Pluto. And that's a team of hundreds
of people who genuinely, I mean, yes, they fall prey to all the petty competitive, you know,
motivations that we all do. But there's also this level of self-sattrophes that we're all
in this together that we're all seeking this common goal. And humans do have an amazing ability.
You know, unfortunately, a lot of times it's like our army against their army, which is what
unites us. But there's that capacity that, you know, faced with the challenges of
really the existential challenges that we're starting to become aware of that will require
some level of global cooperation that one can imagine those capacities being employed on a
global level to face those challenges. Yeah, and I'm glad you brought up science because you could
look at the history of science and the scientific revolution as being a very much cooperativity
among these scientists that were in different nations. They just transcended that, you know,
for the most part. We have very little time, so please make the questions brief and the responses
brief. Okay. The latter part of your conversation was interesting and made me think of a book by
Frederick Frank to be human against all odds on the ability of mankind to transcend its
reptilian brain, which one has to wonder when we look at the incredible cruelty throughout the
world that man still, you know, perpetrates. And I'm not just talking about areas of conflict,
we can just look right here at home. We don't have to go that far. But the other thing that
was interesting is you mentioned post-enlightenment and immorality, but maybe we need to look at
other societies. If we look at the First Nations and therefore it against the Dakota Access Pipeline
and having another view of the world, which is not post-enlightenment, but is much more
humane and is considerate of its fellow human beings and of the principle that we don't inherit
society, our earth, sorry, from our elders, but that we borrow it from our children. So maybe,
you know, white man's post-enlightenment isn't so enlightened.
Well, speaking as one of the white men here, I don't want it. The panel is...
Is it the area where we discussed white-enlightenment?
Last question.
I probably should have brought this up when mental structures were mentioned,
being from the arts and humanities, there is a big crisis in the arts and humanities because
of the increase of knowledge and the changing of mental structures. And this has a tremendous
effect on the nature of art and the nature of literature and the nature of humanities.
There are a few artists now who are trying something called Gesam Kunzwerk, which is an old term,
about trying to unite science and all the disciplines in an art form. And it has its advantages,
but only a very few can really unite all the complexity of science and the humanities.
And I think it's something to begin to think of. We can't quite go back to the same mental
structures in the works of art. Our world is too complex. At the same time, individualism is
extremely important and must never be forgotten because a work of art does come from a single
individual. So I just want to remind you, all of this complexity is very interesting. More of the
artists should be listening. At the same time, it doesn't mean that it's going to have a simple
solution. And we are in a crisis now in terms of the nature and production of the arts.
Great comment. Thank you. All right. Thank you very much.