Welcome to the Helix Center. This is the last program for this season and before
I introduce today's participants, let me tell you we'll be going from fear to
happiness as of September 24th. Watch for further announcements on our website
helixcenter.org. Now today's participants, if you can raise your hand as I say your
name, Nushin Hajikani, Associate Professor in Radiology, Harvard Medical School,
Joseph LeDoo, University Professor and Henry Luzmosis Professor of Science,
Center for Neuroscience and Department of Psychology, NYU, Eric Marcus, Director of
the Columbia University Center for Psychoanalytic Training and Research,
Professor of Clinical Psychiatry at Columbia University College of Physicians
and Surgeons, Francis Lee, Mortimer Sackler Professor and Vice Chair for
Research Department of Psychiatry while Cornell Medical College, Robert Kurzmann,
Professor of Psychology, University of Pennsylvania. Anyone can start.
Sorry, how are you gonna? No, I'm just gonna wait for you to say something. Go ahead.
Okay, well I guess I'll start. So you know as a psychologist, turned into a
neuroscientist of sorts. I think any kind of psychological question, whether
you're approaching it in the brain or in behavior, always has to start from our
introspections. I mean that's our only access to our mental processes and
internal states and so forth. So you know without being able to introspect
and formulate the idea that we have a line that we have something called
consciousness, we couldn't possibly study that. So there's no way that an
organism that doesn't have that capacity to look inside its own brain and have
its own ideas and formulate those especially in verbal questions, statements
like this that allows us to say okay I'm aware that I have a psychology, a mind,
and that's somehow related to my body but also seems to have some kind of
separate existence. All of that is only possible because of the kind of brain
that we have and we don't know which other animals obviously have that because no
other animal can tell us about this. So from the point of view of fear, we look
into our brains and our minds and we say what is fear? How are we gonna study
that in an animal or another person? And what we come up with is that you know we
fear is a kind of experience we have that we're in danger. So therefore we can
study what happens when an organism is in danger and learn something about fear.
Now the way we observe scientifically the fear of another organism so to speak
is through its behavior or other reactions or responses. Obviously we
can't go inside another person or another animal's mind. So when I study a rat and
the rat is exposed to a threatening stimulus and it freezes, the question is
what do we call that? For the last 30-something years, many of my colleagues
have called that fear. But when I was talking about fear and many my colleagues
as well, we weren't talking about fear as the conscious experience. We're talking
about it as a kind of inner motivational state that connects
stimuli with responses so that a rat is freezing or a human jumps back from a
bus that's flying by before there where the bus is there and so forth. And when
that happens we have these non-conscious systems that allow us to do this. At the
same time when we look into our minds we both see ourselves jumping back and
feeling afraid. So it all seems to be bundled together as one thing and that's
why the most common idea about how fear is represented in the brain is that you
have a kind of fear circuit or fear center that we've inherited from animals
aside. There goes back to Darwin and perhaps even older and through the
operation of that circuit we both respond to danger and feel fear. I mean
that's the natural way to think about it. But as we begin to take these things
apart, not so much in animal brains because we can't really make the
distinction. But in the human brain we can begin to see that when we can create a
threat by a conditioning process is expose the person to that threat and the
person will then respond to the threat. But if we present that and the person
will know the threat is there and so forth. But if we present that stimulus in a way
that the person doesn't have conscious access to the stimulus, the person will
still respond to the threat. So the heart will raise, the palms will sweat and so
forth even though the person never saw the stimulus and claims to feel no fear.
So fear can't be what's driving these responses that are controlled by this
part of the brain that I work on called the amygdala. Fear is what happens when
we become aware that our brain is responding in this kind of way and a
lot of other things go into the creation of the fear as well. So this and you can
study patients who have what's called blind sight where they're blind in the
left side of space. You can present a threat there. You don't have to use any
tricks or anything where it's presented very briefly. You can just present a
threat to the rough visual field and if you're imaging the person the amygdala
will be activated and the responses will be present but the person won't know the
stimulus is there and won't feel anything. So and I'll cut it short now.
So because of this kind, this and many other kinds of pieces of information, I
come to the conclusion that it was really inappropriate to talk about fear
when I was studying the rats' responses to threats. What I'd been studying is the
operation of the defensive survival circuit that allows the rat or any
other organism to detect and respond to danger and that can contribute to the
feeling of fear but that is not one and the same as the feeling of fear. The
feeling of fear instead I think is more of a kind of cortical process,
neocortical process where information about the present stimulus, memories
about what that stimulus is and what it means, schemas about what kinds of
emotions those are associated with and so forth are integrated with the fact
that say the amygdala is already being responding to the stimulus and all kinds
of feedback is coming within the brain arousal and body feedback and so forth
and all of that is integrated in working memory to give rise to the feeling of
fear. So that's my view of things. What's the value of making that distinction?
Well the value is that this is going to take you some more time is that okay?
So the value of what it is for the past 50 years the pharmaceutical industry has
been attempting to develop and anti-anxiety drugs and in 2010 last
post-SmithKline and a couple of others began saying we can't do it. Nothing
is happening. You know we're testing rats and mice in these chambers and giving
them drugs that make them less timid, less behaviorally inhibited but when we
give them to people it doesn't make them feel less fearful or anxious or not
reliably or consistently. So what's wrong? Well the person that's a person
with a social anxiety disorder on a SSRI is more likely to go to the party
but still feel bad when they're there because it's not reducing the fear and
anxiety at the party is just changing the inhibitory behavior about going to the
party. So if we make this broad distinction between
circuits that control these behavioral responses and circuits that generate
these kinds of subjective feelings we can begin to ask questions about
therapy and how it can be approached in a way that's more consistent with at
least the way I think about how the brain is organized.
Joe I think what you said is really crucial and delighted to hear you say it
because being an analyst I believe the mind can be studied
and also that the cerebral cortex in evolution
is crucial and you have just outlined that salient fact
that the brain in humans is complicated it's layered
their levels their connections and many of the most
interesting things about mental function are probably widely distributed circuits
maybe even whole brain and that's crucial because it may allow us to begin to
correlate cerebral neurophysiology with what analysts call meaning
and meaning is a tricky thing because one it's mind
number two it may be unconscious as well as conscious
number three big point it's symbolically presented
it's symbolically represented and when that happens
something's happening in the brain both in word presentations and thing
presentations that stores this meaning for us
but it isn't mind it is brain and as analysts we deal with very
paradoxical fear which is called usually anxiety
fear being something that has happened or about to happen
anxiety being something you worry about that it might happen
and the anxieties that we look at as analysts may be unconscious in their
contents are often paradoxical patient fear what is not
not just for most people or even more so they fear
what is positively reinforcing for most people
and so we have to understand not the fear or the
or the the um the affect generated but the affect meaning the affect
contents mark solm's is here which takes me back to
makali makarly and hobsan who when i was a young tad just as a a new
attending out of residency they gave a grand rounds at psychiatric
institute big news the dream has no meaning why
because the generator of the dream is in the midbrain
i got up and dared to say you know now three years old i saw my first movie
snow white in the seven doors in the movie i turned to my mom and said mommy
what was that and a kindly usher says come here get out show you
takes me upstairs in the back shows me the projector it says that's the movie
i say wow that's the movie and i thought man i'll never understand grownups
this man over there said you know what they're actually rolling about the
physiology of the dream and began to show that higher
cortical function is intimately involved in the dream
and that brought meaning back into the study of neurophysiology
it's a very tricky study because mind is not the same as brain
there are carlots but the qualitative experience of mind
is probably a whole brain experience consciousness is probably a whole
brain experience doesn't mean that we can't have very useful
correlations but it does mean that as an analyst i study
mind and qualitative experience not only event occurrences and quantitative
experiences what would you say
how fear and anxiety are expressed in the brain when i do
imaging of that and and that of course is a very
artificial settings because what what we do is we put people in big machines
that make a lot of noise and and we show them stimuli
and they know that's nothing is going to jump on them and attack them or anything
like that but still we do see circuitry that
that gets activated for certain things i was very privileged to once image
this famous blind side patient gy who was so we were first asking him what do
you see it's nice nothing i said but just guess
decides press left or right whether it's this or that he said okay i'll do it if
you want me to do it but i really see nothing
but his guesses were better than chance he was it was actually really
he was without being conscious of what he was saying he was
saying it the interesting thing is it was it was not only fear it was saying
which was also happiness actually it was reacting to
happy stimuli as well and um and so it was really amazing to see that
somebody who was not conscious of something that he was perceiving was
still able to show brain activation in all this
circuitry that we that we know that are involved in in in the perception of
so you're saying that his perceptual circuits were lighting up
yes yeah and the cortex prefrontal cortex that stuff so no so not the
prefrontal cortex that's the interesting part is that it was the
earlier visual areas and and motion areas and sort of
mimicry even areas that were being involved but not the prefrontal and
not the parietal in in his case so that was
and i think the prefrontal in the parietal cortex are essential for the
experiential feeling of the emotion so to follow up on Joe's point then
in your human or imaging studies i study mainly
mouse threat circuitry so have you found based on what Joe has
laid out it would seem that we should find new areas in the human brain that
have not been yet figured out by optogenetics or other
things within the rodent brain that are related to fear
have you based on your sort of i know very laboratory based still sort of
paradigms have you found other areas that
have not yet been found in rodent brains i guess all the mirroring areas are
not definitely i i i don't know much about rodents i have to say i've always
been you know i don't think it has to do with areas
we can talk about circuits that you can pick up
you know in an imaging situation and certainly the
you know the rat or mouse prefrontal cortex is very different very
different um you know other primates have much more similar
prefrontal cortex but even in the even the differences between
humans and non-human primates exist in terms of
you know connectivity patterns and and other kind of subtle connection
and other things that that wouldn't necessarily be
you know that imaging wouldn't be sensitive to
or i mean some of them are like the connectivity but you know it's
there's i i agree with what you said that may mean my whole
position has long been my starting position as many of our
starting positions is probably from our graduate student days and i studied
as a graduate student conscious experience in split brain
patients and how information presented to the right
hemisphere couldn't be accessed by the left
hemisphere but the left hemisphere could you know respond to the behaviors
being produced by the right hemisphere and was always generating these
complex explanations of why the behavior is being produced even though it had
no idea and so this led gazanaga and i to the
this idea that part of the role of consciousness is to
kind of tell a story about ourselves that that
sort of glues together all these random behaviors coming from all these
unconscious processes including so-called emotional behaviors and in
this Freud said the of the consciousness is the tip of the iceberg most of what
the brain is doing is under the radar can i push a little bit on that so
if you take the research that you were talking about at gsk so one way to read
what you're saying is not only is that research
not going not in fact helping us understand how to suppress
the feeling of anxiety this sort of phenomenology
phenomenology of it but one one way to take what you're saying is
they can't in principle because the thing that we do in
sort of as phenomenological beings as humans is this going to turn out to be
different right but i would say can't directly inform
feelings but obviously in a in a real emotional situation unlike what we can
do in humans and laboratory the feedback from all of this stuff so
you know there are lots of things going on let's put it in terms of three
consequences of a make-it-all activation that would
impact say working memory and its ability to
synthesize all of this information one would be
direct connections from the amygdala to cortical areas
another would be outputs of the amygdala to and i'm just using a make-it-allist
example not necessarily see how that's answered everything
the second would be connections from the amygdala
to arousal circuits in the brainstem that are going to you know light up the
brain and say something important's happened and cause
attention to begin monitoring the environment seeking an explanation
as in the old shactor and singer experiments where they aroused the
people put them in a situation where things were
happy or sad going on and the people adopted the
the emotional tone of the the context because what you're in a
in a row situation you know cognitive dissonance why am i aroused why am i
feeling this kind of tension in my brain and body
and so you seek an explanation for that so arousal is very important but also
then there's the feedback from the body which is the key to
demosios theory i think that's one part of it but not the entire explanation
of where our feelings come from and then there's a fourth one right
show inhibitory tracks from the prefrontal cortex
down to the amygdala right okay uh well the
darsalato prefrontal cortex and the new reports
don't have any connectivity with the amygdala it's very very crucial point
right but it's the higher levels that do well that's pretty high
or yeah well prefrontal but darsalato prefrontal yeah no connection to the
mimic are there inhibitory tracks somewhere up there
back down to the mimic so darsalato and other prefrontal areas connected to
medial prefrontal areas which do in fact connect the amygdala so okay
yeah so the the you know the consequences of activating one of these
defensive survival circuits whether it's you know a threat circuit or a
feeding circuit or anything else uh is that changes take place widely in the
brain it creates a global organismic state within the
brain and body that the body and brain then have to
brain test a deal with now you know one of the reasons that
has moved me to this more cognitive view of fear
is and other emotions is the fact if we just stick with fear
you know we have to be able to not just account for fear as a defensive
survival response so we can be afraid of a snake at our feet
but we can also be afraid of starving to death and that would not be
part of the defensive survival circuit that would be a homeostatic mechanism
involving low energy supplies or dying of dehydration so we begin to worry
about that because our hypotherlamic fluid balance
circuits are out of culture or are freezing to death in the sense of
failure of thermal regulation so these are not traditional
threat circuits but yet their activity can cause us to be afraid
and we can even move beyond that to broader fear such as the fear of
anxiety of not leading a meaningful life or of the
eventuality of death an existential kind of threat
so a circuit you know if you say fear the amygdala is the brain's fear center is
as is often said you can't possibly get to an explanation of both
existential fear and the fear of a snake in one explanation
so it's there's only one way you can do that it's through a cortical processing
of all these various kinds of inputs fear is a
kind of construction or an assembly or an emergent property
of a lot of ingredients that happen below the surface
yeah now Joe you you have taken fear and applied it
to the fear of not leading a happy or satisfactory life
an analyst would say no that's anxiety actually
no that's I said fear or anxiety okay no my
I think that whole discussion about fear anxiety is not settled because I
still no matter how much I look into it I can't see what exactly
differentiates one from the other but that's another matter you were
going to say well right sorry I do I do wonder a little bit about these 10 to
which these are semantic issues and 20 center content
so for example it seems like it could be that when we talk about the fear of
not eating a meaningful life and the fear of getting hit by a train
that we're using the same word but in fact it's not it's going to turn out
that it's sort of a nervous to tell you in sense we haven't carved nature I
just joined properly in the natural language
and so my bias scientifically is always as a splitter as opposed to a
bumper and so it seems to me as that it could plausibly be that there's
lots of systems which if you kind of went down they kind of look like they're
doing more or less the same kind of thing keeping us from doing it so for
example you know getting us to eat when we're hungry or
worrying about the fact that we might not but that would all of a sudden done
when we're all done with our work whether we're talking about the cognitive
level or the neurophysiological level we're going to look at these things where
you see oh I actually turned out that those things were of a family and the
Eleanor Ross sense of family resemblance but they weren't exactly the same thing
right and so and so I have a fear that my microphone just dimmed
I agree with that and but the the point is that so the field has been so
narrowly focused on fear I'm saying let's consider all the options and
whittle back from there rather than you know kind of just being stuck in this
defensive mode where you know a snake is the canonical form of fear
when we know that people never encounter snakes in New York City and that they're
a lot of fearful and anxious people when you are so maybe including fearful about
snakes that they have never seen exactly well they're also human snakes
editing much more frightening so an analyst would say look if you want to
study brain physiology about human fear and anxiety you have to look at the
neurophysiology of meaning and probably that means you have to look at the
neurophysiology of representation
I'm not sure I completely agree with what you say because I think in some cases
you can put people in a state chemically that will make them experience anxiety
even if they have no reason to experience anxiety so if you flow your system for
example with thyroid hormones your blood pressure is going up your heart is
beating you have all these symptoms that are normally present when you
experience fear except there is no stimulus that would provoke fear and yes
you feel anxious you have the deep feeling of being anxious even if you
know there is no reason to be so so I think that there is no meaning there but
the body is still sending a signal and makes us interpret whatever the signal
is as inviting those people who have panic attacks say I feel like I'm going to
die
yes but but they have that's different because they have a
condition that makes them have panic attacks but I'm telling you is if you
do that to a perfectly you know normally if there is a person a healthy person
who is feeling well you give them this medicine and then suddenly they will have
this huge surge of anxiety and that I think is interesting because because
it also shows that things can just arise from body signals into the
absolutely fear-promised actoma but often either it's true free-floating
anxiety which is rare or the person even though they know it's physical
has a mental experience of it it has a representation to it
they can say or what does that feel like feels like I'm going to die
feels like I'm suffocating feels like I'm falling
no but what does that tell you what that tells you and it
means you could say anything wait a minute you could say anything at your
analyst yes you could say anything but what you do say
may be actually influenced by who you are right
and the question maybe so maybe what you heard
maybe you heard people who are panic attacks think they're dying so when you
have a panic I think I'm going to be dying they don't necessarily think
they're dying they say it feels like they're dying right but maybe you have
you know especially in this as you go on the internet it says people who are
panic attacks they think it feels like dying
it doesn't matter if they say it's another one would be like a lollipop
that's fine we're not talking about the content the specific content
but only that affect in human beings tends to have a content
and that if you want to understand the human experience
of affect you have to understand what Joe has already said
that there are links between cognition and affect and physiology
that the package deal in humans tends to be represented
in that package deal and they will express it we call that package deal in
human beings meaning the meaning of the affect
Prancing or psychiatrist and the neuroscientist what are you like
it's hard to say because I'm actually a neuroscientist I've actually it's much
easier for me to think about what I was actually thinking about as you were
saying this was actually about there's a certain group of patients that were
studied at the University of Iowa who basically had congenital lesions of
their amygdala you're familiar with these courses
and and that recently there was a paper that came out a couple years ago that
if they were given some type of carbon dioxide sort of
inhalation they actually felt for the first time a fearful response
we would or at least they had what looked like a physician's first time
so it wasn't there no that it was just showing that they could feel
they could have a physiological response too
but did you look for those people they still have
they still felt fear in some on other things like as you said
these are great subjects because they have thoughts that they probably have
fears that their life has no meaning or various other things
you know but I mean that's part of my argument against the idea that they
make the lives of fearsome exactly these people can have fear
without them a mingle walk exactly even though they don't they don't have the
physiological response of whatever if you put them in the laboratory and
shock them and put a yellow square in front of their face
you know and they won't freeze or have a physiological response to that
mingle is the key to the output yes those to the circumstances
that's a tremendous response but if you interview them they will actually say
right if i mean list felt actually um is it
my you showed this and with Adam Anderson i think in 2002
it didn't get as much attention as the the Iowa paper more recently but it's
the same the fact that you can have the amygdala is not involved in the
experience of these emotional responses i mean these emotional states but
only in the expression but i actually prefer to think of their mingle as a
relevance the factor as has been proposed by some people
because i think it's it's been it's present in a lot of tests that i do
for them if i just show neutral faces versus objects
faces are more relevant to us because the biological stimuli i get a mingle
activation even if there is no fear involved in those things
so i think it's it's we we need to broaden our view that we were talking
about fear so we talk about the amygdala but there's a dozen parts of the
amygdala take only the lateral nucleus of the
amygdala that we can divide into three parts
uh one that is involved in plasticity and learning another that's
involved in the transmission to other amygdala errors and so forth
so the circuitry is i mean in an imaging study
you can see you know positive and negative and all of that and in the
blob called the amygdala but when we get into the detail and that's why the
animal studies are important we can see the circuitry
cells that will respond to positive but not negative and so forth so at a
subtle level of micro wiring there are these
distinctions so you know what what it is is
you know we i think what we have to think about is
a circuit that is detecting threats by predators versus
circuits that are responding to positive incentives
versus circuits that are responding to uh
dehydration or changes in temperature all of those are going to
you know may overlap but they're also going to be criss-crossing
and you're not going to be able to pick that up through uh
through you know crude imaging technology
crude where it is today but you know i think the
i mean it's less crucial it's less crucial
the usual idea is that you can the ultimate resolution of the magnet will
be somewhere along with the idea of a cubic millimeter right?
yeah and having that is a very tricky part because you have all kind of things
around that that makes it difficult yeah like one of the early studies of
mark reichl's that implicate the amygdala turned out to be jaw muscle
never rather than the amygdala i believe i got to know you're
saying something so important which is the complexity even of the
amygdala right the complexity of the brain and how its
function is over determined and multi-determined
which is an analytic concept well they're based on froid
and it's a basic physiological fact about the human brain
and how it functions
i wanted to ask you something Joe you said that
people take the tranquilizers and it doesn't
take away their anxiety SSRI it's even more interested i didn't say
tranquilizer it's an anti-frantic look i said SSRI's
so what about when you take actual tranquilizer
anti-anxiety medication so okay i mean we get it now we get into the
details so there are receptors for benzodiazepines and
prefrontal areas as well as the amygdala all over the brain
so the question is two questions i guess one is
when a person is feeling less anxious on the benzodiazepine
is that because one the benzodiazepine has
specifically reduced anxiety or is there a more general
change of emotional processing and if it's
uh a second question would be is it because
you've changed emotional processing per se
or because you've changed the cognitive underpinnings
of that emotional processing by blunning activity you know
benzodiazepines or GABA agonists so they blunt
activity wherever they bind so if you blunt cognitive processes that are
involved in the assembly of higher thoughts or even
fears and anxieties and prefrontal cortex then you're going to feel less
fearful anxious but have you done that by directly
changing anxiety you might say okay as a
therapist it doesn't matter you know if it works it works that's great
but as a scientist you want to know why it's working
and is it doing what you say it does because that's what's led to
billions of dollars being spent trying to make animals less
timid in these behavioral situations to find drugs that can make people less
people less fearful or anxious you think prance is a bad
i still am amazed as a as a psychiatrist and as an
nurse scientist that we don't actually know where
where the site of or what circuit or what network is being affected by the
events of the as we've been giving them for decades
and you would think that we would there would have been a conditional receptor
knockout mouse that would have been done at some point
but for some reason that has not been because it was
I mean the pharmaceutical industry moves in the direction of
okay we've got this drug yes let's get the next one
with you know tweak to it they'll make more money right yeah
so they're not going to figure it out they're not going to figure it out
so scientists have to do that and but look at it you'll have a certain piece of
data for you I took once a benzo librarium for a
plane flight yes my brother met me he said to my
wife the plane landed at noon eric landed at one
well it wasn't only fear of us the fear it was a wow
a really good feeling well we're on the subject of ethics for
example giving people drugs we don't really know how they work for the last
decades and we used to give people aspirin
and on this note of social anxiety I don't often have the chance to talk to
people in the clinical world so I'm interested in this story for example
about the introvert who we medicate so that they go to parties which they
subsequently presumably are you know are very difficult for them
right because they're introverts so they actually don't really like
going to these sort of social events right and one way to read introversion
is that's Darwin's way of saying you know what you should maybe devote your
attention to the non-social stuff because whatever the social stuff is doing for
you it was really not working out so there might be other ways
should we should we be suppressing anxiety at the point where we get people
into situations which are subsequently going to be
unpleasant even if i may maladaptive for them
is this something that we do in the clinical community i i was not aware
other than yeah i was aware that we give people all the time medications which
we don't understand how they work that's cool with that it's called
being a doctor yeah
i know i've always i've always been impressed with my friends over the
medical community it's even if they go to they are to
empiricism we haven't even known to ask that question because it's all
seemed like one thing in the brain you know fear and anxiety like
fear center anxiety center happiness but there are some things that
are a touch more specific i don't know how they work
but people who have stage fright they respond to in the raves
i think that has not become uh solid as it used to be
and also what response does that mean the subsequent studies have not been
this clear and the question is what response to enduro
the tachycardia the sweating that response the tremor
that response to enduro they then have to say if they can
wow nobody can now see that i'm anxious and the anxiety may
in certain people fade because of that
or maybe because you don't get this body response you feel better because you
don't get those signals but that's the key
that's the previous understanding what you're saying that there's new
sort of doubt right that this is why i actually think that enduro does work
because did you take some deploy
no but if we have um if we condition rats in a certain way
that make them avoid situations um we find that there's a group
of about 20 that never acquire the response but if we inject
propanolol and enduro directly into their central amygdala which controls the
outputs to the freezing and all that the animals stop freezing
and start performing the response so they can now approach the threats and
and so forth so it has this in the traditional sense an anti-
anxiety effect in terms of behavior right but i wouldn't call that
anxiety we call that reduced uh defensive behavior reduced
behavioral inhibition um so the you could i mean that would be
consistent with the effects of enduro given to people
you give it to them and they're more willing to go
on stage and and perform so whether they i mean in and the the body feedback and
all of that that's suppressed would indirectly
make you feel less anxious even if the enduro itself is not directly
reducing your anxiety all right i wanted to get your opinion
what did you think of the recent study that came out
about giving instance we're talking about enduro where they did where they
were conditioning humans who had a spider phobia
too and then they sort of brought up they
did essentially a reconciliation type experiment
where they gave the enduro during that window did you actually
we were a window was this the uh Dutch study?
yes exactly i'm not going to comment on that
i mean that there's some issues i don't want to go
the experience in terms of experimental design
in general yeah okay
but a couple of drugs we don't know how they work and and why they work
have you seen this study that showed that paracetamol
which is something you'll take for pain actually
alleviate social pain in these games where you
you know give the ball to people and ignore them and so forth and i thought
i was also something that's interesting in terms of
circuitry is interacting and and responding because who would think of
paracetamol as a things i already think do they know how it works or
we don't know how i mean it's a cop's two inhibitor it's an interesting
but but it's nobody really completely understand how paracetamol works i think
yeah currently at Cornell we're doing a there's a clinical trial which we're
doing i'm a sort of a very small member of this
clinical trial but it essentially is looking at
people with post-traumatic stress disorder and this was a
an anti-tuberculous drug called desyclocirian it had gone by the trade
named ceramysin and it had previously been thought of
by serendipity to be actually opening up the the glutamate
and mda channel but what people have found is that it can be given a short
time periods as a cognitive enhancer and so what
what the trial we're doing is we're actually giving them
about 45 minutes or an hour before their cognitive behavioral exposure
treatment they get this drug and or a placebo
and then they do their exposure treatment so we're actually going to see
whether this works this has been all been very well
worked up by mike davis a researcher at Emory University
in rats but this is one that had been initially been worked by karaa wrestler
to decrease phobias of fear of heights but now we're going to do something
much more complicated in looking at something that is
even even though post-traumatic stress disorder is considered to be
something that has elements of fear and anxiety
it's so much more complicated than that and i think we're going to see whether
or not this at least helps the it's not the it's not
model therapy for the PTSD but it's actually going to be used in conjunction
with exposure therapy i think the and there's been a few meta
analysis recently that suggests the effects they're like
many things you get an effect in the first study right then the biggest
effect now it's uh start a fall start a fall
apart so that'd be interesting let's see what you
get on the meta analysis in the voted models or in the humans i know in
humans uh a lot of um stuff on hoffman and uh mike
mike lotto at the uh have done a lot of that
it seems that the things that don't work for
desyclic serine are things like snake phobias like if you
if you have a if you have some type of certain phobias are not as amenable
to this but again we don't actually know where this
works there have been some studies that suggested
effects both the amygdala it's whatever firing rates in both the amygdala and
also the prefrontal cortex i don't think it's been
as clearly mapped out unless i've missed some paper
yeah but that would go along with representation
right meaning the significance of yes that's according to a
prefrontal concept or i can still say that because i'm arguing against that
whole concept yeah so i'm just going to take a
moment and i have a new book out called anxious
uh little promotion in the in the book um one of the things i
propose is that you know that because the if in fact the
conscious experience of fear is distinct from these more basic
threat processing circuits um we might
profitably approach exposure therapy by directly attacking the amygdala
independent of conscious awareness by using subliminal
presentations of the cs of the the spider the snake or whatever
and reducing amygdala's response is outside of consciousness
then do conscious exposure therapy and then do
psychotherapy to help the person cope with the situation kind of a three-point
plan what do you think of that it's uh but look i think that's potentially
terrific and analyst would either after you're done or before
or instead of ask the question why is this person afraid of spiders
do they have a traumatic history with spiders many don't but what do spiders
mean to them if you will what is the what activates
the affect circuit what's the affect meaning
and then get the story of that so that the person themselves
in a certain other circuit cognitive more cognitive circuit
understand something about the symbolic representation spider
and may deal with the actual elements of what they are afraid of behind the
spider image that is crucial suggestion is a very very powerful tool so
you can change things by suggestion is the equivalent of placebo
so and i think it's always a very powerful thing you can see it in the
brain you're changing the terms of the discussion from is there meaning
to how do you know the meaning and does the meaning work i was addressing
only that there is a symbolic representation well
that's all but if you take anybody any student that comes and you
put them in a magnet and you show them subliminal images of snakes
you'll see they're all fear circuitry that lights up
it's has the meaning to them do you think
the snakes the fear of snake it's coming because of a meaning
or do you think it's just yeah don't you think that that people feel oh my god
the snake might bite me or get inside me or they don't know it's there
no you rapidly show it okay now we're talking about the analyst view of the
unconscious they don't know it's there yes that's right
the whole analytic theory of human mental function and neurodic pathology
is that there are aspects of meaning of it of which we're not aware
and all of the analytical literature on techniques it talks about how to make
that unconscious conscious maybe it's baloney maybe it doesn't work maybe it's
just placebo different question the idea however the analytic idea
is human meaning is there and maybe unconscious
sorry my point is not that I might show you show snakes to anybody
and anybody will have these reactions because of the meaning of snakes
so you mean that you think everybody has a problem with snakes because of their
history no no no no everybody's afraid of falling
but the falling is conceived of representationally
it's not just stimulus reflex that's all i'm saying but what i
understood this to be would be that joe was throwing out that there should be
a clinical trial where you do treatment as usual or to add on top of it
this type of subliminal
it's a normal reaction that's that's we evolved
of course representation of things that are dangerous for us
snakes spiders hides etc so i think that's that's a normal thing to have a
reaction to when it becomes a problem that interferes with your daily action
then it's a problem that you need to solve but but otherwise i think it's a
normal thing that we have it's like we see faces everywhere
we are we we can see objects that look like a face
and in 170 milliseconds you will activate the areas of your brain that
normally sees real faces because you treat
yes that's why that's all i'm saying that's all i'm saying that's the design
yeah you can and and that's why babies orient to faces after just a few
minutes of life because we have this sub-particle system
that orientes us two things that are important for evolution
and and i think that's something that doesn't need to have extra
you know meaning no i think we're saying the same thing
meaning is innate to human beings that's what i was saying i think you need to be
careful to put meaning to some of these things
i think you but the way you are saying it you are
putting meaning to everything but you don't need meaning
in other words the person who has the fear that the who goes under these
imagings and they all respond to snake fear
that don't have to the snakes don't have to have any other meaning for them there's
no unconscious meaning to it the only meaning is
that evolutionary we are going to have to guard ourselves
against snakes okay add your now reducing meaning to its minimalist
significance which is fine but now you want to take a step further and say it
has no meaning at all snake doesn't even mean snake
it's no no a snake okay so snake has a mean that's only because we have given it
the name excuse me it has meaning the name is given in a name
i mean in terms of meaning if if it has meaning
then you're really the same we have to protect ourselves
so i would just go back to one of the things you said to kind of
tie it into the things like the um you said the job of the amylist is to make
the unconscious conscious but if the meaning is wired in to
say the amygdala yeah there's no way to make that conscious
i mean there's the circuitry because the prefrontal cortex can't
look at the amygdala and see what it's doing you know there's certain things
that are unconscious but in this thing yeah certain things that are unconscious
because of wiring not because of repression oh no that's right
but there are actual fibers from the amygdala to the pre-chortex we
like i asked you about that right and their actual fibers back then again
no and so but right but not well okay i mean
one could inhibit one's and make all the responses we do it all the time yes
we're good at inhibiting yeah but less good at uh i'm sorry
every the other way the other way yeah i mean it's
um it's very well i mean the the asymmetry there is that it's very easy
for the arousal of these emotions whatever you want to call them to
uh affect our conscious experiences yeah but less easy for our conscious
experience to change our emotions as we all know that's why you are in business
right
you're thinking well no i would just add to that so i i mean again i feel like
this notion of meaning ironically enough can have to be a semantic issue so
uh it might be helpful for some of us to understand
what it would look like for something not to have meaning because the examples
that i think i'm accustomed to seem intelligible in this kind of
Darwinian context without needing any of them additional
but on this on this note about consciousness and so forth i think most of us
sort of take a view that um it's interesting i feel like all of the
discussion about the fear of dehydration has led to this moment right here
you know that one that i think that most people would agree that a signal
feature of the mind and this goes all the way back to the early work on
split brain patients and so on is that there's modularity that is there are
systems that are isolated from each other again not in virtue of a suppression
you know sort of uh but the fact is that you know there's lots of stuff going on
our heads and they just do the little things
behind the you know behind the veil and it's just fine that they do those sorts
of things and i i take it but that's why you get many of the effects that you do
and another way is just to bring this back to the very top of the conversation
which is you know if you sort of take that view
then the question of what consciousness is doing now maybe it's a narrator along
the lines of kazanagans and so on that's here to tell us stories
but that does bring me back to the point about rodents which is that if you
think that what's going on in terms of phenomenology and consciousness has to
do with telling stories in the social world
then critters that don't really talk to each other which is you know every
other species more or less roughly and these with natural language
they wouldn't need that and which so one one direction that does sort of
point you is it to make it makes you think a little bit about if phenomenology
has to do with the narrator then maybe it's something unique
which again would then go all the way back at the discussion of what the
animal research is telling us on this topic
yeah i mean i'm reluctant to say it's unique
because we don't know but i would say that if it
if animals have phenomenology it can't be anything like what we have with
language i mean as soon as we as soon as an experience
begins to develop we are labeling it and defining it and giving it meaning through
our words and our history and our experiences
so um you know we have 37 words in english for
variance of fear and anxiety and it must be that must be an
important kind of emotion for us because we have so many
words for it just like that many words for snout too right
and to go back to your um not understanding the difference between
fear and anxiety or not accepting it um i mean so
i think the the usual view i'll state stated as i know it
uh which is that fear is an emotion that you experience
when the threat is present or expected in imminent
whereas anxiety is a worry about something that hasn't yet happened and
may never happen right well i know i mean
once you start digging deeper into any of these
distinctions you find holes in them so where what are the holes
well if i uh i recently saw that uh the you can have people uh
subliminally do something and where they could cheat or not cheat
and subliminally effect their views about right or wrong and religion
and uh if you put in the ideas about religion
they are more liable not to cheat right now is that anxiety or is that fear
because what the idea is has to do with the notion of god
i was just neither god is watching either no so god is watching you
and god wants you to do the right thing so uh is that fear or is that anxiety
why but i mean are you saying only the religious people
when in that direction the people know when they introduced religious ideas
and the subliminally the people cheated less
because of the notion of right or wrong and the fear of god
than when they didn't so let me give you a change in the example
no but hey you're not going to know unless you ask the person
no you want that one made that we're back to the movie projector in the
movie yet no we're no no no if you if you think about fear
of anxiety you yourself i like when you think about it
that's the point when you when you speak about it
mental when you speak about it you're going to use in certain situations
the word fear when in fact with the definition that
joe gave you should be using anxiety necessarily
how to ask the person no that's not important okay
an analyst said ask the person how they experience that
some people experience god as a living presence
now i'm going to go back to the experiment not
what we are recruiting to so let's go back to the experiment so i can give you
a very similar experiment that has nothing to do with god
um john barge who's uh used to be at NYU now at yale
that studies at NYU where he brought in
participants in the study and had them unscramble
um the blocks of war you know had the reassembled words
and sentences from blocks and so there were two kinds of
sentences that were scrambled like this one kind had to do with uh
you know sentences about old age and another kind had to do with
just random things nothing about old age and the these were all undergraduate
students and so the students who unscramble sentences about
old age took longer to walk down the hall afterwards
just as a sign i would call that fear inside it's
it's activating in non-conscious but that's an uncomfortable
good let's finish let me just finish with that so the
you know you had in your study they were responding to they were
being jic what would they extemulate in
i don't remember the details i tried this some time ago but it had to do with
when they were when they subliminally introduced ideas
religious right ideas then the cheating was less so we have these
non-conscious schema that are kind of sitting there where they would classify
information that comes in for and reaches consciousness so you can
activate these schema with probes or primes like religion
old age blah blah blah and then that becomes part of your conscious thought
process because you've been primed to do this the classic priming thing which
happens unconsciously that leads into the consciousness i don't think it has to
do with fear joe's talking about unconscious schemas which we call
representation he's got a much more complicated you with the mind than you
do right now no that's not that that doesn't solve the
the problem of the distinction between fear of anxiety
but that was a sidetrack that's a good representation
nobody's saying that's not the issue right it's more complicated than that
that's not not i don't know what you mean by more complicated
what i'm saying is there are many definitions and many attempts at
distinguishing fear and anxiety and i don't find
that there are any of them that are foolproof because you're looking at the
definition when you were talking about it before you set fear and anxiety
because if it were possible to make as clear a
distinction as between fear and something else
we wouldn't have this discussion so obviously a fuzzy there is something
fuzzy about that distinction it's not important in psychoanalysis but it's
not a question of definition you won't find the answers in words and in
epistemology you have to find the answer in the mental experience
and joe has shown in the brain of course you have to find it okay so you can't
argue that any definition has holes in it because that's not the point of course
any definition of anything that's it's the mental experience and it's neurophysiology
you're totally misunderstanding because we work backwards from the concept
talking about definitions and that way work backwards from where you are
happening what about fear of being in the putes and
anxiety being more chronic that's one of the other
that's the same thing that we're talking about that fear is a response to an
immediately present seems anxiety is a worry about the future but suppose we
start with worry and say that the threats that we worry about
are anxiety but when the threat is present it's fear
no so let's say you are sitting alone at home yeah
and you suddenly start thinking what if i'm alone
and somebody breaks in yeah that's anxiety and then you go and you check
the door double make sure it's double locked and so on
is that fear or exactly sorry so for you the temporal element is
is free so i so on this kind of view i can't
fear that something is about to happen me i can be anxious about it
if it's imminent so if you see for example a rat in a box
well let's forget rats so to say that you every time you
touch this bottle you get an electric shock so
even though you're not touching it you know you're going to get shocked
so you're you know you would say that you're afraid because it's there
um whereas anxiety would be you're the next time you come here you're worried
that there might be a bottle that will shock you if you come in
can't we just settle this by fiat right so we're scientists right don't we get
to decide what words mean yeah well i think
the problem with that is that we get when we do that i mean that's what my
field did a long time ago it decided fear was a
non-conscious or non-subjective state motivational
physiological state that connects threatening events with responses
um but they called it fear and they use it to try and help people
feel less fearful or anxious and explain fear and anxiety in people
so when as soon as you do that you're out of the non-subjective and into the
subjective and nobody makes a difference so
people will go to society for neuroscience as a thousand posters on
freezing rats and talking about curing anxiety
in people right so i think we have to be very careful when we redefine things
scientifically when we take common language words and redefine them
scientifically because our cell we open ourselves in the trouble when we're
talking about things that every day people experience
and let me ask you my terms then so again as a as a Darwinian guy
my guess is that where you're really ultimately going to be pointing to our
systems that have different functions so one function might be you know what
i need to incubate about something that might happen because that's going to
help me down the road so i think you all agree that a certain amount of
anxiety isn't such a bad idea because it
potentiates planning for those virtualities are supposed threats
so one kind of a system would be a a forward-looking system that maybe
simulate something which might be threatening another one is
a system that's designed to take appropriate evasive action
given what has happened in the past and that of course fits with some of the
learning stuff right so so if we start to carve the
world in terms of functions instead of by fiat do you feel like that might get
us in a productive direction would that satisfy your friends at the
site? Well that is anxiety is a byproduct of the
fact that we have a brand that can imagine the future
and so you don't think it's you see a byproduct so in my
world this is what I've got semantics on my world that means you think it doesn't
have a function that it's sort of non-functional
it doesn't have a function what does it exist i mean
but the reason it's not there in virtue of the fact that it did some particular
job that I'm saying anxiety i think it's really
good
i mean i find that remarkably unlikely but you know well so you know your
ability to imagine how to build a building is not that
different from your building ability to imagine
that that building is going to fall down on you
mm-hmm well maybe it is maybe it isn't uh
i mean it seems to me uh we could have we could have the ability for this kind
of planning with respect to building in terms of
that could be an artifact manipulation system like that's working memory
allows me to think hey what if i strongly bow this way
um whereas but i mean it could be a different system although it makes use
of some of the same components where i think about what are all the things
that might go wrong that maybe i should plan for so for example maybe i should
make my building with stuff that makes the most dangerous or
unlikely that whatever um so it seems like certain kinds of anxiety seems to
me uh like you wouldn't want to suppress all kind of anxiety so
Randy Nessey who's the only psychiatrist i sort of know lives in my world and he
has this example where you know if you're a mouse and you have
any if you get anxious every time you smell you know feline urine
then so you scurry away that's kind of a good that's kind of a good thing i would
want to say i'm not anxious the math so he's not anxious at all
we should see but he's certainly one one of these
having a threat response right yeah yeah yeah i mean how would you distinguish
his behavior from the subjective state i mean the only way we can do that in
people is to ask them but yeah but yeah people can
lie they can but you know at least we and they can in fact your
work shows they can be wrong right so all this but framework that's not the
point the point is that in humans we're all operating with the same
kind of brain but when we go to another animal they're operating with a
different kind of brain and the way the human brain is different
isn't exactly the circuits and so forth that
allow us to experience our world they put a different way if you could
get eliminate everybody's anxiety about everything
would you do that no well absolutely not anxiety is
you know it again it allows us to anticipate the future which can be
very useful to us in many ways and that's the value of anxiety because
it allows us to uh try to charge the brain up a bit
and work on the future in a way that makes it
important rather than just oh something is going to happen in the future
yeah that's i mean that's sort of what i think too but i would say that that's
why we have in the first place now you and i can disagree about how it's
about but it's just saying that how it came about may be a spandrel
maybe so that you have the capacity to imagine the future
and when that is associated with brain arousal and other things like that
that becomes worry and what about pathology then so if it's true that
the system by and large is a pretty good job can't we can we think about
cases of pathology of social anxiety fear pights and
spiders so for example all these things you should sort of have some of that
i mean you can hear New York City right you know to be against what the
snakes do you don't want to have something that will
actually make you stay in your apartment yeah right so that's
me that's getting us so there's like a setting that gets slightly altered right
well maybe again maybe should stay near where i mean i'm not in your cities
oh i just ran into it i just ran into red small corner here
um so it seems like the pathology then is do something that's
useful but to set to kind of a higher to low level okay
yeah yeah but it was but psychiatrists are very simple-minded people so all we
know we if they don't leave the apartment we know something's wrong if they can't
go to a job we know something so it's a very simple bar of if it's gone to the
level where you can no longer function in society or it's significantly
limit your ability that's something that it does not
simply be giving you any evolutionary advantage
and that's when you try to give some medication it was my
kind of a of action we don't understand to that person
so are you saying to have anxiety as opposed to fear
you have to have cognitive function or you are saying it's true of both
i think cognitive functions are required for both exactly
but of a threat is the matter whether the threat is present or worried about
in the future but a response to a threat does not
require that no exactly just my opinion so that in essence
what your work is saying is that you can still
respond and protect yourself without having the cognitive component of it
exactly and that the 50 years of work done in
roaded models in particular have been studying that type of threat
defense of research and that's important because it's part of
it you know if this is correct we need to treat
different systems in the brain differently we have to have to have
road psychiatry from the point of view the way the brain is wired
and so it's important to have drugs that will change behavioral
inhibition i mean behavioral inhibition is often
equated with things i and i think that's you know part of the problem we use
these words and the semantics of it gets kind of lost in space and
to confuse things by using the same words for different things
but you're in what you're getting back to what you were saying in the future
if you could develop either a behavioral probe or some
magical nanoparticle that would just go straight to
getting to the threat and tamp down a person who is psychiatric patient who
had an overactive threat response system then you might then it will allow
that person to actually go to into psychotherapy for example and then
work on the yeah but that probe would probably affect the same circuit she
was asking about they're involved in positive responses to signal
yes exactly but through behavioral interactions with
the patient like through exposure specific stimuli you could be more
specific i think that you know that psychiatry has much more to gain
through behavioral than pharmaceutical approaches it's
sort of stunning that our pharmaceutical agents have worked at all
yes yeah we've given us with serotonin reuptaken hip
which are that essentially blocks all serotonin
reuptaken the entire body there's some studies that show that it doesn't
actually work yeah close to placebo yeah well
actually as my and my colleagues he's a he's also a psychiatrist but also a
neuroscientist at Stanford he goes psychiatrists have
used the placebo effect to maximal benefit whenever we give it
the great thing it doesn't if it doesn't have side effect like most of these drugs
have i mean i thought i have people be cured with you know sugar pills
as a placebo then with these things that have all these
personal side effects exactly exactly there's some of these really that do
work though right like maybe no i think
well my colleagues i conceptualize is that 30 years ago 40 years ago when they
were first introduced the people who had the most
severe untreated depression these probably did these were you got huge
effect sizes and then what you notice is that the effect size is kept on getting
smaller but so that there is some subset of the depression syndrome at least
that that responds to these but then we don't have those patients anymore because
they're all on these drugs so that's true
everybody's on drugs i last one more thing before we go to the
audience eric had mentioned panic attacks before
so panic attacks are attacks that have to do with anxiety or with fear
well so you know there's a specific stimulus like an
inter-aceptive stimulus stretching in the chest or
chest pain so you would say that that's a stimulus that
is probably then making you anxious and then that's causing a feed forward
loop that's if they don't always exist that that what you just said is
involved in that case and i mean that you know that the
truth is that let's just accept that for the purpose of this
except what i had described is fear and anxiety
but as soon as you're afraid it more thinned anxiety right so
this is snake at your feet so you have first your your fear of the snake but
immediately you begin to worry about is its poisonous will it bite me
can i get to the hospital will they have the antidote if i die will my family be
okay on and on so that's where i draw the distinction
the snake is there you have that rapid autonomic nervous system response
and then you kick into worry and that takes you forward
it will be very hard to make that distinction in
in to to somebody who has the snake immediately their thoughts goes those
ways right so it's inevitable in a way in those situations for one and the
other to coexist but you could also start with a
you know with anxiety and that you know perhaps could
how could more fit to feel that could more interfere
sure and so somebody who's anxious of crossing a bridge you take their hand
and you go towards the bridge they start getting pretty afraid
but next thing to know they leave your hand and run the other way
Ed also gave an example where anxiety morphs into fear maybe
did i lock the door not then the person gets up to check whether they lock the
door not
i don't want to go up at the event but something i've done very interesting
you talk about the pharmaceutical approaches and you talk about
maybe more of the kind of homological approaches are experiential
when you talk about drugs like all those visions don't seem to combine both of
those properties throughout biologicals and they're
seemingly very intense and experiential
um does this interest any of you or um how that's
it's how these drugs both combine these experiences and yet
they're not steady as often as you think it's a lot of work now on the
one yeah yeah who is new to us and it's due that came out in the last two weeks
yeah yeah well yeah what about the whole brain
connectivity under LSD but as a therapeutic tool to a lot of
yeah stuff it's happening i don't know it mentioned LSD
i did
you recommended it and also um there is a
one a decade ago we would not be having this conversation but that
now one of the most important or most highly studied drugs for depression
is ketamine because it is and that in order and the idea
for the way ketamine works is that there is the belief that you have to
actually have this sort of dissociative experience
in order for it to be effective so this pharmaceutical industry have made
ketamine like drugs that don't have this dissociative experience
which have fewer side effect profiles and now them work as well
there's something that they think is magical about
there's some big news on ketamine this week that just came out and you study
showing that its effects are due to some metabolic
so the glutamate so the metabolites of ketamine that was actually
yeah and the idea that the main target for ketamine had always been thought of
one glutamate receptor subtype called the NMDA receptor and now they think it's
the other subtype called the AMPA so the metabolite might be the active
version of it but you know but these are all grad studies
we know one has yet there are the human studies are
ongoing right now so it's not clear whether or not
that causes the metabolite might not cause a dissociative effect
that's the key actually I um there's this
there was a studies going on about NYU and Johns Hopkins and at least
I read about it last spring on psilocybin where
and I don't know if you're familiar with that but with people who are
in people with cancer who are dying and have
death anxiety they've been taking they've been taken on psilocybin
trips and the images that they've been encountering
help eliminate the anxiety and apparently the anxiety after six months is still
not there so I don't know if you're familiar with that study but it just
goes to the other questioner thank you
so first of all I just want to say mr. Lidue you got a little Matthew McConaughey
in your voice
I'm from Louisiana I think that's what
Texas is saying
so did you talk about the you know the circle thing
the thing that I have a question about is and maybe this isn't the appropriate
way to ask it and maybe it's a simplistic way to view the mind
but my question is whether or not minds that are considered creative or
logical have different effects in the feeling of anxiety and fear
for example somebody who might be considered more creative
a creative thinker having more experience of anxiety
than fear in a logical thinker because of the
eminent threat right going on the definition of time
having the effects right in front of them so I just I just be or the the
threat right in front of them so I'm just curious
about your perspective on the kind of the the duality of the brain in that
sense and its effects on fear and anxiety
I may say conceptually it seems right that the person who is more creative
and more imaginative and you know doing all these kind of
anticipatory things are separated the other not necessarily out there in the
present world would perhaps be more prone to anxiety
I don't know if that's actually the case
okay is that is that would you I mean is that
a good way to look at it or do you think it's flawed in in that sense I mean is
it flawed to to think with this topic right or
and left brain or logical I think that's right right left brain
I mean that you know the the brain right and left comes from primarily from
what the split brain work and there you have left and right for sure but the
in the normal brain everything is connected and
crossing and integrated and so while it's not
appropriate to think about our hemispheres controlling different aspects of
personality this that doesn't mean that we don't
some people want more logical and others more spatial and imaginative or so
forth in their personality traits it's just not perhaps not
separated so neatly in terms of the brain but maybe the way you can think
about it is that if an anxious person manages to help their anxiety by
being creative that's a good way to deal with it
and constructive way to transform the anxiety into a positive thing
didn't got a nigga didn't got a nigga feel there were things from the right
brain and from the left brain in non separated laws
we have to grow up and separate from our parents
isn't language still a little bit
language not a lot of language has he changed has he changed his position
he's not so left right I mean he's still you know he's got a little bit of
connection to that but he's not as strong as you will
I mean some functions are more left or more right I think face perception is
more in the right having sphere language for in the left but doesn't mean
but because the causal connection are so huge and efficient and everything
it's there is never anything that only happens in the one side and stays there
hi thanks a lot for this talk it's been really educated
the the the the discussion that you guys were having about
fear and anxiety that's been going on in the literature for a long time
I you know and I know that you've been talking a lot about clarifying terminology
I wonder if it wouldn't be better to talk about this rather as a stress
response system and to look at it temporarily because of the fact that
we're really what we're talking about is you know the urgency of response
and what level of the nervous system is going to trigger that response so
if you're in a dark alley and somebody touches you in the back
there is going to be an immediate response and the representation that's
going to be this there is going to be a very low level reflex
and then the next level would be perhaps at the habit system if you're
a karate guy you know and you have developed these skills over the years
then you would have more sophisticated representation of your response
to that situation and then you know if you're watching a movie of somebody being
robbed then you're you're able to access a higher level of representation
and abstraction and you might ask whether he had a good relationship with his mother
you know that he's you know robbing things. I think the analysis you
described is dead on but I wouldn't call it a stress system because that's a
whole other part of you know my pile of baggage and well I
I'm sure that people have more sophisticated or
very specific way of talking about stress but when you're talking about like the
amygdala and stuff like that you know so much literature has been devoted to
you know the fear response and things like that but the amygdala is also
has positive valence as well as negative valence
and when you connect the amygdala with and the extended amygdala with the
the peri-actyl-so-gray and the hippocampus
then you're you've got a system that is
addressing different stimuli and classifying that and evaluating
and and then creating responses according to those schemes. Right my
solution to that is to talk about defensive survival circuits. Survival
circuits one of which is defense others are
dealing with other kinds of biologically significant activities so
but I think you know we're on the same page
all right my question
thank you yes would you mention the typical examples of
spiders and snakes in eliciting fear and or anxiety
and wouldn't possibly be an altering factor be
an expertise and knowledge and be able to differentiate which ones are lethal
and which ones aren't lethal affect your reaction to it because only a small
percentage of snakes are in fact you know venomous
and and and those are aren't that are dangerous
you know maybe the large constrictors and spiders all of them technically have
venom but only if you are potent enough to
affect us and then I know if it's out by now if I saw a
black widow spider or brown recluse from the pattern I would know
you know that there were bad news when it's ranchola if it bit me I'd probably
experience something like a beast thing rather than that
but so I'm spider I don't think I wouldn't think twice about it
so I guess that he was with that could that alter someone's response or
you know I mean that the as you guys can say better than me but
the phobias are not sensitive to information and logic
so there's no amount of reasoning so this is not dangerous and this is is going
to change the response to the snake and he says I understand right I was
saying it's medically encoded like in never doubles that you're going to be
panic if you see something in a broader classification even though it's not
venom even though it's not dangerous it's a better to react
too many times than to miss one time so so it's very to react to a known venomous
snake than then thing oh yeah well maybe not and you know so
so we are we are primed to have quick reactions to
things of a category that are potentially I just don't want to squander it on
those are like the reserve it for those things they could actually
harm me yeah and that way not waste that way
anxiety on something that's uh the time but we we talking about things that
are happening in in less than a hundred milliseconds you don't have time to do
all these you know thinking analysis that you have a cross
on it or not the thing of knowledge is accumulate over a period time that you
could recognize instantly uh in less than a hundred milliseconds
yeah it's also not that simple because there's lots of
mimicry among poisonous critters in nature right so
apismatic coloring right so that just means that
if i'm a non-poisonous snake and there's a poisonous snake that kind
looks like me selection is going to favor me looking even more like the
poisonous guy because the benefits i get from other critters being afraid of
me so it's actually so there's two things one is
there's a problem of maximizing expected value which means false you know
you do a lot of false positives and try to avoid misses
but the other one is mimicry really undermines these systems and they move
faster than uh we probably do in terms of the
selective history it's a problem but he does have a point
about education helping with fear and that's basic to human learning
um i have a question which may be a slight detour um but uh
um speaking as a layperson and particularly a layperson in terms of the
way in which most of the question is being addressed in terms of remedy
um cause and remedy and um so my question is really about
fear as not what happens to create fear but what happens
when we have fear and is so various questions related questions
about that what is that what's it doing what does it do is it bad
when is it good can it be used what happens when conflicting fears
come together what does that feel like and what does that makers do
and um also thinking about uh this is uh i had a
sidetracked to the sidetracked um talking about fear is temporal
i'm thinking we can imagine the present too we can be in a present situation
and obviously we don't necessarily know everything about situation that we're
in and it may be an ongoing situation or situation that's not like
a appearance of snakes can be something that goes on for
half an hour or an a half whatever um and so
what's our imagination about a situation that we're actually in
which is not necessarily a bad thing um and i'm not again not talking about
necessarily the remedial
speechless
i think probably we agree with what you're saying that there's a complex series
uh that one can't substitute for another we got into that discussion
about the snake automatically triggering the neurophysiology very rapidly of
fear but whether that is fear or what we mean by fear and the higher
cortical representation of that uh which doesn't mean that that doesn't
happen uh and it doesn't always mean that that happens
they're actually related but different and so when you're describing different
categories of complexity essentially i think most of us
sitting here would say right on but i think maybe the essence of my
question is about whether fear can be good and what we can do for example
about going inside fear rather than necessarily
going to the solution of getting rid of it yes i think i think
all of us would agree from the adaptive to the psychoanalytic
right i mean from an evolutionary perspective i mean yeah i mean if you
imagine what it would be like for our ancestors who felt no fear they were
not our ancestors because they're dead they got
they got bitten by snakes they got the snake or they were sticking their
hand in the fire whatever they were doing if they work out so well so
there's no doubt uh at least not in my mind um that fear is a very functional
part of the architecture we need our fear yeah right um
and not just that but it's got to be complicated because there's lots of
things that are threatening to people uh there's pathogens and there's other
people and there's big cats and uh you know where we're at evolutionary time
there were lots of ways that you could come to an end i mean we're really
complicated the thing about complicated things is
if you just perturbed them a little bit they become damaged and no longer able to
work right so to keep us healthy you got to do all this
cool stuff but to disable it's all i need is a little ice
peck and i'm done i mean it's really simple to disorder
very and you know complicated systems so fear is basically the way to say look
here's a thing in the world that could damage me could harm my fitness
interests and then motivate me to take appropriate action
now for some reason we have phenomenology associated with that
maybe we don't need that but at least insofar as the
reactions to the stimuli those are definitely good for us and
yes if you were insufficiently afraid then you would be in in big trouble
and the other way too right so some of the clinical friends can tell us about
the dangers of being too afraid of the world so that you stay in your
apartment which here i'm understanding i was very small
which is a great reason for everyone to move to Philadelphia anyway
um so so sure and then if you're asking about the
phenomenology i mean i i think that's a hard question
why does it feel like something to be afraid i i think you could ask that of
why does it feel like something to be anything
and that's that's hard i think you know some of the things that we've heard
here especially joe and others work has spoken
that a little bit no okay i'm still uh here in the
remedial even inside the embracing of the fear but
okay thank
hi thanks for letting us listen in um i have a question that i i hope kind of
ties things together because it has a couple of components and
things that have come up and one of them is um let's say last night i had a dream
of falling and one of the things that we talked about
was mice and one of the things we talked about was humans
but we didn't really talk about the in between very much in terms of the
complexity of brains and processes that can happen
my understanding or at least i think that there's some question that that
dream of falling comes from great ancestors back in the day
and to me that would seem like something that's anxious
and so i wonder about anxiety and fear and primates and things that are more
advanced though they don't have a clear language
but they have some form of communication how much information has been garnered
from that kind of study well because we can't ask them we
have to just go on their behavior and so when we're
looking at behavior if depending on how close we want to stick to the data we
can describe it in terms of their threat responses or the responses to danger
and uh leave it at that or we can speculate about things that we can't
prove which would be to say that there's a state of fear that
intervenes between processing of the threat
and the control of the responses so at this point it's a matter of
where what your comfort level with is and what your approach to the science of
it is whether you want to put that subjective experience in the middle
of the responses when we know from human studies that
you don't need that experience in order to get some of these responses
the dream of falling comes into the dream i mean it's like a very
cognitively up there sort of thing and so to me
i do think that that's something that you know animals i mean i watch my
pet's dream and they twitch and whine and i imagine they have anxiety
when that happens and fear i just it's so i don't want to try to
separate it so i go home every day i pet my cat and he
hers and i think he's feeling good and so we're good together and that's fun
but when i'm in the lab i can't allow myself that kind of
supposition so you can feel whatever you want about
the interesting thing about animal dreams is you know that these studies
where they would cut the thing that's when you dream you're paralyzed
when you and and you can but but if you cut that and you let the motor
system work in cats you can see that their cats is rehearsing everything
that makes a cat a cat i mean they attack the he's
the they've made they have all these dreams that that
sort of reinforce all the circuitry that that is important for their
species so i think that's animals do dream it but i think it's rehearsal
of of of things that happen in the day
is that also true of humans i don't think and the IRB has approved that
experiment but wait there's a separate question
the question is do you think that that one function of human dream name i
very well be to practice the sort of things that we as humans yes if you
ask people what they dream about that's a significant proportion
mark here we get your influence
as you say we can't make the same cut in humans
severing locus through lius from
motor neurons there is a naturally occurring condition
rim behavior disorder which is due to a degenerative process in the
midbrain which is sort of roughly the same area
and so we do have humans who act out their dreams
and the interesting thing is if you go with your statement that what the cats
do is everything that makes them a cat
what humans do is mostly aggressive
very very aggressive but to the point that it is
quite dangerous to your sleeping partner if you have rim behavior disorder
it's better if you're single than maybe it makes you aggressive to have
rim behavior disorders or maybe we come from an evolutionary history that
turn on a lot of aggression among our species
oh there's more questions i didn't realize
yeah um i think we've pretty much resolved the issue that
anxiety is a necessary part of human mental experience and we would be in
bad shape if we didn't have it um one thing that also is specifically
human is super ego anxiety so i'm wondering if there's been
any attempt to study what circuitry might be involved when some kind of
stimulus that stimulates super ego anxiety
supposed to just something like a snake can you describe what that would be
yes what Ed said about the religion being
you know religion and then you don't write it was Ed's question that actually
got me thinking about this whether there would be some way to
elicit that kind of response by showing a stimulus that has to do with
something that would arouse a super ego response like seeing something like
torture right um i'm just wondering if there's been
any study of pathways that would be so specifically human
that would have to do with anxiety um i don't know anything but it could
be there the only thing that i know that's getting
slightly close to that is an experiment that we've done and it's not published
but we had uh mip student taken oath and then
have an experiment do an experiment where they could cheat or not
and they would make money and those who were
under oath and it was not to a god or anything it was to the to their
university and uh first they cheated less and when they were losing money
because they were telling the truth the whole actually reward system was
going up so it was rewarding to lose lose because you were under oath and
your heads were not to cheat so that's the thing that can get
that that's a good thing about some humans
well you folks succeeded in arousing quite a number of thoughts and
questions in my mind but let me start with
thought experiment can you imagine that you are
new and that you are migrating in the searingeti in africa
and suddenly you look around and you see many other news are running like crazy
so you you're joined and run now uh you have not been
not been frightened by a snake uh you have not been told
something as dangerous as no communication nobody has said anything
so uh and another matter about it is that these
news although they may be uh especially if they're old and wounded
uh they may be susceptible to being attacked by lions or other
things but they have probably survived many more generations because they
don't live as long as humans but quite a long time
without speech and without fear and without anxiety or at least if they
have it that we don't know about and as a matter of fact there are other
species which have been around much longer than that
like turtles turtles have been around for a long long time
so the question of what is the use of consciousness and fear and anxiety and
all the attempts we make to make distinctions
uh what what good is it that's uh that's one thing
uh second the second point is about uh the placebo effect
now uh what do we know about the placebo effect
uh when i was a fellow and after my psychiatrist residency
i worked with the with more riser it was a period when
uh psychosomatics was changing from being explained by Freudian concepts
like an ulcer is what happens when you incorporate your mother
and she's biting in the stomach and it changed to
what are the physiological accomodiments of
hypertension and so on and we did a little funky experiment
uh which uh was that we we just got some
subjects and we put them on a couch and we had them look at a light
that flashed a subliminal flat just so that you know that there was
flashed there was nothing in it other people were trying to
describe how uh let's say a rebus uh in in such a thing could
stimulate thoughts fantasies and so forth we just asked these people
to close their eyes after they hadn't seen this light
and let's let something come to mind so picture come to mind
then they could draw it and then they could tell give it a title
and we came to a conclusion which is not so
remarkable that the main effect of the experiment had to do with how they
conceived of it and what their relationship was
to the experimenter and some people well the activation
uh was i think kept me out of the army and that at the time of the
Vietnamese war because i think that the CIA this had something to do with
a lie detector test because we we used skin resistance among other
things and you could chart this and then you could compare
with what they imaged and what they drew and one very impressive person
at least i was very impressed drew a picture of Don Drysdale throwing a ball
and it was coming right to him and this was going boom boom boom
boom and then after after a few minutes
everything calmed down and when we asked if he could remember what he
what he had done that was left out he forgot he was a sort of a
went into a doves after we were very curious about this
but we couldn't get refunded so i gave up
the thing but uh you know that this is that there is a negative
aspect of placebo effect also and uh it's also
it's been very very interesting to me that people say
that we have to compensate for the for the placebo effect because
it may give a beneficial result when the drug isn't doing it and so on so
forth but it also depends on how the experiment is set up i would
think and how the person responds to it whether it's positive or negative
and it's very important of course and but it also goes back to the other
point about the the new the ganoo's uh there is so much
communication between animals and between humans
which is not on a verbal level but which has
obviously got complicated content and communications
uh and how we can really learn by just depending on the words what the
report is of something now the last week or a week before i had a
tia and i was sitting in a meeting with some other
some colleagues and psych psychoanalysts from france
and i was uh having a happy conversation with one of these people when it
came about that i couldn't talk i couldn't make words i couldn't think of
how to speak and i just had to sit there
uh but i'm and i must but i must tell you if you asked me how that felt was i
fearful was i i wasn't fearful and i was an anxious
after it went away and i started going to doctors
and they were going through all kinds of possible diagnoses and this and that
they're like not anxious okay uh in retrospect
i knew that it was uh you know somehow hazardous
but i mean all of this is uh churning around in my mind that i thank you
for it maybe i'll do something thank you
last question so um also want to add my voice to come
but in a lot of these i've been a lot of these sessions this was one of the
best i've ever been to this was i think a really really terrific
discussion and i i treat PTSD for a living so
um nevertheless i found that you were able to
uh manage to interest me as well as people who were
in all different levels there were two just two very simple clinical
observations i i don't feel comfortable
uh leading this discussion without making the point that the
it's very common right now to talk about the placebo effective SSRIs
and i have to completely agree with friends as both from my clinical
experience with about 10 000 severely depressed in patients over a course
of a lifetime and my own recurrent severe depressions
that SSRIs are incredibly effective when that and it's really dangerous
um if we don't make that clear to people on the outside
um that what's happened is diagnostic creep so that there are a lot of people
who are on SSRIs who maybe it wouldn't be but for severe depression
i don't think there's i've just seen it too many times seen it with other
peace people and in myself it's a light switch and it makes a huge
difference life saving difference and i think
within the scientific discourse about about that we have to be clear because
there's already too much resistance to taking medication when people with
severe depression point one um so uh second point point point is
that in treating lots and lots of PTSD patients i found that one of the most
i do exposure therapy and things but one of the most effective things
that i've done is that it just sort of stumbled on this is at the beginning of
the whole treatment process i will say to the patient and usually these have
been non-sophisticated uh psychologically non-sophisticated
people cops firemen metal workers other 9-11 exposed people will say you know
the issue here is that um your life your feelings and your behavior are run by
a committee inside of your head and you are not invited to committee
meetings and the goal of this is to get you invited to give many meetings
it's a very simple metaphor but it's the metaphor about the non unity of mind
which i think we have such an evolutionarily powerful drive to have a sense of
unity of mind um that when you tell this to people it's an
incredible sense of relief and an incredible new model for them thank you
bravo