I guess.
I'd like to talk once.
I'm sorry?
You've been lunch with me?
Yeah.
And then it's my app to make sure that it's going out to me.
What is it?
I see.
So, you just had a quick walk.
Oh, that's not so heavy.
Well, we went into the kitchen with drivesome.
So, no one did?
Well, I was in the kitchencle.
It was kind of news because we run into their
vehicle.
She said we're going to take drugs.
So, you're going to come at the doors?
Yeah.
Okay.
Welcome. Welcome the Hillock Center. My name is Gerald Hurrowitz. I'm the associate director
of Hillock's, Ed Nurse-Sesian. Can people hear me? Okay. No? Okay. I'll speak louder,
but I will get a little bit more amplification. So my name is Gerald Hurrowitz. I'm the associate
director of Hillock Center. Ed Nurse-Sesian, our executive director, is out today. Unfortunately
for him because we have a wonderful program and I think that's reflected in this wonderful
turnout we have here today. So welcome everybody. Before we get started, I want to mention
our two of our upcoming panels, the Round Tables. On March 14th, we're having a round table
on the many minds of memory. And then on April 18th, the topic will be ethics and AI, artificial
intelligence and ethics. So let me do a brief introduction to our panelists today. The discussion
today is based on Joseph Lidoux's new book on the emotional brain. And let me just say
a few words about Joseph and we'll go through the rest of the panelists. So Joseph Lidoux
is the Henry and Lucy Moses professor of science at NYU in the Center for Neural Science. He
also directs the Emotional Brain Institute located at the Nathan Klein Institute at NYU
and is professor in the Department of Psychiatry and Department of Child and Analysis and Psychiatry
at NYU Langone Medical School. His work is focused on the brain mechanisms of memory and
emotion. Lidoux is the author of the Emotional Brain, which is the basis of our talk today.
The Synaptic Self and Anxious. The latter received the American Psychological Association
William James Book Award. Lidoux is also written about the brain for the New York Times and
Huffington Post. He's received a number of awards, including the Carl Spencer Lashley
Award from the American Philosophical Society, the Frisbee International Prize in Cognitive
Science. Gene Jean-Louis-Singeré Prize of the Ipsen Foundation, the Santiago Grisolia
Prize, the American Psychological Association Distinguished Scientific Contributions Award
and that's enough. No, and the list really goes on and it's quite wonderful and impressive
at the same time. His most recent book is The Deep History of Ourselves, The Four Billion
Years Story of How We Got Conscious Brains and that's the title of our talk today.
Kristen Linkwist, who I'm imagining you can identify because she's our sole woman on
the panel today, is an associate professor at the University of North Carolina at Chapel
Hill where she has appointments in the Department of Psychology and Neuroscience and the Biomedical
Research Imaging Center in the School of Medicine. She directs the Carolina Effective Science
Lab which uses tools from behavioral science, physiology and neuroscience to examine how
our social worlds, bodies and brains conspire to create emotion. She's interested in how
emotion and emotional regulation varies across the age span and health and disease and across
cultures. Carl Nicholas, you'll raise your hand since you're not as easy to identify
there, although the beard helps. Carl J. Nicholas is the Liberty Hyde Bailey Professor of Plant
Biology Emeritus in the School of Integrative Plant Science Cornell University. His research
is in the Plant Biophysics and Evolution with a particular focus on the evolution of biomechanics,
complexity and multicellularity. He has written over 400 peer reviewed articles and five books
and they're listed here, you could find them on your introduction to the talk today. He's
a fellow of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, the Institute of Advanced Study at
Davison Shafte-Koleg in Berlin and the American Association for the Advancement of Science.
David Rosenthal is Professor of Philosophy at the Graduate Center of the City University
of New York with courtesy appointments and linguistics and cognitive neuroscience. He's
also the coordinator of the Graduate Center's interdisciplinary concentration in cognitive
science. He has published widely on consciousness, the mental qualities of perceiving and sensation,
the representational character of thought, the nature of emotions, the self and related
topics including his 2005 book Consciousness and Mind. His work on consciousness advances
the theory that a psychological state is conscious if it is accompanied by a thought to the effect
that one is in that state. He's also published in the Nature of Emotion, the Mind Body Problem
and the Relation of Thought and Speech. And I am the last panelist, as I mentioned,
Gerald Herwitz. I'll just say I'm a clinical neuropsychiatrist and psychopharmacologist
who practices here in New York City and I'm in faculty at Columbia University. So we're
going to begin with Joseph Lidou giving a brief sort of praise of his book and then we'll
commence having our conversation.
Thanks, Jerry. So it's really great to have these panelists because in a book that covers
four billion years we need a lot of different expertise to get into all of this. And when
I was writing the book, the work that each of these people has done comes into play because
it's in part about the early history of life and I consulted quite a bit with Carl as I
was trying to understand how single cells became multicellular organisms and he was
incredibly helpful to me in that. Kristen's work on the cognitive construction of emotions
is very consistent with the kinds of ideas that I'm interested in. And I also am a very
good friend and collaborator with David Rosenthal here who has the grandfather, the main god
of higher order theory of consciousness which I also mostly subscribe to. I have my own
version of it. So it's a real pleasure to have all these folks here and to be able to
interact with them. So let me just tell you a little bit about the book. If you know anything
about my research, you know that I study a part of the brain called the amygdala and its
role in threat detection and responding to danger. And I've done that for about 30 or
something, 30 something years, maybe 40 years I don't even know anymore. And so at one
point I started thinking about something which is that the molecules that we've discovered
in the rat brain that are important for the detection, learning about danger and responding
to danger are also the molecules that are present in bees and flies and snails and other
organisms like that. So Eric Candel's work for example in discovering all of these molecules
was very influential and helpful because those of us studying mammals would have a much harder
time doing that. So we used the clues that Eric and his colleagues discovered. And I was
talking to one of his colleagues once about how do these things come together, how do flies
and bees and slugs have the molecules that we end up having as well. And of course it has to
do with there being a common ancestor that had all of these molecules. So if you think about
that, that takes us somewhere around 630 million years ago. So it goes back a long time. And this
fella, his name is Seth Grant who we tried to get to come to the panel. He's in Scotland and he
would love to have come but he had a conflict so we weren't able to add him in the extra seat
here. But Seth's work is on the genetic mechanisms of memory and the genes in particular underlying
certain kinds of receptors that are important and plasticity. And Seth had found these that these
molecules not only are present in mammals and invertebrates but also in organisms like jellyfish
and snails and slugs, I'm sorry, jellyfish and sponges. And so we're now talking about the
beginning of animal life. But he also noted that they're present in protozoa. Now protozoa are
single cell organisms that are able to learn and they're able to detect danger, respond to danger
in their environment, incorporate nutrients, balance fluids and use behavior to do all these
things. They also reproduce. They produce the protozoa, which the protozoa are part of,
are the beginning of sexual reproduction. So a single cell, how does a single cell reproduce?
Well sometimes it's self fertilization but other times there are male and female cells that
will fertilize the female. So we're now going back about 2 billion years or so to get to where we
still have these molecules that are present in us. Now these animals, these organisms don't even
have a nervous system. So what are they doing with learning and plasticity molecules? There's
nothing to be plastic about. So the point is that you don't need a nervous system for behavior and
you don't even need it for learning. And that's kind of a mind-blowing concept. And so if you keep
going back and I kept going back until I got to the beginning of time, to the beginning of the
time of life, which is about somewhere around 3.7 billion years ago, 4 billion years ago,
where the first cells that were able to successfully reproduce and continue to reproduce so that the
rest of life then followed. These were bacterial-like cells that also had to do these same things.
Detect danger responded to detect danger, incorporate nutrients, balance fluids, reproduce and things
like that. And they use behavior for many of these things. So when we think about these in humans,
we're talking about danger, we're talking about fear. Incorporating nutrients, we're talking about
feeding and hunger, balancing fluids, we talk about thirst, reproduction, we talk about sex and
pleasure. But these mental states have nothing to do with why these behaviors exist. They exist
because they were necessary for these early bacterial cells to survive in their environment.
Behavior is a tool of survival, not a tool of the mind. We use behavior with our minds, but most
of our mental capacities do not necessarily impact our behavior. So for example, in the work I do
on the amygdala and threat detection in rats and in people, we often hear the amygdala is the
brain sphere center. That's absolutely wrong. The amygdala detects and responds to danger. Your fear,
as Christian will talk about, is a cognitive construction interpretation of what's going on
around you. It's not simply a bottom up thing that we turn on the amygdala and all of a sudden
bam, you're afraid. No, the fear is what happens when you realize what's going on. So you jump
back from a bus flying across 2nd Avenue here and you do the jumping back long before you feel any
kind of fear. Your brain is able to keep you alive because it has survival talents. And that's
really what we are survival machines. And we use our greatest capacities such as consciousness and
so forth to help us survive as well. And that's an unusual thing in the history of life that we
can anticipate the future and use our understanding of what's going on in order to keep us alive.
Now, our conscious minds are perhaps our greatest talent, but they're also our worst,
they're responsible for our worst proclivities, greed, anger, envy, narcissism, and all of the
things that are getting us into trouble today and potentially preventing the future survival
of our species. You know, we're kind of, I think, maybe Carl can address this more accurately,
but species have a kind of typical time course. And I think we're probably pretty close to the
end of ours. The only way we can get past that, I think, would be if as a species we come together
and use our collective of conscious minds to do something good for the survival of our kind.
So that's, that kind of takes you from the beginning of the book to the end. And I guess we can throw
it open to the conversation now. That's great. Well, as someone who's read through Joseph,
Joseph's book, I can tell you, it's just wonderful, magisterial, and all the, and you could imagine
four billion years, a lot of time to cover it. And he covers it beautifully. I guess there's so
many places to jump in and have a conversation about the contents of the book, but I think maybe
we should start at the beginning and talk a little bit about the development of behavior.
Was that sort of an interesting entry point?
So, continue, or, I mean, as I said, behavior is something that every organism does in some way,
including plants which Carl works on. A tree that is absorbing light, or certainly sunflowers,
are going to adapt to the light. The roots of plants will seek out minerals and water.
And there are many things that plants do that are quite amazing behaviorally. And I think that
that's actually kind of a hot topic now, plant behavior. We just have to be careful not to go
too far when we over-interpret plant behavior in terms of mental states. And I'll just stop there
and throw it open.
Well, I would add that behavior probably should be viewed as an example of any kind of biological
trait that spans the continuum of the tree of life. And if you look at its evolutionary history,
even consciousness, you see that to one degree or another, it exists within every lineage of
life, including plants and bacteria. But it is elaborated progressively with the appearance of new
evolutionary groups. And you see that it becomes more elaborated as you go from unicellular to
multicellular. And in multicellular animals, for example, it becomes more elaborate from
those lineages that lack a central nervous system to those that do. Now, even though
one can look at it as a continuum through the tree of life, that doesn't mean that it doesn't
have discernible thresholds. So the analogy that I would give is if you look at the visible
electromagnetic spectrum light, and you see that the wavelengths go from blue to red in increments
of one wavelength, you still nonetheless see the different colors of the rainbow. And so those
are the thresholds. And so we can say, for example, in lineage A, we're not sure that there's a level
of consciousness. But when you get to, let's say, homo sapiens and primates, yes, consciousness
appears to be the most elaborate. So as again, there's this continuum. But there are these
increments that when you go from one wavelength to the next, you go from orange to yellow or yellow
to orange line.
I ask you to talk briefly about the importance of genetic compatibility of the cells within an
organism, and what was required to create a multicellular organism with all the cells having the same
genetic compatibility. Okay, very briefly. So if we look at the fossil record, and I brought a
prop, which maybe I'll discuss in a little minute, we see that every lineage plant animal begins as
a unicellular ancestral form. And then if we look at the progressive evolution, we see that we go
generally to colonial, then to simple multicellular, and then to complex multicellular organisms. So
the theory is that there are two very critical stages. The first is a stage in which the unicellular
to colonial has to have genetic compatibility amongst adjoining cells.
Just maybe explain colonial. So a colonial organism would be something like a sponge. So you have a
bunch of aggregated cells that are, to some extent, cooperating in behavior, behaving in a
collaborative way. If I was talking about plants, I would be talking about some kind of alga that is
just a glob of cells glued together by an extracellular matrix. But those cells have to be at least
initially genetically compatible. And so it's comparatively easy to do that in the sense that
one is cell divides. Its derivative cells are very, very similar genetically. And so there's this
gamutlic kite, this community structure that's established. But then the really difficult stage
is this second stage, where you go from cells that are cooperating to cells that have now exported
their fitness. So in other words, the survival of the multicellular organism doesn't depend on the
survival of the individual cells. It depends on the reproductive success of the multicellular
entity. And that's a very difficult thing to achieve. Nevertheless, if you look at the fossil
record, multicellularity is evolved at a minimum of 27 independent evolutionary events. And it all
started with something like this. This is a fossil which I'll pass around, but don't cut yourself.
This rock is 2.6 billion years old. It's an example of a thing called a stromatoline.
It's minerals that were precipitated by a bacterial biofilm. And inside this are microfossils,
which are visible when you take thin sections and look at them through the microscope. Now,
if I was alive back then, 2.6 billion years, I would still see things that perhaps I would
identify as behavior. Because these biofilm organisms are collaborating. Some of them are
doing one function, another, another function. But getting them all to collaborate is a single
multicellular organism. That's a very complicated thing. So if you'd like to pass this around,
just don't cut yourself on the edges. It's sharp. So one of the ideas I end up with at the end of
the book, and it's kind of a crazy idea, but anyway, is that the human capacity for self-awareness
is, results in our brain having a rogue component that is different from anything else that has
existed in a multicellular organism, which is the ability to go against the good, the greater good,
of all of the other cells of the body, and end your own life. And I think that that doesn't exist
in any other organism. You have to be able to know you exist, to know that an end can exist,
and to choose to bring that in for fruition. So that was one of the most amazing things,
many, I discovered many amazing things, reading Carl's work and other really deep biological
thinkers on these topics. But one of the things that stuck with me was the compatibility
of an organism. And to have an organism that has many cells, all of the cells have to work towards
the purpose of the organism to stay alive. And that's why unlike in a colony where you can remove
a cell or a cell can defect and live on its own because it's not dependent on the colony.
It helps the colony if the cell was there, so the colony needs to protect some way from the
cells defecting. But if we remove a skin cell or any other cell from our body, the cell dies,
because we have so many different parts of our body that are interdependent. Our circulatory
system depends on our respiratory system and so on. So it's just a multicellular organism,
it's just a fascinating thing, and I thank you for everything I learned from your work.
So maybe David, we could talk about consciousness.
Well, I was going to ask you a question in what you just said about this suicide thing.
If the animal, a human, thinks, well, this is a good idea, I'm going to end my life.
And it goes ahead and does that. Why, I mean, there are all sorts of psychological things that
I'm not competent to say anything about. But let's assume that we have a case of a person
who decides I'm going to end my life. And it's actually from the point of view of the person's
psychological functioning. That's a good thing. Why is this going against the rest of it? I mean,
because it's the rest of the body doesn't want to die, it's purpose is to keep on living.
Well, the rest of the body is doing whatever it does as long as the animal is alive.
But you have one part of the animal, one small part of the animal that is making a decision for
the rest of the body. Normally, the body is working as a unit.
Well, so if I'm a tiger and I see prey over there and I say, I'm hungry, I'm going to go
kill the prey and eat the prey. This is my psychological functioning that's driving the rest of my
limbs and my mouth and all of this stuff. I would say psychological.
But I'm sorry. I wouldn't make it cycle. I would say that it's the survival imperative of the
organism to do that. I mean, that may be some psychology that goes with it. But I don't think
that's necessarily what's driving the behavior. So when you talk about psychology, it's got to be
conscious. I was assuming that what happens above the neck, so to speak, that's going to be psychological.
But our medulla is causing us to breathe and causing our heart to root. I don't think we can
take everything in the brain as psychological. Well, I was being a little loose that way. But
in any case, the brain is not asking the kidneys or the feet or any other part of the body
about this business of going over and killing the prey and eating it. The brain is driving
the rest of the body. So maybe there's a smaller piece of the brain that says,
I know what, I've been around long enough. I'm going to put an end to all of this. It seems to be
a continuity between the brain running the body for killing prey and the brain.
The point was that, as you said, it's not a small piece, but there's one component of the brain's
capacity that is making a decision that is going to terminate the activity of everything else.
It's not, whereas biologically, organisms are designed, not designed, but are built
so that they can persist. Would you agree with that? Yeah, I would. I'm a plant person,
so a lot of the examples that I can give are probably very alien because plants are not alive.
At least a lot of people don't view them as living organisms. But anyway, I can think of a few examples
amongst plants where the entire organism essentially commits suicide. But in each case, it's for
reproduction. So the sunflower, for example, a lot of aquatic plants will reproduce once.
And when they reproduce once, they will divert all of their energy from the somatic, non-reproductive
cells. They'll divert all of their resources into perpetuating, and as close as it can, ensuring
the survival of its progeny. So that is one word that comes to my mind is it's an example of
altruism. It's not saying I'm tired of living. I don't want to live. In fact, it's committing
the ultimate Darwinian self-sacrifice for the fitness of the next generation.
And it's a decision, but it's a process of the entire organism.
It's actually genetically programmed. It's genetic. So I don't know. I'm not going to use
the word consciousness, but it's certainly behavioral. The purpose of the brain is to
regulate the body and to ensure survival. And so it is odd for a human to sort of override that
process. In the case of plants, they're ensuring the longevity of the extended organism.
Right. So the biologist Emil Durkheim had an interesting discussion of all of this.
This is where I'm getting this idea of the human being, the only organism that intentionally
terminates itself. When you mentioned Carl, the development of multicellularity and how now the
cells with similar genetic endowment now, as you said, they've exported their fitness.
And this may sound like it's a digression, but I think it is related to what we're talking about
now. And so does that make rubbish of the self-esteem notion? And I mentioned it in the context of,
well, are there directives, that's called them, from nature, that are at odds with one another?
In this case, you see it. They may line up differently depending on whether it's a
colonial versus a multicellular organism. Well, if you read Dawkins very carefully,
the selfish chain. He's really not saying the gene is in control. He's been interpreted to really
push that point of view. And later on in his subsequent publications, he kind of has. But in
that book, he really is talking about the emergent properties from the level of the genome from the
genetic structure. And we know that genetic structure does not directly map to the phenotype,
to the appearance of the organism. When I was a student at CCNY, I was taught, well, DNA,
messenger RNA protein. We didn't know about alternative splicing. We didn't know about
intrinsically disordered proteins. We didn't know about gene silencing. We didn't know about epigenetics.
What we do know now is you cannot directly map the genotype to the phenotype. And so this
self is gene, the way it's been interpreted in the popular literature, is rubbish.
Well, the idea of the fitness being exported, which I think is a wonderful phrase. I haven't
got a latch onto that. It makes it simple. That's now the element that gets affected by natural
selection. And it's some slightly more abstract sort of thing.
I mean, if you talk about the export of fitness, what you're really saying is the fitness of the
organism does not depend on the number of times individual cells divide. It depends on the number
of times the multicellular organism reproduces. So if you cut off your arm, which is not suicide,
by accident, all those cells are dead. But that's irrelevant. Their fitness has nothing to do with
the individual's capacity to reproduce and produce progeny. So that's one way of thinking about the
export of fitness. It's a major, major transition in every evolutionary lineage that's achieved
complicated multicellularity.
So whereas there are instances of, say, for example, program death like an apoptosis,
and you mentioned an example of the plant, I think Joe, what you're talking about,
still is something different. There's a meaning behind my act, then my life,
which it seems to be in a different sort of concept. So there's a reason out of
this lower level biological functions that might include program death.
It's a higher order thought. Right? Well, I think, so Joe is alluding to my theory of consciousness.
The theory of consciousness is basically along very common sense lines, I think.
If you're in some type of psychological state, the state counts as conscious only if you're aware
of being in that state. And that seems natural because if we have evidence that somebody is in a
certain psychological state, and the person says, no, I don't feel that way. I don't see the stimulus.
I don't have that thought. I don't have that desire, whatever it might be. That's evidence that
the, but we still have evidence that the person is in the state. And it's possible under all these
the conditions that I just mentioned to have such evidence. Then we have a case of, we have a clear
case of an unconscious mental state. So that pretty much implies that what it is for a state to be
conscious is for the individual to be aware of it in some way or another. And what I've argued is
going again from the human case here, though, unlike Joe, I think I would
move down to non-linguistic animals. But in the human case, the standard thing is that if I'm in
a mental state that I am aware of, I can tell you that. And if I tell you that, that's performing a
speech act, I'm saying something, I'm expressing a thought that I'm in that state. So the way that
I'm aware of being in the state is by having a thought about that's basically the theory. And
as Joe mentioned, he likes the theory. He has a slightly different version of it.
So I'd just like to add one thing to what you said, which is that, you know, a lot of people think
I say that animals don't have consciousness, but I don't say that. I say that we don't know what
they have. Precisely because they can't tell us. And we can't use behavior as a reliable indicator
of what an animal is experiencing. For example, this has been tempted in the area of emotion with
the amygdala in fear. We assume that because a rat in a person both frees to danger, and in both
cases, the amygdala is required to freeze to danger, that must mean that the rat and the person both
feel fear, and that the rat feels fear because the person feels fear and they're both using the
amygdala. But the assumption is wrong that, you know, often when we are running from a bear,
we are afraid. But that doesn't mean that fear is what causes us to run. They're not the same
thing. Those are correlations, not causation. Every scientist is taught from day one to not confuse
correlation and causation. And yet we've been kind of seduced by this correlation to think that if
an animal or a person is responding to danger, it must be because they're afraid. But when we look
in the brain and start trying to analyze how fear is coming about, we see that there are people
who have damage to the amygdala, that under some conditions can still report fear. So
also if we present stimuli to a person subliminally, so the person that means a very quick flash,
for example, that means the person doesn't know the stimulus is there, doesn't report feeling any
fear, but the amygdala is activated, the heart is racing, palms are sweating. So the responses are
there, but fear is not what's driving them. That doesn't mean fear is irrelevant, it's just not
what the amygdala is doing. So we have to look elsewhere for where the amygdala might, or where
fear may be coming from, and building on your theory, I and others have talked about high-order
states involving prefrontal cortex. In fact, you and Hawkewan Laude written about prefrontal
cortex. So let me just say a couple of words about prefrontal cortex. There are different
parts of the prefrontal cortex, one of which has properties that are only found in the human brain,
and this is called the frontal pole. Now there are other parts of the prefrontal cortex, for example,
the dorsolateral prefrontal cortex that are only found in primates including other humans,
and this has also been actually implicated in consciousness in humans. So I'm willing to say,
yes, probably other primates because they have this part of the brain could very well have some
kind of awareness, but an awareness that is made possible by that kind of prefrontal cortex,
as opposed to the other kind. So my idea would be that these dorsolateral regions shared by all
primates are involved in a kind of knowledge of what's there, whereas the frontal pole, for
reasons I won't go into other than that it's relatively unique in humans, might be involved in
the ability to know that it's you that is aware of what's there. So that extra higher-order thought,
that that awareness that you have, it's definitely worth pursuing in terms of this frontal pole.
We don't have an answer to this question yet, but in your paper with Hawk 1 Law in 2011,
you mentioned the frontal pole and that's really how I got onto the frontal poles, and thank you.
But now if we go to other mammals, there are a bunch of prefrontal regions that are present
in these animals, but on the medial side of the hemisphere, inside the, we have the two hemispheres
of the hot dog one, and we spread them apart, so the white, untested part would be where the
medial areas are, and these are the mustard. Yeah, and the dog, yeah, or ketchup. But the,
so these other mammals have these medial prefrontal areas, and this may
allow a kind of body awareness that is another level down, that beyond that knowledge that,
you know, that they understand what's out there, and beyond their knowledge that they know that
it's them that's having that state. So I allow for all these things that just don't know how we
would test it. So here's the thing, there's an experiment that Alan Cowie and Petra Sturring did
with some macarcomonkeys. So blind sight is a condition where some area of primary visual cortex
is ablated or damaged, doesn't function. And if a person with blind sight is presented with a stimulus
that goes to that area of primary visual cortex, the person will say, and I'm seeing anything.
On the other hand, the person will be able to guess if the experimenter presses the person to guess
you say, well, guess about what the nature of the stimulus was that you're saying you didn't see,
and the subject will say, well, I can't guess, I didn't see anything, please just guess,
and they get it more or less around 83% of the time correct, which is very good.
And there have been a number of human subjects of this sort, and the results are pretty constant.
So what Cowie and Sturring did was to surgically ablate, I think it was the right side,
the left side of primary visual cortex will see the right visual field.
And they had a monkey that in two separate experiments performed as follows. The monkey was able to reach out
and touch something in the right visual field, even though that's the blind sight area for that monkey.
Then several months later, the monkey was trained to distinguish between a stimulus in the left side
and a blank. So if there's something, you press it. If it's a blank, you press another button, which is the
blank button. And then it turned out that this monkey would press the blank button for a stimulus in the right side.
So the monkey is able to do pretty much what a human can do. That is to say, in a certain way, the monkey is able to guess
that there is something there, and the monkey also says, I don't see anything. And it seems to me that it's hard to explain that pair of results
without assuming that the monkey has blind sight. That is to say that there's a difference for the monkey between seeing and consciously seeing.
So I'll just refer to what Larry Weisbrand said about that, which is that yes, it looks like they're seeing, but because it's an animal,
we can't, Larry Weisbrand says that the person who discovered blind sight and has popularized it. And also, in the commentary piece of Coward's story, we're using Larry said,
we think that the animal is conscious, but we simply don't know scientifically that there's no proof.
So Larry was the one who told me that this particular experiment was produced. I don't. But in the conversation he told me, he thinks this is Evans.
And it's a finding, Joe, that I think is hard to explain any other way. So,
I'm not questioning what it's saying.
Can't surrender for a hypothesis. What's the hypothesis that would explain the fact that the monkey can actually detect, but the monkey presses the blank button for a stimulus on that side.
I'm willing to admit it's possible. I'm sorry. I'm willing to admit it's possible.
But the other explanation would be that there's some sort of disposition to act that doesn't necessarily include what we often refer to as consciousness.
Right? Isn't that? I mean, even when that is exactly.
But what I'm asking for an explanation of is the pair of results.
Why is it? So if a stimulus is presented on the left side, the monkey presses the stimulus, where the stimulus is on the screen.
If no stimulus on the left side presses blank.
And if the stimulus on the right side presses blank.
And so that's one kind of experiment. And the other kind of experiment is that the monkey can actually detect it.
So it seems as though there's a distinction between the ability to detect, which I'm suggesting corresponds to the human's guessing on the one hand.
And the monkey is counting it as a blank.
Whatever it means for blank.
The blank means I don't see anything.
I'm not sure if this is relevant. And please, I'm apologizing.
I'm speaking as a botanist.
But I think it was philosopher Ned Block that made the difference between the phenomenology of responding and receiving signals.
And the phenomenology of being aware of those signals.
And so I'd like to point out that plants, which lack a neurological system, but nevertheless have an electrical signaling system within them,
clearly perceive external stimuli and respond to them adaptively.
So that's kind of a phenomenological awareness.
But it's by no means self-awareness. There's no reflection as we might project from our own experiences.
So this thing called consciousness is a touchy subject.
I'm not sure. I think it was John Locke who actually used the word consciousness for the first time.
He was Descartes.
Was it? Well, Locke said consciousness is what happens in man's mind.
And that was the definition.
Not the definitions are holding.
But I would just say that there's one attribute that I think defines all forms of life.
And when I was a young person, oh, God.
It's not only a century ago, but a millennium ago, the biology book said life is defined by irritability.
And then you read on it and it says, and as I get older, I become more irritable.
But what it was really saying was that life responds.
It reacts to external stimuli.
And I think that is from bacteria all the way up to us.
But this thing about consciousness being self-awareness, as I have to agree,
I'm not sure that any primate other than us has been shown to be truly self-aware.
I think in your book, Joe, you do spend a lot of time trying to push back against certain intuitions.
Even you criticize Darwin for this in a way.
For adopting anthropomorphism, maybe prematurely, or as you say prematurely.
I think it's such a woolly concept, consciousness, because we also mean slightly different things
than we use in different sentences, for example.
But I'm interested in the famous story about running from a bear.
Because I think where you might also lose some of your audience is that it would seem to me
whatever impels me to start running when I see a bear, at some point along the line,
especially if I think about it, hypothetically, I get fearful.
And I can imagine even in the actual event of running away, halfway down the whatever it is.
It's not a block, I guess, of a mirror bear.
But you are fearful, but it is your fear of the cause?
Right, right, exactly right.
So at some point, it certainly kicks in.
That's for sure.
Maybe, Chris, I can't.
In the history of the study of emotion, there's a tradition of assuming that there's some centrally
organized state that is causing behaviors.
And you see that as far back as Plato, right?
And Darwin was certainly guilty of this, and perhaps is the one who has sort of ushered
that idea into modern science.
And yet, behaviors are often emerging more quickly than conscious experiences.
And so the brain is perceiving behaviors as they're unfolding.
It's perceiving stimuli in the world around it.
It's perceiving vis-a-motor changes in the body and is categorizing those experiences.
But there's not clear evidence that there is some centralized mechanism that is fear
per se that is causing a certain suite of behaviors or anger per se that's causing a
sort of sort of a suite of behaviors.
I was just thinking about how when you're addressing people and trying to explain that,
there's such a kind of pushback because our conscious, you know, deliberations about
these episodes so strongly inserts fear.
That's right.
You know, if all we needed was intuition, we wouldn't have to do experiments.
Science would be irrelevant.
So I mean, intuition is often the starting point of an experiment, some scientific endeavor.
All, you know, men we live in our heads, we live in our folk psychology.
And this is why we do psychology and one understands how it all works.
But ultimately, we have to get to what's going on in terms of how these processes really
work.
And what I've tried to argue is that the processes that control these innate behaviors,
like freezing or escape, are separate from those that are making us feel fear.
And I think this is consistent with Kristin's work as well.
You know, it's the, we're innately anthropomorphic.
I mean, it's been said that anthropomorphism was very useful to our early ancestors as
they were living with cows and creating farming and agriculture.
It was helpful to treat animals as little people, big people would have been on the
animal.
And that, you know, because they were partners in this process, maybe not equal partners
or enough.
One guy, he didn't even know that.
And so something could be innate in our brain and yet not be scientifically correct because
it's not about whether it's scientifically accurate.
It's about whether it was useful to our species.
So you know, I say this almost every lecture I give, I go home, I pet my cat, he purrs,
and I think he's happy.
You don't have to be a scientist every moment of your working life.
Science is a different thing than life.
We, you know, we lead our lives in the ways and sometimes science is useful in leading
our lives.
But certainly it's not a way to, if you didn't have another hat, you could never have a pet
if you were a materialist, scientist like me.
Right.
I would argue that we're not just innately anthropomorphic, but we innately assign agency
to things.
And so we infer intention from behaviors because it's a useful shortcut, cognitively.
And therefore we are likely to infer intention of other people's behaviors in animals behaviors,
in natural events, in ways that they don't actually exist.
Cartoon characters.
Right.
And plants.
Yeah.
The one advantage to being a botanist is that your study organisms don't bleed on you.
And the other is that it's almost impossible to project human emotions when you're looking
at an organism.
I think some people do that.
Well, yes.
But as a scientist who studies plants, I have no fear about projecting human emotions or
attributes to plants.
Now, what about this, this, maybe that rubbish of the touring test?
You know, what?
Well, the idea that we answer more fives away from valentoring said famously that if you
are interacting with a computer program and you can't tell the difference about whether
it's a conscious being or not, then it's conscious.
So this line of argument would suggest that's just totally wrong.
Well, I think Turing's idea is that Turing imagined that Turing was considering whether
you could have a computer program that would be as elaborate and flexible as a person would
be.
So that's not, I think, along the lines of anthropomorphizing an elephant or a palm tree
so much.
Right.
But he's relying on the notion of acceptable anthropomorphization as a criterion for consciousness.
Well, he's relying on a particular hypothesis that humans are able to react in a conversational
setting like this in marvelously flexible, unpredictable ways.
And so some very smart programmer, he was a very smart programmer, might be able to design
a program so that a very smart psychologist wouldn't be able to tell whether a program
was behind the screen or a person was typing out answers.
And so it's a particular hypothesis about, I think, the nature of human thinking rather
than something having to do with anthropomorphizing.
A thought that has occurred to me while listening to this is, and it's a question I'm not sure
anyone's really ever asked is, when does the individual human being become conscious?
We started out as a fertilized egg, as I go through the blastula, gastrula, etymological
modifications.
Right.
The point is that that's the same organism throughout its ontology.
And this attribute that we call consciousness makes its appearance at some stage in that
ontogenetic sequence.
So it's fair to say that we're not conscious throughout our entire embryology or in many
parts of our life, or most of our life.
It's worth making a few distinctions.
One distinction, we use the word conscious to distinguish between the way we all are now
here, and when we're asleep we're knocked out or amesthetized or something like that.
So that's one kind of consciousness that has to do something like biological functioning.
We also use the word conscious, so unconscious of a table, unconscious of a water bottle.
So and it might be that the psychological state, the visual state in virtual work, where the
table in front of me is an unconscious visual state, one of these subliminal states.
So if you say, well, David, is there a table in front of you, I would say now there isn't.
But then if you ran some tests like priming tests or force choice or whatever, you wouldn't
be able to see actually.
I was seeing the table.
So I was conscious of the table, but not consciously conscious.
And sometimes this appears in the popular press as a distinction between being aware of the
table and being consciously aware of the table.
So my question gets back to this.
These three things that developmentally will emerge at some point with an animal's development.
My statement actually was meant to provoke that kind of response.
But also to point out that, not that I'm heckle saying that on Tajini recapitulates
by Rajini, but it's kind of interesting that when you look at the tree of life from unicellular
to multicellular, from simple multicellular to complicated multicellular, from early primates
to late primates of which we're the most recent example, the question may be the last.
The question is when does it make its appearance that we would say this thing is self-conscious.
And so that's even beyond what I was talking about.
So if we're talking about the difference between seeing something consciously and seeing it
subliminally, that's not a matter of self-consciousness.
That's something more primitive.
And then Joe talks in the book a fair amount about this.
This is this notion that he borrows from Endel Tovin about auto-noetic consciousness.
I'm not completely comfortable with the distinction between auto-noetic consciousness and noetic
consciousness.
But at least something that involves reflective awareness in itself is a more advanced stage
of development than simply consciously seeing.
So Michael Lewis is a developmental psychologist, has written a book called the Dawn of Consciousness
or something like that for you exactly in the title.
And then that he proposes that the child becomes conscious in an adult kind of sense with the
development of personal pronouns around the age of two or three.
So that you now have something to hang your understanding of who you are, I, me, mine.
And it's not that the child was asleep all that time, but didn't have a sense of me the
way you have when you have a concept.
I think maybe Christian can say a lot about concepts and emotions and consciousness and
so forth.
Yeah, so there's a lot of developmentalists who argue that self-awareness in children
emerges around two or three around or 18 months around the time that they can identify themselves
from other individuals via this mirror self-recognition task.
So you put a dot on the child's head and you make them look in the mirror and instead of
touching the other baby in the mirror, they touch their own forehead.
And it's thought that that is an indication of the self.
But the self, like any concept, is a concept that is accumulated over time that you are
you and you have certain features and certain likes and certain dislikes.
And it's clear that that's something that emerges over top of their hood.
But your comment was interesting regarding ontogeny as it sort of recopitulates the phylogeny
that Joe outlines in the book because it is this gradual process, right?
And there's an urge to infer these stages at which they're shifts and it's much more
complicated than that.
Yeah, I'll go back to that analogy that I made with visible light when you break it
up with a spectrum that you know you go from one frequency to the next, click, click, click,
click, you go from red to blue and in between are all the colors of the rainbow.
And there are demonstrable thresholds when we would all agree this is yellow, this is
orange, this is green.
And yet it's a continuum as a process, which to me is rather interesting even from an evolutionary
point of view because as you probably all aware there's an argument between sultational
evolution and gradualistic evolution.
And I don't see them as necessarily mutually exclusive by virtue of that analogy that I
can get you know go from a fish to a terrestrial thing or an amphibian and that doesn't mean
that I had to go through a massive reorganization of the body structure of the organism.
You know that analogy really answers the question I was about to pose, it doesn't completely
answer I think, but that is I think what an amazing sort of miracle or a mystery is that
we all pass through this developmental stage when we're unconscious and become conscious
and then likewise every day there are lots of instances where we're self aware or not
self aware.
I'm thinking of the example of driving in the car and something that you're very you
know and then you suddenly realize where's my mind been all this time even though obviously
we're responding to the thing but the I think well that's an amazing miracle why can't
we pinpoint why we're like well that's aha that's where I became conscious because we
don't and we don't know that but it's interesting with the analogy with the color spectrum is
because you know there are those odd ball colors between yellow and orange let's say
or blue and purple where we might stop and think I don't know where the line is here
I'm not sure where the line is right and that may be some I don't know I'm putting out
there's a possible analogy to our difficulty knowing when we're fully conscious or not
you know coming back to more complicated in terms of emotions I mean we have these specific
words that we use and you know but the gradations are not so clear and Kristin you've done a
lot of work on emotion words and also in terms of culture and maybe you could yeah I was
actually going to start that off with the color analogy which is interesting because
it turns out that there are actually cultural differences and where people see cut points
and visible spectrum of light and you know there's hot debate surrounding this but it
does seem that you know even within a culture people disagree on where you know where the
categories begin and end and certainly across cultures people disagree about where color
categories begin and end now if that's the case for color emotion is much more complicated
and there much of my work has shown that the emotion words that people know and acquire
through their culture name rich sets of categories that help people to parsley the world into
emotional meaning and so the richer your emotion vocabulary the more likely you are to see
instances of these categories in the world around you and so in that sense to come full
circle to the point about language humans may have a unique form of consciousness that
is predicated on their ability to use language which essentially warps perceptual space it
makes certain things look more similar together to one another and certain things look more
distinct from one another and that's not to say that animals don't have complex representations
but the question then becomes one of gradation again right so to the extent that animals
have the ability to represent these rich caches of knowledge in an abstract way they may or
may not have emotion concepts that that look something like humans you know I think it's
interesting that we can translate a word like fear across languages but obviously we know
that there are cultural differences in the experience of these things but we assume because
we have the same word we're all experiencing the same thing and this is you know a huge
problem in geopolitical politics where we take the translation literally but it means
acts to the people who are listening to the translation and why do the people from whom
the translation is coming from so I mean words are our friend but also can get us into trouble
with sloppy use and I think scientists are often very sloppy with words I have a percidifical
these happen even in very local context and very often because you know people are being
nice they don't say anything about it or they may not notice it but I don't think that you
have to travel across national boundaries or language of culture and that is the bad
thing yeah you're gonna say something oh I was gonna be personal example I was writing
a book with a German colleague and we were working together week after week a lot of
math and we decided that one day we would speak English and the next day we would speak
German so our brains didn't fry and at one point the day we spoke English I'm trying to
explain something to Christoph and he said 999 that it doesn't make sense so I said it
in German he said oh yeah
that's a joke you do make a very interesting introduction to this topic of deliberation
as a chapter on that I think this goes back to maybe even the example with the monkeys
there's this I guess one one thing to make some of us believe that an animal might be
conscious if they seem to deliberate they're conscious themselves I know the stoic philosopher
Christophus mentioned that would describe how animals for example who might be preparing
to leap over crevasse will size up their ability to do it and seem to be in some way deliberating
and aware and he uses as a he believes a demonstration that there's some degree of self-awareness
at least in that regard I I know how far I might be able to jump or not and will I do
it so sometimes the animal back off and sometimes it kind of a week and that's a very interesting
challenge to the idea that animals aren't conscious I mean I'm not saying I accept him
but I think it's everything interesting sort of you know one of the points I tried to
make about deliberation was that you have to distinguish conscious from non-conscious
deliberation so our cognitive capacities are a lot of what we do is done non-consciously
we make decisions all the time and we may justify them after the fact consciously but
you know in the process of making snap decisions we're not like analyzing everything consciously
so the animal that's making that snap decision whether they jump or not or maybe it's you
know maybe it's not so snap but you don't know that it's consciously exploring it's
probably is I'm not saying it's not right but it's an interesting challenge because
it's just so much appears to be that but I would add to the worry that sometimes at
least it seems to me and other people that I took to what happens well I don't know whether
to do A or B and instead of being Aristotle and whatever Aristotle was saying about deliberating
which would be very conscious I turn my mind off so to speak though I don't turn my mind
off but I turn I stop thinking about it consciously and I let it simmer and you know it's going
on somewhere but I'm not paying any oh then I see things clearly and so this is the unconscious
processes that are doing the work which really are deliberating many instances yes I'm not
suggesting that they aren't deliberating I'm suggesting that they aren't conscious and
that we can't extrapolate from deliberation to consciousness I agree with that Joe may
be familiar with this work but there's evidence that you can look at cells that map out space
in a non-human animal and as the animal is preparing to behave it's simulating which pathway
it's going to take and you can see that playing out in the firing of the cells and then the
question becomes is that deliberation right so again we need to be careful with our with
our definitions it's amazing what it is well it's something like a decision making process
so was you worry about whether it's deliberation whether it's conscious deliberation I'm just
pointing out again that it's slippery right where where we begin to infer some sort of
human-like state right humans certainly deliberate by saying oh should I take you know this route
or this route but if the if the animal brain is is simulating these future events and sort
of weighing which one to guide behavior the question is that's something that's all you
know space and place cell and all that came from Tolman's observations that rats are deliberating
as they go through a maze and then there's a middle modeling of the maze so yeah I think
you know there's a lot of stuff that happens outside of what we're thinking about plant
roots are an example actually a number of measurements showing how roots penetrate the
soil that the tips are the growing points of the root and you will occasionally see the
tip of the root stop growing and it's sensing and we know the mechanism which is the weakest
root and that's the one it follows so you know is that deliberation but it's it's really
perceiving alternatives and it adaptively takes the easy way out so to speak so Joe just
go back to the you know your question earlier about the hard sell about that it's not fear
that's causing us to respond this time so this is coming at it from a different angle but
this is your field in terms of psychopharmacology and so let me ask you a question how would
you evaluate current treatments psychopharmacological treatments for novel treatments for anxiety
right now well haven't much evolved over the last you know forty years 40 years I guess
it reminds me of your comment you know that people could not have an amygdala and still
have fear you know it's very difficult to pin down exactly the conscious experience
of fear but you know it's interesting there's some interaction between the sort of sheer
physiological response like for example in a panic attack and the experience of avoiding
behavior right because we usually in psychiatry think we don't talk about fear actually is
that much in literature I mean usually which is it is a shame people patients certainly
do but more avoid behavior and so most of the efforts are made to tamp down a lot of
physiological responses and I think it was interesting we've spoken about Donald Klein
earlier who was the psychiatrist recently passed away who distinguished panic anxiety
from sort of generalized anxiety and he'd also discovered that the mid-permine which
is one of the older antidepressants seemed to be effective for that and was better than
taking a benzoylous like Valium or Xanax and that was a very interesting breakthrough
because it did seem to create a very distinct and unanticipated benefit from a class of drugs
there was no reason to think aside from what got Don thinking about it no obvious reason
to think if that would work but it does actually help and there are a lot of theories about
why that's so but there is this sort of residual problem of patients going through this and
still being troubled by avoid behavior I mean another example would be PTSD it's very difficult
to get people to despite all sorts of pharmacological and behavioral treatments if they succeed
sometimes of course but there's no you know perfect solution to those things
Danny Pine and a psychiatrist and I wrote a paper a few years ago I know I said so in
this paper we reviewed the efforts to find medications and so forth to help people with
problems of fear and anxiety and I guess more anxiety than fear because you said it's not
as fear is not talked about as much but one of the things that comes up is the fact that
the pharmaceutical industry is getting out of the business of developing new treatments
and the reason is because nothing has been discovered over the last 40 years really and
so what we propose in this paper is the problem is not with the studies that are being done
but with the interpretation that's being applied to them because the way the research is done
is to work on for example avoid a behavior in rats or mice and to assume that that's
going to make the person less fearful or anxious but because the amygdala and these subcortical
circuits that control those behaviors are not generating the fear and anxiety itself
the subjective experience the patients don't quote feel better so the problem is that we
assume that you have this fear center that can be targeted by drug and that if you change
that fear center the person is better but that's not how it works I mean the subjective
experience of the patient has to be an endpoint and I think this is not my field as an outsider
it seems that subjective experience has been marginalized in the field both in cognitive
therapy and in pharmaceutical therapy as a goal of the whole process well I'll say since
we're sitting here at the Ndibsy you know psychoanalysts don't make that mistake I know
right but they do give a lot of consideration to that but I like to say when patients challenge
me about how long is taking from them to get better that is a little bit of a cheek out
but I'll say look it's an amazing your mind's unbelievably complex and complicated and it's
not a tremendous shock that it's difficult to fix it I don't think you'd want to be simpler
so that it would be easy to find a drug to do this and I really do think that's true
if you imagine consciousness that's why that's also what brought the mind the story about
running away from the bear maybe somewhere along the line I'd say well for sure now I'm
just beautiful to bear right whether or not I first bolted because I saw one and that the
symbolic rendering of a fearful object or a beloved object or of the object of jealousy
whatever whatever so the symbolic representation that may very well sit in the very part of
the brain that you're interested in you know associating with consciousness of a prefrontal
pole and the mechanisms which are novel to humans you say and I accept are not the sorts
of mechanisms that respond easily to be infused with a certain molecule so I don't think it
would be possible to change the content of a conscious thought with a drug I mean how
would you even design that exactly that's exactly what I'd say you know what's interesting
because the sort of operas is that is patients because they've read that some drugs can induce
suicidal thinking really which I think is done more badly more bad than good because a lot
of people stay away from medicines and otherwise help them really literally get this notion
that this will put this idea in my head you know and I guess in some sense that's kind
of true but it's not it's not an idea that's being inserted in their head right at some
level of arousal and agitation and dysphoria and happiness that might then lead to it but
it's not as though you're suddenly brainwashed that's this sort of idea and that's exactly
why when we're trying to make people unfuriful and when their object of fear can be a very
complex affair it could be very not just a bear but something much more complicated
than that it's very difficult to figure out a way to neutralize those I think the drug
companies would be better off if they sold these as avoidant medicines or you know physiological
arousal producers that would be much more accurate and it would create the right expectation
of what's going to happen with the medication as opposed to fear or anxiety medication absolutely
I know I look I think you know the basic outline of how the mental health field tries
to deal with these conditions is reasonable enough I'd say because but it's not in practice
always done very well that is the most people understand I guess PTSD is a great example
of this because it's so difficult to treat and many people who have that condition do
take medications for it and I think for good reason but it's very clear that's just one
step in a sort of rehabilitation and the rehabilitation which is sort of like the rehabilitation of
another chronic illnesses involve you know what involve a community you know it's not
just this thing or that and getting them better they need therapy demands they need to expose
themselves to what they're fearful of this reminds me of a large body of literature and
some of which is greatly debated but what's called the integrative phenotype and that
is it's as you go into more and more complicated organisms and I'm not sure we can identify
or quantify complication but we can think of the human mind is one of the most complicated
organs that it's such an integrated phenotype that it's very difficult to target a particular
aspect of that phenotype that doesn't have a generic effect and you know much of science
is reductionism we think that we can reduce complicated ideas to some very simple phenomena
and laws but as we really begin to look at biology in particular we realize that reductionism
is only the first step after you reduce all the components you then have to rebuild conceptually
and integrate all of those factors and then you see a large number of emergent properties
that could never have been predicted based on those very simple physical laws and relationships
so I'm resonating with this discussion about pharmacological solutions to behavioral issues
because it's not it's one organ and you're looking at just one facet of its behavior.
There's another condition that's not as often advertised as being a common target for psychotherapy
or psychopharmacology and that is the state and this pertains to consciousness state of
depersonalization where people feel detached from themselves and what's amazing here again
is I think that term covers a wide gamut of experiences I mean I've had patients who say
they feel they have no like as if they had no working memory as if they had no conscious
scratch pad they're not they're sort of they feel like an automaton and there are others
who won't say that but they feel very disconnected from their emotions they feel but they're
muted and they feel distant from them there's a really a wide range of abnormal states
and that's also something very difficult by the way to treat and it's from my way of
thinking because it involves ideas about the self which are so complex as you know if you
talk about different concepts built around emotion so that I just think how many of
them are built around myself right there are so many flavors of depersonalization and it's
a challenging condition to treat.
The other kid I've we were there open up for questions with it but there was one other
I think oddball state that I just wanted to hear everyone's thoughts about and wants
to comment on and that is to the opposite of blind sight which is this Anton syndrome
and people who are blind in fact and provably blind because they can't walk with obstacles
and such who insist that they can see.
Now this is and of course it's often referred to as a state of confabulation so they're
making excuses for their blindness but even the most absurd circumstances they'll go
to absurd lengths and insist that they can see.
So now I wonder okay are they conscious of seeing what what's going on in that situation?
David do you have any thoughts on that?
I think that they could have conscious visual states and but it's a tricky thing and people
in the consciousness racket debate some about this but my own view is since so here's a
visual state and just by itself it isn't conscious it will be responsive to stimulate
but that's all.
Then there will be what I call a high order awareness of the state that is to say the
individual will be aware of being in the state one will be aware of oneself as being
in the state.
So this is a separate state so now you can take away that and then you would still have
some kind of visual awareness right without the so that is to say you would be aware
of yourself as seeing you would be aware of yourself as being in the visual state even
though in more in fact as we as you mentioned biologically we know that there is no visual
state but that's not the way it is for the individual right and I don't see any reason
why this wouldn't be the case I think with these end tons patients it's a bit of a question
how fine-grained it is and what the nature of the visual consciousness is but it seems
as though this particular model of what it is for psychological functioning to be conscious
provides a very nice explanation of what's going on.
So you're the patient you described sounds more like Charles Monet.
I'm sorry sounds more like the Charles Monet syndrome that Richard and Hocklawn.
Oh yes right there's a lesion of visual cortex and the person still has these vision that
can report these visual experiences but what's the damage or what's the condition in the
end tons?
The neurological.
You know I'm not sure I know let's get to it.
So it's some disconnection between the fibers of travel from the occipital load towards the
temporal parietal load.
Okay.
Same basic kind of thing.
From the in terms of what we're talking about it's basically the same.
But it's interesting that they're so productive in I think in general we have a whole talk
on confabulation one day or at least I'll have one and I'll pretend all the rest of you
are here that it's very productive and I wonder about this idea that sort of like this gestalt
completion that concepts and sometimes actually create consciousness of some sort.
There's this great paper from the 90s looking at color space representations and congenitally
blind individuals versus sighted individuals and they you know sort color concepts as similar
and different and then you can use multidimensional scaling to infer what's seen as similar and
what's seen as different by people.
And what they find is that this is shepherd and kuber I think what they find is that congenitally
blind individuals have a representation of color space that's remarkably akin to sighted
individuals and so via language people are forming representations that are then shaping
some sort of conscious experience.
You know it was studies of confabulation and split brain patients that made me turn to
rats to study emotion.
So we studied these patients who's brain just split and have to control epilepsy and would
ask the left hemisphere which you could talk to why you did a certain behavior that had
been elicited from the right hemisphere.
So the left hemisphere has no internal information about what's in the right hemisphere but can
observe the behavior that's being produced and the left hemisphere would make up all
these narratives these explanations, confabulations to make it all make sense.
And so we were discussing this my mentor and I Mike Zanniger were discussing this and we
said well maybe emotion systems or something that would be generating behaviors non-consciously
that would require this kind of explanation.
So the light bulb went off in my head and I said okay and so I left once I left Mike's
lab I started doing rat research ended up in the amygdala and here we are today.
That's great.
Alright well I think we should open up for questions if people want to please one of the
time and please make sure it's a question and not a laboratory if you don't mind and
take it away.
Thank you so much I'm a big fan of the work for the African circles doing future in my
life.
Close to the mic please.
Mike, did you work now?
No.
So if you are right that Donald Trump might win a game on pressure.
The reason I say is that you know we have to talk about representations as well because
propaganda is extremely successful and we have to acknowledge we make people think a
specific thought at the same time billions of people can think that way and we all know
that conditioning works how low the experiments have proven that conditioning could be you
know is effective and an organism could be made to salivate on arbitrary things.
So my question is that knowing that Homo sapiens are tribal and the start is narcissists are
there any representations which can make us more humanistic more planetary conscious more
peace-loving more human rights-loathing.
Thank you.
Well we have to figure out how to make that appealing to people which apparently is not
anybody else has any bring into center.
I think attending the Elex Center.
But thank you for your comment.
Noah Harari in his popular in several senses of the word book sapiens talks about 70,000
years ago a consciousness revolution.
Have you read the book?
You know what I'm talking about?
Yeah well what do you ask as professionals really in the field?
What do you think of that concept?
Well if consciousness as we humans understand in our own particular way is part of our evolutionary
history as a species not necessarily as an animal then yeah maybe that's going to happen.
I mean that's a wild guess in terms of putting a number on that.
Yeah I was sort of wondering about the assessment of the data that Harari used to find that
out to claim it shall we say.
I think he's a great writer.
I'm not sure he's a great scientist in terms of all of this stuff.
Well.
Well thank you.
Even though we talk a lot about consciousness it seems to me that most cultures have also
developed techniques to become unconscious or at least unself-conscious such as Buddhism
seeks to become unself-conscious and connected in a form of unity where in other cases depersonalization
we're becoming unself-consciousness it's fractionated depersonalization so it can go
either way but one seems to be much better state than the other.
But in that regard can we look at death as a means, final means to assure unconsciousness.
The same way we use alcohol, drugs, dance, trance any other myth.
If I'm not mistaken Plato said he looked forward to death so that he could be pure conscious
or pure mind.
Back in 2016 I was so struck by Rudolfo Linas' comment about the improbability of cells
coming together for a multi-sality organism and remain then as a unified entity that it
struck me that would require a mechanism to make that happen that would be a turning point
and that mechanism you could begin to identify with consciousness provided you remove self-awareness
from consciousness and therefore if we thought of consciousness as first of all the unifying
element of what brings multi-cellularity into a unified being and then we humans came along
later and added the ability to turn that on ourselves and to understand our own consciousness.
So I wondered if you see that shift to multi-cellularity as being, even if you don't agree with my
connection with consciousness, if you see it as being like a fundamental turning point
in evolution, it must have led to a new set of characteristics coming about even if you
are not agreeing with them being called some of the being called consciousness.
That first step towards multi-cellularity, the formation of some kind of colonial organization,
in each lineage that has achieved that, it has achieved it by virtue of an extracellular
adhesive.
Now what's interesting to me is the fact that different lineages have used different materials
to accomplish adhesion.
I'll give you an example.
Almost all of the cells in your body are adhering because of transmembrane proteins called
cathearins.
The cells in the plant body are stuck together by virtue of pectins which are carbohydrates.
So our bodies are stuck together by proteins, plants are stuck together by carbohydrates.
And if you look at the metabolism of what a photosynthetic versus non-photocetic organism
does, it makes intuitive sense.
Carbohydrates are cheap.
Proteins are relatively easy to make because of the physiology of the animal.
So that's not consciousness because every unicellular ancestor has used the adhesive
for a different purpose.
So for example, you think of unicellular things as well, they don't stick together.
Well, of course they do.
If reproduction requires two cells to come together, they have to adhere.
And they're using that adhesive to form the colonial organism.
So contingency and a co-option, co-opting the use of something as an adhesive here that
now gives you an adhesion here.
The real major step is not sticking together.
It's working together.
And our species has yet to accomplish that.
More scotch tape.
I feel like red tape.
Joe, I haven't yet had the pleasure of reading your book.
But would you perhaps characterize how your work differs from Antonio de Masios?
Because it seems to me to be the converse that you're suggesting.
Yeah, so Antonio and I have been on writing books about emotion and rougher at the same
amount of time.
And we have different perspectives that ultimately come together in terms of the higher levels.
So for him, he started out by saying that the somatic marker hypothesis, which is the
idea that body signals, somatic signals that reach the brain, are interpreted as defining
the emotion.
So my view is that those signals are important in modulating the experience of it not defining.
So that's the main distinction.
But Antonio had an interesting component to that, which he called the aziflu.
So if you don't have the body states, you can conceptualize, you can simulate it.
And for me, all emotions are these kinds of simulations rather than predetermined events.
And if I may just one other question, perhaps the brain is a distributed system.
Beyond what's in the skull, of course, it started with a gut.
The tube was the first brain that's evolved subsequently.
And of course, there's a lot of work now going on around microbiome.
In fact, work with rats, reared in a sterile environment, having a propensity to be more
anxious than those with a stable, healthy gut microbiome.
In fact, plants have just come up with a conference where it's discovered that tiny
filaments and plant roots that actually co-op bacteria in to do work with them and then expel
them out into the environment later on.
Is it perhaps that the brain is a distributed system, the amygdala perhaps part of it, but
it's much broader, challenge than that?
Well, there is, I guess, a distributed processing within the brain.
I don't know.
I mean, it seems much of what you mean exactly.
What I'm talking about is, in fact, a lot of work is going on at the moment about gut
brain access, anxiety as a function of dysbiosis in the gut.
Oh, you mean that the body is a distributed system in the brain?
I'm talking about actually the ecology of microorganisms in the gut being another community
that's contributing to the concept of intelligence.
I mean, you know, it could use intelligence.
Oh, anxiety.
You're right, yes.
So, I mean, I agree, I mean, we're doing some work on the microbiome now.
Okay.
So, I think it's all one system, obviously, and I think the brain is special, but I'm
biased.
Thanks.
I mean, just to put this into perspective about the history of life, we can think of
the amygdala as a continuation of that first bacterial cell that had to detect and respond
to danger.
It's the, I'm not saying the amygdala itself, but the circuits within the amygdala that
detect and respond to danger are just a continuation of that, that protective survival imperative
that we have.
And so the amygdala and other parts of the brain that do those kinds of things are just
allowing a big multicellular organism accomplish those goals.
If I can add to that, absolutely, I agree.
We used to think of plant, a tree as a separate organism.
And now our ecological evolutionary perspective is, well, yes, it's an individual that will
have a life in death.
And individuality is another concept that's somewhat difficult to define.
But we now know that those trees are actually interconnected to neighboring trees by Michael
Rizy and bacterial colonies, and that they're actually capable of exchanging nutrients.
And that is that one tree that is overproducing can actually contribute to the carbohydrate
gain of another and sharing minerals and things of that.
So you know, this integrated phenotype, what is the individual from an evolutionary or
a biological point of view?
It's really a fascinating topic.
What about the idea that we're just here to support bacterians?
Yeah.
No comment.
Hi.
Forgive me, I have not read your book, but I was thoroughly interested in coming here.
I guess I have a two-part question.
The first is from the description itself.
It says, emotions you concluded in your book result from our efforts to make sense of the
significant moments in our lives.
And forgive me if I missed it.
I don't recall your, could you comment on that?
So preceding that, I'm trying to reconstruct where that sentence came from, but preceding,
is that from the description here?
Yes.
In the book, that idea is preceded by the fact that we have these biological systems
that control our survival activities in terms of finding food, mates, balancing fluids,
finding liquids, and so forth, and all of these things that are important in the ecology
of daily life, and emotions are a conscious awareness of those significant things, and
putting those significant things out of biological context, not that psychology is in biological,
but allowing us to experience what we're doing when we have these biologically significant
moments.
Thank you.
And so this also goes to the gentleman next to you, but obviously for anybody, the psychopharmacologist,
and you just mentioned, I guess, the juxtaposition between, you said not that psychology is not
biological.
So my question had to do with what effect does the taking of, let's say, multiple psychopharmacological
drugs, not only for anxiety, but mood stabilizers, a whole bunch, and in the long term, et cetera,
have on perception and behavior.
And we're talking about humans here.
That's a small question, I guess it depends on what medicines or what agents you're talking
about.
I think that most concise way to respond to that would be...
Forgive me for interrupting, because before you did, you did a really good job of saying,
well, these psych or any sort of measure, anxiety meds cannot change your thinking, but you
were talking about the suicide warning.
I wouldn't say they can't change...
Well, they don't implant ideas in your mind.
That's for sure.
They could change the way you think about things in important ways.
But what I was about to say, which I think is the most concise way to respond to you and
to the concern about what are the...
You didn't say adverse, but it's implied, I guess, adverse effects are taking lots of
bills over time.
We're just the effect.
Okay.
Because they don't do studies on it.
The...
Especially you're right, when it's multiple meds, they certainly don't.
All I'll say is that a person's ability to function, be creative, be alert, sleep well,
make up, have energy, all of those things, those factors are more important in the long
run than the number of medicines you take.
So the bad outcome would be someone who's taking lots of medicines and they are thereby
very impaired in terms of their alertness or their cognition and so forth.
And they shouldn't be on all those medicines.
But when people really...
It requires a careful analysis and a discussion and it's not something that necessarily can
happen in one quick session.
But in the long term, looking at how well that person is sort of fitting into their
lives and I call it just generally a healthy way, then typically with a few exceptions
based on blood tests you have to get once in a while, typically the effects are good.
That's what I would say.
Okay.
There are lots of exceptions to it, but watching the overall sort of functional state of the
individual is more important.
I guess one perfect example would be there's a short one, it's only one type of medicine.
There was a great viewer that rose a few years back because of a study that said benzodiazepines
cause dementia.
And I felt that study wasn't well done and there was a follow-up study, large multi-institution
study that found that no, the connection was false.
Okay, it may yet still be debatable, but I do know this.
Anxiety in the elderly is a very strong risk factor for dementia.
Okay.
So when you confront, well now you have to make a choice.
And there are important choices.
There are ways to do it intelligently, but it would be wrong to assume that the medicine
necessarily is going to happen negative outcome, and net, so.
Okay.
Thank you.
Sure.
As I was listening, I was on the various themes here.
I was trying to put it in a context of some other research in a different field, and perhaps
Joseph and Kristen might come in on this.
A quorum sensing in bacteria and the ideas of how bacteria, first of all, are not solitary,
they're social, and that took a long time for the field to come to that conclusion and
the research to start from that as the foundation.
And similarly, consciousness is social, it's not solitary.
I mean there's the solitary expression of it within an individual, but that's still mediated
by all of the other influences that have been social.
And the one thing that sort of hit me when we talk about the consciousness and developmentally
around two and three years old, well you know, the terrible twos, the tantrums.
If I don't get my way, I'm going to start screaming.
Well, when that stops, and the child becomes more pro-social, that's when the consciousness
component of it develops.
So I think that that's a very interesting thing to start looking at.
Okay, responses?
Anything to say about quorum?
Well, I can respond only in terms of the comment about bacteria, and that is it's very interesting
because quorum sensing in bacteria, we think, is a mechanism to gauge the availability
of nutrients in the environment.
So by sensing the size of the population and the extent to which the population might be
growing or diminishing, that is a feedback as to the availability of nutrients for the
collective.
What's interesting to me is that in a lot of bacteria, the molecule that's used for quorum
sensing, which is endolicitic acid, or IAA, is used by plants as a signaling molecule
to go from the tips of leaves and the tips of roots and the tips of stems.
So it's a beautiful example of where quorum sensing in the mechanism that was used by
bacteria is now been highly elaborated and sophisticated in terms of now communicating
amongst the cells within the plant body.
Great.
I want to make one quick announcement after our next question, which has to be our last
one.
We're going to have the pleasure of listening to, I don't know if you know this, but Joe
is a music app performer and he's going to put on a small performance for us in the guitar.
Should I go?
Yes, regarding the consciousness of vision, in the words of great culture, and the words
of great cognitive scientist Stevie Wonder, just because a man cannot see does not mean
he does not have a great vision.
It's working, but seriously, folks, human designed experiments, one person smiles.
Human designed experiments have shown that species as greatly separated from us as birds
can figure out human designed puzzles and strategize and plan ahead knowing that if they
figure out a multi-step puzzle, they'll get to the reward, the food.
We know that dogs can dream, we know a dog will sacrifice its own life to save a human
being.
And I believe there are documented cases of urban cats jumping out of high rises, knowingly
that they're jumping to their deaths because of disturbances in a loud noise in the city.
So my question is when humans design experiments to test the animals of consciousness, when
it's obvious to a lot of people that they do, isn't this, you know, what we're talking
about here today, isn't this really more anthropomorphic chauvinism than science?
As we said, if all we needed was intuition, we wouldn't need to do science, but it's
difficult, it may be impossible to know what's on the mind of another animal.
But no one's saying that the experiments we design are designed by using our own biases.
Right.
I don't do those, sir.
Yes, I think.
Well, this is a quick one.
Yeah, quick, wait a second.
C.C.N.Y.
Sorry?
Yes.
Okay.
Can I have a second?
Yes.
Yeah.
I'm that old.
C.C.M.Y.
Okay.
Human beings, Homo stapiens have been on this earth for about 200,000 years.
We're also hybrids.
We're Neanderthals, decibens, and perhaps some other species.
We're a brand new species.
Only in the last 10,000 years have we created civilization and now technology.
And ways to kill ourselves.
And one of the people here who spoke, one of the gentlemen, talked about this may be
the end.
And yet it may be the end.
And can we fix it?
Well, we are evolved monkeys.
We are evolved chimpanzees.
If you look at chimpanzees, they're always after each other, there's a male, alpha male,
and they're fighting, they're killing, and so on.
The question is, what can we do with ourselves as humans, as Homo sapiens, to change that
aspect of ourselves which is built into us?
Does anyone have an answer?
Find a common enemy.
That's us.
Yeah.
I can't think of any one, you know, a quick response to that because I just think that
there are so many ways, there are so many ways in which that can be affected for the better.
But it's through too many things to enumerate, I'm sorry to say.
And again, I was joking about the healing center, but having general discussions of this sort,
and it's a little bit of a joke, but not extending humanism as a sort of a guiding tool.
It's a good way to do that.
So, with that, as soon as we're all set.
All right, if anyone wants to get up and leave, you can do that now.
No hard feelings.
Please take your time.
So, I'm only going to play three short songs.
We were originally supposed to have a larger group here, but we couldn't get everybody
together, so we canceled the whole thing.
Then at the last minute, I decided to do something I never do, which is performed by myself.
So, let's see how that goes.
All right, so we have a band called the Immig Deloids.
We invented our own genre called Heavy Mental, which is music about mind and brain and mental
disorders.
And we've actually played here for the New York psychoanalytic Christmas party once upstairs.
There's a video on the web, and that's just came across.
All right, I'm going to do a song called My Mind's Eye.
If you look into my mind's eye, you would see the way that I cry deep inside in my mind's
eye.
We had love.
It was good.
You were there.
You understood everything.
Yes, everything.
I can't always trust what you think you know.
Can't trust what you believe.
Sometimes your mind just puts on a show.
It's simply disease.
And my mind's eye, you were mine, but my mind's eye was blonde.
If you look into my mind's eye, you would see the way that I cry deep inside in my mind's
eye.
Can't always trust what you think you know.
Can't trust what you believe.
Sometimes your mind just puts on a show.
It's simply disease.
My mind's eye, you were mine, but my mind's eye was blonde.
My mind's eye was blonde.
Oh, yeah.
Okay, thank you.
So sometimes when I write a book, I write songs that go with the book, and that's what
we're going to play here today.
And some of this has electronic music and so forth, which obviously we won't have today.
So I'm just going to do one song from the book, which is called Life.
There are four songs in the book.
One is called As soon as there is Life, There's Danger.
And another is about, these are kind of dystopian, either beginning of the world or into the
world songs, except this one, which is about beginning and end of life.
Oh, I just...
All of the things that I think about are all so things that I think that I doubt.
I can't keep straight all the things in my mind.
Too many thoughts and too little time in life.
Life.
The states of mine, they come and go.
Sometimes fast and sometimes slow.
Some leave a trace in my brain.
Others just wax and wane in life.
Life.
life.
Life, life, life, life.
Thank you.
Thank you, thank you.
Thanks, Kristen, Carl, David, and Gerald.
And the Helix Center.
And Miguel back there in the booth.
Okay.
Thank you.
You're a large 14-year-old boy.