...
wise
evidoring
I'm Ed Nursece in Director of the Center.
Before we get going on today's program that was proposed by Beverly Zabriski and Harold
Atman Sparkers, I'd like to tell you what we are planning for spring of next year.
So far we have planned three round tables.
One will be on data versus this course, humanity is in the age of big data.
The other would be on the ethics of AI, machine learning, and the last one would be on the
general subject of memory looked at from various perspectives.
Beverly will take over from this point and introduce the speakers.
Thank you.
Let's see.
Let me do this way.
Welcome, welcome.
The persons in this room are one of the three audiences for this program.
There is also a live stream audience and there will also be a YouTube audience going
through the years.
So remember that if you get up and ask a question or make a remark, you will be recorded out
at infinitum and that's taken as a release that we are allowed to use your question
and your presence in the YouTube video.
So welcome to all three audiences to this day.
I'm a Jungian analyst at Gave Me Permission to say that in this hallowed building and
tells you what an ecumenical mind he has.
And Jung said that if he ever came back to another life, he would study prime numbers.
That's how he would spend his time.
And he urged all of his followers to do so.
I have not done so.
So the closest I get to understanding mathematics is by being around minds like in this circle.
And so I think that's a pleasure we'll all have today.
So thank you all for agreeing to come and to be with us and Alma, especially to you.
You stepped in the last minute because Stephanie was ill.
So thank you.
Alma did not intend to be here this morning and here she is.
And she's a great lady.
So Harold and I were talking about this as a possibility and he suggested the title
Mathematics and Other Reality.
So that's what we'll be speaking about today.
And it's a spontaneous conversation.
There's been no preparation.
And it's meant to be scholars and intellectuals who hear each other and then get into an exchange.
Harold is a senior scientist at the Collegium Helvetium at the University of Zurich and
the Polytechnic in Zurich.
After a PhD in physics at Munich, he worked as a research scientist at the Max Planck Institute
for extraterrestrial physics.
Then he served as head of the theory group at the Institute for Frontier Areas of Psychology
at Freiburg.
This fields of research are the theory of complex systems, conceptual and theoretical
aspects of quantum theory and mind matter relations.
He's the president of the Society for Mind and Matter Research and editor in chief of the
interdisciplinary journal Mind and Matter.
Last summer I went to Harold's conference on the Science of Consciousness in Interlochen.
He said it was one of their smallest conferences, it was 620 scientists from around the world
discussing the matter of consciousness and where it emerges from and scientific perspectives
on that.
And Switzerland, we like to keep everything small.
We're a small country, after all.
And then Amma Steingaard.
Herages the interplay between politics and mathematical rationality.
Her second book, Accountable Democracy, Mathematical Reasoning and Representative Democracy in America,
1920 to Now, examines how mathematical thought and computing technologies have impacted electoral
politics in the U.S. in the 20th century.
She investigates how changing computational practices from statistical modeling to geometrical
analysis insinuated themselves into the most basic definitions of fair representation of
the American electorate.
Nothing could be more timely than what you're working on.
In pure abstraction, mathematical thought and high modernism forthcoming.
She investigates the influence of axiomatic reasoning on mid-century American intellectual
thought.
She's a junior fellow of the Harvard Society of Fellows and a pre-doctoral research fellow
with the Max Planck Institute in Berlin.
Pardon me?
I was a junior fellow.
I'm now in Columbia.
All right.
So, yes, that's true.
You are now a professor at Columbia that was not added to this.
Thank you.
Michael Harris has become a mainstay intellect of the Helix group here.
He's a professor of mathematics at Columbia and is on extended leave from the University
Perry D. Duro where he taught for 20 years.
He was professor of Brandeis, got his PhD from Harvard.
He's organized and co-organized more than 20 conferences and workshops.
In his field of number theory and until 2018 directed the European Research Council Project,
arithmetic of automorphic motives.
Fantastic.
I have to find out what it means, but I know it's fantastic.
He's been a visiting professor at Bethlehem University in Palestine.
He's been an exchange scholar at the Stecholov Institute in Moscow.
He's initiated the project of science for people in Nicaragua and London Paris number
theory seminar.
His book, Mathematics Without Apologies won the Prose Award in Mathematics.
He is a contributions to the Langlands program.
Maybe you'll tell us what that is.
He won the Grand Prix Sophie's Jormendow, Blocademy in Sciences in 2006.
That he asked me to condense his introduction because it was not too long, so many accomplishments.
Harry Field is a silver professor and university professor at NYU.
Before that he taught at Princeton, USC and CUNY Graduate Center.
He's the author of Science Without Numbers, Expanded Edition, and Saving Truth from Paradox.
As well as numerous articles in the philosophy of mathematics and logic.
His Science Without Numbers defends the view that one can develop physics without assuming
the existence of mathematical entities.
He's been working in the philosophy of mathematics, less on the existence of mathematical entities,
and more on the objectivity of mathematics, which you're going to prove today.
Chris McDonald.
McDaniel has a BA in Philosophy from Western Washington University.
His PhD in Philosophy is from University of Massachusetts Amherst.
He's been teaching at Syracuse University until 2019 and is now professor of Philosophy
at Notre Dame.
His publications include the books The Fragmentation of Being and this is metaphysics, which is
forthcoming.
Topics in metaphysics, ethics in the history of philosophy.
Welcome, Chris.
Marcus.
He's one of the founders of New Realism.
He studied in Heidelberg, Lisbon, New York.
He has held the chair since 2009 for epistemology, modern and contemporary philosophy at the University
of Bonn.
And at his appointment, he became Germany's youngest philosophy professor.
Now I just heard you upstairs tell the others that now there's a younger one.
The mathematics, he also won a fields medalist at my university, he was hired one month
after me, so I was the youngest full professor at my university for one month.
And then Peter Fausberg was hired at the age of 21 and just won the fields medal last year,
so apparently you go tired.
Yeah, so that's the reality of mathematics.
Someone comes along younger, right?
He's also the director of the International Center for Philosophy in Bonn as well as the
Multidisciplinary Center for Science and Thought.
He's held faculty in visiting positions at many different universities, including NYU,
and he's written popular books about philosophical issues.
His book Why the World Does Not Exist has been translated into 14 languages.
Sometimes we wish that was right, right?
So I would now, after this long pause, ask Harold to open up the discussion and thank
you for your patience.
On this round table, you will hear a lot about the term ontology and ontology as opposed
to epistemology.
So I thought it might be a good idea to start with a very brief, maybe anecdotal piece,
which illustrates to everybody what ontology is all about, what epistemology is all about,
and then we might go from there.
In my example, my anecdote of course comes from the history of my own fields from physics.
It goes back to the early 1930s, it goes to Ireland to Dublin because at that time I
was working at Dublin and he was often visited by his physicist colleagues, like in this
case, Erwin Wehrner Heisenberg and Paul Dirac.
So Heisenberg and Dirac just took a little walk after the lunch out of Dublin in the hills,
I hope, and then they come over such a hill and in the valley they see a huge herd of sheep.
And Heisenberg says, look Dirac, these sheep are all shorn and Dirac, he was known as a
very meticulous thinker, so he had to analyze the statement before he could answer.
And then he said, well Heisenberg, at least on this side.
So you see, this is about being and knowing, right?
So I don't think I have to explain that, but being, this is the notion of philosophy which
ontology deals with.
So ontology is about existence, whenever you make an existence statement and philosophy
this is about ontology.
Whenever you make a knowledge statement it's about epistemology.
And I think many sciences in the 20th century have seen a tendency to build up an ontology
which many of them call a fundamental ontology, which in physics would be about the existence
of particles as kind of building blocks for the universe and everything else.
Like for instance, biology, genes or even up to neuroscience is actually in some way,
in one way or another reducible to these particles.
Even though this program is of course not completed, but the assumption is in principle
this is the way to go.
And you know, when I still was a student I had a PhD advisor who could still tell me
that chemistry is not yet understood physics.
So the hope was really to take all of chemistry back into physics.
And the research program for instance of microbiology or molecular biology is set up in the same
spirit, just produced in the smaller parts.
In the neuroscience there is the neuron doctrine where people think that you can understand
everything in the brain once you understand how the neurons operate and cooperate.
So this research program is the program in all these fields to build up the kind of fundamental
ontology, we have the notion of ontology.
So there's only one fundamental sort of beings and everything can be reduced to that.
Now interestingly the second half of the 20th century voices here and there came up and
these voices became one more who sort of doubted that this is really working.
So we see today a kind of development in which people at least in the natural sciences, that's
what I can talk about really started out this notion of fundamental ontology.
And talking about fundamental of course raises immediately a resonance with fundamentalism
in much broader sense.
So this round table is also at least to some extent a round table that could be, I don't
know how it works, how it will develop, it could be a kind of critique or traces of a
critique of fundamentalism generally.
I mean in physics and in the sciences we see that anyway.
And I'm really curious to hear from all of you how you think about that.
You want to do a round?
Sure.
Yeah.
Well yeah I can say a few words about the meaning of those terms, how I understand them
and then how this relates to this claim that you flack that the world does not exist which
is short hand or like a slogan for saying that we shouldn't even be foundationalists
in ontology itself which I think is not identical to physics.
But just a few words about that how at least I understand those terms.
So I think ontology is the systematic investigation into the meaning of existence or depending
on your methodology just into existence.
Right?
So it might be a good idea to think about the meaning of existence, statements to approach
existence.
So that would be a good methodology that's why I'm saying it or just into existence.
And epistemology is the discipline which deals with the nature and scope of what we can
know about what there is.
However I think that of course the two cannot be thoroughly separated because trivially
knowledge exists.
Right?
So and what we've learned from just the development of modern natural science is precisely that
there's a sense in which the universe insuffides the observable universe is somehow intimately
tied to its nobility by creatures such as us for the trivial reason that our best and
maybe only way but you will tell me about that to know anything about the observable
universe is by way of interfering with it.
Right?
By intervening.
That's you know you don't know the universe a priori maybe there's something that you
know about the universe without experiments such as that the universe is the universe
or maybe some more demanding things but anyhow so you know I think that one of the things
that we actually learn from the development of modern science is that we need to take
into account that no one exists within the universe.
So this is something that I would also like to discuss with some people here.
Right?
There seem to be paradigm cases of very demanding knowledge claims where we precisely cannot
just distinguish between epistemology and ontology in that neat way.
Oh well I have opinions about the universe but none of them is legitimated by my professional
expertise I'm going to keep them to myself.
And instead I'm going to talk about what existence might mean to a mathematician because
it's a word that is used systematically and yet as I've thought about this for some time
I in its use the use entails no metaphysical commitment whatsoever.
This is certainly how I understand it now there are versions or interpretations of the foundations
of mathematics say a hundred years ago people might have thought differently that it is
a need to found mathematics on something that's metaphysically transparent but not so many
people think that way anymore and when the word existence is so that a typical mathematical
statement begins the theorem there exists such and such.
Another typical opening for mathematical statement is let X be something.
When you analyze that of course this is just really a performative gesture that is saying
this is how one opens the discussion if you analyze that's an imperative.
Now who is to whom is that imperative addressed?
It's nobody who is reading it is going to object or is going to prevent this X from
existing.
So this is just a way of talking and you might say that mathematicians have managed
to develop a coherent system of communication in the absence in spite of the disadvantages
of natural language the fact that.
So that's a first approach and the other thing I would say is that at least over the past
well maybe 50, 70 years mathematics has been increasingly the practice of mathematics has
been increasingly dominated especially in my field of number theory by the fact that
our imaginations are expectations have outrun our ability to verify them.
So there are large programs in which people are working.
The aim of which is to construct objects whose existence in whatever sense one wants
to mean that and again I don't think it's metaphysically very significant but the existence
has been anticipated.
So there's a that's to say there's a there are series of conjectures that such and such
as structure should be invoked to explain the what has already been studied in terms
of something more.
So this is this is a this is a different this part of the discussion I don't want to get
into it but something that one might call more fundamental although in a sense it's the opposite
of more fundamental as that would be used by the physicists.
So for example Peter Scholzem was given this position became the youngest professor in
Germany on the basis of his contributions to constructing a theory kind of theory that
had been anticipated that explain many many of the phenomena that had been or the mathematical
theorems that had been developed.
So I think I should just stop there.
Sure.
I'm I have to say I guess the two things that I want to say isn't I come to I'm an historian
so I come to this question for a little bit from a different perspective.
What I'm interested in is the question how question of existence ideas about ontology
and specific specifically in mathematics have changed over time.
So what Michael was just talking about the question about foundation right we know that
interest in the foundation of mathematics really at the end of the 19th century and the 10th
or 20th century really start because of the discovery of non Euclidean geometry right.
So part of what interests me is how new mathematical developments new idea new research project
call into question what are already kind of existing assumptions that people and mostly
are both philosophers but they're also thinking about mathematicians himself are thinking.
So this is kind of the the question that interests me is how this idea is about ontology and
post-emology change over time in relation to research itself.
And then to get to this question that you're saying about the ontology and epistemology
I was very interesting because one of the things that I've been thinking about for a
long time is that in a way in mathematics there is no distinction between ontology and
epistemology I mean I know I'm saying I know it's a big claim and I'm throwing it on purpose
out there but if you take something let's take something like that notion that there
exists a four dimensional object right.
For years for centuries mathematicians did not acknowledge that this is something that's
even possibility it's only in the 19th century that this idea that the four dimensional space
right exists comes along and then first how mathematicians learn to think about the four
dimension also then shapes what is the existence of a four dimension is.
There's a way in which the way people think about ontology and the way of thinking about
ontology are so linked in mathematics and I'm surrounded by philosophers so I kind of
want to throw that back at you you know how to make that distinction historically and even
right now.
So I don't do philosophy in mathematics but I am interested in existence so I assume
that's why I was invited here.
So I think that's maybe one thing it's a couple questions just as a person coming to the
outside of this that maybe I'll just enter into the discussion or downstream people to
consider.
How do we tell when we are using a notion of existence that is metaphysically committal
or not?
You might think when you're doing mathematics you don't care whether or not it is the day
the numbers that you're talking about or the functions or what not really exist that might
be something that's not relevant to your concerns as a practicing mathematician but you might
still wonder does the fact that I don't care mean that I'm not using a notion of existence
as committal or is it that I just don't care whether I am using a committal notion?
I hope you said.
May I interject because I have a it's not a joke.
It's a true story.
I was one of the reasons I'm here is the first things that happened.
My career is a mathematician who was invited to talk about things other than mathematics.
I was invited to review a book for the notices of the American mathematical society.
In the book I made me I had to read a fair amount of philosophy including Heidegger at
the time which...
Did you say Heidegger?
Heidegger, yes.
Heidegger.
It was written by a mathematician but he well well...
Heidegger studied mathematics people who forget that.
He was an utterly agree mathematics and theology which kind of explains what's going on.
So while I was thinking about this I was at a conference in minster and I was sitting
at a table speaking beer with some of my colleagues and they were discussing the reality
of the continuum.
There was a German and American and a French.
This is a true story.
This is one of these things that you can't make up.
So the Frenchmen said and didn't believe the real numbers existed.
These are all very successful mathematicians by the way.
And they all work in numbers theory.
The Frenchmen said no he just doesn't believe it.
It doesn't stop him from working with them.
The Germans said well he doesn't believe that they exist individually but as a...
As a collective.
They had some sort of collective existence.
And the Americans said not only do they exist but he can show you one anytime you come to
his computer screen he can just make them exist.
So all of them are doing mathematics, the same kind of mathematics reading Joseph's papers.
When that sense I would say if there's a fit metaphysical commitment it's something
that escapes any of the people who would supposedly be committed.
And so I would say that if a commitment is not conscious it doesn't count.
One of the things the last three or so comments bring out is this idea you started in like
by mentioning that some objects are positive.
Some seem to be discovered based on mathematical research.
Others one starts by positive.
So even the idea as you say I'm a four dimensional space was originally sort of put out there
as a almost like a prescriptive.
And then later it seems to be an existence and maybe that's a little bit about what you
were talking about at the beginning.
There's this edge between the being of it, the positing of it and then the discovery
of it which is more of a epistemological issue I suppose.
So Chris look what you provoked.
Do you want to actually carry on?
Maybe part of the good change.
So I liked the idea of physics as fundamental that Harold started with.
In in in in particular the idea that particles in fields are fundamental which seems to have
gone out in recent versions of recent news about quantum mechanics.
I also liked Michael's idea that in mathematics.
So entities don't exist in the same way that physical entity to do that.
That existence in mathematics is a special.
My early work was trying to put these together.
So there's no there's no problem when you just consider pure mathematics of just saying
well basically any consistent theory is fine.
There is an issue though about the applications of mathematics.
And so in particular people there there was a time at least when when when people argued
that the same reasons for for believing in particles and fields also were reasons for
believing in the existence of mathematical entities because the idea was that the reason
for believing in mathematical entities is that all our business theories postulate them.
But all our best theories are foreign related to the heavy mathematical language so they
also postulate mathematical entities and so some same same argument that applied to particles
in the fields all to apply to mathematical entities.
So I didn't like Chris conclusion.
I wanted Michael to see you that basically in whatever sense mathematical entities exist
is just because there's a consistent theory in in faulting them.
So a bunch of my work has been trying to reconcile these two things and the in the initial stage
it was trying to show that you can actually formulate the physical theories without positive
stability mathematical entities and in more recent years it's kind of taken a different
turn but the but it reconciled the views that the two of you mentioned it's been sort of
a major project of my work in philosophy of mathematics.
Let me just relate to what the mathematicians sort of speak but the idea of non-committal
or something when you talk to you mentioned that conference in Talaqah last year.
One of the keynote speakers there was I guess who Roger Panros is actually both he is an
accomplished mathematician and an accomplished physicist and Roger Panros I mean he's completely
clear about his belief that mathematical objects exist and not only in the sense of
let X be or something like that.
Ten years earlier we had a conference with Alar Khan.
Alar Khan is a totally serious about mathematical objects exist out there and this is interesting
also with respect to another debate the debate between the question is mathematics discovered
or is it invented and of course all these people have written a lot about this and I
only want to say that it seems to me simply due to the existence of these people that
somehow the question is still unresolved.
And I mean as you know their physicists like whatever you know David Doyle is George Ellis
who now say mathematical objects are the prime cause of force for the universe.
I mean George things causation is primarily from mathematical objects to the material
energetic system of the universe and it's not that he's an either an incompetent mathematician
or an incompetent physicist because he wrote the standard book about space time with Stephen
Hawking in 1973 so I think he knows what he's doing in the technical field but he believes
that right and David Doyle is also not like a zero figure in quantum computing and he
also argues that you know he thinks the major mistake that the philosophers that he surrounded
with that Oxford is that they do not get this so I think it is an interesting sociological
piece of evidence right so there are those and there are those mathematicians and physicists
right so that apparently it's not sufficient to be either a good mathematician or physicist
to just to finish what I wanted to say originally the idea was actually also to have Max Tegmark
here.
Max Tegmark has written this book you all know it in which he claims mathematics is not only
existing in the sense that it is a basis for physics but it also exists per se I mean he
the book's title is the mathematical universe it exists per se and every you know if you
would put kind of evolution of existence then mathematics would be the first thing that exists
in his belief I mean I'm only I'm only throwing this around you know it's a little bit hard
to buy I mean Max Tegmark is an extremist in this in this case but I don't know invention
or discovery.
Can I bring a back to history just because I always find it useful so I think that a
lot of the this this conversation about the issue at stake about discovery and not to say
the discovery and the relation between physics and mathematics in terms of existence is again
something that becomes a real problem only in the turn of the 19th century and early
20th century it was even if until then people believe that mathematics arise out of them
anyway arise out of the world right if a mathematical concept understood is an abstraction right
the notion of a fundamental triangle was an abstraction from you know all the individual
triangles that one have seen right that's the basic idea so if you think about mathematics
this way as mathematics existing abstract is something that comes from the world then the
notion that mathematics then applies to physics and that you need to be in the mathematics
and physics is not as problematic right it's only once at the turn of the 20th century
once you mathematicians and philosophers believe that mathematics is no longer bound
by the world if mathematical ideas are not just descriptive of what's out there then
the philosophical question about what's the relation between physical mathematics become
as troubling as it is for us today right so it's not to say there's an answer just to
say that that itself has history itself as kind of a history that's I think important
I think and I don't have the answer to that but I think that looking at what was the question
of the turn of century helps kind of think through a little bit about how we think about
this question about existence and the role of mathematics and I'll just say one more
words about it at the turn of the century mathematicians really I mean there are a lot
of mathematicians that really cared about it and the idea was so people like George Beacock
for example or Vaitland as well they were thinking about what is it now to say that mathematics
applies to physics right what does it say now to mathematics if mathematics doesn't
come out of the world it's not an abstraction for the world how can we think about it and
and the argument they end up making is that you know should say building on kind of a
kind of Hilbert idea of mathematics mostly but the argument that they end up making is
that the difference between a number and you know an electron is not one of kind but of
degree that it's all abstractions all the way out and write them in that there it is
and it's not that the numbers are in that terms are two different kinds so again this
is all things that have been contested at moment for particular reasons right so even
in even in the case of say mid-nineteenth century math like remind differentiable
manifolds so there's I mean if you really think that all that exists is physical space
in its contents there's so the way you standardly explain differentiable
manifolds introduces things that are not in the physical space because it it introduces
the attention spaces and so if you really think that all there is is physics then you
might think that well you you really need to be able to read read describe the mathematics
of differential geometry without going into the attention space but just using the curves
in the space itself and probably that can be done but there is at least a technical challenge
and so maybe maybe you think this challenges and really worth doing because because the
tangent space is a fairly simple idealization but but it just depends really on your attitude
to how much I do a station you are or are prepared to think is is okay
I'm wondering how often some of these formulas are used as analogies and if that's relevant
to what you were starting to say Chris in terms of the other realities that are somehow
related to all of these these ideas and elements can you say a bit more about what you mean
by analogy well I'm just I mean coming I know that there's all sorts of analogies that
are drawn from physics and drawn from mathematics by people like me who don't really know what
I'm talking about and yet I'm talking about something that has to do with existence and
experience and I thought you were sort of approaching that realm in what you were saying
earlier.
So the question I was at least trying to raise was a question of how we can tell whether
a theory is committed to some genuine entities or not and I was suggesting that it's not
sufficient to simply look at some practitioners who are disavowing commitment to say that the
theory isn't committed and maybe the kind of antidote that you were alluding to do with
people that you both mentioned further illustrate that point because you can have successful
theoreticians who disagree on whether or not the theory is committed to the entities in
question.
And so I think it takes a bit of work to figure out what actually are the metaphysical
consequences of a given theory whether it's in mathematics or physics or what not it's
it could be that there are some people that don't care about that and so it's irrelevant
to the primary things that they're working on.
And let me add that you know like you need a lot of philosophical theorizing right to
state exactly what is at stake when you ask for instance say the discovery versus invention
of the section so there's a very broad tendency and I think this is a mistake in ontology.
So it's as it were not an obvious real mistake but you know it's a mistake that many people
make I call this an e-fontalogical realism so according to an e-fontalogical realism you
think that you're really committed to something that it really exists if it's mind independent
right so you think of it in terms of you know how things were before they were minds or how
things are if you abstract away from the fact that their minds right so remarkably you
think that the hallmark of existence is what I call the world without spectators take the
spectators out and what's left that exists right that is I think problematic to the as
a criterion for existence trivially because minds exist right so if your views their minds
they should matter and then there's matter and that this shouldn't be mental and whatever
is on this side is the existence stuff and the other thing is kind of either non-existent
or has to emerge supervene or do things that are not fully existing I think then you already
got into like philosophical trouble and some ways of formulating some versions of formulating
the discovery versus invention distinction for mathematical objects or in other fields
you know fictional objects have similar you know very similar problems you know dream
objects you know dream of a certain unicorn you know then you know did you discover the
unicorn or did you invent it you know they're similar problems there and I think that quite
often you know if we don't settle these purely philosophical issues beforehand then we get
easily confused I think that's really a contribution that philosophy will make there and you need
to be you know why right you need to be like a trained ontologist to be like a really good
mathematician or physicist these are you know orthogonal capacities I think yeah yeah well
in physics usually the practicing physicists is not concerned with these questions at all
in in most cases I mean in philosophy of physics we have exceptions of course right but the
practicing physicist if you ask him around ontology he will just he will either not understand
you or he will close the door and keep you outside you know because he is just he goes into his
lab in the morning switches on the pumps and makes his spectra and then he analyzes them
and that's that's the work of 99.9% of people working in physics then there is this remaining
point one percent who are actually interested in these philosophical questions and then
you know the advent of quantum mechanics actually erased the attention of this point
one percent you know because in quantum mechanics the first time in the history of physics the
measurement itself becomes a problem that it didn't happen before and why is this so
it is so because I don't know I don't go into all these formal details but conceptually
speaking it is so that the state of a system that you measure has to be understood differently
from the state of the system as it exists on tickle before you measure it and that the
additional complication is once you measure the system you extract information so this
is an epistemic process but at the same point you act back on the system so that it becomes
so that it moves into a state of being the on tick state in which it was not before so
the information that you extract is actually already outdated outdated when you read it
out somehow and that's that's a complication that you that you never had before and that
drove people crazy in physics in the early in the early days of quantum mechanics until
in the 1970s some philosophers of physics Ehrhard Schuyber and others came up and really saw
how they can conceptually solve this riddle with the introduction of on tick and epistemic
states which is now when you go to perimeter institute and other institutions everybody
talks about Scientology and scientist dimension this is this has become a standard notion
in the interpretation of quantum mechanics an interesting case actually because they
are it becomes important otherwise you confuse everything all the time if you don't make
that distinction and of I don't know whether this is now really a and a philosophic whether
this is a distinction that philosophers might understand as something that has really to
do with ontology and epistemology or whether this is again only another kind of practical
use of the notions you see what I mean so I don't know the issue about measurement was
different I mean even even pre quantum I mean measurements do always disturb the system
I mean and you can say okay well well you can reduce the disturbance to a small amount
more more than you can in quantum mechanics I agree completely but I think disturbance
by measurement is certainly not itself novel but I would have thought of this is the real
problem about measurement in quantum mechanics is that the early formulations of the theory
took it as this this special process that wasn't quantum mechanically explained so so
there was supposed to be this more or less general law of quantum evolution but then it
was supposed to be broken by measurement even though measurement presumably is a physical
process so so how how could it could could it measurement break the general laws and
I think I think around the same I do I do think that in in recent years there have have
become attempts to to to resolve this problem I think I would have cited John Dell as the
business that made the greatest contribution talk about these measurements now we can reduce
the interaction to an extent that is almost becomes invisible anymore but I agree with
you completely measurement is always an interaction that's right right but in quantum mechanics
it turned out as a problem and you know of course you are right that the measurement
does not follow the laws of unitary evolution that's what you're mentioning you need a different
law or at least it at least in the early theories they both said that law didn't hold but also
didn't offer a serious alternative law that did hold I don't want to emphasize too much
but let me just mention why I still think that it is an important conceptual difference
because what you come up with a quality is I mean the important insight that sequence
of measurements makes a difference we call it non-commutativity of observations and so
on that can be easily understood actually by the fact that when you make a measurement
and you change the state then you make the second measurement of another observable then
you make that measurement already on another state which means that when you when you
invert the sequence of measurements different result right in that sense it becomes important
and really at the basis even at the mathematical basis of the theory let me get back to mathematics
that to say even starting when you talk about measurement then pretty much all the time
you are talking about a measurement with respect to a theory which is based upon properties
of the real number of course real we are talking about reality nothing is more real
nor less real than the real numbers there were real was introduced in as it is to draw
distinction with the imaginary numbers which were very problematic and even I didn't even
realize this until yesterday that even Cauchy invented a theory of complex analysis of wrote
somewhere that he would have preferred not for their not to be imaginary but but that's
but the and what were they are there or not but they come up in the in processing equation
whether real numbers or invented I guess maybe I gave that away but I could also say discovered
it was that people use these things in this indiscriminately for the purposes of physics
and to allow and to make it possible to to get past the pre-secratic paradoxes of continuity
and so things were fine things were fine there were people were working with real numbers
except that there was no there was no axiomatic complete axiomatic theory until the middle
of the 19th century and then it turned out that the axiomatic theory was settled but then
these real numbers have properties that people couldn't understand the the the the the the
point the chronic crucial point was the discovery that the continuum hypothesis was undecidable
you don't know how many real numbers there are in fact you can it's up to the theoretician
to decide how many how many real numbers there are and so I'm maybe right now I should I
wanted to make an apology to the set theorists because I was I've written an article in Quanta
in which I suggested that the set theorists were concerned about the kind of foundations
for set theory that were used in by number theorists improving for example from us last
year there was a there was some controversy around that and that I actually learned by
interacting with set theorists that this is not at all their concern they were not trying
to establish roles for wave to the any if they're any if they set theorists are watching they
were not they're not all interested in establishing rules some people not set theorists were concerned
I'm not sure where this where this controversy came anyway that's the the upshot is that
as to maybe to move to the 21st century that's now yes well we're not going to project the
same questions remain unsettled in a sense that is to say what kind of foundations for
set theory do you want and it so happens that the kinds of mathematics that are being developed
not in in fact in part in order to provide mathematical the coherent explanations of
some physical theories theory some some things that are being developed in in in string theory
in particular involve going beyond the axioms the zermelofrankel axioms of set theory so
on inaccessible cardinals for example and so then the question is who decides who decides
what is what the foundations might be my what are the foundations of mathematics well it's
becoming more and more popular to develop series use theories that are based on the presumption
of existence of existence in the sense that one works with them of inaccessible cardinals
but that means there's big big sets that are much much bigger than anything one can produce
by the intellect one has to this whether called inaccessible because there's no reason cannot
establish their existence on the basis of the axioms even including existence of infinite
set they're much much more infinite in fact there are something called a hierarchy of
different kind of infinities which where it was one want to stop within that hierarchy
well the only the only historically reasonable answer that question is that mathematicians
are going to use whichever kinds of foundations what for set theory that provide the answers
to the questions that they that we consider to be reasonable and important
I was just going to say that I mean it's it seems to me that one of the things that came
out in few of the comments is this distinction between the philosopher and the mathematician
and what sort of kind of what you think maybe the mathematician itself don't have certain
kind of commitment but the commitment that you know that's where this is come but I'm
going to try to push on that just because I'm here and why not and just ask can you even
go like I mean what does it mean to go beyond the mathematicians themselves right I mean
the example that Michael just gave is why in which the mathematicians are the one that
getting to a point that they redefine with the foundation or the question of deciding
infinities to the correct you need to read the question again what the foundation which
the theory builds on right so the where the kind of questions about the existence always
come from the practicing mathematicians or I mean the innocent question or I mean physicists
you can think about as well so what is even the separation that you're between them the
philosophy and them the kind of the mathematicians well you know mathematics is a discipline
with its own rule book including a sociology you know what counts as evidence you know
like a whole discipline that you can characterize in manifold ways and so is philosophy and
they sometimes intersect in the history right sometimes big time Plato Aristotle some sometimes
like super big time Kantor set theory right then a little less right now right so you
can describe those curves and philosophy is just one of those disciplines right so and
then philosophy to something so it would be of course an interesting question right I
mean contemporary ontology is like a very well developed field right it's there's a lot
happening in ontology and metatology and metaphysics and metamethophysic and how they relate right
so that's its own development and these fields like intersect in very interesting ways and
that always remains to be explored right with what's going on in contemporary mathematics
my experience talking to my mathematics friends and colleagues is that indeed there's a very
widespread pragmatism when you talk to you know very high level mathematicians they would
say there's a sense in which right now we care less right so you know and then there might
be an interesting question about why this is solved right so why in the field is this
the case right but I think that what we need to bear in mind when we ask these questions
about philosophy and other disciplines this is often this often goes unnoticed in particular
in the Angofon world because there's a different very different way of thinking about the philosophy
is you know position in the academic division of labor but in my neck of the woods you know
we think of philosophy as just you know another discipline it's just one of the sciences so
I want to make sure that you give me this understanding.
No no no no no this is I think this is a you know so that's why you know if you ask me I
think you know we all if you do philosophy off and then that's another discipline same
mathematics or history of course I'm in history mathematics so I understand what you know that's
what I'm trying to say it's not I'm not trying to say that philosophy has no place there was
not really the really question was try to say how do you explain the the relation when
you think about those specific question right about ontology of when we're talking here
about ontology mathematics now then how do you understand the relation between the philosophy
and the mathematics is again historically right how do you understand the way in which the
ideas that arise from mathematics then infronts the kind of philosophical debates or that
the way right now you do think that there is obviously there's two ways yes it goes two
ways yeah yeah like but how do we that's the question was related to say how do you understand
that relation yeah I would ask Michael Fenson skin or the way in which Michael developed
his relationship you know towards set theory you know I would want to know whether you would
you know so there's a view let's just call it you know mathematical pluralism and you
know I'm heavily simplifying but you know like roughly it go would go something like
that look they're very different you know it depends on the foundations that you choose
right so there's a really there's a sense in which you can just choose your axiom system
this is something we learned from mathematics of the second half of the 20th century right
and and then there's this mathematics and this other mathematics and the the choice between
the axioms can be you know in terms of like elegance they can be all sorts of mathematical
internal criteria for why I am a mathematician mathematician would say I go for this rather
than that right and then this kind of pluralism would just mean that there's no you know then
this would raise for instance for me a philosophical question you know is there even a universe
of mathematical entities you know if we interpret the contemporary mathematics realistically
right so so even if we think that they're comitable you know given mathematical pluralism
is that like a universe of mathematical objects given what mathematicians know right now that's
something that would come to my mind but this would also depend you know like we have a
leading philosophy of mathematician here so I don't know how Hartree looks at this how
you would describe this discourse right so just I I I view myself as a pluralist here
and and so just sharpening the issue of slightly in the in the terms of the example that Michael
raised about so Michael said that the continuum hypothesis is under side of all I mean in
in some sense is radically understated things in that you can give almost in the answer you
want to what it sizes and it will be consistent with the rest of the axioms of
of said it's a no it's a no it's a theory yeah but so so a version of the pluralist
view that that I kind of like is that there really is no serious question what is the
real size of the content you are there are basically any any consistent answer is perfectly
okay and the idea of of asking which is the right one is just a wrong way to think about
it and that this marks a serious difference between mathematics and physics where where
basically there is a right answer even if we don't know it aren't you considering that
there might be at a later time a reason to choose there are the set there is yeah I want
to they want to find right maybe add an axi because the set of right seems was just established
to make set theory workable and use useful and if they have access right but more right
but but but what they do is they offer aesthetic criteria for for saying well you know it's
it's a prettier theory if you make the size of the content you own the smallest possible
or the second smallest or or whatever and and different people offer different aesthetic
criteria that you mentioned a different geometry before we have it could be described perhaps
this way and then using the dimensions and how does that decision get made and is that
an aesthetic one or other consideration well so I'm not sure I understand the question
I mean one thing which I think may be your question but but probably isn't but but so
theories of differentiable manifolds are developed using the theory of the real numbers and the
different answers to the size of the continuum give you different pictures of what the real
numbers are like so but so there's a separate question as to how much objectivity there is
about say lines in physical space but even if you thought it was completely objective
what the size of in affinity of the of the lines in in physical space was
that doesn't really settle the size of the continuum as mathematicians tend to view it because
because mathematicians tend to think well mathematical reality is it's one thing physical reality is
something else of course we we we got to our conception of the mathematical real numbers
by thinking about physical space but still there are different things it could turn out
empirically the physical lines aren't anything like the real numbers I mean maybe there's just
like the rational numbers but but the mathematical realist things well that doesn't tell you anything
about the real numbers it just shows that the physical lines need to correspond to the real
numbers so so even if there is a question as an objective of question as to the size of an
affinity of physical lines I think the the typical mathematical non-pluralist is going to say well
there's no obvious reason why the answer to the question of the size of the genuine real
numbers has to be the same as that I was sorry yes I just wanted to get to the other realities
yes exactly that was my point too yeah I think that has enough to do with the notion that that
popped up in some of the commentary in the last maybe 10 minutes the notion of pluralism
you know in the in the sciences when you look at the development of the sciences I mean physics
is the paradigm example but the others too talking about ontology always had I think historically
speaking the the or or brought the implicit request not only to talk about something that exists but
actually to talk about one thing that exists not many levels not pluralistic one fundamental
ontology and of course this has good reasons I mean for physics one of the interesting reasons
behind that was actually that physicists try to formalize mathematically and in the mathematics you
can very powerfully do that with symmetry principles and and this is the symmetry increasing the
symmetry always has the kind of taste of the unification picture unification picture leads to
one fundamental ontology now this fundamental way to look at things also created the idea that
in physics this is actually a byproduct it's secondary but it's created by the fundamentalisms
let me speak let me say that everything can be reduced to this fundamental level so all other
descriptions like thermodynamics hydrodynamics physical chemistry can somehow be reduced and of
course then we have to explain in detail what we mean by that to a kind of elementary fundamental
ontology and I think this program has I mean it from the very beginning it was of course not
realized to its full extent but people were thinking in principle this is doable and now in certain
areas we know for sure that it's that it's not working that way we know now I mean this is still
not covered in the textbooks but we know that thermodynamics cannot be reduced to statistical
mechanics I mean what I'm saying is the knowledge that we have at statistical mechanics is not enough
to create thermodynamics and the fact that Lord Kelvin and others Boltzmann they they had this
heuristic guess of this of the relation between the kinetic energy of the molecules and the temperature
was completely heuristic we only understand that really fully since the 1970s through quantum
through quantum field theory and developments by Rudolf Harg and others this is algebraic quantum
field theory only at that late time hundred years after the heuristic guess it became possible to
build the bridge really in a pro mathematically profound way and then it turns out that you in
order to make the bridge it's not enough that you know that you know the lower level the mechanical
level you have to you have to select a context at the higher level and implement that at the lower
level and then you can make the bridge formally in a formerly sound manner so this this is in a
way in an example for a kind of pluralism because if it is if this is so then you have to assume
that the temperature of a container of gas is also a property that exists in the ontological
sense in physics it cannot be fully reduced to the to mechanical properties I'm keen to
explain that more fully I don't I don't know if it makes it just my I don't know if I do want it to
say well that's stronger than I know to say but but I I would like to be convinced in more detail
of course this because yeah okay technical pretty extraordinary but we can make it
you know but they know something I'm ready to do that actually but I'm only giving you this picture
because everybody knows what temperature is and everybody knows what the motion of molecules
somehow is and it's it's actually a simple example which I wanted to use to really talk about
now to get the discussion into the pluralism thing and and I think for us in physics we in some way
we have to to give up this kind of deep seeded conviction that everything goes back to the
particles let me ask a question about other reality maybe you don't want to answer this because
much more radical than than the emergence of temperature as a separate property is the notion
that you can actually quantify over all possible anthologies and then there are I don't know how
seriously physicists take the notion of multiverse but is that okay is that what is uh but I but
people certainly do talk about it quite a lot I know I see
so and this is a this is a different idea of pluralism because if you if you go that way
then you have you have all these levels of description that I want to have as pluralistic
you have you you double the pluralism in each universe you have them again and in the next
university of all of that again and this is that I mean I know this is an interpretation of quantum
mechanics which some people um appreciate I don't I want to switch the register a bit to get more
to the other realities because from the outside mathematics and number carry the notion of real
truth the reality is carried by by the numbers whether it's polling numbers or you know how many
people believe such and such and I think it's had a profound effect on our society and our culture
and Alma has written and worked on the whole idea of how numbers get used in terms of the political
scene and I mean I think you maybe don't realize the amount of authority that we on the outside of
your world project onto number and I'd like to understand that a little bit in terms of how it
affects the other realities not just what the other realities are is that of interest to you Alma
to me it's of interest but I'm I'm in a company I mean I should say just that there's a I wonder I
wonder to what degree this to conversation relate to one another I think that you absolutely
write it that they greet the which the reality or kind of so there's a very famous book in the
Eastern mathematical by a that protocol trust in numbers which really deals to this question really
of how making numerical argument have you know one in a sense why why and he has I mean the argument
is much more complicated than this the history that he tells but this notion that if you were saying
that numbers have a certain kind of numerical argument has certain kind of validity that
other sort of argument might not have but I wonder to what degree and I'm asking that back I mean to
a degree that relates to the ontological question of number I don't know right I mean he's just a
convent the numbers used as conventions here when people make new argument based on kind of
numbers or is it really has to do with that other question that we were talking about until now
which is down the existence the real existence of numbers so I'm kind of going to throw that back
I would have thought that the reason why numerical arguments that use a lot of numbers
tend to sound more convincing is just because they get the appearance precision and oftentimes
they are more precise so it's clearer to see what the argument is so that's not a very deep observation
I suppose but amidst it's what this precision that's I think a deep question
why is precision important?
Yeah, where is the subjective factor that gets related to these things?
If you have quantum mechanics or if you have a electro dynamics and you solve a sort of problem
then you get a solution and experiment coincides with that solution let's say in five digits after
the comma and after that if you measure further than it deviates now you do quantum electro dynamics
you get the next three digits correct in that in that sense precision might be an important thing
to test your theory precision in terms of numbers but the way it is precision of a true value that
you know no I think I think the way in which we as physics I mean it is in theoretical physics
or mathematical physics the way in which we apply let me say mathematics has nothing so much to do
with numbers it's really what we apply is the structure it's actually a qualitative feature
but that goes into the physics when you come from math and then of course when we solve it
and we have equations you can have an equation and then it sits there but then you want to solve it
and then you know you put in initial conditions and all this kind of stuff initial conditions are
not something that I think mathematicians feel so much with they just have to form a structure
I mean yeah yes and no but I think another strategy if I was trying to say since
we were more responsible I think we we would find more precise arguments more compelling because
a more precise statement is more easily is one for which it's more easy to figure out whether
or not it's a correct yeah and people that are willing to assert responsibly who are responsible
about making assertions will be willing to assert statements that are more easily falsifiable
proportionate to the degree to which they've evidence for them and so that in an ideal culture
we would ideally try to state things that have a degree of precision proportionate to our evidence
for them and maybe you know we're not obviously we're not there yet but given that that is something
that we could imagine as an ideal it wouldn't surprise me that looking outside we think oh this
is this guy saying something sounds very precise he must have really good reasons to say it like
what the rocks said at least on this side can i bring in another reality where you see I think
that some of these ideas about precision and the relationship or truth break down quite quickly
right I mean take most of the things that we all believe to be true such as there's a certain
amount of you know there's either finite or we're clearly finite but you know either an odd or
even number of people in this room right or here there's either an even odd number of people here
right now that is in some sense not very precise it's not quantum mechanical fine resolution
because from the quantum mechanical standpoint it's going to be hard to find the people here
right but it's perfectly all right and objectively true and completely unproblematic and just true
that there's either an odd or even number of people here even though probably no one in this
room or not all scientists together in the world right now can tell you what one person is because
we don't know what unifies an organism etc etc right so I think there are like very good
exceptions to the rule that a scientifically rigorous statement that's not what Chris intended
right with precision but I think that if if the scale of precision that we deploy and thinking
about the objectivity of truth etc etc right is modeled along the lines of the progress of modern
mathematical physics then I think we run into very serious political problems right so if you know
like social problems cannot be tackled in this way clearly not now so you know like if we
wonder you know the unification of physics and reduction is a hard enough problem but going from
there to like making a real prediction was going to be the next president of the United States of
America right there are very very many gaps right that you cannot fill out you we can fill them out
as a world almost and try all right right in a in a group of you know like here we can maybe
figure out whether we should be reductionist about social facts or not right but in the real
world you know where this stuff matters there's going to be a different form of precision right
so and I think that it will be ultimately you know very problematic on the real level of social
facts or political facts to think that you know decision procedures there should be mathematical
or etc in that sense so there are different kinds of precision an example that one of my
you know professors in philosophy always gave for this you know the relativity of precision
problem is simply this right I mean you fall in love with a certain person right and then there's
a degree of resolution of that person's phase in which you can still recognize the person and
fall in love etc right if you come to close and you look at you know like whatever you know molecular
details then then the object that you're dealing with in this particular case simply dissolves
so I think there's no you know there's no absolute thing you know precision and that is the that
is you know like be precise and then you're more likely to say something true I think quite often
if we if we have precise mathematically we're going to say something false
yeah not in mathematics right of course there's not a point about mathematics but we don't only
think about mathematical objects if we think about them at all I think that's one of what was a wonderful
place to put pause to our conversation and maybe invite a few audience to come up and ask questions
Tess some of you indicated that you believe that mathematical objects exist in the real universe
and Roger Penrose next peg bar not not withstanding the fact of the matter is that we described the
physics of the real universe with abstract concepts like Euclidean or Riemannian geometry
and differential equations and these are all based on abstract concepts that do not exist in the
real universe a point a line a plane a manifold even a particle do not exist in the real universe
so my question is can any one of you give me an example of a mathematical object or more specifically
a geometric object that you believe exists in the real universe then then you would tell I mean I
would have a question for you I would say I need a better grasp on what you think is a real the
real universe because for some people this is real for some people that may be real well if you let's
start with the most basic object in mathematics a point in geometry a point does a point exist in
the real universe the mathematician who thinks about mathematical realism in the sense like Roger
Penrose does yes well it's mathematical realism but it's not physical realism there's no such
thing as a physical point well but you know it's fact real things like what he says let's say
which I think we would say racism exists but you can't little point to well your racism exists but
it can I don't believe that it could be described mathematically you think New York City system
is correct do you think New York City exists in the real I believe I believe in existence but
my question is using mathematics to describe exactly the existence of real objects is a fallacy it's
an approximation at best even I want to say if if you I mean as I do actually have a pluralistic
worldview then I would say biological species exist in biological reality physical species
exist in physical reality mathematical species exist in mathematical reality minds exist in
mental reality and free will exists in free will reality I don't know okay but I but my question my
original question was I thought that some of you agreed with people like Penrose and Tegbark that
mathematics mathematical objects actually exist in real universe uh-huh that the real
universe consists of what we call mathematical objects this is I have to apologize this is
not the idea we just brought this up in order to have something to discuss right I'm not I don't
I know I believe that here I know that I thought some of you said that you do believe that not
that I think okay oh I don't know maybe does anyone does anyone I don't even sure I understand
what the question is okay yeah okay I have two questions for you um the first is is there any
work on whether this issue is decidable so as you said there are crucial issues in mathematics
so they've been decided that we have discovered are not decidable and I'm wondering whether you
feel that one can look at this question from a perspective of is it won't be possible ever for
us to decide this issue is there any work going on in that arena which question is that exactly
or whether math math objects are real or bad so this and the second question is this we are creatures
formed from evolution we believe and there is some sense in which that limits how we can see the
world and I'm wondering if there's any work on whether that inherently will affect the type of
beliefs that we can come up with and the types of reality that we can come up with and whether
that then plays into the the question of whether this is decidable or not so two related questions
well I think there's a lot of work I mean contemporary philosophy is like there's going to be a huge
landscape I don't know about philosophy of mathematics whether there's like a prominent like skeptical
position right now where someone would say that you know the answer to the to certain ontological
questions in philosophy of mathematics is somewhat unknowable or undecidable it's clearly not a
prominent view I don't know if this but you know for any I think for any you know so that's
that landscape is very rich and the other question you know this there's of course a huge
literature and discussion about that I mean most recently now I think people are debating the
Donald Hoffman book the case against reality right so this is a nice you know case for for I think
your second question you know the most recent version of neuroscience has discovered for such
and such a reason we cannot know reality I think this is nonsense but it's a very widespread kind
of argument I didn't understand your answers whether there is serious work like specifically
on the side of this question of the philosophy of mathematics question yes just general I don't
know I don't know that's I would ask if I if you ask me you to ask I would ask I would ask
you to ask somebody else if I want to hear what I can say is there is an interesting book
which collects dialogues between a mathematician I mentioned the name before
L.R. Kahn who is a convinced a convinced playfulness in that sense with with a brain research
person Jean-Pierre Georgie and they talk about this issue and it's a discussion it's it doesn't
result of course there are two there are two points which they try to make over 250 pages
and at the end you decide
I'm sorry you know this is are you know that book probably right sorry you know that book
I don't know the title I'm trying to remember but if you if you go by the authors con c o n n e s
and charge you that's you find it okay well this I'm always bringing in the another issue but it
relates to pluralism and it relates to painting in particular and also to the question previously
painters have particularly always thought they want to find the truth or do they want to find
the truth within the world of painting and early on in painting in the Renaissance they saw for
linear perspective for anatomy for understanding the body and as painting evolved they became more
and more involved in this very issue of what are they searching for are they searching for
similar for similitude in the world or are they searching for something ontological in terms of
internal or external search and I think right now is a very pivotal time in the arts and particularly
in painting which I know where there's a lot of confusion about of the motivation for the creation
of works of art and there are painters more in the in the 40s and during the wartime where they
explored topological space they went against non non-neuclidean space and they attempted things
but then when they dealt with it they didn't deal with it probably with the true logistics of the
way a physicist or mathematician would deal with it but it's very much a pivotal issue
do we do we follow what we what we are searching for internally in our internal brain structures
or are we looking at the world precisely and trying to reproduce the world obviously painters and
not can no longer need to reproduce the world and the way they once did so I came today because I'm
very fascinated by this very crux of problem ontology and epistemology in which many painters
have arguments about with one another about what they're trying to do I don't I don't know if you
can even be good but just I just some of your thoughts may be on the possibility even of an art
form entering any of this discussion I'll go ahead I just want to say that there actually have been
work on that have argued that the kind of there's this the moment of the turn of the century is a
modernist transformation but there is a relation between the modernist transformation in both arts
and mathematics specifically so I'm thinking about the work of Jeremy Gray and I started
mathematics that actually made the link specifically that this sort of question like you were saying
about what is mathematics about what is painting about etc are actually quite similar so there have
been I don't know but I can't answer the question right now I can say that they have
been works that looked at this moment in the turn of the century and made that comparison directly
and physics as well yes it's part of exactly yeah
yeah I mean I recommend a forthcoming book by this gentleman art and object that's a debate
between Graham Hammond was the author of the book that I recommend and Michael Freet about this
issue you might find that interesting so there's a whole recent trend in ontology of art you know
which relates to that you know so that might be interesting looking you know Michael Freet set
the tone for a long time but they're like recent ontological trends also in philosophy of art that
might speak to that question yeah because the traditional aesthetic theories don't really hold
in terms of what the real problems are now or even in the middle of the 20th century yes yes that's
why there's like a whole new like strand of theorizing about this which in the art world goes by the
title of speculative realism so you might find that material interesting
it may say one small one small thing it might be interesting to look in whether or not there are
analogies in the philosophy of music so music it's a tone structure it has there's structures
that musical pieces exemplify and there are similar questions about the ontology of music so is the
is the symphony the the physical performance is it the physical inscription on the paper or is it an
abstract object that's represented by those things and that's why one and the same symphony can be
performed in different places it might it might be that because the nature of music is is more
easily detachable from particular performances of it in a way that a painting doesn't seem to be that
the the questions will seem more parallel if we're considering those art forms rather than maybe
architecture has some architecture would be another one to think about this is also this very interesting
analogy i'm not sure whether it applies across the board but there have been instances here where
we hear we learn that mathematicians or physicists don't spend that much time wearing without their
ontology many physicists and i think mathematicians would say well that's good and we need to we'll
look at it and if we're interested in it we might look at it the question is is that a quick
prescription for painters or artists as well should they be spending a lot of time thinking
about the ontological implications or is that really what art is about is a good idea we're a
bad idea to focus on that should they do that more of it than mathematicians or physicists say i'm
not sure i know the answer but similarly what what would you how does the following sound to you
you know the philosophers are currently discussing whether they should spend any time on doing
mathematics right i think this would be like a bad headline and i think similarly the other
headline is equally bad mathematicians now this and physicists now you know think that they should
do less ontology i think it's equally bad you know and just go back to the great moment you know
we you mentioned the foundation foundational crisis and quad mechanics etc you know Einstein wrote
you know like one of my colleagues we just moved him from caltech he edits Einstein's papers he spent
a lot of time reading neo-kantian philosophy literature writing reviews which are now published
it with the Einstein papers etc and so forth for the other great figures and that might not have
been a coincidence that often physicists right now worry about the grand unification and when
it's coming and then they are doing honestly speaking incompetent metaphysics like max tech
marker i think this is terrible metaphysics what's going on there or Donald Hoffman is just an incompetent
philosopher of mind and so you know like so that's you know he is bad news neuroscientists care much
less about ontology right now are you saying this is good or bad i think this is terrible equally bad
because it becomes a philosopher who doesn't care about mathematics you know that's what the baby
with the bath water because you know you can do bad metaphysics as he i mean i agree with you and then
typically what physicists have you know learned to say is when someone does metaphysics at all it's
all automatically bad physics or bad metaphysics but there is very helpful metaphysics also of course
someone mentioned the name of john bell i don't know you you mentioned john bell came up with
actually two metaphysical assumptions and then he derived for one of the assumptions classical
local reality and inequality by which you can test whether this assumption is right or wrong so you
can make you can make empirical tests that are motivated by metaphysics but then it has to be good
metaphysics yes of course i think i think with the artist or with painters it's really the study of
the brain because i don't think it can really be controlled of what they're thinking in categories
i think very often that the arts come closest to an attempt at some kind of unification of the
intellect the mind the emojis and so therefore it's very hard to say well don't think about this only
think about that because the act of creation is an exploration and a search for where they stand
and where how they relate to the world so i i think the divisions are very dangerous in terms of
creativity and probably in science too if you go deep into it i don't know enough i have a good i
i'm sorry i don't want to dominate this but since we are talking about art now it's uh i this is not
directly about ontology and episode but it has to do with it there was this German artist who was
made ridiculous who was ridiculed by many people Joseph Boyce Joseph Boyce had really he had a
philosophical philosophical talent to some extent and in terms of his actions he did this action
art even here in New York in New York City the the the the action with the coyote i mean i don't
what what what Boyce did conceptually was he undercut the subject object distinction because he as the
artist made himself an object of his own art by the action so he this is this is i think remarkable
it's it's a great idea just to show people that um it's not that here's the artist and here is the
painting he just puts himself into that room and together with the coyote right and and he does it
in such a way that people were standing there and looking through the glass through the window
and wouldn't go away for hours because they thought something must be happening and nothing
happened except he was lying there with his i don't know you know all these these stuff that he
usually brings with him and then there's the coyote you know that was amazing and people were of
course they were getting angry because they were expecting something and nothing happened but they
didn't go away amazing then see he really had this talent to to do something that is philosophically
highly relevant in a way that affects people it was just i mean i'm just you know but Michael
what is the same thing i was just going to say that the history of art is a good place to look
for a history of the of the value attached to precision because there are different periods when
a precision is considered an important value but then it doesn't always mean the same thing
and in fact it can take opposite meanings and there's also uh this is not unrelated to the
history of objectivity as analyzed in the book of dastard and gallisin which again the valence
objectivity in that case is the value but what it means takes it becomes moves to its opposite
from one time yeah i just wanted to say also as far as ontology and mathematics there is
a small group of mathematicians who are talking to philosophers it's called the n category cafe
and the uh it's been online for quite some time the original motivation was precisely
uh the the some concern or not necessarily concern about the uh development of
mathematical uh practices that were not based on on the axioms of set theory specifically that
were uh and the but what i've noticed is that this there's not any much interaction between
this uh this circle which was mathematicians and philosophers and physicists and the rest of
uh philosophy so there's a lot of researching contemporary ontology in europe and france in
particular of category theory as a matter of fact so that idea i've also like happened to have
written something about this so there there's uh you know there's just a little more there but
yeah so that issue you know like given that so category theory was uh you know like people
became aware of this and it's through interaction with mathematicians yes yes
through self-centaction actually with some of the founding fathers actually
in the most in the french context uh oh okay i'm familiar with this i know you know this
i'm familiar with it yeah but this this is a different because this is there are mathematicians
from various uh different fields this is because to keep the category theory so we're working
we're talking to the french philosophers were category theory that was that was what they did
they were not yeah they were somewhat isolated within mathematics yes this is something different
yeah i had the question about history and it was mentioned that um
in popular imagination the fourth dimension at the beginning of the last century
uh and then when i was a kid watching tv watching twilight zone uh i think his name was surling
he talks about the fifth dimension and now we're in the internet age and we were during the
introduction uh we talked about the three audiences the audience in this room the audience beyond
this room the future audience that might be looking at the archive of this event and many of us who
are observing and participating right now may be in that audience right because when this is
uploaded we can all look at it so i guess my question is about the the culture and how um
um the past president future is changing so quickly um and how our our participation in the
technology is accelerating that and there's a buzzword uh post truth i'm sure we've all heard that um
and what that could possibly mean so i guess my general question is about um what is all this how
is this impacting our culture and our our imagination and our politics sort of a broad question
and if there's anything you know now that you did not know at the beginning of this conversation
i would be very curious about that thank you
i know that i have to withdraw some of my projections onto math that's very important
lesson and also i've been thinking about daniel connamans uh endowment principle
uh of how much what we endow is having value because we know it or we have it
changes our perception of it and its value in the world and throughout this conversation i've
been thinking about that that whole endowment principle idea anyone else yeah i was i i actually
wanted to ask you that later tonight what do you think of don huffman's book but now i know yes
you know i run a research center of reality in crisis a center for the human being in the
digital age it's a large international research network uh withstands disciplines here at uh
and my new university of Tokyo of picking university and pericine kamrich in the future and um and so
it's uh deals with all these uh post truth etc phenomena on various levels so i think that
you know let me be very brutal about this i think that some of this huffman's style material is
you know what people worried about here in the 90s in particular in philosophy about you know
post modernism and so forth giving up the truth and richard rorty and so forth i think the kind of
incoherence what really people worried about this has now infiltrated politics neuroscience
but other disciplines too you know like rovelli the way in which rovelli speaks about physics
and nobility i think it's the same so i think that's like a whole i call i call this climate of uh
misdegotten conceptions of knowledge uh food Kantianism you know it's the worst of koko and the worst
of Kant and it's also crazy Kant food Kant it's also it's a valgus form of Nietzscheanism and i think
donald trump you know like if you look at this you know Nietzsche it's the first of what Nietzsche calls
the blonde beast and uh and this whole truth thing i mean there you know everything that we worried
about you know decades ago from philosophies like you know now this has come become a principle
almost everywhere and i think there's a lot uh of work for philosophers to be done and in many
in europe the contemporary philosophical trends are therefore often associated with the label of
realism new realism that's just my word and speculative realism and this realism and that
realism and the reason why in particular philosophers in europe have you know moved to the realist
cam broadly speaking right uh is you know resisting that we have our own version of it you know the
in germany the christian democrats but since people don't think about this you know you think
about the far right when you think about political problems in germany but we have the christian
democrats that's nasty i shouldn't have said that on the record
well i did say that was the last question but we will have one one last question now
but yeah the whole thing i'm sorry i'll make a little nervous
well i suppose this has to do with realism um in veda there there's 40 aspects well one is
yoga and there was this patongently who cognized it four chapters the third chapter is called city
sidhi and sanskrit often translated as perfection power uh super normal ability attainment
cities are are listed as things like levitation walking through walls and visibility strength of
an elephant um being in multiple bodies at the same time knowledge of past and future knowledge
of the contents and nature of other people's minds uh challenges to our understanding of reality and
veda deals with these seven states of consciousness neurophysiological states of consciousness
beyond the first three being waking dream you've sleep so we've been talking a lot is about mathematics
as kind of a one application of mathematics is to describe physical reality but here you have a
physical reality which is you know right here i mean in the room if some of these things
um actually exist which doesn't seem to be challenged um so what are your thoughts about this uh
this knowledge has you know quite serious um um history and uh
maybe i can't say two things about this there have been attempts to actually in some of the
labs particularly in the u.s even in Princeton to demonstrate phenomena like this and much of
that has been shown to be um some experiments haven't been done well designed some experiments
have been well analyzed and so i'm doubtful about that material but still there are other
situations in which these cases happen spontaneously i mean not under under laboratory conditions
and then um my first reaction would be is that really something that fits into the range
of validity of physical theories i mean i think we all agree that the world does not only consist
of consist of physics and physical reality right there's more to depend on that and for instance
what we do not understand at all up to the present day uh not withstanding all all neuroscience and
brain and stuff and so on it's the relationship between the mental and the physical we don't have
any clue we can measure correlations but we don't know where they come from what they do and so on
i don't know what science will bring us when we understand this better i'm not saying that we
can explain this all this all then but i'm only saying that it is maybe not the not the best reaction
to try and ask physics to explain that because it maybe may go far beyond what physics is designed
for it to explain so well thank you everyone for an excellent afternoon and i'm looking
forward to looking at this for years to come on youtube
so