Patrick Rosal and Jean Valentine, we're going to read their poems and discuss each other's
poems and we hope to have a very nice informal conversational experience in which the poets
share their appreciations of each other's poetry.
Patrick, we're lucky to have him as a member of our Poetry Committee here at Helix for
our poetry programming.
He's the author of three full-length poetry collections, most recently Bone Shepherds,
named a notable book by the National Book Critics Circle and the Academy of American Poets.
He's also won the Association of Asian American Studies Book Award, Global Filipino Literary
Award, and the Asian American Writers Workshop Members' Choice Award.
His poems and essays have been published in Grantland, Tin House, Harvard Review, Language
for a New Century, Best American Poetry, and many others.
He's a founding co-editor of some call it Ballin, a sports quarterly, and is a former
Fulbright Fellow.
He teaches on the faculty of Rutgers University, Camden's MFA program.
And Jean Valentine, I think, is the author of a dozen books of poetry, the first being
Dream Barker, which won the Young Young Poets Prize, up through her door on the mountain
new and collected poems, which won the National Book Award for Poetry.
And I think Break the Glass is the most recent book.
She's a recipient of the 2009 Wallace Stevens Award from the Academy of American Poets.
She's taught at Sarah Lawrence, NYU, and Columbia.
So the format for this afternoon will be that Patrick's going to read some poems, and Jean's
going to have a conversation with him about them.
And then I think Jean is going to read her Lucy sequence, and Patrick is going to talk
with her about his appreciation of that series of poems.
Patrick will read a couple more poems.
Jean will respond, and then I think Jean may finish with a couple of new poems.
Is that still your plan?
Super.
And then we'll have time for the audience to comment.
So we begin.
Thank you very much.
Thank you everybody for being here, too.
I'm fighting what I hope is the tail end of a cold.
I'm used to very energetic readings, but I'll muster whatever I can for today.
A lot of the things that I've been interested in lately have been, I've always been interested
in my family history, but more and more I've been trying to place that in terms of a global
history.
My parents are from the Philippines.
This poem is called, The Lendre Undone.
And so we've all been told to shut up.
Don't talk, they say, too fast, too loud, or for too long.
Don't take too much time trying to tell the truth.
But this is my work, to break out among strangers into laughter.
How I've watched small children, for example, fill with the lucky gust a poem can ride into
the mere stillness of a room and dance.
For that, I am always, as now, grateful.
My father tells me in his seminary days, during the Japanese occupation, most of the priests
who ran that school were German.
The boys then were to speak only in Latin and would surely be slapped three Sundays
back if heard speaking in the language of my father's country, which is a beautiful
country and a beautiful language.
And which has a curious word for being so suddenly seized by affection, you clench every muscle
from your eyelids to your toes, for wanting to hold a loved one tight, squeeze one, and
kiss one so deep you place yourself and your beloved on the brink of physical harm.
There's no word for this in English.
No word for those small provinces of silence or for the kind of love that will trouble
that silence into music.
My work is trying to find the very word rippling in my body, which is a woman's body, my mother's,
and a man's body, my father's, and nowhere to be found in the languages that have conquered
the land of my ancestors.
In the outskirts of every empire, there are man-made lakes large enough to receive with
ease, 100 villages worth of bones tossed into them.
This is a fact.
There are more than 7 million illocanos in the Philippines, maybe a million in diaspora.
All of us at one time or another have been told to shut up.
Don't talk too loud, too slow, or for too long.
In Saudi Arabia, in Madrid, in Tokyo, in Milan, on Bowery, near the foot of First Street.
You've been told this.
Some of us have been famous liars, Ferdinand, for example, who married another liar, Ymelda,
and my grandfather, Capitano de Barrio, who clinged to kick the shit bare-fisted and
single-handedly out of 14 ruffians in the small barangay of Santatomas.
Actually, he kicked the shit out of five.
Nine ran away.
These are not lies.
This is the truth.
I'm not wealthy.
I can't buy space or time on billboards or websites.
The name I inherit doesn't part columns in the city's daily journal.
My family comes from a long line of farmers.
My cousins scrubbed their chopping blocks with salt.
They shushed the goats before they killed them.
So Santatomas is essentially a barrio.
And the barangay that my mom comes from is Santatomas.
I was born and raised in New Jersey.
I went to the Philippines for the first time when I was 14.
But I didn't go back for almost 25 years.
So this is a welcoming poem about how I got welcomed to the Philippines after 25 years.
In the middle of my uncle's yard, a goat bounded the hooves wags its tongue.
I've traveled 10,000 miles to be welcomed home by a town that knows me only by my middle
name and photos sent by post more than 25 years ago.
And there is an old man from the foothills of the barrio's far edge who has heard my
uncle Charlie drag this small beast to the block.
Heard the news by music, the bottles, the banging, the laughter inside the slaughter.
The old man limps the half mile by foot up the long dirt road, unshod, a ratty tank top,
a brand new Vegas cap, a cut black strip of inner tube draped around his neck.
And in front of him, he's rolling the whole way, a common jug on its side, emptied of
its vinegar, dusty, immense, to his hip in height and three times the old man's girth.
My uncle is strumming the guts out of his ukulele when the old man arrives and sets the
huge jug upright, pulls the bike tube off his nape and stretches it across the jar's massive
ceramic yawn, holding the rubber strip in place with one big muddy toe and on the downbeat
of the first measure of the second chorus, he joins my uncle in the kind of mooing these
beloved geysers swear has several times tricked a field of blossoms into blue.
The old man plucking from the makeshift base, not so much a moan, but a pulse that ranges
a full octave into each man's chest, the sinews of the old timer's arm straining, the
long muscle of his back top, his quadricep, his calves, his black foot pumping blood into
his whole awful body, his maw flashing every one of his seven good teeth to have him.
And if a man become part of a giant, the song of a giant, each one of us laughing like a
giant, if each one of us fulfill the exact measure of a man, and if the goat at the same
time is singing as it's dying among men who are singing and dying, the youngest cousin
among us butcher slaughtering elbow deep in the animals belly does not sing.
The carcass bloodlet now also silent as if it's stillness were a source of music too,
the way in death one becomes all the sounds one cannot make, the sum total of everything
the living cannot say, sometimes we have to sing just to figure out what we cannot say.
Sure.
Let us know how she feels about your problems.
I love your problems.
Thanks, Jean.
And it's great to sit here beside you and hear them.
Usually I'm over there hearing them and it's so nice to be near you.
And I was thinking reading them the weeks coming up to now when we would be here.
But I can't really, having her to read, I can't read these without hearing your voice.
And it's so, it's such a gift.
Even if I don't have it really in you being in the room, but the voice is so, as you can
hear, the voice is so present in everything that writes and it's so important.
And one thing I want to ask you is, I've probably been asked this before, but when you're writing,
do you talk it while you're writing it?
Yeah, I think that there's a sort of, you can call it a collaboration between my voice
out loud and my interior voice.
And so I don't know that I necessarily read it while I'm writing it down or composing,
but I certainly, sometimes I will say something and I'll stop to record it.
And then I'll read it again.
So it becomes, it's like kind of transubstantiation between sound and ink, right?
And it goes back and forth between those two substances.
I think that's more what my process is like, but the out loud part feels very important
to me.
It's important to you too though, isn't it?
Yeah.
It's important to every poet, but I hear, what you've said is perfect for me too, I think,
but not the way I read, as you know.
But I hear the voice inside, and then I put it down.
But I wondered if you actually talked to yourself like Hamlet or somebody.
Well, I love hearing you read.
It's wonderful.
It's beautiful.
And I loved that you have this verse, I guess it is, by Neruda in the front of your book.
You feel like reading that to the folks?
I could do it.
Yeah.
I'd like you've had a chance to read that on, but it's wonderful to hear that voice too.
So it's slipping for me now.
My mind is, I'm drawing a blank.
Anyway, I'll read the verse.
It's from Heights of Machu Picchu.
I can't remember which section it is though.
Show me your blood and your furrows.
Show me I was punished here because the jewel didn't shine or the earth didn't surrender
it stone or grain on time.
Point out to me the rock you fell upon and the wood on which they crucified you.
Strike for me into fire the old flint, the ancient lanterns, the whips lashed upon those
wounds throughout centuries.
Show me blood-bright hatchets.
I come to speak through your dead mouth.
Thank you.
I love having that in the front of your book because I think it's what you're doing.
Not always dead mouths, but through others' mouths.
And I think that's really what poetry is doing.
Do you hear us okay?
Yeah?
I think the great poet Mary Ponzo is among us, so I just want to be sure she's hearing
this.
I think I've never really, I don't think, met a poet who isn't trying to speak for others
at least some of the time and for people who couldn't speak for themselves oftentimes
or who you feel that about.
But when you read, I've seen you, we work together at Drew University, so I've seen Patrick
read on different occasions something formal like this or something where you're helping
to get something going or to announce students' names who are going to read at that time
or something like that.
So I've seen you in different degrees of formality or not.
I think you have such a gift of really using your body, I know you must hear this all the
time, but really the whole body comes into Pat's poetry and not just the voice.
So that's something like I suppose we might be used to a great actor doing, but it isn't
every poet who can even aspire to that and it's a wonderful gift I think.
Can I say something?
Of course you can't.
The Kwame Dawes says, he talks about the sound of a drum and that the striking of the drum,
the moment that you strike it, the attack is like a consonant.
And when the drum rings, those are like the vowels of language, so he likens language
to making drums.
My buddy Roger just told me this last night, I think it's brilliant.
What I think also is fascinating about that too is that in terms of language, the consonants
are mostly made here up in the mouth.
So those become the percussion and the metronomic sounds in a line or in a poem and that ringing
of the drum, boom, the vowels, they become the harmonics that come between percussiveness,
but they also, they come literally from the body in order to sing them out loud.
You can't say a vowel without, it comes from the body and so, you know, I wasn't trained
as a singer and an actor, but I think that I've always felt very, I was a dancer, I was
a street dancer when I was younger.
I've always felt very connected to my body.
So I think that you're reading something about my own practices and my own engagement with
art.
Coming from that, yeah.
Yeah, thanks, that's fascinating.
I never thought of that consonant vowel thing before, but you mentioned musical instruments
and it's a mouth a lot in your poetry, of course, drums, we just had a wonderful one, that amazing
barrel with the tire.
God, I love that.
And then guitars and, yeah, homemade things.
Yeah.
Piano.
Piano is definitely piano.
Yeah.
Beautiful one.
Maybe you'll read that to us later on.
That's a big poem.
You know, when I was young, I think the biggest reader I ever heard are the most impressive
reader I ever heard was Dylan Thomas.
Oh, wow, yeah.
You ever hear recordings of him?
I have, I have.
Yeah.
And I think although it's different, he came from a tradition, the Welsh tradition of
singing and reading and he just took our heads off when he came over here, you know?
I just, I never heard anything like it.
I'm sure there was stuff like it, but I just never heard it.
Yeah.
And speaking of consonants, I mean, the way that he sort of was able to conjure sound
in a poem is just unbelievable.
He's a real model for me in that way.
He's a real model.
Yeah, yeah, absolutely.
Yeah.
Wow.
There's so many different styles of reading, but I really love, I love sound so much.
It feels like it's more than half of what goes on.
Were there any readers throughout your career?
Were there any readers?
I think that it's sort of, it's easy to perhaps remember people who are dynamic.
They're like readers and good readers.
But were there readers who were more pulled back that you found not just their poems being
sort of arresting, but the performance of their poems?
Being arresting?
Yeah, or being able to grab your attention by being not sort of bardic necessarily, but
more interior in their performance.
Oh, more interior and arresting in that way.
Yeah.
More.
Yeah, I would think, well, let me just think for a minute.
There was a couple of interesting things about Robert Lowell.
I don't know if you've heard him on a tape or anything.
I think he'd never heard any tapes of him read ever.
Well, he was from New England, but he had gone into a southern accent somewhere along
the way.
It was important to him.
So that was one surprise when you heard him read if you didn't know anything about him.
You thought he came from Boston, which he did.
But then he, at first, would we, and I didn't hear this, but he talked about it in interviews.
I don't know if any of you ever heard him in life?
You did, yeah.
Oh, great evening at St. Mark's Church.
Ginsburg was there.
And Peter Orlowski was sort of giving him a hard time from the sidelines.
And Ginsburg was very like a supplicant.
It was surprising to see, because most of us were sort of younger, heard of hippie-ish
group, sort of on the Ginsburg side of things.
He got right down and he kind of kneeled in front of Lowell as he was reading.
It was Ginsburg.
It was quite a sight.
That's wonderful.
I think they became friends at the end.
Yeah, that's beautiful.
I heard that they went on a march to Washington together.
And there was a reading, and of course Ginsburg is heard by everyone.
And Lowell got up there, and there was a mic and everything.
But people kept saying, we can't hear you.
We can't hear you.
And he said, well, I can't do anything.
I could shout, but you still wouldn't hear me.
It was a big, huge crowd of people, I guess.
He just didn't have that Ginsburg.
But the interesting thing that I was going to say is anecdotal anyway, that he would
read quite formally as he wrote at the beginning.
And I think quite resolved.
But then he went out on a reading tour in California.
He said, no, the country in those days.
It was very different, politically and far geographically.
And I think he sensed that nobody understood a word he was saying in this very formal,
very kind of formal metrics as well as formal language.
And it was before life studies.
It was the more formal work before that.
And people just didn't get it.
And so he started in response to audiences talking much less formal, including the way
he would read.
But he would also stop and say something if he thought people weren't getting it.
So it was happening in front of people's eyes that he was changing his style of writing
too, as we found out later when he got to life studies.
So the audience helped transform the way that he saw his own poems.
I mean, that's a wonderful story, I think, an interesting story anyway.
Now, people don't think of you as somebody who performs your poems, but you do embody
your poems in the way that you're crafting silences and your lyrics.
But do you imagine yourself or do you think about performance at all or an interaction
with the audience?
Yeah, I want to talk to the audience.
I want to reach the audience very much.
But I don't think of myself as performing because I've seen yourself and other people
who really can reach probably wide audiences.
And I don't think I would be good at that.
But sound is everything to me.
So I want to have that.
And if I've got a good mic, I'm okay, I think.
But as you know, if I don't, it's pretty hard.
I haven't ever learned how to really project my voice.
So I need a mic.
As you were saying before, you feel that probably all poets want to speak also for someone
else who doesn't have the same capacity to speak.
And that should bring us to Lucy.
Because you're speaking to Lucy and speaking for Lucy.
And...
Cross my fingers.
Yeah, she certainly spoke to me.
Yeah.
Yeah, thank you for bringing her up.
I'll read that later when we get to my turn.
I was thinking when we were talking about sound and performing how I once, when I was
in Ireland, there was another anecdote, but there was a sign by the road that said poetry
school.
And it was pointing down this way.
And so I said to the guy, I was, I said, let's go.
I was so lonely, I was dying.
You know.
So I said, let's go see the poetry school.
And so we drove down this little dirt road and it got to the ocean.
And there was a few rocks piled up on each other where you could go in and say it.
And it said poetry school.
And I thought, that is the best.
I ought to just stop right here, you know.
Never leave.
It was just wonderful.
But I was thinking about the first poets probably, they had to speak.
They wouldn't have gotten the job otherwise, right?
I mean, that was the job, I think.
That's not true anymore, but I think it's true of some people.
Yeah.
So should we hear Lucy?
We could do Lucy.
I don't know how time is.
Do you do this?
Well, we're going to think about it.
I don't know how time is.
Well, we're going to 3.30, so I don't know.
You think it's probably 20 minutes to read those poems or more?
I don't know.
I can stop at 20 minutes though.
But you want to get Patrick a chance to respond to the Lucy sequence and we have some more
things to read.
And to read more to us.
Well I don't know if you can hear back there.
I said, okay, you're where you want to be.
Okay.
This is a sequence about Lucy who is a hominid so called, whose skeleton is approximately
3.2 million years old.
You've probably heard about her.
And they found her skeleton in 1974.
And she was, if I understand it right, she was one of the first early people who was
able to stand up and walk.
And for me she's very much a mother.
And one thing about standing up is you can then hold your child in your arms because
you're not on all fours.
And so that was one of the moving things about her, that development of humans.
And she was found, I told you in 1974, the Ethiopian people where she was found referred
to her as Dinkenos, which is an Amharic language term meaning you are beautiful.
And they called her Lucy, the, what do you call the people who find skeletons?
Anthropologists, paleontologists, people who found her called her Lucy because they got
back to the campground.
Oh, this is a thing I love about this finding.
And if you went to the museums or any of the exhibits you'd see, they were walking along,
end of the long day.
And they didn't see anything, they were looking for her but they couldn't find anything.
And then one of them saw a little gland of light out of his eye and he turned around
and it was a bone poking up from the sand or earth or whatever it was.
And they went back and that was the beginning of the skeleton that they found.
And I love that because it must happen all the time but you know it's just chance what
we would call chance if you hadn't turned around.
You know, somebody else would have found it later maybe but it's so chancey.
And then when they got back to the campground, the radio was playing Lucy in the sky with
diamonds.
This was Beatles time so they named her Lucy from that.
Lucy, your secret book that you leaned over and wrote just in the dirt.
Not having to have an ending, not having to last.
This is a quote from a song.
In thy book all my members were written which in continuance were fashioned when as yet there
was none of them.
And this is the poem again.
Two hands were all you owned for food, for love.
Now you own none Lucy nor no words.
Only breath marks, breath marks only nor no words.
For what do you do now, Lucy, for love, your eyes?
This has a quote from William Carlos Williams, my saxophage that splits the rocks.
Lucy, my saxophage that splits the rocks.
Wild good mother, you fill my center hole with bliss.
No one is so tender in her scream, wants me so much, not just but brings me to be, is
when I am close to death and close to life.
The spider in her web, three days dead on the window, Lucy.
In the electricity of love, it's lightning strike or in its quiet hum in the thighs,
like this little ice box here, not knowing any better, or in the dumb hum of the heater
going on.
Little stirs in the room tone, I rush outdoors into the air you are, Lucy, and you rush out
to receive me, at last there you are, who I always knew was there, but almost died, not
meeting.
When my scraped out child died, Lucy, you hold her all the time.
This one has some names of people I knew who died around this same time, this next one,
also talks about a story of Chekhov's called Easter Eve, where there's a fairy man in
this story whose name is Jero Neem.
Lucy, when the dark bodies dropped out of the towers, when Ruth died and Grace and
Helen Ruth, and Iraq, and Iraq, and Nikolay, Lucy, when Jane in her last clothes goes across
with Chekhov, you are the fairy man, the monk, Jero Neem, who throws your weight on the rope.
I wash my plate and spoon as carefully as a priest.
Did you have a cup, Lucy?
Oh God, who transcends time, let Lucy have a cup.
You Bodhisattva, here with us, you wanted to come back.
I'm afraid and can't pay attention to it.
I'm wild with heat and cold, and my head hurts.
The nine wild turkeys come up calmly to the porch to see you, Lucy.
When I was writing this, I began to get the idea that Lucy's name, at least, was going
to be in every one of these things.
I didn't have any idea about that beforehand, or anything else, really.
This is called My Work of Art for Lucy.
It's a piece of brown wrapping paper taped to the wall over the table in this beautiful
room with no pictures.
First written across the top, quote, it was as if she was standing across the road waiting
to see if anyone wanted to get to know her.
Then taped under that, forgive my German, I'm going to quote Rilke for one line only,
do dare do vise, und gessen, vaiten, svissen.
You, this is Rilke still, you who know and whose vast knowing is born of poverty, abundance
of poverty.
Make it so the poor are no longer despised and thrown away.
Look at them standing around like wildflowers, which have nowhere else to grow.
That's Rilke.
Then a blue panther, a 26 cent stamp from Florida for postcards, then a Catalpa leaf curling
from its huge curving stem, curving rather from its huge curving stem.
The leaf a little broken and its passing from the west onto the east.
And the note, I found this leaf on my way to the post office.
Then Lucy, you, hominid, sapiens, seperi to taste be wise.
Rilkeleton standing around like a wildflower.
Lucy, what you want that I will do to hear you know your poem, but you need nothing.
The deer and the wild turkeys that draw close now to hear you my life is for.
In its language, your voice, I can't tell cold from heat, anxiety, dust, death, no,
not even dust.
So I don't know.
Let's finish it up.
Okay, we'll finish it up.
But hang that too much further to go.
Your picture, brown museum hair, brush the way they brush it there, brow lit from inside,
intelligent eyebrows, a slightly wrinkly nose, a little flat.
Brown woman, I want your nose, your cheekbones of light.
I was brown, I got white.
Her large and friendly mouth, half open, in a half smile, surprised.
But Lucy, your eyes.
So I gave all I had to the poor, standing around like wildflowers.
Lucy, the spider moved last night and again this morning.
I wonder, do you sleep and wake where you are now?
Do spiders hibernate?
Do they lay eggs and webs on window panes?
You must know everything.
Enter the sweet why.
Don't treat it or question why.
Whistle why.
Whisper why.
Was sweetness done to you?
What I wanted most, the mother, has come to me.
Will she stay in my ear?
Lucy, is it you?
Still all night long my Lucy, I entreat you.
I will not let thee go except thou bless me.
Well, here comes another character in the last few pages of this and his name is Martin
Ramirez.
He's what we call an untaught artist.
And I have to just say that I was looking at his work one time.
He did a lot of tunnels, railroad tunnels and railroad tracks and landscapes around railroad
because he was a railroad worker from Mexico, came to California.
What they say had a nervous breakdown, no longer could do that work, was put into a hospital
and mental hospital in California where he began to draw and paint.
And different people in the hospital helped him and brought him crayons and pencils and
paper and everything he needed and gave him time.
And one of the doctors particularly collected his work and that's why we have it.
And so when you go to these folk art museums and so forth you can find his work there,
Martin Ramirez.
And I don't know how he got into this but here he is.
Except I love him.
That could be why.
You think so?
You love coming to the poems, don't they?
Martin Ramirez, be with me.
It looks, oh this is something I heard in the gallery when I was looking at one of his
paintings of tunnels.
I'll start over.
Martin Ramirez, be with me.
It looks just like a vagina, a bystander said.
Yes, it is a vagina with chains and tunnels and like in the great cathedrals a clitoris,
a starry one and a womb, John T. Martin being born, Lucy, did you hear animal woman screams
in the night?
Were you afraid?
Was it you last night?
Your scream over and over as you give birth.
How did you pray, Lucy?
You were a prayer, your hands and toes.
When writing came back to me, I prayed with lipstick on the windshield as I drove.
Newton made up with the world.
He had already turned himself into gold.
He was already there.
A skeleton woman in, down, over, around.
Blessing from the old English bleats the end.
Its root is the same as for blood.
My head is at your window, Lucy, at your glass.
But we offer nothing but money now.
We beam it to each other near and far.
But you are my skeleton mother.
I bring you coffee in your cemetery bed.
This morning I miss most of all you, Martin, and her who when you were born looked and
blessed your beauty.
You see, when you are with me, I feel the atoms racing everywhere in this old oak table
in the eight pointed double star spider and in the starry rippling all around us.
Newton woman, guardian, death woman, Lucy, here, a picnic, cornbread, here, an orange
with my teen and me at the lip of the earth's surface world.
So, last semester, this spring, actually, I first taught this course in the fall semester
to undergraduates.
It's about digital remix of all things.
And that I taught it again as a graduate seminar in this past spring.
So Lucy Palmas is one of the assignments that I signed in this digital remix course.
So for the remix, for those of you who might not be familiar with the concept, essentially
remix is gathering random or disorganized data or even organized data for that matter
and then reorganizing it into another form.
Any kind of data can be sound or whatever.
This is how I've almost always composed poems because I came out of a music production background.
I thought about gathering data, gathering bits and figuring out ways in which these different
pieces fit together.
Reading the Lucy poem gave me this window, I think, into what many, if not all of Jean's
poems are about or the process anyway.
And that I think it's about collecting bits.
And it's very clear.
She was sort of, she was making the commentary and she was going along, but there's a quote
from Assam.
There's a catalog of the dead.
There's personal memory.
There's an elegiac address.
These are not necessarily things that you will find next to one another.
Up here in this long poem inspired by Lucy, she draws them together and rearranges them.
I don't mean to talk about you in third person, but it's funny, Eugene.
I'm happy.
I actually had never heard of Joseph Cornell before Jean had told me about his work.
And I'm fascinated now with his boxes.
And I see a real correlation between what Cornell is doing in terms of collecting these
bits and arranging them in boxes and what you're doing in poems.
Is that, do you see that parallel as well?
Not until this matter.
But I'm very happy with it.
Is this still working?
I'm very happy with it.
I love him as you know, and is my cooking?
Yes.
I get you.
Yeah, I love him.
But I've never thought of doing that.
But on purpose, you know, like he did.
But you know, he did it first little brother.
It's so sweet.
Yeah.
So I guess that would be a wonderful reason to make anything.
I'm so happy to know that you love him so much too.
Yeah.
I think the other thing that I love about that sequence too is that the book has, it's
elegiac also, the book.
I mean, it has the elegy for Reginald Shepard in there too.
And so this long sequence ends a book that goes in and out of elegy.
This is a long sequence that ends up addressing the dead.
And it's the oldest dead that we know in some ways, the oldest standing dead that we know.
And I love that pairing.
And what is it that paleontologists do?
They excavate.
They dig up the remains.
I think poets are trying to do that also.
And in fact, in DJ culture, one of the things that you learn is the art of digging, which
is going into record stores and finding sounds and records that nobody has found before.
Right?
And anyway, so on so many different levels, that long poem, I mean, it's just a moving
poem anyway in terms of both personal and long historical meditation on motherhood, on
being in the world, on death, on living, on making art for that matter.
On so many levels, that poem is beautiful to me.
And I think that if I told people that you work, I find these parallels between your
work and mine or the way that I think about art, I think if people heard us, people saw
us walking together in the street, they'd be like, what an uncoupled they are.
In my mind, I think we make the most sense, actually.
Yeah.
I feel the same way.
I'm so happy.
Well, because I do think when I'm reading through this book of yours, which I have here
Bone Shepherd, it's really a sequence, too.
I feel that.
You know?
I don't know if you've thought of it that way, any of you.
But it really may partly come from being in such a, your family's part of diaspora and
your drawing on a lot of that and your travels back and your travels back here and all that.
And that's a little further back in my life.
But I wonder, quite a few generations back.
But I wonder if part of that is maybe unconsciously wanting to bring things together a little
bit.
Absolutely.
Like making a box for your younger brother or putting things in it, even if it's not
a pointed to sequence, things that do kind of, I felt that reading your book a lot, yeah,
this book.
And I feel it when you read, you know, from music to speech, too.
That's another kind of historical sequence, isn't it?
For everyone.
But with you, it's very, very alive, you know?
And I love that.
So I wonder if this happens to you, because what happens to me, and there's poets in the
room, I'm sure I'd love to hear.
When I was writing the Lucy thing, I was very fortunate, because I was in one of these artist
colonies for probably a month or something.
I had nothing to do at all.
And so, except if I could write something.
But with that kind of silence or any kind of silence we can find, you know, or a little
space, maybe in the summer vacation or something like that.
I wonder if things come to you the way, I just sort of sat there, and things come, you
know, by themselves.
If you can have that kind of quiet, sometimes that will happen.
It doesn't always happen.
But this poem, that was happening.
You know, I'm just copying down.
Wow.
Really great.
Coping down what I heard.
So a lot of it came just as it was.
Because I've seen you sort of, I'm confessing here that I've peaked over your shoulder while
you're kind of composing on your yellow pad, and I see you arranging and crossing out.
Yeah, I'll do that.
But for this poem, it seemed to sort of let itself out.
Pretty much as is.
You know, I had to look up some stuff, but I even went to the house and used the phone.
I didn't have a cell phone.
I went up to the house of the writer's colony and called up a friend, mutual friend of
ours, Anne-Marie Macare.
I said, I can't stop writing this thing.
I said, I've been depressed, but I've never been manic.
You think I'm in trouble?
You know, I was going day after day, you know, writing this thing.
She said, you know, she said, isn't it funny when something good happens.
People think they've done something wrong.
Yeah, and she said, it sounds like you've got a little more to do on that poem.
Why don't you go on back and do it?
And she said, just don't operate any heavy machinery.
You can hear her say.
I can totally hear her say.
Both of her, you know, in common.
But it was just amazing.
I don't usually certainly get things like that, but I wondered if you do sometimes.
Occasionally.
And it does, I mean, teaching doesn't allow for a whole lot of silence because most of
that quiet time is being used to think about my students and so forth.
But you know, I just told you I moved to Philadelphia about a month and a half ago.
And it's a different quality of silence than living in New York City or other places that
I've been.
And there's a kind of, I don't know, you just settle into a place.
And images arrive.
I think part of it is that the silence allows me to access deep memory.
And that doesn't necessarily mean that this deep memory is whole.
Sometimes this deep memory is fragmented, but it's their intense fragments.
So yeah, I have a very intimate relationship with silence.
I would have thought so.
Yeah.
So if you want to help an artist, give them some silence.
That's it.
That's the thing.
Yeah.
That's why they had that poetry school down by the way.
Down by the ocean, a couple of rocks.
It's got the waves, but nothing much else.
Oh God.
So, Packard, maybe you could read a couple more of your beautiful poems.
Yeah.
I'm sure which ones I gave you later.
I'm just going to start picking from the book.
I wonder if maybe I'll read a couple of poems that I don't normally read out loud.
There's still quite narrative of the poems, but they make more lyric leaps in Al-Ajean
Valentine than many of my other poems do.
So this one's called Undrowning.
In Spanish, there's a word called disallerci.
I learned that word from my friend Jessica and it sort of gave me this poem.
She was going through a hard time and her mom said that you have to undrown yourself.
Yeah.
Undrowning.
Who needs to be convinced of loneliness in murmurs?
In the palimpsest of a few words rising out of a sentence you don't understand, unless
it's whispered directly into your fingers.
The rain itself isn't terrible.
But sometimes I believe whole oceans are lifted in the name of some worshiped fury and dropped
into our eyes mid-life.
You tell me the word is disallerci, which is to say you've already drowned.
And to undrown you must recall how the light of Venice's lamps and the stars long traveled
a reverent burn break on the wake of a small boat, ferrying you and a couple friends.
One you now grieve, another an opera singer, drunk her hair you remember sweeping over
the prowl.
If the gondolier speaks a word of English, it is yes, which is one of two words in the
language to contain so many disparate categories of sadness.
I mean in the whole of one syllable, half a universe stays afloat, sinks, swims back
up with too much liquor or wine in its blood, and in drowning or its opposite, a life doesn't
flash before your very eyes.
But if I say the multitudes of ghosts put to sleep by centuries of conquerors awaken in
your veins.
And you must answer them with a grief that is neither famous nor deadly.
It's even simpler than that.
One Saturday night you sit under the slant ceiling of your cramped kitchen in a winter
that's lasted a few extra days into spring, doing precise damage to a bottle of coconut
rum that will pay you four times back.
You turn up the sad tangos your lovely shit-talking father used to sing, he who could dream in
the steel language of flight, and you weep.
Your lamentation counts you squarely among the living.
Get either.
I'm sorry a beautiful young man you once laughed with under the near blaze of a foreign sky
while an opera singer slammed her melismatic eyes into the stone and glass of a city sinking
into its shallow glacial canals is dead.
We can't call up all the wreckage of generations.
Do not forget you are witness to a scent.
Tonight sleep well.
When solitude calls it doesn't mean to kill but offers the kind of sight one earns when
you've lain a long time still.
It's a beauty.
Let me read Despely d'Ardiente.
I was teaching at an MFA program in the hall.
You can teach a line.
You can teach meter, you can teach rhythm, you can teach form.
There's a lot of things that you can teach.
The hardest thing to teach, maybe it's impossible to teach, is how to make a poem blaze.
This is my urging towards my students to make it blaze.
Despely d'Ardiente.
Dear feverless, dear poets, dear love sick ones now cured.
There are bloodless battles to be won, but stout your maw with your finest curses.
Yap your demons to their proper graves.
O meek weepers, asymmetries, be kissed.
Let the trash stack in the kitchen.
Keep your lover a full day from work.
O sweet neglect, O nectarine, those bitter pits are meant for more than nibbling.
There is a holy jump off.
There is a funky genesis.
There is a reason love and jive kind of rhyme.
You oblong fruit not three days ripe.
Somewhere in you lies the science of typhoons, a dream of strings.
Oh dirty word, oh first murder, oh cocoa butter whiff on a smoky bus.
There are theories were made of mostly nothing but motion.
Oh dap tooth guitar.
Oh sound hole, you far away drum, you slang mouth blessing, you long time, you chamberless
sex step.
Let me leave you with a few last words.
When mad dogs break chains to run at you, charge back.
Bear your very teeth.
No monster I promise outruns you.
Let them on the ankle with a stick, chase the bastards down.
Listen, this vertigo, this wreckage, this bad ballad straining the thickest tendons of
your legs.
Oh darling sleepers, may you wake in the middle of the night strange.
Sounds you champions of laughter.
All you have to do is speak simply.
Your business is the truth.
Your hearts catastrophe is just a little a histories twisted bulwark.
If there were not a sky within your chest worth breaking, believe me, you would have
stopped all this singing by now.
Hey, that's so great.
I guess I could tell a story about that poem.
I was teaching at the University of Texas at Austin at the time.
One of my colleagues was doing a project in which he was getting several different people
to record song of myself, every line.
I think there might have been six or eight of us who did it separately.
I went into the studio and for one day in one session I performed song of myself out loud
all the way through.
I didn't take any breaks but I would flub a line occasionally.
It's remarkable how easily his long lines sort of fly.
You can imagine the physical intensity of doing that poem I was exhausted.
I fell asleep by 8.30.
But I woke up at 1.30 in the morning and this poem came out.
That's one poem that did come out.
And I know that the spirit of song of myself was in that poem.
That's a great story.
I'm sure he's glad.
That's wonderful though about how the spirit and the body are one and you can get into
someone else's spirit and body.
I'm going to go home and do that.
See if I can get something too.
Yeah.
Oh boy.
We could all do that.
Yeah.
I have a theory that poetry does on maybe molecular or sub-molecular levels and maybe
there's research already done about this.
That it changes the body.
Do you believe that too?
Yeah, I do.
Yeah.
Like music does.
Right?
Yeah.
I suppose that's one reason why we love it so much.
You think?
I mean even when we're little kids we love it so much.
You're poetry.
Come in and change our bodies and make us feel better.
Yeah.
You know people always talk about Emily Dickinson as being Emily Dickinson and Jean Valentine.
Did what men play a part in your reading life?
Does he continue to?
I mean they're always sort of posing them apart as these kind of binaries right?
Emily Dickinson.
And what women?
I think that's crazy.
Yeah.
They say he's the man and she's the woman.
No I think they're very much, I think they're very much, I mean they're called the mother
and father of our poetry and all that but I mean that doesn't do any harm I suppose
just to think we have one but you know or two but I don't see that myself.
You know I think they were both going right to the heart of what was going on and coming
out different but.
They were both.
I mean I suppose it would be like thinking, I don't quite what I want to say but like
thinking men and women are different than we are but we are so much the same.
You know much more the same.
I also think you know they don't sit out to do what they do they just do what they can
right?
Just like all the rest of us.
I think Dickinson just did what she could and he did what he could and they were called
differently but I don't see them as opposed to each other at all.
I feel like they give us ourselves and lucky us, lucky us you know.
It's just beautiful.
What if we only had one of them?
Wouldn't be as rich.
But I think that kind of opposition is silly don't you?
I think it makes everything smaller instead of what we got.
We could have only had one of them but somebody had to dig up Emily's poems out of the drawers
and make sure we got them.
She didn't try to get them to us.
That's right.
At the beginning I guess you tried to.
I guess it didn't show anything away.
That's true.
I think.
That you probably put there was probably a great deal of feeling involved in the way
she strung the poems together into those little booklets.
Oh yeah.
Oh absolutely.
Yeah.
So did you want to share some new poems with us?
You said that you might.
Those were some together.
Mine are stuck together with white out.
All of the part.
I take out and write something else over.
You know what white out is?
I don't know if in this age you use it anymore but that's my sad state anyway.
Let that one go for the moment.
This is a strange one.
They're all strange to me anyway.
They're strange when they come to us don't you think?
If we're lucky.
They are.
This is called for Robert Lowell who was a teacher of many of ours of my age and younger.
And I'll just read it.
I looked and there he was my father in poetry, my guide to the underworld.
I was shy to speak.
He said here take my hand.
We cross here.
And I said what you went to earth for.
Did you find it?
He was tall in a blue shirt.
He pointed across the street.
Over there he said that was the last time I saw Delmore.
And I shared it said at the beginning Delmore Schwartz was a good friend of his and died
before Lowell then.
So that's how he came into that.
And I don't know if you read him anymore.
You do?
Yeah.
I think he's wonderful.
I also love his name.
So you know both those things got him in there.
I wanted the sound of Delmore as much as I wanted.
Not as much but also you know.
It's to me that you were describing a dream.
It felt like you were talking about a dream of being with Robert Lowell and saying that
you were doing that.
Maybe that's some of the oddness of...
It is odd isn't it?
Yeah I think between dreams and poems I'm not sure where one ends and the next begins
you know for me anyway.
The three words I often mix up are poem, memory and dream.
Yeah.
They slip into each other's categories.
Do you ever read that book?
Memories, dreams, reflections.
I love that one too.
I read one more it's called song.
I was...
Oh this...
This has a little back reference which isn't going to be in the poem but since we're sitting
here together it's another untaught artist.
Gee what's his name?
Finster.
I don't know if you know Finster.
It's Howard Finster and there's also an echo poem you'll hear it.
Stevie Smith, very famous line of hers.
I was not waving but drowning.
It's very famous so I thought I could echo that without people being lost.
Song.
I was asking pardon who am I of them who I am, pardon, of the slow wearing gown, of
the window, the sun.
I was asking forgiveness, of the crocodile, that good hider, of the heron, that good feeder
and of Christ the Pelican.
Christ said over a thousand pages of scripture and I was not reading but dreaming.
It's the same right now he said.
He just stood there.
I was not painting but watching the animals.
I was not copying but dreaming.
Over one thousand newborns in this clearing we started to lick some clean, dreaming one
by one.
Thank you very much.
Patrick did you want to say anything on the first hearing?
We get smarter.
I was thinking about the Neruda epigraph in my book and both of us have a relationship
to the dead.
Not necessarily in a Macaw way but in a way about how to think about who we are in history
and where we go.
I think even in your book you talk about you trouble time also.
Time and matter, run into one another and the straight hour of time gets confused in
your poem.
If time is reoriented or redefined then so does our relationship to death has to do.
So the dead, the dead, like Lowell in this particular poem is allowed to come back and
instruct us where to cross.
The other thing I love about your poems is that some of the matter that remains after
I read the poem are questions like who is the cheetah or what is the cheetah.
You have the space cheetah in your book.
This is an exercise that I asked my beginning poetry students do all the times.
I would say anything authoritative about a poem right away.
Ask questions.
And so with your poems I find myself with the questions and I'm able to sort of hold
on to those questions for a while.
And they're often very interesting questions about how to live, about time, about space,
about the dead.
They invoke other lyric lines for me too.
So you find that when you're writing too, that you're asking questions, maybe when
you finish something, like where did that come from?
Yeah, I'm sure you do because I can hear it in your poem.
I showed this Lowell thing to somebody and they said, oh yeah, he's showing you how to
cross the street or something like that.
And I said, yeah, I was surprised when he said that.
It was like I think it sort of spoke some or something.
But I was surprised when that came, when I was writing it.
You know how come?
It sounded okay.
It's interesting.
I think when I'm having a hard time writing, the questions are happening, but I don't hear
them or I am refusing them.
And so when I have the silence that you were talking about earlier, it's like I can make
space for the questions and the unknown and the uncertainty of the poem.
All you and I need is a do we know castle.
Yes.
Good day.
You and I and everybody else here.
You can buy one, let's go get away.
Just get quiet for a while.
Yeah, and then all the terrible angels will arrive.
That's true they will.
They will say hello.
So maybe we can open things up to the audience and they can begin to participate out loud.
Anybody want to ask a question or make a comment?
Yes.
My question is why do you say the poem changes the body?
I always thought the poem changes probably the mind, the spirit, maybe the soul, but it
definitely gets you away from the body.
And I like mics because in a mic, with the mic, through a mic, the poem even gets away
from the human voice.
It gets into a life of its own and stands in the room by itself, away from the poet because
ultimately the poet is also a body is part of this earth and the poem gets us away from
all of that.
So that's why I was wondering I never heard that the poem changes the body.
So that's my question.
It's a theory that I have that the poems change the body.
I know that when I've gone to poetry readings, the poems are really good.
I feel something in my body.
I don't have a description for it.
Emily Dickinson said that it feels like the top of her head comes off.
And she used the body.
She didn't compare it.
It feels like the sky.
It feels like something in her body is happening.
For her, the top of her head is coming off.
For me, I don't know.
Sometimes my hair stands up.
Sometimes I've felt so moved by a poem that I want to jump up and run.
I've felt that many, many times.
I don't know if it's true or not.
There's something about it.
I think also that deep memory resides.
I think that I believe that geneticists are going to find out that deep memory gets handed
down across DNA.
And if that's true, then what role does intense language like poetry have in the making of
the human body at the DNA level?
We don't have tools to measure that yet.
I'm just proposing that.
Maybe somebody with $75 billion to do the research.
But I put the question out there.
I suspect it.
And I think it also goes back to something that Jean said that early on, poetry as a
written art is much younger than poetry as a bodily and performed art.
It was meant to be in the body.
It was meant to be performed and shared in a room full of bodies.
Many times those bodies were dancing.
And so I think that you can't just erase that very old and persistent tradition of the body
and its relationship to poetry.
Well, the meter is dance steps.
Exactly.
And that's the fundamental aspect of the sound of poetry is meter in some way.
Or the notion of plowing a field, right?
The work of the body in the field, going along the lines.
So it's just an idea.
I also think of singing, the mother singing to the baby.
Oh, yeah.
That's a very fundamental kind of poetry, whatever's going on, I think.
Excuse me though.
You go ahead.
I just want to weigh in on that.
I think the poem has a life of its own.
Okay.
Patrick, two questions.
Is it fair to ask you the Tagalog word for suddenly seized by affection?
Yes, Tagalog word for suddenly seized by affection is gigal.
Spell it.
G-I-G-I-L.
Gigal.
And pronounce the second syllable, emphasize?
That's the first gigal.
No, it's the first syllable.
Gigal.
Yeah.
So if you see, I just saw a video of my god daughter last night.
And so I felt a gigal towards her and she's Nakaka Gigal.
But the L isn't pronounced like an L in English, right?
It's close.
There might be a slightly different, yeah?
Okay.
The other question for you is when you read that poem, how to make a poem blaze.
I love this line.
Still it.
When a bad dog, when bad dogs break chains to want you, bite back?
When mad dogs break chains to chase you charge back.
To change, okay.
I love, I just revise it.
That's pretty good, not one hearing.
Bite back.
I wrote bite back.
Yeah.
Okay, good.
So we'll use that.
And I can always look that up to sighted great.
Jean, I was very moved by our meeting when I spoke to you about having been studied with
Marie Ponceau.
And you said, I'm not worthy.
You did that gesture.
I'm not worthy.
We were so pleased.
And then I said, I'll give her your regards.
And after I said that, I thought, well, when in hell am I going to see Marie?
And then you said to me, she's right behind you.
So that was really a great moment for me.
Chekov is somebody I've been studying.
I mentioned to Marie, I'm studying with Professor Tom Bird, who's a doll.
He's been at Queen's College.
I think since the 1950s, long time, and still teaching.
And we studied short stories of Chekov.
So I remember there was a short story, they had a fairy boat.
Do you happen to remember the story?
What is that?
Easter Eve.
May I have lost my mind.
It's called Easter Eve.
Easter Eve.
Great.
Thank you so much.
Wonderful story.
Anyone else want to thank the comment or ask a good question?
That's for the obvious.
Gina, if you could, I'd like to ask you to talk a little bit about how your work might
have evolved in a way that in Lucy, for example, you have these very small intersections of
awareness that the speaker of the poem that you have of a moment of a relationship with
Lucy.
And they're so simple.
And yet in that simplicity, you find such poignancy that I wondered if that type of a
trained eye was something that you found over the course of your writing career, an ability
to distill or find the more critical essential bits and pieces and pair away more of the
unimportant parts of a poem.
In other words, do you define that your work became sparrow more essential if that's clear
or is it poem by poem maybe different?
Does that make sense?
I think I started out more sort of saying everything in a more grammatical way than I
do now.
And I've noticed over the years I take more out, you know, I might write a lot and take
a lot of it out and ask my friends, you know, if it still makes sense.
But that's more a way I work now.
And I've also come to love sequences because I might write something and it doesn't amount
too much, but then if I put twelve of them together, it might, you know, so that's something
I came to later.
Yeah.
But I'm not so big on sense as I used to be.
And I think it was really being able to be with other poets and read more also.
And boredom, boredom can be your friend.
You know, if you just are writing something that you've written before or you've seen
written before, you might not have any interest in it.
So you might go somewhere else, you know, even if it's what you feel.
But it doesn't have any life for you.
Do you know what I'm saying?
It's not that it isn't true, but it isn't alive for you anymore.
And so I don't mean just to put something in a new way for newness's sake.
That's another thing I would try out to do because that's boring too.
But it can be when I try it sometimes.
Just to kind of feel your way and see how much you really need, you know.
And then I couldn't live without my poet friends because then I asked them, you know, do you
think this is there or not, you know?
Okay.
Thanks.
Is that kind of answer?
Yes, very much.
Also if I could just add, they did do a study, I don't know if it cost 75 million, but once
you've been in the woods for three hours, your body physically changes chemically.
So I'm sure the same would be true of reading poetry.
Yeah, that's great to know.
Wow.
Please.
I don't like these things, microphones.
But I love your presentation.
And it's really an honor to be here and hear you both talk about writing poetry and reading
so much poetry.
It was wonderful.
And I agree when I've only been writing poetry for about seven years and, you know, like
not full time, but a lot.
And when I write, I feel the same thing with the spirit and the soul, you know, that is
there that was in your Lucy poem and in your dog poem.
And, you know, I mean, it's just, it's wonderful.
It's wonderful getting out of the body.
I don't know what it is.
It's supposedly like other artists tell me that that happens when they paint a painting
or whatever, you know, they're, I don't know because I can't do anything else.
You know, I can walk.
And my spirit.
I feel, you know, my soul is happy when I'm walking, but it's not like, you know, I don't
know that nitty gritty, you know, deep down soul changing.
And it comes out on the page, which is so exciting.
And I don't know what's going to come out on the page, you know.
And that is, that's the thrill, you know.
I wish I could do more.
But thanks for giving me the idea of the sequence thing because I never did that.
And I think I might try that.
That Lucy is so wonderful the way you brought her to life, you know.
When you read the first piece, I said, oh no, you know.
But as you went on to each other piece, I said, oh, this lady has something going.
Yeah.
Thank you.
You know, it's interesting because if you read other sequences that can get you kind
of maybe towards it.
I was reading The Orpheus Sonnets when I was writing Lucy.
And I didn't sit down to do that.
It just happened.
But I think it's like, you know, it can help you.
If you read other people's sequences, whatever you're looking for, you know.
It seems like you were saying about Whitman too.
It can help you out.
Not being directly imitative in any way, you know.
But just like soul to soul.
Yeah.
Who's your wife in the game?
We are.
Which one are you?
I'll be you.
Okay.
No, it's so much fun because we didn't get the chance to do this before.
I've admired you from that part of the room.
It's so much fun to do this.
Thank you, David, for asking us to read together.
Well, I'm very glad we're coming in a real pleasure.
I'm sure for everyone.
So our time is up.
So we'll stop for this afternoon.
And we'll do something like this in the fall.
Excellent.
Thank you.
I've got to stop right now, let me go.