Welcome to the Hillick Center, I'm Edner Sessien, the Director, just a couple of...
No? Can you hear me now? Okay, so just a couple things before we I introduced the
participants of tonight today's roundtable in two weeks from now I think it's
November 22nd we have a roundtable on translation matters and it was organized
by Anne-Marie Levine and the participants are David Ballus, Bella Brodsky, Suzanne
Gill-Lavigne, Mark Politzotti and Michelle Woods. Then the first weekend of
December I believe it's the fifth and the sixth we have a meeting with the French
group Adapas and that's a think tank which has a section that is devoted to
Freud's work and there will be two days of meetings about four or five round
tables with participants from Europe and the US and some of the people who will
be here participating for that are Philip Dus Blazie who is the who's a
past foreign affairs minister of France Charles Melman who is the founder of the
Lacanian Association International Association Mark Smoller who's the
president of the American Psychoanalytic Association Ian Buckingham who's the
president of this association Paul Fry is a professor of English literature
from Yale Vincent Capenzano is a professor of anthropology and
comparative literature from the City University Jean Michel Rabat who's a
professor of English from UPenn and Emil Malet who is the editor of a
journal called Passage also will be a diplomat George Agash and Pierre de
Sennath Cleans who is professor of international affairs in Geneva so it's a
diverse group and the title of the whole conference is in which way Freud's work
can help us understand the what ills society today so today's round table is
on speak memory aside from being composed of water proteins fats and
sugar we are composed of memories and hopefully we will learn more about it
today I will not go into the details of everybody CV because I think you have it
already why will introduce them Christina Alberini sitting there is
professor in the Center for Neural Science at NYU Sven Bernakar sitting
here is professor of philosophy University of California Irvine Tom
Karoo is professor of neuroscience NYU Center for Neuroscience Martin Conway is
professor of cognitive psychology city University London and Penelope Lewis a
senior lecturer of neuroscience at University of Manchester about to move
to University of Cardiff so the format is there's no preparation you will
speak spontaneously and try to enlighten us thank you
I'm the count of 3b found spontaneous is that
well I'm not sure if I'm ready to start but I can try since no one else is I think
my attempt to start would be by saying can you reiterate the question which you
want us to try and answer in this discussion and then then we can start
to discuss it why don't you start by you saying what's memory
that's that's quite a difficult
well all right I'll give my perspective on what memory is and then and then
these guys can tell me why I'm wrong for me a memory is stored representations
stored representations and I'm not going any further than that other people can
elaborate and he's going out on the limb with that since I happen to be in the
loop I'll pick up where she left off it's a it's actually a very deep question
there's not a one-stop answer to that on the one hand everyone in this room is
convinced that their memories are real but they also convinced their their
memories are true the former is definitely the case the latter is only 50 50 the
case there are many cases in this room and around the world and everybody's
study of memory that are you have an intense feeling of a memory that's real
but in fact it's not true it's not accurate not always but sometimes and I'm
sure Christina will pick up on that theme for the idea coming back to you
consolidate a memory so I think that to open the conversation it's I see
memories is essentially threads in a tapestry and each memory is a piece of
that and after a while we've assembled a tapestry that no longer has individual
elements any longer but has color and shape and texture pattern and that
becomes this kind of it captures our collective aggregate experience and in a
very real way we are our memories I mean that's what you got when you ask who you
are you think of your kids you think of your experiences you're relying on your
memories to extensively to calibrate and express the person that you would point
to when you pointed yourself so in a very real way with the sum total of our
memories then we'll get into what happens between our ears that'll be later I'll
toss it to my friend okay I want to make the point starting from the biology
which is where I come from I got interested in memory exactly because of
what Tom just said is a complex function is who we are we are who we are
because of our memories and when I got interested in this coming from a
background of biology that was very little known and we shared the same
mystery here we did the same type of progression in trying to understand
or address some questions about the biology of memory and I think in the
last I would say 25 30 years there has been a tremendous tremendous progress
in understanding of how the brain process information and store information so
memory is retention of information and then we use that stored information when
necessary and we do that by retrieving the memories more and more it becomes
clear in the last as I said 25 years that the storage of memory is very dynamic
and although before it was believed that storing information means to keep them
in a fixed fixated way in the brain now we know that that's not true we keep
updating our memories and so this has also a lot to do with what Tom was saying
our memories are not reflecting the reality of the experiences that happen
but they are constantly elaborated so we store information and then we retrieve
that information in a new context in a new moment in a different time and we
restore them in a different way and we keep doing that and and therefore that's
why we have memories that are not reflecting the reality but they are
reflecting a re-elaboration of history continues re-elaboration of our history
so those phenomenon or processes are called technically consolidation or
re-consolidation a new memory exists for some time in a labile state and during
that time which is temporarily limited it's strengthened and it become resilient
to disruption so initially as I said it's fragile so we can disrupt it easily if
some interference comes around it could be another learning event some pharmacology
some other type of interferences that can be used are disrupting the memories
very easily during this initial phase and in the biology field this was an
important discovery because one of the interfering events that can't disrupt
memories as soon as they're formed or prevent long-term memory formation are
compounds that block new synthesis of proteins and this is where biology
became biologists became very fascinated about the question of what are these
new proteins that are made to strengthen to make this memory strong and
resilient to disruption and in the last 20 years there's been you know great
progress in understanding those proteins and the regulation of how those
proteins are made are you talking about memory in general or particular kinds of
memory we're talking about long-term memories and thank you for the question
that reminds me to say that this is an evolutionally concerned feature of
long-term memory formation and it has been found to to be required in many
different types of memories so it's a general feature of long-term memory
formation so once they are stable these memories they if they are retrieved they
become fragile again and again there is another temporal window during which the
memory re-stabilized so by analogy the process that with retrieval the memory
becomes labeled and then re-stabilizes again is called re-consolidation and
there has been many studies in the field trying to understand what re-consolidation
is about because if we think there is it is not really advantageous to have a
memory made long-term and stable and then with retrieval make it lay by it
again why should it be that way doesn't make much sense right why did why was
it stabilized in the first place become lay by again with retrieval and and
again in the last several years several labs have tried to address this question
which is not fully understood but certainly we know that during this time
is it gives the opportunity to memory to the memories that are retrieved to
change and therefore to change the strength they can be modulated they can
become stronger or they can weaken or new association can be linked to the
retrieved information and this is why the updating occurs continuously
otherwise our memories will be compartmentalized and we will not be
able to make new association with the old experiences so all these mechanisms
are clearly very exciting in treating important for understanding how memory
work they have a lot of repercussion in the clinical questions and to mention
one definitely in psychoanalysis and in psychotherapy where the subject recalls
memories and then in the new setting with the therapist to re-elaborate the
memories think I'm gonna stop because otherwise I keep talking I thought I
thought it was very succinct well to do this I mean it's a real issue about
what memory is because it's lots of different things you know mine my
knowledge that Paris is the capital of France is memory but that's very
different from my knowledge all very nice restaurants I went to last night
which in turn is very different from my abilities and ride a bicycle for example
which is also memory I think the type of memory we've been most interested in
in recent times in the more behavioral cognitive area of the field is what's
called autobiographical memory so memory for the knowledge and the events of our
lives and it turns out that this this knowledge the representations of
episodes of experience and conceptual knowledge about our own lives is highly
dynamic as you said and if you put someone in a scan over look what's going
on in their brain when they recall not to biographical memory you get
activation from the front part of the brain it's almost as though the brain
sort of breathes a memory if you want and it's in this area where when people
suffer brain damage and also in in an older age when the brain changes that we
start to see impairments emerging and it's those impairments which have been I
think quite a big focus of a lot of recent research in this area so memory is a
lot of different things I think the autobiographical memory episodic memory
kind of area is the one where at the cognitive behavioral end would be most
interested in recent years
even the autobiographical memory it might be interesting for the group before I
return to you but just because to leverage up of your statement how many
you in the room have heard of a patient called HM yeah not so many so you know
in clinical it is a clinical tradition to always just use the initials of a
patient to for confidentiality but HM passed in with the last ten years they
was Henry Mullisness but the reason it's so interesting relevant to what
Sven said is the following because he was a sea change in how we understood
memory systems in the human this is a young man who fell off his bicycle as a
teenager had a horrible accident with his head and then was given to seizures
thereafter forever I mean it's to the degree that he would be probably die
from these seizures they were recurrent and just horrible and at the time there
was a surgeon and Hartford Connecticut named Scoville who did a kind of
surgery to remit seizures and what he did was to take out part of the brain
bilaterally but the brain is a bit like a walnut you open it up and it's more
less palindromic structurally so he took out some part of the brain called the
hippocampus and some other structures in the temporal lobe and the seizure stopped
and so from that point of view Henry HM was not cured but was better but a
devastating consequence of this surgery was the fact that he never
remembered a proactive fact again exactly the kinds of fact he remembered how to
ride a bike he could learn how to trace a mirror backwards and he's starring a
mirror backwards so there's things he could learn but the person that studied
him forever was Brenda Milner a gifted woman in Canada and then her
students isn't working and every day we come in hello Henry do you know me says
no I don't my name is Brenda nice to see you great they would work together all
day she come the next day in Hartford hello Henry do you know me no I don't
for 25 years for 25 years why that was important in all kinds of ways was that
here is a fellow who could learn certain kinds of things just find and
remember them new tasks like riding a bike or and the like but had this
devastating amnesia going forward he was also outraged at the price of
refrigerators on TV because he remembered with them back 25 years ago and he was
outraged that there were now hundreds of dollars it showed across 35 because
that was the last that was where he was frozen in time and it taught us
dramatically that there are different literally different neural substrates
different real estate in the brain that take care of different kinds of memories
because one was destroyed and one was completely intact we knew that a little
bit before but that was a startling case and so the connection that we've all
been deeply affected by is the basic science that Christine and I do but also
the connection to the human condition which is not just an end in itself but
terribly informative and how we think about memory in modern terms
it's all yours so the question was what memory is and we have the initial
definition according to which memory are memories are stored representations and
I think that is a that is a very apt account but in some respects it doesn't
seem to cover enough and in other respects I think it needs to be things
need to be to be added so Mark already mentioned the the many different kinds
of memories habit memories or procedural memories and declarative memories
semantic and episodic and so on and so the question I think would be whether
really all of these various phenomena can be subsumed under this heading of
stored representations whether learning how to write a bicycle or certain
procedures learning how to how to walk upstairs whether that is the learning
of a representation in other respects the definition of memory as stored
representations maybe doesn't isn't detailed enough because of course
representations can be stored in many different ways in books archives store
representations or at least can be portrayed as the storage of representation
so what's so special about storing representations in the head as opposed to
outside of the head or the body as opposed to outside of the body and it
seems at least to me that not it's a particular kind of storage that warrants
the name memory you mentioned really truth and you said many of the things
that we seem to remember aren't in fact the case the way they are we talk readily
about false memories from my perspective false memories aren't memories they are
they give the impression of a memory but they are in memories they don't give us
a window into the past they don't allow us to know about the past things like
problem with that though is that if the person who's remembering a false memory
experiences as a memory they don't question it it's just a memory for them
then I think maintaining it's not a memory becomes problematic I agree well in
that respect it's like any fact of attitude to take knowledge many of the
things that I claim to know I actually don't know because they aren't the case
they're false so I think it's a treacherous slope to say false I mean I
just I'm interrupting it but go ahead but I think that there's nothing
wrong with a false memory say it again we want the discussion so it's okay to
interrupt well then okay but but do you know
Dick Nizer is so Dick Nizer did a beautiful series of studies this was a guy
he was one of the fathers of this field he's at Emory University before in
Europe and he took advantage of the Challenger disaster yeah and 1986 so
if I first folks in the room it can see me if I do this does that mean anything
to anybody what's that what did what just happened in your head when I do
that exactly so you saw two white trails on an azure blue sky so folks who can
visually bring that that's a memory and I just evoked it without a word right
well he took advantage at Emory University of going around the day of
that disaster there's many of the kinds of studies but his is canonical and
said where were you Penny when were you when that where were you at when that
happened and the kind of what he at the time what he would hear from students
would be what I'm gonna now recount is if my wife my marriage on I've been
married 51 years she's over in the corner so we've been together most of
our lives that's important because if I would answer him I'm gonna make this up
I would say well I was a more way back from chemistry class I met my wife
who's a painter met my wife on way back from art class walking across campus
and we stopped as we usually do to get our pita for lunch we're gonna sit
outside and we looked in the Commons and we saw these activity and people are
crying and they're looking at the TV I'm intentionally being very granular because
they're very detailed memories I just gave you now what he would do is then
talk to you a year later two years later and I would give that account
Mary Jo and I met we were the only problem was I didn't meet Mary Jo until
the next year right now was I lying no I was trying to make sense in the
present and integrate as much as Christina said about updating is memories are
trying to try to make sense of the world and so that was an absolutely real
memory that was felt and perceived and had a neural basis everything is that it
just wasn't true and so I don't think I would disagree if that if it doesn't
allow it to be in the category of memory what it does is mean that it's it's a
try to an updating of an experience that we're trying to make sense of and and
and I think memories allow us to make sense of that just as we create a
statistical model of the world if we hear this outside we would not think it's a
giraffe we would probably think it's a horse right but if we were also we would
have a very different perception of the same sound so often we're just trying to
make sense of our world with the best information we have and since I've been
with Mary Jo 51 years it's a pretty darn good narrative it just turns out to be
wrong where that really matters is when you get into the realm that you are in
in therapy and trying to deal with memories that are painful or are hurtful
for folks and want to try to deal with them and access them to get at them what
do you think Penny you believe any of this stuff I think that I don't think
there's a problem in this discussion between I mean I think your point that
some memories are false and your point that those are still memories can coexist
I think you absolutely right it can go in this but it's difficult to make room
for the dynamic nature of memory the sense making the meaning creating yeah
feature memory to make room of the of that aspect of memory and still allow
memories to actually give us knowledge about the past where knowledge is
required so it's compatible I believe but it's not easy to say how maybe maybe
one way kind of out of this is that a lot of people have been thinking recently
because of the work that's been done on people imagining the future or
imagining alternative past if you put them in the sky and see what's going on
in their brains it's really no different from when they're remembering the past
right so people have been talking about rather than a memory system I remember
a remembering imagining system if you want if you think about it you can't
really imagine things unless you can remember amnieces patients can't
imagine the future if you say to an amnieces patient what are you doing next
Friday they just become very distressed so it seems as though you need a memory
to be able to imagine and that the two are kind of interlinked together and
it's within that context that bits of the past emerge some of which are
somehow a reflection of the past and some of which are perhaps something that's
more imagined I think the point is we get to that we all get worried about is
that it means an implication is that well maybe all our memories are false in a
sense they are because if you think about how an event gets encoded first of all
it's massively time compressed so when I remember this event in a month's time
I'll be remembering in two minutes even though it took two hours so in that
sense all memories are in a sense not accurate representations and just as in
the side now stops off because it's your turn really but I think we've got a
problem here that the heart of our beliefs about memory we think that
memories like a video or it's like photographs and it absolutely is not
right it's a psychological representation so if you can do it with that would
believe then you can begin to accept that memories are some sort of
representation of the past to come back to your point Penny but the question is
what sort of representation I think that's the maybe that's what you could
arrive at but I think that's the interesting bit at the heart of this
bit of a discussion so yeah to what extent may memory alter change or edit
the stored content without being confabulation and still be memory
exactly it's an interesting question now I think just to come back and
reiterate again the question really goes to the heart of what is it that's being
represented because we do not know about how memories get encoded we don't know
how our memory all of us in this room how our memory of this event gets encoded
into long-term memory if we went around nasty everybody next week everyone I'll
have a different version of what went on and you might want to say well that's
because we will have different interests and we attended to different things but
we don't know how we got in there and we don't know what form it's in either
although we do know that memories often do come to mind with some visual imagery
but otherwise we don't know much about them so I think it's worth jumping in
here and and talking about how memories evolve as well because you're making
the point that memories and labile and plastic and they can change and it's
because they're labile and plastic that we sometimes wind up with false memories
otherwise if they were just fixed we wouldn't have these so that to me
raises the question of why are they plastic why do they change and for me
that's one of the things that's the most interesting about memories they there's
a reason why they're plastic and why they change in fact there are probably
lots of reasons the one I want to touch on is how do you so you mentioned it when
you talked about memories of fabric with lots of individual threads and you
know initially you might see individual threads and then eventually you see the
pattern of the fabric itself for me this is an important aspect of the
evolution of memories Martin I think mentioned the fact Paris is a capital of
France as a form of memory that's what we call semantic memory it's very different
than remembering what I had for breakfast this morning which is what we would
call episodic memory and a major question in my mind is where did these semantic
memories which is our general abstracted out knowledge of the world divorced from
the individual events which we experienced to build it up where do those come from
and this is incredibly important because that semantic knowledge is the basis of
who we are you know everything that we know every prediction we make about
things that are going to happen the consequences of our actions how people
respond to us it comes from the semantic memory and so one I'll just finish this
though and then you can jump in so so one idea about where that semantic memory
comes from is that those episodic memories build up and then those
representations of episodes actually change their plastic they evolve across
time and across sleep which is my particular interest and they become
abstracted out and generalized and they build up schemas of how things in the
world relate to each other that's the basis of our semantic memory and I could
say more about it but I think Martin wants to come in that I completely
agree with what you said actually I mean just to add to it one of the it's very
interesting amnesic patient many years ago reported by just some like lead
some like a physicist right highly intelligent man theoretical physicist
who had a stroke basically meant he could no longer encode new information
into memory and they could give him very complicated articles in the physics of
light he was a laser expert and he could read those articles and pretty much
understand them couldn't return anything from them at all so without these
mysterious episodic memory things whatever they are we can't learn either
so it seems we can't learn either right and it might be what's happening with
children for example is maybe the hippocampus is functioning when you're
born or around about then and they can form episodic memories I mean there is
a whole developmental theory that says how a child learns the meaning of the
word ball is that mum rolls the ball along the floor and says ball and then
they're outside and she rolls it along the grass and says ball and the child
builds up lots of different episodic memories with this verbal label ball and
eventually the key bit of all of these episodes this labeled ball gets separated
out and becomes the semantic representation it's one story not
everybody buys that one but it seems that people who were born with a
sorry I'll stop talking people are born with a disorder called developmental
amnesia who usually because of an anoxic accident at birth don't have a
fully functioning hippocampus nonetheless some of them seem to be able to acquire
semantic knowledge without having episodic memories and that's another
mystery we don't know how they do it it's a really this is so much fun because in
our world in neuroscience Kristina I have been friends for 40 years and work
together and so I'm not surprised we have a vocabulary that overlaps a lot but
listening to you is so much fun because it makes me have to read cat actually to
literally I need a libretto to to now know what we're talking about and it
makes so much sense the way you just formed it even though it's a little
different we think about it one thing that is fun that I've been thinking about
the last couple years in our world in neuroscience maybe in the psychoanalytic
world as well we often ask how does it work whatever the it is how does it
work when I move how did my arm get told by my brain to move when I think of my
daughter Amy how do I remember her face and we often center on the how how does
it work what's the mechanisms with the schema what's the underlying texture and
so on but the it needs some attention as well the it really matters because
sometimes the very same it's that you're looking at has a different underlying
mechanism it's not like there's different you know episodic versus
somatic memories but the very same memory looks exactly the same I want to
what one guy studied it's so interesting it may open up another domain of the
discussion so Larry Fee years ago in in Boston looked at an animal model of
memory looked at a mouse we can make designer mice we can put genes in and
out of them it will now and he has a mouse that had a genetic problem I
won't tell you what it is it was a G protein and the mouse had it had a
problem with hippocampal memory a task learning new objects and it had a
problem with with a brain mechanism called LTP synaptic facilitation that
sought to be a mechanism of that memory so the the mouse had a problem and they
gave these mice a lot of external stimulation it's called an enriched
environment they got on running wheels and they played with each other and they
pushed each other around and they got better the memory got better and the
brain mechanism got better if you looked in the brain oh my gosh it's back so
you might say wonderful we just made it better it's a different it turns out
that the brain mechanism that got better had to do it was not the same mechanism
it was something else it still got you to the same phenotype the same endpoint
very different underlying mechanism why is that important well obviously
theoretically it's interesting but if you're gonna now talk about therapies and
targeted therapies for giving kind of cognitive disorders we better know the
it we better know how it's what its texture is that's what Krinstina does for
living is to figure out how it works so the fun thing is that even within a
category that we'd accept as a common category what looks like it maybe have
four or five six different ways that it got to that final end state that opens
up for philosophy real question of well when is it still the same thing or not
that's what you do for living and out of it but does that really matter sure
does it you're gonna give me a pill and make me better well I was actually
thinking exact opposite I was thinking if you can boost someone's memory and
intervention does it really matter how it works as long as it doesn't have a
negative side well there you go first of all the notion of side effect I've
always loved there's no such thing as a side effect there's effects the ones we
like and the ones we don't like so the real problem is not in this task only
at its top where you can have exercise making it better but if we're gonna for
example have some targeted drug for Alzheimer's right well we better know
what what we're trying to fix because every drug every put in the brain has
pluripotent effects there's no such thing as a singular effect well let me
play devil's advocate for a minute gonna be a fight since I'm here because of my
interest in the impact of sleep on memory right and my field has a way to
improve memories non-invasively without drugs right without understanding what
memories actually are absolutely I'll briefly describe it so we know that
memories are newly spontaneously replayed during sleep that means that
the brain activity associated with something that you learned in the day
spontaneous the reoccurs while you're asleep and this is associated with
strengthening so the memories which replay are remembered better the next
day that's great but it doesn't allow us control recently and research has given
us a tool to control it so instead of waiting for this to happen spontaneously
we can pair a memory with a sound or a smell and then represent that sound or
smell when people are sleeping it will trigger that reactivation and that
memory will be selectively strengthened and we this is this has been
replicated many times in many labs around the world it works we know it works
we would like to apply this in Alzheimer's disease hasn't been done yet
would be interesting to see how well that works but we still don't know what a
memory is and we certainly you know know not much further with the the kind of
chemical cellular basis of it we know we can strengthen it so that's fine right
why can't we use that intervention you can't they're not mutual school from
anyway you can absolutely do it that way in fact what you're doing is
strengthening it without knowing the mechanism exactly but that's just fine
as long as you we appreciate that there are other ways that that could be
in inventive and useful and there are other things that are not as useful for
and people are in suffering and you got to worry about them too so we can't it's
not one stop shopping that the last thing about the fig study that's gonna
blow your mind is remember I told you that you made the rats run around and they
got better their kids got better their kids got better the rap pups got better
how they're Lamar clicks right the kids got better for about to how that well
what happened was that it's transmitted to the mother and the mother's womb in
the mother's hormonal environment transfers the gain of function it
remember they might still have the darn mutation the pups are still rap pups
with the mutation mice with the mutation but they had memory the memory was
improved and their brain was improved because moms uterine environment and
the hormonal environment allowed that to be transferred for two months so and
it's not Lamarck it is the fact that there was an experience that's epigenetic
that gets transferred and where there's no I don't think there's any tension
between doing things we don't know why I go to the gym to try to feel better I
don't have any idea what the hell is going on except that I hurt like hell at
the end but it I the illusion that it's good for me and I don't care what the
muscles are doing I just want to feel better so I don't think we need mechanism
all the way along but but I think that the reverse is hard to defend and you're
not saying it's not fair to you that to not understand it wouldn't be a goal I
mean to understand it will always at least help us get further along sure yeah
of course what do you think Christina well I think in biology this is what we
are trying to do right and and that's why I mentioned consolidation or
reconciliation so consolidation last for episodic memories in a rat that we're
studying in the hippocampus requires more than 24 hours to complete why 24 hours
so you are saying oh during sleep they are replaced and clearly we want to know
what goes on in these 24 hours what goes on in the phases of sleep for example
another labs are studying that so it is important to understand the underlying
mechanisms because if we have a handle of those then we can actually target
exactly what we want to see happening the reactivation of memory the recall
to give the smell during this lead reactivates again the cascade of changes
that lead to memory strengthening this process of consolidation so there is a
lot actually known not enough is the beginning but there is quite a bit of
dawn in terms of mechanism of how to strengthen the memory with a retrieval
so you present a cue the trace is reactivated doesn't have to be in the
awake state it could be while they're sleeping but the reactivation we know in
certain experiments that lead to memory strengthening but can I say it's probably
not the memory your strengthening its access of the memory what we know is
that consolidation last for quite a while and through consolidation memory
strengthen and stabilizes so I don't have a problem with consolidation that's
fine if if then we're saying well you know retrieval is gonna be better
access with time perhaps I mean it's something that has to be really carefully
dissected but in terms of mechanism they seem that they built over time and
this building leads to memory strengthening well I suppose the part I'm
trying to get at really is what is being consolidated what is being
consolidated now people often talk about as it's the memory whether the memory is
being kind of you know linked into other things or is it instead not the memory
which has been consolidated but your ability to access it for access bits of
it and that might be a really very different thing and I'm saying that
Christian you won't like this because I don't believe in reconciliation we can
talk about it extensively I mean this is what we are studying so I know I know
what we do I know the work of other labs in reconciliation so we can talk
about that so the reason why I'm saying no I don't think that that's the case
because you know shorter memories are very detailed I in the form in the moment
we are in the experience but long term memory built with time so if there was
you know a problem in like getting better in accesses them then why do we
have shorter memory with all the details that actually disappear so there are
different memory processes that occur depending on the experience and the
duration well a number of points though if I think most people would say that if
you've got a memory this has a duration of more than two minutes and it's long
term memory duration of short term real it's got to be about two minutes well
no we're not saying that I'm just going to get you know I suppose the
cognitive end of memory research but okay if we said to everyone in this room
now tell me everything that's happened to you today they could give us an
exquisitely minutely detailed account we ask everyone again in a year's time
maybe nothing maybe a few details that doesn't mean to say that information
has been lost from the system what it might mean to say is your ability to
access it has been lost well this is actually and this is where we can turn
to you who do philosophy for living I think that we first of all let's not
confuse metaphor and mechanism right so we use a lot of language to capture
stuff which is fine storage retrieval the brain doesn't know what that means
ranges adapts and engages the world and succeeds or not and so on so animals
from mice right up to our kids are pretty good at it we capture those
events with short hands like storage and retrieval those are semantic constructs
that allow us to talk to each other about it brain to know what that means and I
think my own view on it is that if there's an impossible disentangle that you can
never show a storage deficit you can only show a retrieval deficit because
let's say I try to get a memory out of Ed and he can't give it to me and then I
give him a glass of water and it comes back that means if you couldn't access it
but I didn't put a new one in there so if we had trouble accessing it we'd call
that a retrieval problem so so the only way you can know there's a storage
deficit is by virtue of retrieval in some way so they're conflated inexorably
by our language and the way we try to capture what we how we talk about it
and and I and for me it doesn't really matter is I like to because I believe
you've brought up evolution I think not just us but critters on the planet
forever have been really good at updating memories to be adaptive and changing
the risk analysis based on current things like hunger and I don't like so
that's a very complicated business I I don't have a problem with calling it so
I think it's perfectly reasonable to say you could probably just have can't get
at that memory but I don't think that we'll ever be able to untangle that at
least certainly mechanistically we can't because the only way you know a memory
is there is to retrieve it that's that's the that's the route but it does have
really really interesting implications if you think that it's all in there but
you just can't you bet oh it's phenomenally because it's probably still
influencing a great deal of your behavior in the world your conscious
behavior even though you don't realize it yeah so the people you're attracted to
the people you don't like the things you want to go and see the things you don't
maybe be driven by information you cannot get into consciousness but it's
nonetheless in there and it's still influencing processing well I have a
question about that or sometime are those would you consider those memories in
other words would you consider the person you are attracted to the result of
memory so what we which touches on the issue like you are a two and a half year
old and your father dies or your mother dies and so now you have a different
person taking care of you or your mother is depressed because your father has
died so your mother is different now and this is inevitably going to have some
impact on you are those effects which can manifest themselves 30 years later
in the type of person you chose to marry do they are those memories those
experiences that are formative in a certain way no David someone sitting
next to you wants to speak to that one I'll speak to you as well well go ahead
I wanted to open a new topic well very brief then I mean you say all these
memories they're the stuff from which memories are generated is why it's a
way or could it principle be if you could just access them I mean most people
can't access memories that occurred events that below the age of three
anywhere from the pre-verbal period of the sort what kind of a memory would you
say it is if you are interacting with the mother who wasn't depressed last
week and who is very depressed this week what kind of memory does a two-year-old
or two and a half year old have about that well exactly and I think it goes
back to a point that came up early on and that is we don't know how these
things get encoded we just don't know what the selection process is I mean
Freud had a great the great term for this didn't he called it after
afterwards than us I can't say it in Gerbt I can barely say in English but
the whole idea was that the memory you end up with after some eventually
experienced has this reprocessing that's gone on some selections and details
have been made available some of not been made available you know so you've
been hibitry process as well as an ex-itatory activation processes what sort
of memory a two-year-old has I just I really don't know but I would assume it
would be primarily nonverbal and effective and it might have some you know
modality specific information in it imagery or something like that
nothing should he or new topic
next to what you were saying that the episodic memory is in a way after a
while turning to semantic yeah I don't know how tightly that links to the
retrieval issue which is really what you're talking about I mean what I was
gonna ask you at the risk of seeming very ignorant is I mean I think everyone's
probably aware about this idea that all the memories are still there but we
can't retrieve them but what's really the strongest supporting evidence for
those memories being there what evidence is there other than the Roger Penrose
stimulation stuff from the 60s I can give you an example if you'd like sorry I
do that every time I lean forward yeah I don't remember it from moment I just
going with to well that's all cool well there's been a lot of work recently with
people using body-worn cameras what cameras body worn cameras these
cameras you were around your neck for example one we've used was originally
called sense camera it takes photographs and response to sensory
changes it detects okay let's say you go for lunch with some money where the
camera will take maybe about 300 photographs all right and then you go
later we come back in so we'll do you remember that lunch you had with your
friend Ruth and you I have no idea I can't remember when we last went out
together so I get to sit down and look at these photographs one by one very
quickly you're at a one per second so to a couple of minutes to review an event
that took two hours you will experience what we call pristine moments you'll
remember things that you didn't know for a million years you had in your memory
and actually those things won't necessarily be things depicted in the
photographs so I give you one example just by way of illustration and then the
larger point of course is that all this information is in there we just can't
access it that's what this is all about so a very skeptical colleague of mine
all this camera conference in Australia about three months later we go into
look at some of his movies we call them but they're not movies really there's a
series of still photographs and he's walking down the street in Sydney up to
the University of New South Wales where the conference was taking place and he's
walking past a line of cars and he was looking in these photographs and he said
well I'm not remembering anything I just can't remember anything about it and
then suddenly he said a swear word very loudly as he remembered the song that
was playing on his iPod as he was walking down the street three months
earlier and there's been quite a bit of work using these very very
powerful rich bodies of cues which do seem to show that you do return far more
than we realize it may not be everything but we do seem to could could that mean
that even when memories have become very very weak so that you know there's a
trace there there's information there but it's very weak and so when you try and
remember what you were doing in that location on that day three months ago
you don't retrieve it if you've given the appropriate cues yes even if it's
very weak you can kind of get it would you be happy with that interpretation
well the bit I'm sorry I don't have to accession to is I don't buy this idea
of memories becoming weak
it's all I think with access and cue effectiveness
particularly particularly as we get older you know the cues we encounter in
the world we've encountered them billions of times before that's probably one of
the reasons they're not very effective at eliciting specific
listen to the nature of our language right now we're talking about I don't
make this attribution if it's not right then push back that that memories by
retrieval are pulling a card out of a rolodex and it may be faded ink or not
but it's a card in a rolodex and that's certainly not the case what is the case
is memories are active reconstructions of them so it and it's the same in bird
song it's not just our special flood and privilege on the planet this way a lot
of animals and birds are beautiful for this kind of study I'll tell you if you
like but what you do is you make the best sense of what that means that's why
you occasionally have these nominally false memories because it made sense
I remember Mary Jo we've been together 50 years but it isn't and push back if I
don't have your thought right but I really love the work and I believe it I
think what it allows you to is have more cues to actively reconstruct that and
we're pretty good at it we're trying to make sense of it and I'm gonna remember
you were sitting on my right and casinos on my left probably with for a long time
so we're pretty good at reconstructing things especially if they fit into a
normal environmental expectable tableau sure scheme of perfect so I don't think
it's so much like it's a weak memory and you have a better flashlight on it I
just think it's a better access to the reconstructive process that allows us
to make the best sense of this experiential tableau we've got inside he
wants to hang a right-hand turn go for it something we all agree upon is how
important memories are for who we are and what we know and having thought about
memories for now about 20 years I'm getting it actually more more interested
in forgetting and the virtues of forgetting because it seems to me that a
normal rate of forgetting not a pathological but a normal rate of
forgetting maybe as important for an explanation for how we cope cognitively
in the world as memory is of course there's the story about whether or not our
storage is finite or not depending on what answer one gives to that story it
becomes important to free up storage space by forgetting now maybe our
storage is infinite I don't know I'm not I don't have a horse in that race but
in any case the retrieval speed and probably also the retrieval reliability
will improve the smaller the database that has to be sifted through they also
seem to be epistemological advantages to partial forgetting it's it's easier to
have a justified belief when the content is watered down is diluted then when
the content is very rich it's much harder to to know rich contents then then
impoverished contents it may be that partial forgetting is what allows us to
see patterns it may be that it's important for attention that you know if
you if everything reminds you of something it's quite hard to attend on
the here and now but also for new learning for new learning correct it and I'm
I'm just speculating it could it be that partial forgetting is one of the
features that strengthens the social bonds because if I don't remember X but
I remember that Martin remembers X then I become dependent on him on his memory
perished thought they wouldn't help you well I was gonna say just a point it all
depends what you mean by forgetting really but from an evolutionary
perspective one might want to say that an animal can never know at the time
whether it's important to return a memory of an event or not right so maybe the
system set up in such a way that it's just gets into long-term memory it's
there the representations of that you can combine together and I completely
buy into the constructive idea we're arguing about it for 30 years but I don't
use the word reconstruction just construction so you can't know what is
you need to retain so the system set up to retain it but very cleverly what it's
done is it's made it difficult for you to access it right but it can still
influence processing and this is all based upon a story a friend of mine
told me called Jillian Cohen who was a famous old cultist psychologist and a
very keen horse rider and she told me she was riding a horse along a canal in
Oxford one day and there was a blacksmith forge there and some sparks came
flying out of the window the horse took right shied and ran off and it was a
quite dangerous moment for her the next year she was running along the same
track on the same horse but the last most of the clothes down they're not down
the building and as it got to the very point where it was the horse shied away
again sure right now I'm not supposing that horse could say well you know bad
thing happened here a year ago and I'm just repeating it but it's a point I want
to get out that the information may well be there but somehow our brains are set
up so we don't have to have it delivered consciously all the time so I don't
need to consciously remember oh it was last week I parked my car over there when
I got to the supermarket therefore this week it must be parked over there you
brain somehow has evolved to cleverly do it for you but the information is still
one way it's routinely measured is by a phenomenon you know well called savings
so very often you say do you remember this I absolutely don't remember we
studied this all the time we've got papers on it last year where animals
show no memory of an event and yet they can relearn that event more rapidly so
it's a very done the theme of it sort of in there in some way another dimension
to it that's really important or patterns I would suggest the horse
absolutely didn't remember the time of day but he sure is how we remember that
that the ones the canals on the left and the blacksmiths on the right and those
contexts and animals have to code context all the time to survive either
honeybee or bird or horse or human so so a lot of what we the way I think about
it loosely about what's retained is not essentially a lookup table but more like
patterns that are are adaptive to now be and actually this is what Christina's
work is about to be flexible because for example risk aversion in animals goes
up when they're sated when they're not hungry and risk aversion goes down when
they're they take more risks when they're hungry well that makes perfect sense if
you're out foraging right well turns out the guys at NYU two years ago found
nodes in the brain explain that and the way they studied it is an amazing young
guy that came up with this idea there was a shared node for for hunger and a
share a node is just a region in the brain where stuff works there was a
shared node for hunger and for risk aversion and he studied people that did
the stock market in countries that celebrated Ramadan pretty smart so
they're fasting and they still traded but the risk aversion changed as they
got hungry or they were well they take more risk in the market so it's you know
these are when you're I'm not just talking about squirrels in the park I'm
talking about your next portfolio a lot of things that govern our behavior from
the memory point of view are also very integrated or adaptive behaviors that's
sort of the point I was making yeah but I agree with the idea that actually the
details are lost that is forgetting this is the way I see it this is the way you
know the data we have make sense because if we would remember all the details
that we process and then they are not accessible a lot of space is gonna be
taken up by something that is not even used it's easiest Thomas suggested to
have you know something that is there and recall and then we make us remake
associations of it and and this is how the memories are not always faithful so
I mean there are so many data this for me suggesting that that's the most likely
explanation I mean the memory researchers that would agree with you is just I don't
and the point is this you say how can we remember all these details if they're
all in their whole lifetime is worth of remembering events I mean how is it
possible for the brain to store all of that but maybe the brain doesn't store
that much of any given event I mean me reason work with trauma patients
suggests that they return three to five what they call hotspots details from
their traumatic experience and actually not much else so when you remember this
event we're in today in a year's time maybe remember three or four or five
details maybe that's in the end all have got through all the got in there so
maybe we're kind of overestimating the information overload kind of story and
given how many connections are there are in the brain and that knowledge is
represented in those connections rather than in the new rooms then there's more
than enough processing capacity I think to represent an entire life and maybe
one or two more I don't know well certainly in the hippocampus most folks
know the hippocampus it's just shaped kind of like a big banana curl by itself a
bit in our brain there's a region of it that is involved in pattern completion
that's what it does for a living you give a little elements and then it puts
together stuff and I think it's commiserate with what you're saying is that that a
lot of what we do is a I going back to I get to write that same worth and that is
you don't need all the elements for an effective adaptive response to the current
you need enough to reconstruct it to then behave appropriately and so I don't
think we should think of memories I don't even like the fact that we've got
10 to the 13 cells and 10 to the third connections so there's plenty of room I
mean yeah if you like a computer analogy that's fine but I don't I think we're
much more interesting than that I think this is a good point to go back to that
idea of cementization yeah and the evolution of memories because at least
one take on that is part of what's happening is is in that evolution of the
episodic into the semantic you're abstracting out the statistical
properties and you talked about a pattern completion you need to know what the
pattern is in order to complete it you need to have a representation of the
you know the gist of a corpus of experiences that overall structure the
rules these are all words that have come up and in order to get in order to
extract that one ideas that you need forgetting right so you need to forget
the details in order to pull out the statistics the rules the gist and then
you have that structure and then maybe when you have a cue that taps into that
structure you can complete sure and you can maybe you can pull back memories in
that way through pattern completion that might have in some sense been forgotten
and by the way I would just make it a bit more complicated and qualify that by
saying you know I believe in this process but I also believe that you can
have both so I think that you can have the forgetting and the gist abstraction
process but you can also still hold on to those those memories that in some
sense in one system they've been forgotten but in another system they're
still there and so maybe that's what's happening maybe you get that gist
information and then the pattern completion can allow you to pull it out
from another system and that could be closer to your perspective I think I
don't know I mean what what got me started was at Irvine we have a group
a group of patients with super episodic memories there's a Jim McGire's group
correct and one of the striking features is the IQ is not any higher than that
of ordinary subjects and most of them are unhappy some of them they're actually
there are some happy ones as well but some I mean the famous ones are unhappy
anyway I don't mean interrupt you but you're right but that I found an interesting
feature you know if what you say is correct that the episodic memories are
sort of the material out of which semantic knowledge is built why are
people with a much larger episodic database not able to get smarter or better
maybe they have sleep problems
that's a good question actually it's very interesting many of them are OCD
many of them have kept diaries since they were four or five and they're OCD
there's a big OCD component to it and not all around happy you're right the
one I've met to the famous one is quite unhappy but but you make a point that's
really interesting for the group to think about and I'd love to hear what the
our guests outside of us I think about this I don't think that memory and
intelligence or smart or whatever the word is mapped onto each other whatsoever
adaptive getting around being clever that's fine but if there's lots of
studies in different domains that run that parameter out like cognitive
ability or problem solving and it may or may not map onto how well you remember
facts it much it's better often it's it's much better predictive how you use
facts it's not how many can you get at but how can you now be clever that's the
whole diversity thing if every read one book this year read something called the
difference it's a guy there's this whole frame about diversity and we're doing a
favor by getting diverse folks in there the trade-off is excellence nonsense
what it is is you get more diverse folks the variance compression because you
don't have consensus bias anymore you got a plumber and you got an Eskimo and
you got a psychiatrist and when they solve a problem you get a female
Puerto Rican and you get a male from from the Bronx you're gonna have a lack
consensus bias and you get a much better problem solved and you wouldn't say
any of them had better memories they just bring more tools to the toolkit I
think I just gave a speech I'm sorry
so I think the I think so you've just said you don't think there's any link
between memory and intelligence IQ essentially I don't think they map onto
what I think there is an interesting relationship and I'll tell you what I
think it is and I think it all comes down to sleep as most things I think I should
take a nap let me say it first and then you can take the nap
so I can remember it yeah but so so we were talking about this abstraction of
just process we actually know that a stage of your sleep called slow wave
sleep is is important for this so we know that memories are replayed in slow
wave sleep they tend to be memories that are related to each other from the
same corpus of information the same types of experiences there's a hypothesis
that there's you know the overlapping components of those memories the shared
elements will be strengthened more and then when everything is downscaled
which also happens in this slow wave sleep you're left with a representation
of the commonalities the gist the schema the structure the statistics what we've
been talking about so that process there's quite a bit of evidence that
that happens and people are better at solving those kind of problems when
they've been allowed to sleep it's predicted by the amount of sleep they
had and you know on and on so here's the thing to IQ to and tell this is this
is complete speculation I like it yeah it's kind of fun so I would speculate
that if you if you can't build up schemas efficiently if you don't build up a
strong schema of the world if you don't build your semantic knowledge well you
can't make good predictions you can't integrate new information as well you
that means that you can't process information you can't you know you you
kind of get deficits across the board if you have a problem with that which
means you probably have lower IQ I mean if you're not taking in information as
well you're not using it as efficiently to make predictions you're not it's
gonna impact on these abilities right so could it be that if people if they are
not if there's some disruption in the sleep processing of information to
abstract out just generalities to build these schemas and if that happens across
your whole life from infancy onward where you're building up all your
semantic knowledge then eventually you know you start to have a deficit and you
start to show and sure enough there's at least a handful of studies showing
links between sleep spindles which are markers of memory replay and non-rep and
slow-wave sleep and IQ it's not a hundred percent it the literature is a bit
messy but it is there so there's a hint towards this but no one has really
tested it properly so I think they are disagree I I'm sorry I wouldn't
disagree for a moment I think that where I would intersect sort of orthogonal the
conversation is what we mean by IQ and if you mean dealing with facts that are
required for problem-solving then you're golden can I give you a take on that
yeah because I think a distinction we'd want to make here that's made in the area
is between crystallized and fluid IQ now when we're talking about memory we're
talking talking about crystallized IQ so if I can remember the decision we
made at the meeting last week then my view is probably going to carry the day
at the meeting this week you know people will have good long-term memories
probably influence things like social decision-making and emotional IQ and
important ways whereas fluid intelligence which is your ability to kind of solve
problems and things like that mathematical problems are you know
logical problems etc probably doesn't depend upon having a good long-term
memory of your life so that captures much and much more elegant phrase but I was
trying to say is that there's a lot of ways that we would call IQ or problem
solving intelligence and a certain class of those would absolutely depend on the
semantic episodic weaving of this tapestry and others would would not so I
only in pushing back on the canonical representation is more facts better
smarter and that that's a small part of it can I can answer it again just briefly
just because I want to mention this we've got one of these guys with a super
memory I do you studied him yeah he's brilliant guy he's a he's a kind of
senior manager at the civil service and England completely normal guy to kids
University his life considered completely normal except he has a slightly
unusual interested numbers it's a calendar calculator and what that means
is if you give him a date let's say I don't know June the 23rd 1971 what day of
the week was that he will tell you straight away it was the Wednesday and
I'll tell you what happened and who won the rugby game and what we did this test
with me put together a load of facts that we got various yearbooks and we said to
him okay he's he's a day tell us what day is he was 100% right on over 150
of these items and he could tell us what big items are in the news on that day
and Fatty was so good right we took our items from a thing called the Collins
yearbook and there was a famous comedian in in England who died on stage called
Tommy Cooper and we had this date in and the famous event he had to tell us was
Tommy Cooper died on stage and we scallove it in Martin we're talking to
him I said actually you did get one wrong there which I've quite surprised
at and he said what was it sort of Tommy Cooper dying on stage and he said well
that's the wrong date you've got the wrong date down there and so we went to
the web and looked at the Collins book of the Colours book printed the wrong
date isn't it it's amazing but he can remember autobiographical events and it
looks like the way he does it his memory is completely coded up in terms of
calendar time so I mean yeah we all research tells us that people don't
retain calendar dates in their memories very rarely but his memory is
completely somehow leaked to calendar time interesting it's amazing
character otherwise complete your view but retrieval does this kind of thing
reinforce it good question I hadn't looked at it from that direction but say
yes it's your view to absolutely isn't that what you were saying that the
information is there and he has better access to it that well yeah that we do
think that because he can use these very specific cues which you know date and
day of the week do you know it's really interesting about recalling and there's
an anecdotal story that Susan Corkin who is the woman who studied HM
extensively Brendan Miller is student and she tells the story that's actually I
believe never saw HM but I really believe it remember he doesn't remember
from the data the next so if Ed walked in and said hi and Ed he said nice to
meet you your chat he'd be able to work with Ed the next day he's never seen
him before all right if you tell the Susan said this was more than once she
would tell HM a joke and he'd love it and she'd tell up to him the next day and
he didn't think it was funny and he didn't remember it he didn't remember
the joke didn't remember the content it just didn't think it was funny so we
I'm that's chasing to me we got to be careful about putting bolts and buckets
right there's a lot more than brain smarter than we are so there's a nuanced
kind of encoding that clearly is going on that's well passed the categories we
have to impose on it to study it the sleep work is beautiful and you gotta
put boundaries on it so you can actually study it and did you push it
further and I don't know they found it funny and I don't know whether she did
it was completely anecdotal but but there were these very interesting quirky
things where it wasn't quite as canonical as it seemed I mean he was
devastated he got lost he couldn't find his way home but nonetheless there it's
not there are really interesting partial amnesia's where folks will have phenotypes
that are extremely interesting they don't forget everything but they just
forget some things you go maybe that reflects how you've categorized them in
the front end one doesn't know but what I'm really saying is the brain smarter
than we are so we have to impose structure on it to talk about it and to
study it and that's wonderful just like an analysis I'm sure you got
to impose the strength the brain is more than we are it is our brain that's
exactly the point yeah because we don't know I want to do something because I
didn't get a chance to ask you earlier when you were describing it when you
say the events of the day are then repeated during sleep slow sleep and
that helps with memory how are those events selected is this the whole day
played back it's a really important question I think what we know we know
from work in rats where they actually measure the replay of these memories
with embedded electrodes they're looking at populations of cells we know
that things that are more salient tend to be replayed more so rats replay
trajectories then they're running along you can see with cells that
represent spatial locations fire in order as they're moving towards a target and
those trajectories the ones that are moving towards food or a reward will be
replayed a lot more than trajectories that are not so we know that we in humans
we know that if you train people on to to say lists of words and then you tell
them we're only gonna test you on list a what tomorrow we're gonna test you on
list a and is how well you do is gonna determine how much money you get paid
for instance so forget about list B and then of course we test them on both
lists they improve much more on the list overnight on the list where they've
been told you'll be tested so it's more salient it's more and yeah so it does
seem that salient things also emotional things seems to improve from the coding
importance in some way yeah and that makes sense in an evolutionary context
it makes sense that if we have a mechanism for selectively strengthening
some memories but not all of them and you know at the same time things are
being forgotten across sleep as well so then we should strengthen the ones that
are important and the salient ones are the important ones so emotions would be
much more important in fact things that have an emotional facts that have an
emotional impact importance more than facts yeah so it's important to remember
that last time I ate this I got sick or last time I you know last time I did
this my my partner was happy you know these are important things but other
things that have no emotional link why should I remember them well because we
need to have facts we need to have facts but the emotion is modulating the
formation of that memory and this story the consolidation there are many
studies showing that emotions and hormones released by stress or arousal
can modulate memory strength right this is they have done many studies in
humans as well as in animal models I mean we're talking about Jim a girl
the K-hill but then many others in animal models but biologically speaking that's
obvious I mean if you think about the biology we need to remember more or for
longer what's important so if we encounter a danger we don't want to
forget after the single encounter if that's very important we better
remember that if we get too close to a lion we are in danger I mean it's
obviously biologically anxiety type situations are the ones that are most
liable to be repeated in during sleep because that would be one of the major
emotions sure I don't know I'm saying sure you're in tuition
it makes sense I don't think that anxiety specifically has been studied I
mean it would have to be in humans because that sounds like a human kind of
emotion and I think that yes people would agree with that but I don't know if
there's empirical data to definitely support it and say that's one thing
that Christina said that's really important you mentioned Jim McGaugh who's a
beloved guy in the field we all know him well and he in the day he found
something that's very important it's almost the reverse of how Christina and
I study memory and if we block transmit we block protein synthesis we block
now Jim found that after trials over he can improve the memory is over now the
episode itself is over the animals already been there it's learned it and
after that if you do maybe think of it is our drugs drugs or hormones that
are involved in arousal you can after so you would think you're only encoding
when you're in the episode right I left the library the books closed but turns
out that for some length of time you can add close post trial enhancement you
can make the memory stronger by virtue of giving animals hormones that are
involved in in emotion so there that modulation is a really fundamental
thing in our world is that there is there's if you can think of it and it's
only a metaphor there's streams of like information but the volume goes up and
down you can tune the volume up and down depending on it and it's really
important to have the volume alone a lot of things because then you're not
riveted by your world but sometimes you need that volume up and it may well be
that during the day when that volumes up that will trigger the kinds of things
that you want to revisit in doing sleep but I'm just guessing with you but it
makes some sense I think it is it in everybody experience we do remember
better the memories that are linked to some emotion absolutely at least
access to it's a more complicated sure but if emotions are too strong stuff
around needs you right but this is also being studied by the same groups right so
they show that if the emotional regulation is too strong there is the
opposite effect so a little bit of stress is good right too much is bad there is
this inverted U function that describes memory retention but complex
function retention with the stress level if we you know if we look at the
relationship between stress level and performance that's how it is expressed
so a little bit is good to remember to perform better too much is bad yeah when
somebody says you know I keep remembering a lot of irrelevant facts in point of
fact they may only be irrelevant because he thinks they're irrelevant but from
your study it would show that they were relevant
I think there's even a condition that's to do with remembering too many irrelevant
facts particularly number type facts does anyone know well there are there
patients that can't admit right so right in this room right now most of us
don't feel the clothes in our body most of us don't hear that you will now when
I said you don't hear that background right so we are it's important for a
normal animals get around the planet to learn what to ignore and you don't even
learn it it just it's built into the system some folks can't do that
there are powerful I don't know the names of them but and I think you're right so
some just can't stop thinking about stuff and it actually is paralytic because
you know if I'm going to turn and talk to Penny well if I'm still fixated and I'm
what we're doing that I can't select my attention like a flashlight it's more
like I'm constantly based and that exists also in memories so kind of
streams of irrelevant information invading you know triggered by any queue
you know everything you might have ever known about this kind of carpet or you
know that kind of ceiling or pain it's a bit like the superlores they have these
kind of memories at least some of them are terribly distracted by it not the
least of which it's important to forget things are painful and they were
remember you know they're when they're puppy-died when they were five and it
still hurts and so for in some ways it's not a bad thing to forget or at least
have it blunted enough we can move on so that brings us to something else which
might be interesting to talk about which is PTSD and this kind of inability to
remove the emotional content from traumatic memories I mean that's
something that is interesting from a sleep perspective as well because there's
one idea that one of the things that happens in sleep to memories is that the
emotions can be decoupled from the memory so you might you might have been
mugged you know and it might be that sleeping you know of a probably not one
night but a year of sleeps might be strengthening the memory for that you
can still remember all the details of what happened but helping you to dissociate
the emotions so that when you remember it you don't have the physiological
reaction you're not as upset and of course people with post-traumatic
stress disorder have trouble doing this or they can't do it they can't decouple
and these emotions invade and they have they can have nightmares and they can
have kind of flashbacks and it can be I'm really disruptive to people's lives
people can commit suicide because of this Christina has the most articulate
kind of view on that with I know you don't like reconciliation or whatever
the the construct we used to talk about it I think that you thought deeply about
that yes so what reconciliation told the field we can talk about this
agreement is that when memories retrieval becomes fragile again and so
this was an interesting point for clinical translation for application one
is PTSD post-traumatic stress disorder the other is addiction addicts also have
very strong and persistent and repetitive memories and they can relapse if they
are brought back in the context where they used even after the talks this is
how they more likely relax is when they go back and they remember of the effect
of the drug so PTSD was one of the fields in which reconciliation was like
oh wow this is gonna be a new way to treat this type of disorders and has
not been so you know resulted or positive as we would we would have thought
because most of the studies in reconciliation have been done with normal
I call them normal let's say adaptive
aversive memories fear conditioning and those are not model of PTSD so this is
to say that that's exactly what you're saying the quality of the memories of
PTSD are different than adaptive aversive fear memories and so we definitely need
to understand more of what is going on in the subject that lead to PTSD in a
population trauma leads to PTSD to PTSD in about 20% of the popular the cases
the number of subjects that become PTSD for example from war zones or from you
know very profound trauma that they experience there are a number of other
feature attached to it previous history seems to be very important and that you
know we don't know enough of what really leads to PTSD what is the
theology of PTSD that's important and the understanding of what's different in
those memories well there's I mean one comment I could make it so there is this
idea that replaying those memories this is it's a hypothesis that comes from
Matt Walker at Berkeley his idea is that replaying those emotional trauma
memories in REM sleep specifically allows this decoupling of emotion and
that's because in REM sleep you have very low levels of a neurotransmitter
called norepinephrine which is if you have very low levels of that you shouldn't
be able to have physiological responses to things so you shouldn't have that
increase in heart rate the sweating pupil dilation these things that are
associated with a stress response an emotional response and so that means
you're essentially replaying the content of the memory without that response and
so decoupling so that's his hypothesis and there is some support for it there's
also some counter evidence but there is interesting yeah there's quite a bit of
counter evidence but the interesting thing about it is that irrespective
whether that hypothesis is right certainly people who are predisposed to
suffer from PTSD have abnormal REM sleep so the properties of that sleep are
different and in rats if if the force to go into REM sleep at a time when the
norepinephrine is high so it hasn't been able to come down as it should because
they've been too stressed then they will show PTSD like symptoms that actually
persist over months chronically so there is you know it's I think it's a
tricky area I think it's complicated and I'm not completely a proponent of this
hypothesis but I think something is going on yeah well is not yet understood
as we will say but what do you what you're saying it will make sense with perhaps
that previous history plays are all into it right okay
question fine
anything what is known about the retrieval process in particular outcome
when I can't remember something then the narrow rate I'm in the shower it comes
to me when I'm not even trying to think of it you've had tip of the time from
home it's your it's so normal everybody experiences it the last thing I do is
try to keep pushing when on the site and then you turn or Mary Jo and I went
to try to remember the French lieutenants woman and I remember I like the actress
and she I could see her cape and her name rind with peep and it was Merle
Street but it was a while back that I could pull it out so you probably have
a cognitive framework for that but it is absolutely common to does anybody
know what's going on there why that happens there's a metaphor I the answer
is I don't but the metaphor is that if you start pursuing if you see bifurcations
of a retrieve you just trying to find something the further down a road away
from the domain the further you get locked into the wrong strategy and if you
just stop and the system can kind of reset you can get back to it but that's
pure metaphor I maybe my colleagues know I don't it's absolutely real everybody
in the world experiences it pisses you off but we are really so the is normal
I mean one thing it illustrates is that the retrieval process carries on
non-consciously absolutely which in itself is quite an interesting thing and
it's associated why did I know it rind with something because we break up
memories I think you made this point earlier we break up memories not
consciously into lots of different things it can be sounded it could be
color so why would I know it rind with something that's not uncommon and it's
because although we codified it's like the movie that's not how my brain did it
my brain already has distributed that memory in lots of different places where
there might be a sound associated with it or a smell like you were talking in
sleep so another issue actually related to is how do you know it's the right
answer because it feels right I never thought here a philosopher saying that's
my answer but you may have answered this question in my hearing didn't pick up
yeah I you may have answered this and I apologize if you did I couldn't hear
everything what are you saying that one's nature if there is such a thing in part
determines whether memories are positive or negative is is it did you talk to
that at all whether an underlying personality determines the nature of a
memory we can have we can both go to Coney Island and go on Ferris wheel and I'll
remember it as a very upsetting experience I had if you were next to me
and you'll remember it is a very positive experience is there any knowledge about
yeah I mean what we haven't really discussed really is the relationship
between memories and goals memories and goals your goals while you do things in
the world right your memories reflect those goals but we don't always cannot
always identify them it's probably how goal attainment is hindered or promoted
by the experience that leads in part to a positive or negative memory so maybe
one factor there'll be others as well
I'm primarily interested in biology so I have a question assuming we are in this
world to survive and possibly in utero perhaps soon thereafter we are
accumulate experience that could be both emotionally physically painful and we
want to avoid to what degree does intentionality to survive come into play
impossibly I'll use the word select but there ain't not be an actual choosing
event but the process the individual wants to survive and what's going on
chemically biologically with that individual
no it's a very important question right where does it start I feel inspired the
answer from the angels where does it start the process that really select
what's going on so that there is survival intentionality I don't know you
know I don't I really don't I don't know how to comment that biologically
speaking is I think evolution has set as selected the number of mechanisms that
that's what they do so if there is an experience they respond in a way that
will promote survival does that answer okay I have my own experience but I'm
also curious about the role of learning with memory that for example the monarch
butterfly it takes three generations to complete a cycle do you are familiar
with the monarch studies they they live in the summer months in Ontario and
Midwest they winter in Mexico but in between they go through another whole
life stage it's not even the same parents grandparents you know it's going
skipping a generation so there's incredible information being encoded
into these butterflies to get them through a complete cycle to reproduce
oh I mean I don't think we are so like separate and better evolved
throughout the scale I think there is a continuum in the evolution and we are
surprised to see how much we can actually then see in lower animals so to
speak you know in less evolved animals I think these mechanisms are very intrinsic
in the evolution I mean I don't know how to answer your question I mean I'm not
surprised that we see this complex survival mechanisms in butterflies in
sea elegance in a plesia and toward the evolution I scale thank you
early in the history of physical science as we started to understand
emergent phenomenon like pressure in terms of models having to do with things
like statistical dynamics and so we started to learn the notion that unlike
the early reductionist interpretations of nature good a phenomenon that came
out of these sort of very nonlinear phenomena so today we are applying
simplified models of the brain to problems in recognition and can do
things in machines that were not doable nearly ten years ago now there are some
interesting problems with these approaches they're intractable in a sense
that is to say we can build systems that are mathematicians and physicists can
actually describe how they work if you investigate this but nevertheless it
does smack a bit of reductionism in a new sense however my sense in talking to
brain science frequently is that reductionism is sort of unwelcome is it
the belief of the panel that ultimately we will have a sort of for certain
segments of the brain because the brain is like the body made up of many systems
but for certain computational components of the brain or information
representation models of the brain we will we have a fundamental calculus of
information and perception what is the panel's position on this
I'll weigh in on it because it's a very deep question one of the ways that this
is impacting the field right now is our cartoon the position in order to comment
on it is that if we understood every connection in the brain there's 10 to
the 16th connections to the math if we end up and they're dynamic they change
with time so they're not just solder joints if we understand every connection
then we'll understand the brain and there is pushback from that point of view so
it's a it's a scientist don't have facts we have opinions and we struggle with
making our facts turn into something that's coherent that said I would frame it
the following it's absolutely necessary but not sufficient so to have that
corpus of information for a complete understanding now we would turn to you
to say what that is me I don't know what a complete understanding means to have
those the understanding the connectivity is absolutely necessary in the long run
but insufficient to then explain the way it works and so what we do is as scientists
and I would follow the reductuous camp in a heartbeat is provide modules that is
I'll give you a molecular module for how genes are turned on to store a memory
anywhere and now you can import that to the cortex and have that one kind of
memory you can port that to the hippocampus and use another and I would
never for a moment say that my simple animal is just a is a human but fewer
neurons it's the rules change absolutely change the computational rules change
but what we can do is say well what are the comp because we really believe in
evolution what is evolution hung on to she's pretty smart so she's hung on this
transcription and translation and phosphorylation and protein folding and
pre-transcriptional modeling and etc up and down to humans right on down to
simple animals so no one would I would never equate what we study to anything
close to a human experience but what we can do is get building blocks that can
inform the computational rules of a given domain in the brain that does balance
or does encoding and memory in the limit case though is in a sense of provable
assertion the way for instance statistical mechanics are relatively it is in but
the keyword is the limit of course but in reality if you think of a machine that
is 10 to the 16th connections that change with time and it's a pretty
complex challenge so sure yeah I was at a conference is all philosophers and the
idea was around if we understood all the connections with you and I was asked to
make some comments at the front when your dean asked to do this you talk about
stuff you know nothing about I do it every day and but what was funny was it
was right when do you remember when when is it called big blue what was the IBM
robot big blue what's it and he was on jeopardy like anyone you know why what
someone because he had shorter reaction time it wasn't that he was smarter he
gets be faster and there was one question I see if the room can get it that what's
and I'll drill back and why this is important what's in blue something that
Jennings got and Watson blue and it's a following you know in jeopardy how you
get a statement and then you recast the question and it was I'm a city with two
airports one named for a famous World War II general and one named for a
famous World War II battle what city am I I didn't know the answer anybody know
way to go it's right so you've got Chicago's O'Hare and and and anyway yeah
but big blue didn't get that and they asked the woman who built him she knew
every connection right she put in there I mean there's a whole team but she why
did you do that she I forgot a clue I don't know why didn't know that so
you referred to as attractability she well I mean but she knows all the connections
right she knew she she knew every dial she knew every and yet nonetheless she
could only approximate why big blue blew it no pun intended so I guess what I'm
getting it is just knowing the connectivity would be extraordinarily
helpful but ain't gonna get us all the way so it won't bring us through with
statistical mechanics I would think not but what it might do is it might be something
something like quantum mechanics is gonna help us and already people taking a
quantum approach to various forms of cognition quantum decision-making is a
big area of the moment yeah well the thing about quantum is it has these
emergent properties and obviously the brain is gonna have those as well without
knowing what those are you're not going to be able to make sense as you'll see
a lot that's going on so it just we need to get smarter about our physics
will be my answer how well I think would be great if reductionism worked I
would I would rejoice but it's I don't think we even have a way of seeing how it
could work at this present moment I mean take take some of the the metaphors
that have been used in this panel discussion to describe the memory
process you know the notion of a trace was passed around we have not not the
faintest idea of how to think about a memory trace if that is meant to be a
representational item what should that be what should that be I mean if if
connectionism is true which I suppose it is then there are no
representational items stored you mentioned again and again that we
shouldn't think of the memory as a as an index card absolutely true but how are
representations we don't have at least as a talk about or as weights yeah a
single synapse has it but in a computational sense there's a number of
shifting of weights that allow a network to recreate yeah but what's our metaphor
what that means is that whatever input you put into the system sure it's the
content of that input and that of course is different when you recall them when
you what you originally had absolutely so there wouldn't be anything stored the
notion of this idea of storage goes out of the window when you take connection
to the system seriously at least as far as I can tell so yeah I think we don't
even know how to answer this question but it's a great question thank you
thank you I'm a bit of a passionate hobbyist about cognitive neuroscience and I'm
that have a small software companies who actually agree with all of his points
which are that these talks are so great because there are so many dimensions to
knowing something that having people from various disciplines you really get to
see the shape of something with everyone that speaks but computer science is
playing such a hard and fast game with this stuff that it it seems it seems like
a great opportunity to have someone who's a very accomplished computer scientist
on the panel you know like when you were speaking about there was a a gentleman
at your college that has a very locked to a calendar personal memory of things
that's very much like a directory and if you had every file that you ever did
connected on to which a day they were of course you could access it right I mean
everyone has computers with so many things where the gentlemen with hyper
accusers of you know in computer systems we hide things that we don't think are
important for the user to know and that thing being broken would be them being
overwhelmed or just everything down the line like or converting memories and
long term memories when you go to sleep right that's been happening in digital
audio for decades now called bouncing to disk you know so there there seems like
there's so many parallels and there's so many interesting ways that to kind of
look at it I was just wondering if any of you intentionally seek out computer
scientists as well to kind of bounce ideas off of you bet yeah no it's a deep
it's a very deep part of our field the site of neuroscience is about 42,000
members all over the world and our typical meeting we just in Chicago had
29,000 people show up so there's a lot of folks and a significant check of those
folks who have fallen to class about your common computer science their
computational scientists their connection to science but they absolutely bring
that to the table and and it's not just building the metaphor it really informs
how we think about things I mean they're there they're one of the most
interesting fellows that I've run into down NYU is only Paul Glimture who
studied what he called neuroeconomics it's now called decision-making and that
maps on everything from risk aversion to addiction things we've talked about
today that came from a computational analysis so he's got economists
philosophers psychologists neuroscientists and hardcore folks in
carot that do nothing but number crunch and and the aggregate is extraordinarily
exciting that's that's what we're blessed to do this no one of us have a
handle on the truth but when you get a bunch of people together it's a
amazing payment pass to do it but it goes the other way as well I think it's
worth mentioning I mean of course it's incredibly useful for us to look look
to computer scientists but it's also incredibly useful for them to look to
the structure of the brain right so that's something that you're probably
aware of that's happening for instance in Manchester where I am at the moment
that they've constructed a computer that does parallel processing with it's
called spinnaker and it's built out of thousands of mobile phone chips each of
them representing a few neurons and these so it's it's mimicking the
structure of the brain somewhat you know to some extent more closely and it has
phenomenal processing abilities because it's this parallel processor which is
not how most computers are right so the what I would add to that be we always
kind of look to nature first to get the idea and then we engineer out the
inefficiencies right so you like you see a flying bird and you make a plane and
you make a faster plane by taking away some of the bird parts right and that
happened a lot with computers like in the 90s the the cra supercomputer breakthrough
was structuring it like the brain is because that shortened travel time
actually for all the signals to coordinate into like a central hub unit
try to you know make sense of things but I think I think what's really exciting
about it now like so for parallel processing right how did computers
eventually get to the ability where they could drive a car which used to be this
artificial intelligence holy grail and then it just accidentally happened in
the background right we got that way because people got really good at
GP GPU general purpose graphics card massively parallel processing because
humans are just pattern recognition kind of monsters right we're super fast at
it so when we finally had enough parallel cores analyzing video images
like on the fly we could have it track better so like it seems the the cell
phone thing I'm not not the cell phone thing the the spin occur the cluster of
low wattage nodes that you're speaking of is that doing a specific kind of
research project or is that it exists in itself using these low wattage chips
the project it's it was a project to build it as I understand but now it's
being used for projects so it has been constructed as something that looks a
bit more like the brain right it's a computer and now people are trying its
ability to perform different kinds of tasks so it goes both ways you brought
up that maps directly and what Penne just said is the field at large is
driven two ways one conception when it's technically and and in I wouldn't have
the vocabulary to tell you it was like 10 years ago if I sat down with
Christina 10 years ago and talked about what we're doing in our labs right now
in our labs right now we wouldn't have the vocabulary for that so that the
techniques can't explain but they can sure be drivers and open up windows
which so all of you are seeing me and seeing each other right now through your
eyes and your eyes have a retina at the back that's processing that and there's
a molecule in your retinas called opsin that is allowing that signal like that
brown jacket to turn into a neuro signal you can take that molecule you can put
it in a neuron attach it to whatever you want shine a light on it turn it on so
now we have a technique called optogenetics we can turn things on and off
and complicated network well we just turn on everybody in this room whose name
begins with them right before it was impossible to do so you can put these
techniques around now they're parlor tricks if you just stop there but now
really smart folks team up together with those technically driven folks of how
can I interrogate memory and for example how can I record a cluster of cells in
this thing called the amygdala that's important for emotion and they change
with an emotional memory like Christina studies and then later I can activate
those with this light and bring the memory back and have the animal literally as
if I've just turned the memory on and bring it I just shine light on its brain
couldn't have not even couldn't have done it 10 years ago we didn't have the
vocabulary for that so the kinds of computational things you're mentioning
can dramatically non linearly boost the field when they give us the ability to
ask a question at more granularity right thank you thank you so much guys
hi I have sort of a two-part question my first question is with regard to the
idea of focus sort of what happens when one orchestrates a situation for the
recall of memory and from your discussion it seems like you know it's it's quite
likely that what that means is is orchestrating a certain level of sort
of chemical stress but then I wonder and I guess a bit of ignorance with with
regard to the effects of meditation but I there's sort of the popular trope of
that of research in in into meditation now I think is this idea that it
increases your ability to focus it increases your memory but also it sort
of decreases your stress level and so I wonder you know are they are they and
you know are focused and the effects of meditation are they sort of
affecting one's ability to recall memories from different angles or are
they sort of I don't know what you might have to say what do you exactly do you
mean by meditation the reason I ask is because California it's different
out here we were close it
go ahead I you know it's sort of a traditional practice of focusing one's
thoughts of being you know conscious of of the experience of one's body and
and sort of practicing a focus of of directing one's thoughts to a you know
specific thing rather than letting you know one's thinking be scattered that
that kind of thing I'm gonna try to give some some thoughts so focused meaning
attention yeah in that sense so attention is regulated by hormones and
those are important for strengthening memory through the processes we talked
about so perhaps that could be a link to think about right and meditation lowers
stress level and too much stress impacts memory expression memory performance as
we said so that could be another link to think about that meditation it doesn't
you know completely eradicate stress but it's immediately it actually is right
or even you know increases one's ability to sort of control the amount of stress
that when if you have control it means that you can lower right the level of
stress hormones and when they are too high there is an impact as we said in
memory performance and some studies actually have shown that what the impact
is retrieval so retrieval is impaired in high stress conditions so that perhaps
could be some link to think about it one thing this Christina said earlier that
was really important in your mind's eye right now picture next more access that
inverted you that describes everything from chemical reactions in a test tube
to the way stars go through the planet it's a phenomenally important function to
a little's not if this is performance too little is no good there's an optimal
and then too much is no good and that it really does describe a lot of things
beyond psychology and in that maybe what I know nothing about meditation but
maybe you're shifting it back to the optimal if you look further over the
right you know maybe you're just shifting that balance back to the optimal and we
have language to capture that calling it meditation or relaxation which captures
it but maybe which really does this resetting it back not really I mean
another way to say we're getting back to that optimal which is moving further
away from the stress level and you know it is important to stay stressed a bit I
mean if you're gonna take a test and you're not up for it you're not gonna do
well so a little bit good but most of us are on the right hand side of that curve
I just wonder you know what it is about meditation that doesn't you know that
all these studies are sort of reporting these very positive results and not a
result that goes completely to the opposite end of that bell curve where
people are too chilled out to you know remember anything or you know focus at
all I mean it's just some suggestion I don't think there are proof that that
that's what explains but it is a reasonable suggestion to think about
thank you and thank you everybody thank you