Hey everyone, this is our last roundtable of the day, but it is by no means the least exciting,
because STEAM education encapsulates so much of what we're talking about.
And we started talking about STEAM this morning. I know that feels like a long time ago, it does to me.
This morning we talked about polymathi, we talked about transdisciplinary groups as the kind of
new version of Leonardo. What are we trying to do when we teach people STEAM? What are the ways
that STEAM gets realized either in the nonprofit sector or in education in K through 12 versus
college? What are these people going to grow up to be like? So these are the questions that we
start talking about this morning. We have a very good group of people here who have very vastly
different experience from teaching for a couple of years to teaching for 45 years. So there's a
lot of wisdom to be found here. I will let Zach as usual introduce the panel and then we'll get started.
Harvey Seifter. Harvey is founder and director of the art of science learning AOSL. He has taught
innovation at GE's Croughtonville Global Leadership Development Center. He is also a classically
trained musician and has provided his leadership in works with numerous award-winning musical
productions. Jill Barganetti. Jill is a professor at Hunter College and CUNY Graduate Center.
She has received an NSF Career Award and Presidential Early Career Award for scientists.
She is also a standing member on the NIH Tumor Cell Biology Study section. She also is a choreographer
who has developed a class choreographing genomics which focuses on teaching genome information flow
through postmodern dance. Paul Fry. Paul is the William Lampson Professor of English and is taught
at Yale since 1971. His primary areas of specialization are British Romanticism, the history of literary
criticism, contemporary literary theory and literature in relation to the visual arts. He is also an
award-winning author. Cynthia Panucci. Cynthia is the founder of ASCI, or ASCII, and is responsible
for creating much of the pioneering art science programming. She has a background in fine arts
and as a professional artist worked with printmaking, textiles, mixed media, and photography.
Daniel Groschkin is co-founder and executive director of GenSpace. He is also the founder
of the Bio Design Challenge. Daniel is a fellow at Data and Society. Additionally,
he has done journalistic work reporting on the intersection of biotechnology, culture,
and business for Bloomberg, Business Week, Scientific American, and other publications.
Ellen Levy. Ellen is a New York based artist and writer and a past president of the College
Art Association. With Patricia Olnick, she co-directs the New York based laser, which is Leonardo art
and science evening rendezvous, as I mentioned earlier. She was a special IDSVA advisor on the
Arts and Sciences at the Institute for Doctoral Studies in the visual arts and has been a numerous
group and solo exhibitions have featured her art here and abroad, including at the National
Academy of Sciences, the New York Academy of Sciences, and the like. With that, let's begin the round table.
All right, thank you, Zach. So, the question on my mind right now is for Paul, and you can get us
started by maybe framing us a little bit, having been in education for 45 years. I'd love to hear
about how you think things have changed, your experience good or bad through changes and either
ideas about what the institutions want or ideas about what the students want.
Yes, thanks, Julia. That's a good sequence of questioning because it puts me in the role of
reporter, which I think is probably the safest role to have me in. Today, the effort to create
interactions between literary and science study is quite lively. In the academy, it certainly was
not when I began teaching. Today, I suppose the most visible, it's been mentioned already,
form of collaboration is ecological studies, which is a lively field in the literary world.
Ursula Heiser was mentioned earlier as one important figure in that field. There are also
quite serious efforts at the neurological understanding of aesthetics. Some years back,
there was a book of essays called Beauty and the Brain, which was interestingly experimental.
It showed, for example, that dogs and monkeys were as excited about the golden section as we are,
and that perhaps four reasons having to do with shelter theory, some of you may know Jay Appleton's
book, shelter theory. In any case, there have been efforts to understand the aesthetic, which
always seems somehow or another to be completely in agreement with Kant's aesthetics and how and
why the scientific approach to aesthetics gives you that result. I don't think I'm qualified to say,
but it's interesting. There are now also interesting neurological efforts to understand what was
earlier referred to as the importance of telling stories. Not so much the anthropological question,
why do we tell stories, but the neurological question, why do the stories take the shape that
they do? A person called Lisa Zunshin is well known in this field, and there are a number of other
people working in that field as well. There have been lots of efforts to correlate the relationship
between literary hermeneutics, the art and science of interpretation, something that interests me,
especially because I really simply think of myself as a teacher of interpretation. If I'm
either or transdisciplinary, it's plainly that one needs to interpret and about any undertaking one
can think of. But there are, there are, there have been efforts by Edie Hirsch and others
to make a correlation between hermeneutics and the scientific method in the argument,
under the umbrella of arguing that there's a kind of unified field theory of interpretation.
This is met with widespread skepticism, and I'd be interested to hear the views of many of you
on a subject of that sort. I certainly share the skepticism myself, and I think that it's partly
the skepticism we heard earlier about the scientific method itself that drives that, in large degree,
and but in any case, this is another field in which there's quite lively interest within
literary study. I think I should stop there for the moment and come back to other aspects of the
issue. I would only add that when somebody said recently that, well, you know, we're all the same
here. There's not much diversity in this group. I feel quite diverse. I, as our children say,
I suck at science, and I can't pretend otherwise, but I nevertheless do, at the abstract level,
take a lively interest in these things. It's really just the hands-on part of it I can't do. I
could never see anything in a microscope. I just, you know, I would look and I would see nothing,
and I would call the lab assistant over, and the lab assistant would say, look there, don't you see
those things crawling around? No, I don't see them. So this was a kind of visual inhibition on my
part, which I've never overcome. I suppose another remote qualification I have to be here is that I
do paint. I was an art major in college, and I seriously considered a career in painting,
but it's only been intermittent. I've done some exhibiting, but not much. So in effect, I think
I'm in the category of that person who dissected those frogs. And I also have a very different
attitude toward the kind of creativity that goes into my own painting, and the kind of creativity
that I admire in my literary studies. It would be very hard for me to talk about a bridge
really between those two activities. Yeah, it's interesting when we're talking about
integrating disciplines, but then we have to recognize and we have been doing this, you know,
that they're different. They feel different, and that's not a bad thing either. So,
Jill, I'd love to hear a bit from you about your experience in your class choreographing
genomics, because I think that'll also really set the stage for this theme.
Yeah, I'd love to share it. I just want to say thank you to you, Julia, and thank you to the
Helix Center, and thank you to SciArt, because it's really been an amazing day, and yesterday
helping me to think about how I integrate art and science and all the discussions that have
been going on here. So in my class, choreographing genomics is what I'd like to focus on, and this
idea of this collaboration, but collaboration within each human being themselves. I've come to
feel today that really I need to describe myself as a scientist and an artist, and that that is
what I'm working to do with my students in the classroom, is to make sure that every student
is describing themselves as a scientist and an artist, and that they are not at odds with each
other, and I think that that's why we're all here because we recognize that they're not at odds
with each other, and that the process of discovery in science is similar to the process of discovery
in the arts, and that allowing young adults, you know, 19-year-olds who are at that process of
discovery to discover in that way in the classroom and get joy out of discovery through art for
science, and science understanding is an important thing. So what I do in the class is to have the
students have two texts, one which is about art and postmodern dance called Terpsichore and Sneakers,
which describes to them a lot of what happened at Black Mountain College, and the process where
many postmodern dance choreographers were learning or thinking about moving out of the realm of
classical dance training in order to give the process of what is art, that process of art,
what is experiencing art, and allowing each student to recognize that their experience will help them
to experience the visual learning of science, because all true scientists are very visual thinkers,
kinesthetic thinkers, didactic thinkers, they're having all these different thinking processes
brought to the table. So to teach students in this forum, or we're talking about education,
I think that it's really important to allow students to learn through what's called VARC,
which is visual learning, auditory learning, reading and writing, and then kinesthetic process,
and so that the students are bringing all of those processes to the learning table. So they're
learning about these different postmodern choreographers, so they can learn about Ivan Reiner and
Merse Cunningham, and they know they can run, and they can jump, and they're all dancers, and all
these different choreographers, so they're learning all these things through the lens and voice of
Sally Baines, who wrote this amazing book, and then they're learning about DNA through somebody
who I don't particularly care for, but James Watson's book, where they get to learn even that lens of
somebody who speaks in such terrible words about people, and you see his lens, and you see his
racism and his sexism through his lens, but you do also get the brilliance of the DNA molecule and
information flow, and so that's the text they have for that, so they can see how you can have both
together, and we're talking about all of these things, and then they're bringing them to the
table to choreograph genome information flow, DNA to RNA to protein, and earlier today it was like,
what is the new icon, our iconic symbol, and it is DNA, and we talk about DNA as the heart of things,
people use it now in language, and the language of science and biology is often couched in language
of choreography and movement and motion and synergism, and all these words we use in science that are
also used in choreography, so the students are using all of this, bringing it to the table,
choreographing, and then picking genes on different chromosomes that associate with cancer and
exploring those in movement, and they all have to be the choreographer, they all use all the students
in the class as their dancers, and they all are being audience, so they're learning the active art,
art formation, art audience, science, conceptual, and I think that's a great way to teach, and I
think it's a great way to learn, and I was lucky enough to have it, and I try to give that to others.
Can I ask a question? You're saying that you're teaching, for example, DNA yields for RNA yields
protein, which was the mantra for many years, certainly when I was growing up, but no longer is.
Correct. So do you also update these series? So this class, in the class that I teach,
so this is Biology 175, the one that I'm telling you about, I teach many different levels, I also
teach PhD students, but in this class right now, I have people who, it's their first semester
in college, and so, you know, I may talk a little bit about microRNAs and all these other complex
things, but these students actually, just having them understand five prime to three prime, and
using their bodies to understand directionality and anti-parallel, and this old to central dogma,
it's enough kind of, you have to decide what you can add on when, when they walked into the class,
so you also have to deal with assessment in education, so when they walked into the class,
the first piece is to do assessment, and to assess, do they know the name of any gene?
Do they know how many chromosomes would you have? Do they know how many nucleotides there are?
Do they know how many miles this would stretch for? And none of them knew any of this, okay?
So you begin with the assessment, and then have to take it from there, okay, now they know how
many chromosomes, they know many genes, they know what those products do, they know enzymatically
where activities are happening in the nucleus, and so, yes, a little, but this is a class to try to
help them determine what your major gonna be, and some of them are going to, they want to become,
they're going to theater, and they want to do puppetry, and others want to become chemistry
majors, and some want to become doctors, and so it's, it's to begin that vocabulary, so the person
who goes into puppetry, who's the one who actually made our flyer, who's so excited to share the
performance, it's taught in a black box theater, there are no deaths, there are no chairs, you know,
they're moving, but he's the most excited to share what they've learned in their final exam,
which is performance-based, so we can't do everything beyond where we were with Central Dogma at the
beginning, but I think it's a beginning of how do you set the stage as opposed to when students
come in and they take general biology, they think they're going to med school, and maybe they get
a C, and all of their dreams are squashed, and they're just like, what do I do? And this, and they've
sat in this classroom with 500 students in the back, really, on their phone half the time,
as opposed to in this classroom where their phone can't come out because they're moving,
and if they don't get five-prime to three-prime, they haven't joined hands with the right person,
and I'm asking them, where are you? Why'd you go there? So we can't do everything.
So what it sounds like for your class is that you're describing a dance class in the service of
teaching science, basic DNA science. Am I in misunderstanding? You are misunderstanding.
This is not a dance class. This is a science class. The class is Biology 175, and it's utilizing
all different kinds of learning possibilities to teach people in many different ways. So they
have to come to class, having read two different chapters. They have to already understand, I'm not
going to stand there and tell them all the things that should have read in the text, so it's almost
of what we call a flipped classroom. So they have to have come in prepared to be ready to go where
they're supposed to go, and it's very evident if they don't understand the concepts where I can
help them, I can help them to feel it in their body, I can help them to articulate it with their
voice, because postmodern dance and performance art, you're articulating, so they're speaking,
they're moving, there are times I'll do a PowerPoint to show them the, like when we're dealing with
five prime and three prime and really getting them to understand the molecule and where the sugar is.
So they're also doing chemistry. Everything is there. They see the chemistry of the molecule,
they have to understand where the sugar is, the nucleotide is. So this is a beginning,
but I think it's a great beginning because much of our vocabulary and science now is based on the
genome. So it sets them up, the next semester they might be going to general biology or they're in
chemistry, it sets them up, but it is not dance. They don't have to point their toe, but they do
have to run, or maybe if they can't run, they have to sit and speak. Whatever's going to work,
I'm just working for what will work. I would agree that this is an essential part of STEAM
education to bring these different things together, but it also reminds me in 2015,
I opened up The New York Times, and I read a fascinating article on trying to decipher the
Herculaneum scrolls. It couldn't be done. This was 2015, or some of it could be done, but not all of
it. A little bit later in the paper, there was another article about the connectome and some from
Columbia, his effort to decipher the neuronal connections in the brain. When you read the article
a little bit further, which realized is that they shared a common solution, but didn't really
realize it, which had to do with tomographic imaging, that they could unfurl the scrolls using
tomography without having to actually invasively destroy them. That was true also for the neurons.
So it would have been interesting if there had been somebody there representing STEAMs that,
what do you guys collaborate and see what happens? I love that idea. That's so funny.
I want to switch a little bit to STEAM outside of the classroom, because there is plenty of
that to go around. Harvey, do you want to start us off? Because you have a lot to say in this.
Sure. So just a little bit of background. I started off as a musician. I learned to read music before
English. I did a lot of sciences again, working in renal immunology. In college, I hung out with
a rougher crowd, so I did theater. And theater was my kind of core professional activity for the first
half of my career. I also kept a toehold in music, and when I became director of the Orpheus Chamber
Orchestra, I had this opportunity to work with this amazing conductorless orchestra. And I became
really fascinated with how the orchestra did that, how they were able to perform that way. And that
actually led me into some broader questions. Not only about what could you learn about
collaboration from a conductorless orchestra, but more broadly, what can we learn from artistic
skills, processes, experiences, in what realms and what domains and how we could apply them.
And it was really growing out of that, and the things that I learned in doing all of that work
led me to believe that there were these, as we looked at the application of these things in
business and research and academia, that the world was filled with these really intractable and
wicked problems that were effectively failures of the imagination and failures of collaboration,
that the fault lines of those failures tended to be where the disciplines were a worn meeting,
and that there might be ways to work with the arts and with arts-based learning to help bridge
those gaps and begin to build new things in the space in between to use the phrase that's been
used a lot here today. So that led me to start the art of science learning. And with the art
of science learning, we've really done three kind of big things over the last decade. The first is
we've developed and we, because there are 40 artists involved with this, and there are artists
that are visual artists and sculptors and painters, poets, filmmakers, choreographers,
improv theater artists, other types of theater artists, musicians. So we work with lots and lots
of different ways that you can experience and explore the arts. We turn that all into a curriculum,
a curriculum that was really designed pretty much for anybody. So not for really little kids,
we have other things that we do with really little kids, but really from for adolescents
and adults from all kinds of different backgrounds and interests and approaches. And it focuses
on how you can use the arts to help you learn and help you become an innovator and innovating
in many, many different domains. So we kind of built that body of work and those best practices
that this is as we were able to find them and put them together in a curriculum. The second thing is
we realize of course that we've designed a curriculum for which no institutions existed that can ever
be taught. So we essentially spent several years creating a large work around as a model. And that
took the form of incubators for innovation, which we set up in a number of cities around the country
in partnership with museums and other kinds of informal learning centers. We brought together
hundreds of people, artists and scientists and business leaders and researchers and high school
students, college students and so forth. And working around specific STEM challenges, exploring them
through the arts and through arts based learning and then innovating and actually developing new
ideas into products, processes, services, curriculum to address civic challenges like water resources
and urban nutrition and transportation alternatives. And then the third thing that we did is we kind
of focused a lot on impact and data because we had a strong sense that for all the power that we've
all experienced at this intersection of art science and learning, we have relatively little
proof that we impact it and so that it was important to try to address that. So we've kind of spent
this these years working outside the formal education system, but I think increasingly coming up with
things that are impacting and creating opportunities. I feel like you have some good input here about
outside of the classroom or growing from the classroom out into the real world. So let me tell
you about my background before I jump into it. I'm sorry, your mic's not on. Can you hear me now
better? Yeah, sure. All right, I'll just keep my finger here and it'll make me look very intelligent.
So my background is as a journalist. I neither have a degree in the sciences nor particularly in
the arts. I fell into it because as a journalist I found that access to the sciences specifically
biotech was incredibly hard once you left the university setting. Meaning I was reporting on
all these wonderful scientists and all the wonderful work they were doing and the second that I wanted
to actually try any of the work that they did themselves, it became immediately clear that it
would take me another decade to get back into the lab and actually try anything of my own. And that
was not acceptable to me personally. And so lo and behold we created something called GenSpace
which is the first community biology lab where anyone regardless of background, regardless of
you know what stage of life they're in and what you know what they're doing with their time can
come into our space and do at least their first genetic transformation and then move on from there
to more sophisticated things like CRISPR or we're about to offer a grow your own lamp using my
celium. So you know historically for me and I've been doing this for the last 10 years I haven't been
sort of addressing these issues within the institution. It was only later that we created the bio
design challenge and that's largely because artists and designers were finding their way to us. Being
New York based that shouldn't be a surprise but it was and what they were looking to do with use
our space as a platform for them to explore the technology. And as someone as a science journalist
who wasn't you know didn't know much about the practice it became very clear that they were
contributing something very very important to the dialogue that was going in on our lab
and I actually think contributing something very important to a larger dialogue about
what this technology what this science actually means for us as a society. So they were asking
well what can I do with this stuff and how will it affect the future of us as a civic society,
us as individuals, us as a collective. And these questions were really really important to me.
So one of the things that I haven't heard today was anything about social justice environmental
justice and it has surprised me and I think largely this collaboration these are the things
that will unfurl uncover sorry going back to being intelligent. Will unfurl and uncover
some of the challenges in social and environmental justice. To make a long story short we created
a program called the bio design challenge where we took classrooms of artists and designers we
partnered them with biologists who would act as kind of guides and mentors offering up office
hours and we asked them to imagine the future and what is the future of biotechnology look like
out in the world. How would you use some of the papers that you've read some of the
new advances in research how would that actually turn out in our society how would that turn out
in the products that we use. And the students then were able to either innovate and show us some
amazing visions but also critique and that became very important and so for the last three years
we've had these students on stage at MoMA presenting their ideas and as much as they are a celebration
of the learning of the science through this novel means it's also a critique of the of what happened
when you take science and technology and you cross it with capitalism and I think that's actually where
where the the power of this begins for me personally. I want to go back to the classroom but first.
Well my background is as a fine artist you know we often have to have a day job to support our
art habits so for 10 years as an artist in New York before I started ASCII I worked with kids
in community settings so I did a quilt project with pregnant teenage girls with a theme of
your hopes and fears of being a pregnant teenager. I did environmental murals with kids at a
religious after school project where you know it was about they got down on the floor and they put
their bodies and traced around their bodies and then those paper patterns went into the big 13 foot
by 8 foot mural but through working with kids in children's museum settings and designing art
workshops and and also interactive sculpture where kids could could accessorize with pattern texture
and form so interactivity became important to me and going into science museums and seeing how
kids were like pretty much programmed to be pressing pressing buttons and I didn't see that they were
getting very much out of that in terms of learning. So I just personally became involved in ocean
conservation from my first snorkeling experience in 98 and when I learned you know that they before
we could go down in the water they said you can't touch the reef because there's a protective film
and it will kill the reef gradually. Anyway I started to get I just read all I could on the internet.
I started to realize that when you when I saw this fantastic agoracal setting with all these
fishes and then I and then we got out of the boat and he said well you know two-thirds of the ocean
reefs are dead or endangered and I thought I was like outraged like I didn't know that and I couldn't
figure out well why in our society I watch National Geographic and like all of you do and I couldn't
figure out you know why why didn't really know but so I started studying about well so what is the
significance of artificial reefs why should we care? Well now my passion is ecology because I've
learned that the phytoplankton floating around in the global ocean is responsible for 80 percent of
the oxygen that we breathe and all the fresh water that grows our plants and that we drink and so my
my pursuit has has kind of gone along this path so I took my interest to NOAA in Washington DC and
I had this project that would was about the ocean health of the ocean and there was a photography
project and a fashion project and all these different components and they said well where's your
where's your youth education project and I hadn't done that so I went back to the drawing boards and
I a year later I came up with this project about collapsing ocean fisheries and there so I reached
out to the oceanography community and got people from the Southeast Asian countries and the Philippines
and other countries to put their children together on a blog and to be talking about for instance in
the Philippines children often can't go to school anymore because they have to take all day fishing
to catch minnow size fish because the industry size fishing industry from the Baltic countries
that is totally subsidized by their governments comes in to the Philippines and you know raids all
of the endemic fish that they can give their hands on so anyway well so friends were telling me
Cynthia don't do a project about collapsing fisheries with kids that are eight nine and ten
what do they care about fish so you know I don't really normally listen to people so I kind of
went on with this project but something amazing happened the project was with fourth graders at
a school in Chinatown because the principal was a very advanced adventuresome principal and she
took it on so we so we had these children blogging to these other countries and they were they were
either acting or speaking for the fish like don't throw dynamite on my reef because you know they're
going to kill me and you're going to destroy the whole reef as well which is what they do in Malaysia
so and then so the kids were to speak to give voice to the fish and also to give voice to the
children in the other countries that were the people their parents were having to move away
from the shoreline because there were no more fish so they had to go and do agricultural things
well anyway it's it started me on this whole journey and when it was over we had this blog
conversation that was supported by this Philippine ocean management fishery management
organization and it was online and it wasn't live but the questions were posed
so in the end I hired a choreographer and I made these fish cutouts as just
Objes dart that the students would the choreographer just designed this movement
some were ocean and chobis some were sea bass so there was a movement and then the music stopped
and the kids would go to the microphone one at a time and they would do this monologue that came
out of the blog that happened so there was a performance that was sponsored by the United
Nations environment program for the world environment day in 2007 and at the end of this wonderful
little performance that the kids did they ran up to me and they said well we have to write a
letter to the president doesn't he know what's going on this was George Bush's administration
but it's I had never talked to them anything politically I showed them a picture of this
the young children in the Philippines on stilts fishing and I told them that they you know these
kids could not go to school anymore well I didn't realize of kids that I was working with in Chinatown
you know that that culture is very interested in education so much so that that's the most
important thing to them and these kids were coming up with these concerns like the children in the
Philippines need to be able to go to school you know anyway it was a totally in terms of outcomes
of projects I had kind of created framework but I had no idea that these children would have been
had a reaction but it was of empathy I think for their fellow fellows in a different part of the country
kind of we've touched upon this before but when you give people the opportunity to have a kind of
cross-disciplinary experience whether they know they're having it or not there's this kind of thrill
which which is it you know relayed at the end and because students are wide-eyed that's that's
why they're wonderful they're open to learning so I just wanted to point out we have kind of
independent artist nonprofit academia nonprofit academia nonprofit academia slash nonprofit
how do we enact steam across these platforms what's easy for you and what's hard for you
first of all I think that there are many more opportunities for art science
insights and maybe in terms of teaching what's important is to not only draw connections
but think how you could impart it I spoke with a woman who is an educator Susan I believe it's
where she said Hogarth and what is word that that's her name and she told me something very
interesting many of you probably realize that both Golgi and Kahal received a Nobel Prize together
but what I had not realized until I spoke with her was that they both used the same staining method
and Kahal came up with Noron theory whereas Golgi came up with a theory that was I think it was
called a particular theory it was discarded and considered incorrect and what she looked at
with her class were the differences even using the same methodology which allowed one to see
something differently from the other this had to do with looking through the microscope
adjusting it using extra resources after applying stains evidently Kahal went and used various
kinds of pigments and coloring on it to bring out certain characteristics then this is just one
this is the tip of the iceberg another really prevalent thing is it wasn't just Galileo who
looked through telescope I mean this happened in at the same year with a man from England named
Hinton but what allowed Galileo to see this was his fine arts education and his relationship
with an man named Chiggling so I think then in terms of teaching having symposium these extra
things need to be brought out where you have creativity on the part of two people and yet
one is able to make even further observations this is something all of you here can use
in your teaching and your communication with others well the future of education is part of our
topic and I suppose I should say that another thing I do is co-chair something called the
started as the Yale New Haven Teachers Institute and now it's a national program called Yale
National Initiative for public school teachers K through 12 in underrepresented schools in collaboration
with university faculty who teach content based seminars for those public school teachers and
what's of interest perhaps in our context is the question how to approach the trans and
interdisciplinary in this setting because of course as other people have said speaking of
school teaching one is beset by codes and standards and above all by test scores and which is still
for us as for others who have spoken the only available form of evaluation that convinces funders
so there's a lot that one's up against here but a lot of us have nevertheless I've talked 15 of
these seminars and a lot of us have experimented with with tiptoeing around the interdisciplinary
they write long curriculum units as opposed to lesson plans so that it's partly an exercise in
brushing off their prose and so I for example teach seminars sometimes concerning poems on pictures
and introduce the idea that actually visual arts and verbal arts have rival agendas and in some
ways envy each other and that there's a kind of a dramatic force field that run encounters in an
eight-phrastic poem as they're called and I try to interest teachers who are English teachers or in
some cases art teachers in the possibility of thinking within the humanities of a variety of
disciplines and it's in that way that we feel we can approach the problem even for the K through 12
teachers whose lives are so scripted and regimented as as we all know it's a it's a small step as we
say on the moon but it is something at least we can do to enliven the prospect of teaching for
public school teachers in the future if I could just hold the floor for another minute to talk about
um something I do myself as a undergraduate graduate teacher teaches seminar quite often called
defenses of poetry which once again has to do with the rival read among disciplines you know Plato
in the tenth book of the republic unceremoniously banished the poets from his ideal republic and
based his whole argument in favor of a just life under the philosopher king on the idea that poets
really have no idea what they're talking about they live in a state of delusion three times removed
from reality and much as we like them we simply can't afford to have them in our ideal republic and
so we begin with a text like this and then we go on attempting to find ways to rehabilitate
uh poetry uh and and bring it back into even a republic that has um ambitions something like those
of Plato uh to me the high watermark um in this effort uh is a wonderful text by Shelley the
ronatic poet Shelley called a defense of poetry and Shelley argues in the defense of poetry that
science in its imaginative moment just is poetry in other words he commandeers the entire field of
thought for poetry understood as the capacity to metaphorize uh he then argues that metaphor
degenerates into equation or law or whatever it might be in the field and always needs the
resuscitation of rethinking so that um he believed for example that the americans revised their
constitution every five years i mean who you know he liked the americans uh naturally they
must revise their constitution every five years otherwise to live under law would be intolerable
because law in other words perpetually needs to be rethought as metaphor uh so this is a good
instance of a unified field approach uh to the disciplines which is which which i celebrate in
this in this setting quasi facetiously because we all know the problems with an argument of this kind
but it's nevertheless it seems to me in some ways an exhilarating one
Matthew Arnold then gives the whole show away he says science is true but it's also hateful
Darwin has told us that we are no longer the signisher of the universe we're descended from some
horrible arboreal creature with prehensile paws uh you know and and and and how can we possibly live
with this well says Arnold what we need is poetry which tells us pleasing lies right i mean i'm
boiling the argument down but as you can see everything Shelley won Arnold gave away in other
words this is in a nutshell uh the drama that i try to communicate in a course of this kind
and of course it tells you nothing about science and in fact in that setting precious little about
poetry uh but it does it does uh oblige you to rethink the questions of the relation among the
disciplines and i and we do spend a lot of time in this setting thinking about that sorry to
have kept you so long so if if we're actually gonna translate steam uh i actually have always hated
that but i and i fought it for i think we can all agree on that if we fought it for a long time but
i've actually decided you know it's out there let's just go with it so okay so um the word yeah yeah
so if if um if we're actually going to translate it from the not-for-profit from the informal learning
into the formal system um we're going to have to tackle this question of of how we measure impact
and i think that if we stick to the traditional measures we're kind of missing the point and
playing out of losing playing field you also not just how to measure the impact but define what
well yes i was just going there so in order in order to measure at first we have to define what
we mean by it and what it is that we're trying to impact so we have all of these wonderful 21st
century learning standards and we all think that collaboration is really important um we don't
really measure that very much um we don't integrate that very much into how we think about these things
and yet we now have actual data that proves that relatively small amounts of art space learning
leads directly to better collaboration among both adolescents and adult scientists um we think
that creative thinking is really important we don't always know how we want to define that but um
um we have good data that we've developed that shows that art space learning actually impacts
specific creative thinking skills ranging from the ability to generate ideas to the ability to
form heuristics we think that innovation is very important but we don't actually focus on that
and yet there are two we have powerful compelling data now and more being developed all the time
uh that shows the direct impact of art space learning on the innovation outcomes of teams so
I think that there's a real opportunity there to work across the the not-for-profit world the K12
world and also to work across art and science because after all if we're actually going to
to change things and move the needle on how we think about this we need compelling narratives
and compelling data we actually have what it takes to do both of those but without the application
of that to to these questions we're going to be spinning on the margins of a system which is
designed to drive other outcomes altogether which are actually as we all know not the outcomes
that we want to be driving as a society can can i can we step a little bit back because I think
we all have different perspectives here what is the positive benefit of steam from your perspective
meaning you're you're talking about all the ways in which it makes us better collaborators more
creative more innovative that would be goals for you but I think all of us have different
understandings of what that might what those goals might be yeah absolutely and and I only spoke
about a few of them for me and ones that I happen to have some data on but I think that they're a
pretty broad and rich set of things that can be accomplished through steam I like to give an
example more exact you mentioned things before but they weren't really examples that one could or I could put my yeah so
and I'm grappling for what will be a helpful type of example when you say an example an example of
an example of what the collaboration led to yeah okay sure could not have happened without it yeah so in
in our project we brought together 28 teams of people these people were artists there were
scientists they were students they were researchers people from very very different kinds of backgrounds
they worked together for a year and in these on these projects which they selected themselves in broad
challenge areas they developed things that I cannot imagine have coming out of any other
process things that were really strikingly original social innovations we had a we had a team that
that started out trying to reinvent the technology behind how people pay for transportation but ended up
with a novel social innovation and sharing economy innovation that has led today to a thriving
nonprofit which has people going to work for nonprofits banking their hours converting them into bus passes
being sponsored and sending about 500 rather 5,000 immigrants to their first job interviews so I mean
these things are coming out in in in lots of different domains they would not have happened if they hadn't
been artists and scientists and students and business leaders people from coming from very different
perspectives and using the arts as a common language and a set of tools to help them collaborate and
generate ideas and develop them. I'd like to talk about what what it means to me and what I think
how it can impact learning and so this morning there was this this term steamy and how steamy
you know steamy has a much more kind of rich thought for for young people like the kids saying wow
that's so steamy so when you think about how it can affect yeah it's hot you know that's like it's
lit it is so when you think about how arts transpires and it hits everybody and and just you can use
it as a way to empower all the learners just for an example from from my perspective when I was in
college even when I started to know I was a scientist I would not tell people I would always say I was a
dancer and even when I was going for my PhD I would go to parties and I would say I was a dancer
so and so now I now then I got to a place where I don't always say I was a scientist but now in
both the scientists in a dancer and the point is that I think steam this idea of putting it all
together allows you to reach audiences you ask this question about social justice and and dealing
with steam as a mechanism to affect social justice to be able to diversify the people that you can
speak to about science to allow science to be accessible to the broader public because the broader
public often when you begin to speak about science becomes glassy I we talked about elitism so in
an elite audience of this type here yes science seems so big and wonderful but in your normal
walk a day world you want to do a party and you talk about being a scientist this is my world
you know my family I don't speak about my work with my family I can speak about dance I can see
so you need to be able to have these conversations and to have young people it's not just students
these students are the the future scientists and to have them think something is steamy
and them to be able to make the new discoveries because it is young minds that make the new
discoveries it is young minds that shift paradigms it is young minds who are able to think differently
just as you're talking about staining something differently seeing something differently being
able to open their minds and not be lost in the paradigms we have now but be able to have paradigm
shifts because they see things differently and I think that steamy will allow us to affect those
kind of paradigm shifts and it's important to be able for people to not see things in this
didactic way that we approach science and that is the beauty of this putting together a part in
science that takes us past this didactic approach I'd like to also take it from there to point out
that we've had some new programs developing and there's some examples here one that particularly
impressed me was and was mentioned earlier was David Edwards program in in Boston I think he
injected it now 100k for high school students and I was part of the group of people who were
brainstorming about neuroscience and art there was the use they these high school students
after hearing 30 different ideas selected what excited them and what motivated them to develop
a project they were given a technologist to work with they were given an artist to work with and
these are people who when I first met them were for the most part fairly in articulate at the end
of six months they were so articulate they were excited they could develop a budget that could
support what they wanted to do I thought it was really quite a transformation and it's not anywhere
on that scale but these lasers that have developed they're all over now they're in other countries
Patricia Olinik who you heard before and I set this up late in 2008 when it wasn't officially
called a laser and we've had people every five or six weeks except for during the summer months
since then three and four people present their ideas and the beauty of it is not just that it's
largely unscripted which is true here also which is really quite wonderful but that at the end of
it we put these people together to talk and see what themes emerge from sometimes quite disparate
approaches and that's really where the excitement for me is is seeing how a theme and understanding
can emerge that had not been there before and I would say this is true of everyone here talking
about their programs both in this group and also in the earlier groups so I think that's what we're
trying to get at I think it's kind of ironic that in our culture here in this country you have to
sneak up on citizens when you talk about science I mean you can't just be blatant about it I can't
with my family either and then you know science is heavily funded of course scientists wouldn't say
so but art is totally almost not funded so here we have two groups you know the underappreciated
and the underfunded but you know somehow we got from our whatever I love for art and science so
how do we put these together in ways that really relate to the the student the young person so
so that they're turned on and they ask questions to me that's the most important thing is how do
you turn on the brain how do you provoke the questioning mind because the answers are all out
there you just look on your phone pretty much so that's what's so exciting in in the impacts that
we've seen the data that we've developed and that we've studied it has this tremendous capacity to
spark engagement curiosity enthusiasm a sense of optimism about learning a sense of agency and that
you can apply things that you learn in your own life and and and change the world around you
impact it we we're dealing with educational systems that by and large are not set up or designed
to do those things so something that you said that you do the seminars with teachers so maybe
we should reach out and do short term or summer session for teachers teaching the teachers so
because then they can if they fall in love with the teachers need the space to do it in so some
some schools are doing that already I'm blanking on the school it might be fisc but we published
about them in August and yeah they host sessions about how to teach in a more steam-like manner
for teachers and where they hosted they hosted it in the school's gallery because I don't know if
there's room there and it's nice to be in a gallery um so uh we're gonna open it up for questions now
right after Ed asks a question if I understand it if I understand it correctly
uh if you have somebody who is going to go into a lab and study the microtubules inside the neuron
the advantage of that person having gone through steam education during his
whole education period is that that person would hopefully look at the problem in a different way
more enriched way than if somebody hadn't gone through that education is that the claim that is
one of them yes and they'll think out of the box creatively because they don't have these
preconceived ideas of what the outcome should be I think well partly what we're describing is the
societal need for people who are both fluent in both and I'm going to add design to this as well
because it's an important one yes so design as well as the technology what or the science
whatever it is uh for for several reasons one reason is simply that when scientists do their work
they are particularly focused on what is going on in the mechanisms under the microscope or whatever
it is um when the designer takes that finding or works with that finding they're thinking about
the people who are going to use that in their daily lives and so they're acting almost as a
translator of the science that's being discovered into the product that will eventually be the
whatever it is we use and I think that person needs to be able to understand both what the
scientist is talking about understand the technology itself and then be able to understand people's
desires and so there needs to be that translational role in society I don't know about the internals
of apple but I will say that you know what we're trying to do is we're trying to create a generation
of bio designers which are people who are fluent in the language of design and also at the same time
can speak to a scientist and understand what they're saying and the hope just like now we have in
computing groups of designers who are working on things that uh basically designing with with
computation there will be a time in the near future probably already happening now we just
don't identify it as such people who are designing with biotechnology with biology you know when we
think about GMOs you know you know Monsanto crops and things like that these are bio designs these
are designs to be used in the context of human civilization human uh the human endeavor human
experiments well I hope they're not doing human experiment well they are well that's what Monsanto
is all about well fair enough anyway my point is that if you have a generation of designers who are
fluent in that language but also into in the social understand the social context hopefully
we'll avoid some of the environmental maybe humanitarian catastrophes that we've had in the past
hello I'm Len Steinbeck I teach in the museum graduate program at Johns Hopkins
I will do terminology has come up if popped up a few times yesterday and today and I was wondering
if you could share what you know about neurological plasticity and the thinking and ways of thinking
that benefit scientists and artists and whether these have these projects have any
lasting effect to your knowledge I can talk oh please um I was going to say that plasticity
appears to be a proven fact that this there is development that it's ongoing but that's not what
you really are asking is it I want to apply it and I want to apply it in both directions because
for a moment before it seemed like you were talking about um there's science artists impacting science
or science impacting artists one way or the other and not as mutually as I hope the conversation
would go especially when you talk about certain outcomes but so but I am interested in knowing
what we might know about how an intensive artistic orientation new to a scientist and you
scientific orientation to an artist changes in a lasting manner the way they see the world
there's a wonderful there's several wonderful books but one I particularly liked is by Warren
Nieden who is both an artist and an ophthalmologist it was written in 2003 and was devoted to how
an art for namely the cinema was sculpting people's brains and I think it's a very compelling
um explanation of work by people like Gerald Ailman yes and I know there there is a lot of work done
about art in the brain more ternering or kind of many have but I'm interested in what science does
with the art oriented brain and what art does with a science oriented brain or my being too specific
and please will read the tell me because I'm not well I can only comment a little bit on one side
of that and that is that um I don't know if you know the late James Catarols work at all um but
but he he did a did a meta study that looked at I think it was 40 neuro imaging studies over a
long period of time and he found a lot of shared neural substrates between artistic process experience
and empathy actually to come back to there's that work is incomplete but um there's certainly
some strong suggestions of things there um can I just say um one influence of um art on science is
Ned Seaman who's at NYU um he is known as the grandfather of DNA nanotechnology he came up with
the idea because he loves art and collects art and it was MC Escher's work and tiling that gave him
the idea for his whole field of DNA nanotechnology so I mean there I'm I think Leonardo is starting
to collect these exemplars and I think we could really benefit our field by having a compilat
compilation such an example I've been hugely impressed by the number of stunning examples of
collaborative success I've been hearing about in the last day and a half
uh and still perhaps a little skeptical about how they translate into the classroom it's the the
uh uh what we're what we're talking about is the um uh mutual insemination of great scientists and
great artists or at least very good scientists and very good artists and uh the uh and in the
future of education this has to give us uh an optimistic sense that more of this kind of thing
if possible perhaps uh not quite at such an advanced level uh but but but still I mean the way the
the instances of these sorts of success that you all have given is extremely impressive to an
outsider I just want to say that well it's uh I'm glad you brought that up because I just want to
note before we move on to the next question steam officially starred in 2008 all of us in this
room found it before then on our own whatever we called it um it's it's only been nine years you
know for a movement that's that's pretty short right so we are now educating the people that in
ten years will be getting those jobs that will start dictating different things that will happen
in institutions so so it's a bit of a a long uh study in terms of what's working right but but I
think uh there are already a lot of good stories hi my name is Jessica Beals I'm an artist from
Washington DC um I work primarily with themes related to science and math um but I'm particularly
interested in one aspect of this particular discussion today I'm related to education because
um I was I was once and I for the last four years have been invited to bring an interactive art
project I have to an annual summer institute for teachers at the Washington International School
where they're focusing on teaching for global learning so not so much about science or art
specifically but um they brought my project in which is a language-based interactive project with
rocks um about identity and community building just as a diversion mostly for the teachers to have
something to um do in between sessions and explore whatever was sparked by my project and of course I
had an underhanded idea about what I was going to do when they turned into my my space um and I
would have conversations with these teachers about what my work wasn't what they thought it was and
if they were told it was an art project in the gallery and they were welcome to look at it they
go oh this is interesting um can I touch it can I do anything with it and say of course it's interactive
do whatever you want with it and then tell me what you think about what you're doing um and they
would go oh wow this is really interesting it's bringing out memories and I'm interacting and
what's this thing there's sort of a seesaw over here what am I supposed to do with that and I'd say
way out way out the rocks way out the words on both sides tell me what you think see see what
happens I was encouraging teachers to explore using a scientific method on a very basic level
um language and another level interact with each other and they're just doesn't really feel like an
art project anymore and I'd say well it isn't they just decided to call it an art project because
it's a diversion um it's actually there's a lot of science here when I use this with kids I'm
teaching them about levers um it's a way to to edge into to physics without telling them that
that's what it is because they might be afraid of it so one of the things that is sparked in me
with all these conversations is that we keep on talking about artists and scientists and how we
have to bring them together as though they're intrinsically separate things and steam itself
is just an expression of the fact that we're all doing all these things all the time and
and our institutions perhaps have separated us um unnecessarily and we're just trying to figure
out how to get back to where we all are which is we're all doing all these things all the time we
just have to stop being afraid to do them at the same time amen to that um that was actually
going to be exactly what I wanted to say was that thank you it was it was good to comment on that
because I mean to please invite you to comment on that because we we are saying art and science and
when you say that you bring a lot with you like you bring a lot of um generalities scientists do
this and artists do this and we think like this and they think like that and um you know in science
communication we it's you know we're trying to we there are a lot of great conversations about this
like we're trying to give you something and and tell and like you you know you must take this in and
um what this whole thing is about is really opening your mind to um allowing whatever insights are
are being sparked by either seeing science and art and things like that um and the fact that you
know there's like all this um fractal consequence that you never really know what the impact of what
you show someone or tell someone or um give someone uh will be and so I um I was just hoping you could
comment on exactly what she was saying you know in this as we're trying to build a future of
education calling it science and calling it art um to start with as opposed to just saying we're
learning about inquiry um and what all can you you know you as an individual now that you have
made insights and connections what can you bring to this um something that has been in my did anyone
else ought to see of the mind is ought to see of the mind something that was so that is exactly
what I've been thinking about all day you know because that's a kind of an area where
in terms of what you want out of a collaboration maybe it's not an end goal or product maybe it's
just to to let people figure out what they're good at and and people are going to be good at
different things so you don't have to take an artist and make them a scientist you know what
I'm just gonna take a scientist to make them an artist you just have to allow them to um really
figure out what they now see the world differently so that was more a comment but I was hoping that
the question of it would be if there was any feedback on that I'd give one and that is that
so we've talked about the institutions and the challenge of the institutions pose there's also
us and the challenge that we pose and by that I mean all of us um because all of us are
expert at something we have our domain expertise and I don't think we want to get rid of domain
expertise I think domain expertise is really valuable um and if you think about really high
performing teams in lots of aspects of life one of the things that's really characteristic of of
of really effective collaboration is that you can leverage domain expertise people can go back
and forth between being an expert at in their particular specialty their domain and have this
generalist knowledge of what we're trying to accomplish together and and to sort of fluidly
integrate those things so our institutions are are definitely not set up to do that and maybe
we're not as set up to do that as we'd like to be and maybe that's a very important thing for us
to think about and develop how do we actually nurture that without sacrificing that expertise
but also recognizing that we all have a tendency sometimes to use that expertise as a kind of
leverage that makes it harder to collaborate I think we should think more about um you know
infants and and really really young children how do they explore the world I mean they put it in
their mouth they smell it they feel it they taste it they hear it all of these senses that Howard
Gardner talks about Harvard education so this this sort of tactile world is even what artificial
intelligence is grappling with now how do we put that into computers and into the computer mind
so artists have a lot to offer because these are the tools that we learn in art school and so um
perhaps we have to go back and unlearn things when I was a student I wanted to draw like Matisse
and my professor said first you have to draw like Leonardo before you can draw like Matisse
so we can't reduce until we know what the reality is we have to train our vision and observation in
the eastern society really knows about observing we don't observe enough we don't slow down enough
especially in our digital world but anyway I think playfulness going back to childhood would be a
really really good starting point for education for art and science and attention is relevant to
it was brought up earlier there I mean there are two forms there's depth of attention and there's
the attention span that gets so much attention and we need to think about the best ways to capture
both forms I just want to make a comment about the the not separating the artist and the scientist
and when people are going to go for the PhD or they're they're applying for things there's always
this piece where they ask you to rate the person's creativity you always have to rate the person's
creativity but in our education system we're not always you know we're separating these things and
I think we need to not separate we need to be teaching in a way where maybe we're not always
on this art or calling it science because the the person who goes on to become a formal scientist
needs to have those moments of creative exploration to set up their hypothesis and that hypothesis
comes from this intrinsic hypothesis place that's this creative place that's the artistic space
so yeah so so there really isn't the dichotomy the way it's been set up because
this actively working scientists are very artistic as was brought up earlier in one of the questions
and talking about Einstein and his violin scientists even if they don't think they're artistic or
somewhere if they're practicing being artistic when they're sitting there they get that free time
that freedom that room of their own should I say for for females but yeah we shouldn't separate
I'm nearly an artist I would say a hacker of technology a citizen hacker so to speak I've worked on a lot of
collaborations on art science art technology teams and one thing in the discussion that I'm hearing
you know it's interesting to be talking about this and to learning about other people's perspectives
about how does one teach people to collaborate how do you best open them up like take this
you know flower and just completely open it well from my experience the most interesting teams
and most interesting productions that we've created have come from listening to them listening to
other there I there's no one way to teach this isn't a linear discourse it's taking for example
a hyperactive kid taking putting building a community of collaboration from all different kinds of
challenges different cultures different interests a kid who's totally interested in music or another
who's interested in the sounds of silence then another another another kid who's like moving so
fast they can feel that they can they can feel the algorithms between their arms you know like moving
them there there's so many things that you can learn from the people that you're putting together
and how and and new and seeing how they create together one thing that I found really interesting
for myself and on some teams were different concepts like reading different articles depending upon
the age groups of course that we're talking about reading different articles about scientific
discovery and thinking really in terms of synchronicity not in terms of disparate movement you know like
there's the past and there's the future and there's this line outliers are are incredibly
interesting and ed edify so much of what's going on in the world and I have found that
when there are groups that are that are put together and people are reading different material
and they're not embarrassed or made to feel uncomfortable to come up with their interpretations
which may be very much out of the box but they may be very brilliant after his i'm in
Einstein would not have been one of your your people how you could have collected that data
he didn't do that hit Malayva his wife did much better university than he did and he collaborated
with her on projects so it's you know on the theory of relativity they work together on it so you
you know i i just think it's important to listen to the groups that you put together
and from that their discussions of things you know i believe some really interesting
collaborations will come about for the teachers to then be able to learn from two because it's
all about learning from each other i'd like to add to that uh one of the things that we found
is that if you create the incentive structure for these collaborations you get a lot of you get a
better result so in the early days of Genspace when artists and designers started to show up and we
had other folks who were with science backgrounds there was a real tension between these two these
groups uh the scientist would feel that the artist is you would be using them for their own artistic
purposes and they'd be feeling taken advantage of on the reverse side when the artist was when the
when the scientist was um more quote unquote in charge the artist would feel as though uh they
are being used to do PR for for the scientist and what i found uh over the last couple of years was
that scientists have found that the the publicity that comes from that collaboration uh ends up
being quite useful for their careers and what i've seen is that they there's been a proliferation
similar literally for the artist it has helped them as well after the scientist all of everyone
seems to benefit at least in some cases and so the more of that we see that the more we'll see
these collaborations i think the single most important thing we can do actually is to create
spaces and environments that foster collaboration maybe offers some some resources some models some
freedom to experience residencies and i think the culture has been changing in a way to promote this
um just some extent to some extent i think i i haven't seen great evidence that the culture
within formal education is deeply changing to support that although i do see examples of it
happening all over the place i would say the new Minerva institute relatively new in california
part of the clearmont system barred the changes they've made to introduce science into what was
previously an arts curriculum um and again i don't think we can give too much praise to the role
that leonardo has played in fostering a lot of this and and but k12 is a tough yeah
great um i'm going to try to keep this brief um first off okay thank you for doing this um i'm
as many of you probably are i don't think i ever had a choice in where i was going to fall in a
career path my undergrad experiences medical illustration my grad experiences museum exhibition
design in between i've done a little bit of everything else and when you are an interdisciplinary and
and when you don't feel like you fit anywhere life can get a little scary can't it so to hear
that you've been uh working on these projects these collaborations these foundations you're doing
this outreach it's really heartwarming but you need to keep doing it
because uh a lot of people want to do this i've been teaching high schoolers for quite a few years now
in fine arts and trying to rope in as much chemistry into my dye lessons as i can
so you keep keep just doing it but um remember that doing this being able to go out on a limb
and chase your dream and exist in an interstitial space where you may not have a safety net is a
privilege and if we want to bring more people into this not just a marriage of arts and sciences
but every single identity that we can possibly rope in because every identity brings its own
perspective to any given question and who knows which one's going to be useful which one's going
to crack the code and which one's going to blow everything out of the water
so how do you think you want to grow and maintain a support network not just for kids to bring them
up and not just for students to feed them while they're in school but for the adults they'll become
thank you for your comment i think um i wanted to let you know a nice sentiment uh which is good
for everyone to know so in the in august of uh last or this year rather uh sire magazine published
a steam issue and this was the first collection of a bunch of steam articles many people in this
room contributed to it um and there were a lot of different viewpoints a lot of different approaches
etc but it was just kind of a general roundup and uh the one thing that everyone agreed on is that
we did steam because we thought it was the right thing to do and we we didn't have to explain why
i was just like yeah of course it's the right thing to do so don't worry people keep doing it
hello again everyone um i am really interested in the the future of steam education as it applies
and you know k-12 but also bringing it into the university and something i've been thinking about
is how we're disseminating what we've learned from these projects that that we're working on so
how are you guys putting out um some of the results that you talked about you know we have
data or your course sounds absolutely amazing you know how would how would someone else you know is
there is there a model um that someone can would be able to take or access um because when i i hear
about the things i'm usually in a room with the person and um on the big wide world of the of
the internet it's it's harder to find and it's not so much um covered in a lot of the scholarly
articles yet so how are you guys um working to to get that information out in the arabore journal
yeah there's um roger what is the name of the woman who is putting together the collection of steam
approaches you know i'm talking about can you give him that microphone
because this is good information to her and her name is kathryn evans um we're working on the
idea of a cloud curriculum project so anybody who's been developing a syllabus shares it with other
people um i call it kind of like a gated commons you can only get in by contributing your attempts
um and it's it's got an acronym c dash curriculum development in art science and humanities
so if you google it you'll find the website we're about to announce it and invite people to do
curriculum sharing online because one of the problems is as you were just saying it's so
difficult to find the other people who've maybe taught for a couple years and have some best
practices or new practices there's a couple of other major places to look one one is informal
science.org um and that's a tremendous resource uh we certainly publish all of our major data on
there and so do many other people and you can find a vast amount on there um the innovation
collaborative and if you can google them and they've developed a lot of best practices and have
materials around that and with a lot more coming certainly our website also has even more detailed
data and information on our work and also a fair amount of other things that we're able to find
out and post that we think are of interest to to that work and to people who are interested in
in in this domain uh and so artofsciencelearning.org lots you can find there uh just to add to that
biodesignchallenge.org uh so we've been working with i think we've we've hit the hundred mark hundred
plus uh university educators who have been working at the intersection of biology and art and design
uh i have their sample i have samples of their curricula online as well as a library of resources
uh of reading materials from all from Foucault all the way to um you know complicated articles on
uh science articles on CRISPR uh which are which is a fantastic resource for anyone who's developing
their own curriculum. Speaking of Foucault uh anyone interested in data mining from my point of view
uh might be interested in following the work of the Stanford literary lab which has uh convincingly
found new ways to think about uh making sense of vast quantities of literary data so. I think we
need we need something that's more centralized so I so i'm an academic and you know i do my work
my own little cloud earth so I think what we're hearing here it's bringing all these people together
and each person saying oh I have this I have this and then you'll sit and you'll google and you'll
search for it but in bringing us all together here the beauty of today is that we're all in this
room and it sounds to me like we need some place where we can all be together in a virtual room
that's where all of these pieces that people are you know saying now are available and
I'm it's easy to to find these things I would love to share but as we've talked about earlier
in the day when we write our grants and we're talking about our broader impacts you know I've
applied to try to get money to be able to share my approach to be able to teach teachers what I've
done I've taught it four times I'll share my my syllabus but it's hard to get money for being
able to to share these things and teach people what you think you've learned and I don't know how
we're going to begin to do that and this is where we say we have academia we have you know not-for-profit
academia not-for-profit I think the not-for-profits have to try to bring in us who are in academia
because we're always going to not-for-profits to try to get money to be able to do our things
and disseminate but unless we get that money and we have that free time to disseminate we can't do it
the way we might want to. Okay we yeah we have time for one last quick question.
We will make the two quick questions and let's order night.
Do we have no profit and academic media in the round table do you think we are seeing the
birth of a new field a new interdisciplinary field called art science or called science art
that is not much separated art and science just like biochemistry doesn't appear it doesn't split
biology and chemistry and is biochemists and astrophysics astrophysics is not more astronomy
nor physics do you think we are seeing the birds of this new field in an environment like this
the second question is do you think the academy will
grill will help to grow up this field because for instance in our academy in Brazil we have a
master in PhD course since 2004 called education for bioscience and health in which we have
a line of research of science and art and we have 10 teases PhD teases on science and art
but I don't know other academies on the world that that give this liberty this freedom to
think out of the box like this like we are doing here so this question before the night.
I just want to make a plug first off for Pearl Premis who was one of the first people to dance
her PhD and yeah I think we need a new a new academy that will begin to look at this today I
began to wonder what happened to Black Mountain College what happened to this kind of place where
people want to work this way where people come together like this in scholarship to to have these
conversations and and it's not silos but I don't know how that would happen and where the money is
for that kind of scholarship to occur. Okay well I think your questions are good ones to also
revisit tomorrow so thank you guys so much for this wonderful panel this concludes our day together
two quick announcements tomorrow morning we're starting at 10 a.m. we'll open the doors at 9.30
number two you are all invited to an art exhibit opening tonight that Syart Center is hosting
10 blocks from here the address is 208 73rd street there's a flyer on the table out there
art reception wine amazing science based art please join us from seven to nine 30