Are you ready?
I'm the associate director of the center.
Before I introduce the participants of today's round table, I have two brief announcements.
One is that the next program on the beauty and unity of mathematics is on December 1.
And then on December 15, it's a program on animal consciousness.
And then other programs you will see if you go to the website.
I will make a very brief introduction of the participants today.
If you want more information on them, you go to our website.
There's a detailed bio there.
Michael first, who is sitting right there, is professor of clinical psychiatry at Columbia
University.
Laura Hirschbein is professor of psychiatry at University of Michigan.
Francis Lee is the chair of the department of psychiatry at Cornell Medical, Cornell
Medicine.
Robert Michaels is the Wach McDermott University professor of medicine at psychiatry at Wyl Cornell.
And Miklo Stott is the neuroscientist professor of pharmacology at Wyl Cornell.
So as you know, the format is a spontaneous conversation amongst the participants.
Thank you.
Who wants to get the going?
Well, we were just talking a minute ago before everybody started about the fact that I'm
a historian and I'm the only woman and the only non-New Yorker, so I guess I have a perspective.
But we were talking about wondering whether the history should start first if we're looking
to the future.
But the problem with starting in the past is if you're imagining a narrative, do we want
the way people tend to use history is to tell the story about the president.
Are we talking about the past as the battle days that are leading to the future with new
discoveries, new advances, new neuroscience, new whatever, or are we going to use the past
to tell a story of decline that we've lost track of the things that we used to do that
we used to do well and now we're in soulless territory of just symptom counting with due
appreciation to DSM.
So you can use the history to tell the story of decline, the story of progress, or as I
tend to see it, the story of things that continue, the themes that come up over and over and
over and over again.
The things that we discover and rediscover, we discover brains, we discover symptoms,
we discover statistics, I'm reading a great book on the history of statistics now that
it points out that we psychiatrists were doing statistical counting in the 17th century.
And so the idea of counting and looking at numbers is not new.
We humans like to do that.
The first step of trying to understand things is to put some order in things that hopefully
patterns will emerge and will have understanding.
So that's what going on for a very long time and that continues to be the main way everybody
wonders in the DSM diagnostic statistical manual, what was the statistical part?
And that was because it originally was used for collecting statistics in mental hospitals
and nowadays I guess you could argue the coding allows people to collect statistics but that's
really the only reason they keep the assets for historical reasons.
It's a well-known document.
It's really not a statistical anymore but you're right.
The idea of starting out by the DSM unfortunately remains a descriptive observational system
with almost no depth to it at all and people have criticized it for that reason which is
certainly a valid criticism but it remains useful because there's no alternative.
It's always the thing when somebody trashes the DSM it's okay so what do you want to replace
it with?
It usually don't get much response.
So it's incredibly limited but it continues despite all of the advances in neuroscience
and everything else it continues to have value as an organizing principle.
It's very limited.
I think the perspective actually is very useful.
I remember 15 years ago I think when Paul the Genius came out I'm looking at everything
from the basic science point you have to just a disclaimer but I remember that one of the
traction of what this field is that this new genes came out and everybody believed that
after a while we will be able to explain some of the symptoms and maybe actually we can
define a certain disease based on diseases, disease genes.
And historically now we know that it's actually absolutely another case.
If anything it's even more complicated.
So I've been struggling with this in my whole lab and in the university that how actually
to solve that problem and we can discuss it later but obviously we have to move out from
the single gene and even multiple gene because we have to understand how the environment
is really impinging on this whole gene network and if you have time maybe discuss about that.
I think still the genome is a hope that the genome can or epigenome rather can explain
a lot of things.
So historically I think we really moved a lot from genes and now we have the epigenome
and hopefully we have some chance to get a little bit deeper into this how because that's
still yes we are in a very simple case we have an epigenome now but like in the 780
90s that we have a lot of things but we don't understand how they work together how to interact.
But I think it's a little bit more bad execution now we have more players so it's almost
that we need another level of understanding.
I think we do know more I'm also a neuroscientist and I was just out of symposium at Cornell
and yesterday and from a lot of different neuroscientists I was coming from the sound
of the video and was actually clear it was muffled here too.
Is this better?
Is it really or not actually much closer to understanding the pathophysiologists like
yeah this order despite the hundreds of genes that have now been found.
The best example I was at this meeting was that the success story now the best success
story in psychiatry is autism.
99 genes will now have met genome wide significance very penetrative high effect sizes they account
for 1% or less than 1% all autism in this population.
But each of these papers is a nature paper.
This is considered the best advance of what we can do at this point.
And it's actually not clear how to move forward and I think this is something that I struggle
with also.
It's just that the hope as Miklo said was that 20 years ago or 30 years ago was just
like in pulmonology or nephrology we could just get a bunch of genes and then be able
to move forward and what's clear is that this is not a linear path.
The brain is probably more complicated.
There's some number like 150,000 or 150 trillion synapses.
This is just us for us to think that a single gene or 100 genes could help explaining this
is going to be difficult to answer.
It was very sobering meeting.
But if I may just to defect that so basically I think it's specific issues like 15 years
ago in the Facebook was or Amazon started.
So basically the idea if you think about it is that you get all of this information,
they collect information, personal information and 15 years ago they just started.
Now they have a tremendous amount of information and that's for me to ask.
Now they have arguments that they can actually figure out what next move is and maybe send
you an advertisement and we want to say that's saying some pet food or something because
you know that you have a pet at home and more complex.
So I was thinking maybe that kind of strategy because we have now genes, epigenomes and
a lot of that low side.
We have thousands of tests.
So how to put together all of individual players as they would pull out the society
to a comprehensive understanding of how the society works and how the brain works.
But I was just thinking another day about this but it's still probably not the right
template because it's a very two-dimensional of what they do.
They just collect and they can interpret.
What our problem is that we have multidimensional, we have genes, then we have synapses, connectivity,
then we have circuit functions and then behavior which is very elusive.
But most people work at that level.
So I think it has to be something where you could integrate these data sets like the
UN and Facebook interface but sets but you would be able to actually in a 3D almost fashion
to integrate all of this information to a comprehensive understanding of the brain.
I have no idea what basically I'm talking about here but I'm just basically saying that
it's just something which will be the next most of time this research you don't really
know what is the next big step but if something has to be very beyond this two-dimensional
understanding what we have now and probably nobody knows this.
It's just somebody will come up.
So that's why I think it's a good idea to invest NIH and IMH puts a lot of money in
these things.
There are a couple of people now, artificial intelligence comes in.
So maybe something is coming out but we don't know what it is and unfortunately we will
not be able to answer the future if I can't see I'm afraid but we just have to put money
and then beating 14 internet as a concept to coming out from this and I don't see it
yet.
I'm not for the major conditions let's say bipolar disorder or schizophrenia for example.
Are the studies focused on finding out what causes the condition or are the studies also
focused on dissecting it into the symptoms and trying to figure out what causes each
symptom?
I think at this point the main, at least from what I can get, the main thrust where the
money is going is collecting as many samples as possible to get hundreds of thousands of
samples of biological samples from ME, DNA and other and to try to do large statistical
analysis essentially genome-wide associations and they've succeeded in finding now over
200 schizophrenia genes accounting again for low percentages of the risk, like 0.5% of
the risk for schizophrenia.
They just completed in England a study where they took 100,000 people with depression and
they were able to find 50 genes that looked like they might be affected.
15, 5, 0.
Again, low effect sizes for each of these but essentially this is where efforts are to.
Again this is sort of like counting, it's sort of like they just want to accumulate as
many potential genes that might be a risk gene at this point and these are still early
days I would say.
20 years ago there was, there were none so if you divide by zero this is infinitely
better.
If you say 50 genes are responsible for the depression then what?
But they account for so little of the risk so it's sort of like it's a small effect size
so that there is a, the best example is one of the genes is a glutamate receptor which
makes somewhat sense glutamate receptors are everywhere now.
So but the problem, this one glutamate receptor they found is that it's everywhere.
So how you're going to actually target a drug to or something like that is going to be very
difficult.
Drug companies have been targeting this class of receptors already so in many ways we know
that this demiurs are stuck then with them again the complexity of the nervous system
in the brain and then even if we have one hit that makes some sense it's still very hard
to move forward.
You know it's interesting thinking about all of this data because again this brings
me back to this book I'm reading on the history of statistics and statistics in psychiatry
in particular where they were drowning in data in the 19th century.
You know one of the, one of Emil Cropelen's arguments was that he was spending all of
his time with data.
He had so much data he didn't know what to do with it and obviously we have a better
capacity for managing data but the thing that came after all of this data gathering in the
early 20th century was Freud and psychoanalysis has said okay we're not going to talk about
these big groups we're going to talk about one person and we're going to talk about how
what makes up this one person and how this one person's inner conflicts manifested in
these symptoms or these experiences and so I'm wondering if the future maybe if somebody
gets to the point where we have all this data and it's little pixels and it's everywhere
and it doesn't cohere to a particular picture that we're going to have another wave of people
saying no actually what we need are individuals, individual relationships.
You know we're spending all of our time bumping into people as we're looking on our phones
not engaging with people or we're going to have a backlash where maybe psychiatrists
will leave maybe will follow to say no actually what we need to do is work on interpersonal
interactions and that one patient again and go back in a different way.
I don't know.
Have we stopped doing that now?
According to some of our patients we have.
I think it's really they are not exclusive and they absolutely you have to just do both.
We do certainly the last day but in the clinics you do certainly the individual but they
our our goal is really to understand the basic framework of a disease rather than an individual
and maybe how an individual can end up with a disease phenotype from this overall concept
and you are more interested in obviously why this person got that but I think it's just
the two sides of the same story and we just have to do both.
There's an interesting sort of like similar backlash going right now in this other field
of systems neuroscience where people thought that you just need your image more people
and as they're going through various tasks or even whether sitting just to look at their
connect their brain connectome just as a to bring everyone up to speed.
Twenty years ago it was found that the brain actually organized itself into sort of like
hubs within their in the brain and you can actually just get a right what they call a
resting state without any task you can actually get a scan and actually see these hugs in
the brain and this is the work of Marcus Rakel at Washington University and people were fascinated
by this and no one has really been able to sort of understand how is it that you can
measure blood flow in the brain and actually see these self organized networks and and
so then everyone got excited and just kept on collecting thousands and thousands of
scans so now we have hundreds of thousands of scans within studies now at WashU where
Marcus was there they now decided that everyone's network is individualized everyone's brain
is that when you average it you get some average of brain that looks like no brain on the planet
earth so now what they're doing is that they're they're actually taking individuals and actually
just scanning them over and over again for example during the course of depression or
during something so they can scan them at the height of symptom pathology and then at
some other point when they're not so I think this is the goal now that that you might want
to basically go back to into and then learn something from these individuals in a way that
that they're not they're not been thought of before.
I think there's a there have been some drug studies on that that this end of one studies
where you you take a single person is the study and how they interact with medication
and that's sort of this new thing that's being there.
There's so many individual differences this is essentially this is that you can't the
principles that even of trying to put together a brain connectome is very difficult even
though NIH is spending lots of money on these connectome projects that ultimately you it
might actually just sort of like you sort of like if you want to understand fruit you
don't blend it together.
I believe that response is a little bit simpler because then you ask the question why this
drug is actually working in one individual actually understand the pharmacology of that
based on an enzyme which is either stronger or weaker in certain individuals it's called
seep enzymes but basically they just metabolize the drug many times this is crucial so and
we can even now a patient can be screened because it's genetically based one can take
a sample from blood and it's every cell is the same and we can basically figure out
that it's a fast metabolizer a slow metabolizer and maybe that's the reason somebody is actually
a side effects or another person does not respond and it's just a dose relationship
so that that maybe somewhat easier to understand than what the underlying cause which could
be thousands of different ways but I still believe that there's a still something common
feature or features that it is a circuitry I kind of start to believe in circuitry no
nobody's but maybe it's just to be as it's fashionable but but circuitry in animal models
at least you can understand how the circuitry can be linked to a certain behavior we can
model the circuitry we can activate we can deactivate certain very different secondary
even we can we can tailor we call it synaptic transmission in certain areas of brain and
we can we can't respond but of course after below and underneath there's a lot of genes
and synapse and other things you just don't really understand I'm gonna go back to where
we started and be a little provocative to me psychiatry's defined like all medical
specialties as everything that's relevant to helping people with a certain kind of problem
and the neuroscience research base that we've been talking about is fascinating exciting
intriguing and essentially totally irrelevant to helping any living patient it may have
some hope for the future although a possible outcome of the work is that this strategy
won't lead to anything helpful for patients or maybe to some modest twists on some of
our current drugs almost all of our current biologic treatments were discovered by happen
stance not by scientific research they're serendipitous if we never spent the penny on
any neuroscience basic research over the last hundred years it would make trivial difference
the current psychiatric patients but we didn't know that I mean obviously clearly that's
the problem I mean it was that we were going to crack the problem by going neuroscience
but as our historian warned us we have to study the past to find out we won't repeat
so it wasn't money weight it was wasted in the sense it didn't give us what we wanted
but it was wasted but it led to nothing yes it was a very intelligent gamble that lost
so it's short term lost we don't know about the future I just want that for background
because when we talk about the excitement of contemporary neuroscience research we're
talking about possible hopes for a fairly distant future we're not talking about anyone who's
mentally ill today or anything that might help that person but one of the side effects
of the neuroscience thing is I believe it's been partly responsible for lowering the stigma
of mental disorders and it's unfortunate because somehow if it's in the brain therefore people
shouldn't be stigma I mean the fact that it has helped stigma in a way is sad that it
took something like this but I think it has people having a brain disease calling schizophrenia
brain disease I mean all over and calling substance abuse if you believe it's a brain disease
but people call it a brain disease partly to try to reduce the stigma so this angle to
split the besides the fact we're trying to look for answers is actually I think had an
improvement with respect to the place of psychiatry and medicine and also the place of patients
with mental disorders within the myths of medical history that's the rhetoric of neuroscience
yes exactly no no but that's a part of the plan of all this money was well if it achieved
nothing but that then it would have been well spent as much as I think it's my thing
the problem the downside of that though is that the patients expectations of what we
can do for them are sky high you know that they they sit there and wait for us to fix
their brain disease while they don't want to put any I have too much serotonin I read about
that which can give you a drug to reduce that and I'll feel better right right and so the
expectations are very high our drugs are okay we our therapies are good but people have to
put effort into it right I think these happen really outside of the neuroscience for example
if it's infectious diseases going back hundreds of years and then figure figure out if it's
a cleaner environment probably can avoid something we need a little microbiome or microbiome
or microorganisms but I think eventually when this boxers discovered cloned the gene structure
understood then we know the target we can design antibiotics more precisely not just by by
lock like not that is silly most certainly a lot but now everything is designed or age
would have not been treated the way unless you know we had the virus we had the structure
we have the genome and actually the drugs which are double up that are targeting a particular
gene so I think we are just a few hundred years maybe behind psychiatry but basically
a history tells me that yes this is the typical curve their accidental and then for just findings
and we use it because that's the only way we have maybe they are not even useful to
them of further drugs like in a certain in blockers so that we couldn't go further behind
that so we need some other information to build another way and be just not there yet
but I think we have to just patient and I don't know we will be see that time but it
just have to be this is the normal course I think every since and I said I mean first
of all as I always say I agree with you Bob is that and I think it's sort of sort of
reflected by the fact that the the Cornell resident's psychiatry residents really have
to know nothing about the brain in order to be an outstanding resident that the training
itself does not require us to even know the mechanism of action of any of the drugs that
they're given because we actually don't know for example even how this year maybe it's
not a good each them medical school it's not taken very seriously but will you say the
way forward is if instead of putting our X percent GDP into neuroscience research how
do you construct moving the field of psychiatry which is to help these people that are that
are leaving very difficult lives and you but more proportion for example in prison and
how do we help these with that psychiatrist and possibly difficult but very important
question and I'll translate it pragmatically how should the nation devote its resources
for toward the issues of mental illness and we're doing it wrong we're spending too much
money in tertiary care for people with serious mental illnesses not enough money in preventive
medicine even where we know certain things that would make a difference and would work
we certainly would do much more for the next x years 50 hundred of the populations psychiatric
problems if we put more money into early child development mentoring experiences at a facility
then in tertiary care strategies for the persistent and chronic mentally ill that are biologic
in nature we know that the pattern of drug use in this country has more to do with physicians
needing to placate dissatisfied and angry patients rather than with knowledge about the impact
of the drugs on their behavior or their brain but we know that the skillful physicians know
that can reduce the patients dissatisfaction with the treatment by writing a description
and more expensive the medicine better the effect of the pharmaceutical and this is triggered
out of walls and we're going along with it but it's very hard to revise the system so
the goal is total public health rather than satisfying individual consumers and current
health delivery system has as its output satisfying consumers rather than the health
of the nation that's a public health disaster which is supported politically that's not
really psychiatry but it has a lot more to do with mental health in the next hundred
years than neuroscience.
The only thing I would say that is we've already put an x number of billions or millions
hundreds of millions of dollars in these sort of early intervention studies public health
efforts such as Head Start and I've not yet seen any data that that is it's just that
we have not put enough or is it that it's not clear to me that we're making we're moving
the needle even with the programs we have now or is it that the needle is just a part
to move?
Well I'm not sure Head Start's the answer Francis but for example you know the study
of sure better than I do that the children of depressed mothers who are depressed during
pregnancy and in the postpartum period have been mental health outcomes.
We know how to treat depression better than most things we know how to treat including
depressed pregnant women and depressed women postpartum but we don't deliver that treatment
effectively to lots of populations.
We would have more public health mental health benefit by organizing a more effective intervention
to assure the mental health of pregnant and postpartum women.
Then almost anything else we get for our dollar and mental health.
I think the neuroscience is fascinating.
I believe we should invest in it but I think that there's a there's a image probably
wrong.
I think we sell it with the implication that it's going to make a difference soon and
I don't think that's true.
On the other hand if we tell the truth we're going to lose resources so people act rationally.
The way you get the largest grant and the greatest congressional appropriation is to
suggest not that the connect homes are fascinating but they may lead to a cure for Alzheimer's
disease possibly Thursday.
You can't imagine anyone not using that strategy because we do have data that that strategy
works.
Well the trade-off there is a fixed amount of money available for research and we've
seen it NIH the amount of research that's going into treatment development.
If all got shunted over into this neuroscience thing.
If we had unlimited money we can do neuroscience and we can do this but it doesn't work that
way.
We are we or somebody is getting the money or certain portions of psychiatry and neuroscience
are getting the money but the patients I think the treatment research is really dried up.
A lot of it is going to form a sort of depending on pharmaceutical companies and they have
unfortunately their motives aren't always aligned with ours so it's a real problem.
That's right this is the way you sell money from the government but unfortunately by diluting
the government into these promises we get don't get good results for the research and
we're really depriving the use of the money elsewhere.
Again I don't know what the solution is but I think that's a problem with the success
of getting money for neuroscience.
What is in the hope that the research is going to give you the tools?
Oh no that's right but I think it's Bob was implying that's not happening.
Well the fact that's not happening Bob said it's not happening soon but what does that
mean?
It's not happening tomorrow it's not happening in 20 years it's not happening in 50 years.
But maybe never is the problem.
The one thing that's been very clear is everybody said the more we study it the more difficult
it gets.
That's the you know years ago this neuroscience thing see oh all we have to do is sequence
the genome all we have to do is this all we have to do is that and every time we do that
we're just waiting for that one is not a single biological test in psychiatry for diagnosis.
One thing I remember when I was working with Alan Francis of the DSM 4 we wrote this guide
book and we put a set to the guide book it was in the Alzheimer's section and we were
saying that we're very confident in the next five years by the time this book is out we're
going to be a biological test for Alzheimer's and boy was that all I'd still offer it 30-
25 years later and we're still you you speak to the Alzheimer's people they said oh another
five year or years to get that right but there's this elusiveness to actually turning these
into now it's not clear what you do about that you don't want to say well let's just
give up and stop doing it but there is this problem with putting money in a direction
that has proven to be very very complicated at what point again if we had an element of
money I'd say well let's keep pursuing that but it's coming at the cost of resources being
spent on research for better delivery of treatment you just mentioned the thing with the delivery
of the treatment you know how to treat depression in pregnant women but there's a delivery problem
I mean putting all our money into figuring how to solve those problems would probably
get better short-term results but that's much harder to sell let's spend money on delivery
of care when I was in medical school in a pathology lab one of the professors would
walk around the lab while we were looking at microscopes of cancer cells cancer tissue while
he was smoking and so we as medical students told him you know you are a professor of pathology
we are looking at cancer there's a connection between lung cancer and smoking where are you
smoking he said cancer is cured in ten years I'm talking about the six days so but that doesn't
mean that the research in cancer has not borne a lot of fruit so that today with immunotherapy
targeted therapy and so on we are so much further than when I was a medical student so
why wouldn't the same thing happen and you're right the parallels there of course right
that it's going to be cured in ten years the hubs all over medicine they've actually made
a lot more progress like the precision medicine is a good example that entire field and all
that you know when you apply that to psychiatry we are so far away whatever precision but
it's discussed it's always cancer I mean that is has been the area of medicine with
I guess you could argue infectious diseases always precision medicine but cancer is a
great example and they have made I mean you could argue that all that money spent on cancer
which is by the way historically much much more orders of magnitude more than was spent
in mental health but you're right that's finally beginning to pay off and part of it I think
however complicated the cancer story is it is more tractable than I think the psychiatry
story because the of all the it's just it's just so much more complex the brain then I
think that we always assume the cancer thing would be that hard because it looks like it
should be simple that's turned out to be extremely complex or there's just a parallel there
it looks doable then we see it's not and you put a lot of money in it and finally we're
getting some results and that would be the argument let's just do it in our field and
the same thing will happen and it's possible but I think the only downside of that is there's
a limited pie of money and what's not being spent on by pursuing this goal but just as
follow up with me closest as and what you're saying it probably means that we will probably
have to spend as much money as we do in cancer which is probably ten times as much as being
spent on all brain disorders so it's not surprising we've not moved the needle at this
point in effect and that it took cancer maybe a better analogy is to think that we're about
thirty years behind cancer that might be the best way to think about it at this point
you know and that but that in order to get to work cancer is we're going to have to
put more money in and I would not be as provocative as Bob I would actually say that the money
that was spent on sort of fundamental neuroscience or fundamental biology is probably the best
money spent because we really don't know the brain that well we think we do if you think
about how why we move so quickly in terms of tackling HIV to a sort of a chronic disease
is because of the fundamental biology of understanding how viruses replicate you know and so just
basically emphasizing that neuroscience is not necessarily just linked to side cafe but
we have to talk about neurology and then many other basically this money first of all is
not a big amount from the basic science perspective to be honest compared to the cancer is like
there would be not but but basically so this money is really not only understanding disease
but also understanding how the brain functions which has different implications in the computer
science or a society of problems or behavioral things which is nothing to do with an exact
disease necessarily but still how we interpret each other social behavior wars and peace
and a lot of implications so I think in fact I think there's no portion of the so would
be a continuous and freshly spent on directly disease related and it's not a lot of money
unfortunately and there's a lot of competition for this money that's I totally understand
that it's not enough other field but I think it's not whether you put left or right the
money just has to be conceptually different thinking of the governmental level for the
city level so it's just a thinking but what we have not enough money going there I totally
agree but it's not a problem the social basic science budget because it has to fight for
no reason I pretty much agree with what's been said I would add something and suggest
a possible inference one is I'm a strong advocate of basic research neuroscience is basic research
like molecular biology or genetics the yield on that is greater than any other research
we do but it has woefully little to do with psychiatry that's all I'm not arguing it's
not interesting not relevant not helpful not practical it just isn't particularly related
to psychiatry it's major relationship to psychiatry is the rhetoric of social funding
you can't get somebody who's in control of a foundation to give you a hundred million
dollars for connect dome study but you can for Alzheimer's study and therefore it requires
someone who knows how to write the paragraph that starts with the statistics about Alzheimer's
and ends with something there and ends with something about connect domes the other thing
is that there is a sort of public image which makes perfect sense that we have these huge
problems we have heart disease we have cancer we have mental illness and neurologic disease
but it doesn't work that way from a biology point of view the brain is more complicated
than the rest of the body put together the brain diseases are more challenging in terms
of their understanding and treatment than all the other diseases we ever think of or
treat that they're helped me we have basic scientists and I want help about 40% of all
the genes go to the brain how much is it expressed probably 60 60% that's a measure of something
or other but how do you express that's the question of course but just the magnitude
is relevant in that we're dealing with what the maker thought was half of his problem
and we know that anyone who ever went to medical school knows that you can slice all the other
organs and then most biomedical research when I was involved in laboratory work started
by slicing an organ and putting it in the wearing blender but you can't do that with
the brain doesn't work that way so the fact that the brain is more than everything else
in terms of the complexity of its problem is an important proviso so certainly we need
more basic research psychiatry deals with very difficult problems and I think Francis
is optimistic when he says 30 years that we're about 30 years behind you said that yeah
Francis and I met 30 years I think we have to recognize that there's an order of magnitude
difference in the problems we face when we talk about the future of cardiology or oncology
or orthopedics or ophthalmology on the one hand and the future of psychiatry on the other
one of the startling things we're going to face in the future of psychiatry is that most
of the people will be treating 50 years from now we don't think of as being patients now
because we haven't conceptualized how we can make a difference in their lives but the
history of the last 50 years in psychiatry is we move from Ed's to major diseases schizophrenia
and bipolar disease to recognize the huge pools of people out there who have personality
disorders who have addictions who have problems in living that we're never thought of as
medical or psychiatric but can be helped by interventions even at the food level we're
at now I don't think we're going to see that growth of patients with cancer or heart disease
or any other disease category but we are with mental health diseases but if I can't just
go back to this cancer example I remember because Memorial Camp so cancer is just next
door and we have a lot of collaborations so they were stuck with cancer like 20, 25 years
ago they have been developing new drugs which are a little bit different than the previous
one they certainly got a little increase but it's not tremendous movement and then suddenly
there was a part of shift with this in therapy which was mentioned and nobody knew that it's
coming nobody just came out from the dark and then obviously people have been working
on it but suddenly there was a critical mass or critical finding the mass of critical findings
which were translatable to humans in amounts one could do that well before but it had to
be developed a technology where you could actually use it in humans and humans would tolerate
this and I think in cancer research will tell you that there was a part of our shift because
now I thought only personally but the the the curate is incredible it's very expensive but
I think it's just you never know when it happens it can happen in next year and it can be
in 50 years so but I'm just waiting for such a part of our shift which we don't really
know as they didn't know that this will pan out because they are trying different things
from bone marrow transplantation to different things but this for some reason became practical
feasible in humans and actually this is but was it because of a I don't know it so well
but is it because there were some basic meat made in immunology that made this happen?
I'm not familiar I'm just hearing from them that this was just suddenly a change labs
which switch to this kind of strategy they're far better and now we have these people who
have been not not a spandex they suddenly a deeper of their throat basically they they
have no chance they just come back this is what people need in psychology that somebody
would be treatment treatment to just ask if a phoenix which is a really serious or an
orthopedic side and then suddenly you have a treatment which we just cannot be comprehended
today we should all study immunology at this point we have to return to study immunology
that are important constraints for example the reason why they made the part of the reason
why they made the progress immunology and so on is the ability to study cancer cells
out there it's not that easy to study schizophrenia cells so cancer allowed you to study things
in a completely different way from different angles and even now the treatment comes in
from different.
Well the lack of an animal model for schizophrenia I mean animal models for cancer have always
been around it's a huge barrier I mean theoretically if there was an ant that could be a breakthrough
some really amazing animal model for some of these illnesses came up that could be opened
the door for a lot.
I would say though that I think it might have been basic understanding of immunology because
that actually also now we have drugs for MS multiple sclerosis that we didn't have and
they're also in the immunotherapy realm also where they target the T cells so it turns
out even if even neurologists just got lucky that it turns out that these advances that
the drugs that they were making to basically make T cells quiescent are actually very
effective for MS which and even and they didn't so I think this will and it's still a chronic
disorder which was there's but they had nothing a decade ago you know the fact that they have
four to three to four new drugs in the pipeline is still quite impressive so I think we were
waiting for that moment also.
So in terms of research where is the research in psychiatry in terms of those major illnesses
I mentioned where is that research focused on?
I think the genetics I would say most of the money right now is in genetics connectome these
are the brain initiatives essentially in your imaging and then there's this continuum.
A lot of money goes to epigenetic which is my epigenetic.
But epigenetics I think just to mention for the audiences that basically what most people
realize that genes do not solve the problem and we know that environment cannot work through
genes so the concept came in that environment will actually produce some change in the DNA
structure or the DNA function without changing a base pair so the sequence is the same but
there are secondary modifications but if you view it from a function of perspective it
doesn't really matter whether you have a mutation and it alters a gene function or
you have a we call chromatin which is the larger assemble of DNA and surrounding proteins
you can have that same functional change as a result of.
So what we many people I know because it's pretty competitive know what is to write a
grant but basically the chromatin is that you propose that environment whether this is
early childhood adversity whether maybe it's a during pregnancy maybe the mother is depressed
but there is something memory built into the child or a field DNA which is again not a
change of the sequence but it's a permanent so the child will work with born with this
it's a regulatory problem like a mutation would be and it ended up with a little bit
different function at the gene level which is translated to a circuit level and then
functional level one the child is less than typical even when his connection is made so
I think that a lot of money goes into this which is fundamental is a very good concept
and very new because we don't really know this we call this areas as a and want to sensitive
areas maybe or we can call it marks or whatever you want to call but we don't really understand
those but even outside of neuroscience epigenetics is also cancer cancer it's actually cancer
is a more more developed phase again so we learn a lot from cancers but some of the cancer
findings cannot be translated because the genes which are regulated are totally different
and cancer you would have that how fast it's as proliferate or divide grow and in a sense
more important how maybe a synaptic function is a little tailored so it's a little bit
different and it's just several order of money to the more complex that's the problem
the complexity but you pointed out which means that it takes more time but just to sort of
simplify your work make less but what you've found in your own lab is that that this the
level of stress of the mother the grandmother or the great grandfather or whatever all have
impacts on the infant so we can trace down on the granddaughters I'm talking about animals
here but there are some human studies but the granddaughters will carry the memory of
a grandparent either you can have like stress infection or even early childhood adversity
which is very relevant to psychiatry so so we can actually tell from the granddaughters
DNA that the grandmother had some impact so that would be very useful to let's say you
have a child and you are not sure whether the child will be more you see some sign maybe
I'm not clinician but I can imagine that you have a child and you are not really sure
whether the risk is very high or no but you see some signs you could go back and then
test whether that child actually had some impact through some ancestor's life and you
would say yes I see some impact so I would be more careful and maybe treat that particular
individual and you can actually sample the epigenome not by having to get a brain biopsy
but yeah we are doing from the blood actually from below we don't have to take cuter models
so we just take a little blood and we can because the blood also responds to this and
there is a correlation between the blood response to the brain response these are not so it's
my talking of memory the memory in this case you cannot say this is how precise like an
episode would be in our life or as room or remembering this environment it's really just
the adversity component it's a negative balance of this whole situation which is really somehow
alters certain genes which will be a genetic fingerprint so it's not a memory we like to
use memory because everybody understands memory but it's a lose memory so you will not just
remember you will not remember that the adversity occurred in A or B or C environment but you
know that was some really bad experience it's not post-Trump Express's order where somebody
can recall the exact location and going back to the same restaurant or a same battlefield
it will have a reaction it is more of a general anxiety that in general the anxiety level
is really high almost sometimes you don't even know why because the person doesn't have
to have an input it's already built in the DNA chromatin or epigenome which was somehow
predated maybe not even in the individual's life but in the ancestor's life so your mechanism
is is beautiful and articulate and very sophisticated but that that that basic understanding that
a person is affected by the the their ancestry psychiatrists have been saying for 150 years
that's not new right so so the thing that worries me of course is that exact thinking
is what got us to eugenics this idea that the best thing to do would be just eliminate
those genes eliminate those people eliminate those races you know and with the obvious
conclusion and what happened in Germany and so and the thing is that the scary part of
those kinds of interventions is they they start off well intended and in the United
States so it wasn't just you know these crazy folks in another country so again the question
is so all right so you found this then what but yeah but but just expanding so what you
would say that is known it was totally anecdotal there was no scientific evidence for that
and in science you never believe so at least in basic science you never take it really
true until you actually prove mechanistically so our standards are really mechanistic but
for the standards of the time I mean but they looked at pedigrees they gathered data they
interviewed families I mean for the standards of the time they do exactly the same thing
yeah but yes so that was certainly a such an association we got association and now from
scientific point of view you want to have the association to cause a relationship because
if this association you cannot do anything about it because if two things can be associated
and you influence one thing it doesn't feel like tonana things but my point is though
for the standards of the for the scientific standards of the of the time 150 years ago
that was true absolutely that was the true it wasn't I mean they believed that was causal
now you're saying this is true and so I'm I wouldn't doubt that your science is more
sophisticated question is 150 years from now is somebody going to look back and say well
you know your science was all very nice but so and that's the that's the kind of but
but a big difference is when you have a causative relationship then you have a chance to actually
manipulate the system if an association then basically the two things are independent
from each other it's a coincidental so you don't have the two you don't have the opportunity
or a chance to actually influence your outcome with something which is correlated with so
that's a difference but they thought they did I mean they thought they did but it's
it's wrong the law of things I mean science we don't know that we don't know that our
that our crude treatments because they're crude you know would match the sensitivity
of that kind of science the treatment even in a SSRI sorry that's not really causative
we don't want causative because it's a association so causative when you have an absolute known
player molecule pathway which is linked to and then you manipulate the pathway and then
then you fix the outcome so that's what we need for develop new drugs or any conditions
where it is being shown specific epigenetic change is responsible for it so this is a
this is this is another problem so there's not one single gene or single logos but and
then we don't have a manipulation very multiple so that's very difficult to make the but I
think that that's actually one way to think about it to figure out a way to work with
multiple genes but I remember when I was school manipulating one gene was a total order nobody's
that student field starting the lab and in my month the person can change that gene or
single gene we can manipulate me three genes and if you asked these people this would be
just a single cell and a lot of same cell they can manipulate thousands at the same
time what we would need is that to manipulate hundreds of genes for thousands of genes in
a complex mammalian neuron and just don't have a technology but people have been very
working but in cancer aren't they using various H stack inhibitors right now yes try to affect
the gene yes but they're not because selectivity that's also not enough they don't have it yeah
select selectivity is really important that you basically target only those nothing else
yeah and there's the the classical manipulation but we had 20 years ago develop we don't have
to have we don't have any multiple genes a lot of genes because at all marketing so but
not only the psychiatric condition of cardiovascular diabetes hypertension there's all the same
problem and they cannot really prove because they have tens of hundreds genes one person
has this combination other person that combination but we do know that this probably a lot of
genes each has a very small contribution but you still need they have different constellations
so these are all systems by which is I think system biology is another field which might
need a lot of money but again much higher level than artificial intelligence would do
nobody's which is one dimensional set fail I want to use this to segue to something that
I think is often not seen this way but the availability of our finer tools for assessing
genetic risk at the level even of an old means that we're really into a form of euthanasia
except very early so when we decide to not implant a fertilized egg that's carrying the
Huntington's gene that's just early euthanasia early eugenics biologically is the same thing
we're clearing the population of a noxis gene by selecting who will support and who will
destroy the Nazis waited a few decades afterwards before doing the same thing and we don't really
have a dialogue socially about the meaning of that in our attitude toward it we're doing
something you know way even more intriguing because the methods for doing this are available
to some social classes and not to others so we've set up a system where if you're in a
certain social class you get eugenics to get rid of bad genes and if you're in a different
class you don't and we're going to distribute the bad genes class wise in the culture that's
a very interesting psychiatric I don't know if it's a psychiatric issue maybe I think much
of what our effective interventions might be in the next few decades maybe at the pre-implantation
level of eugenics we can possibly get rid of some major psychiatric disorders if we have
enough community acceptance of screening and selective implantation of fertilized of them
that don't carry those disorders the thing that is I mean apart from the larger ethical
issues of which there are many the other thing that strikes me is if we're trying to help
say schizophrenia for focusing on schizophrenia where if we're trying to convince our patients
who have schizophrenia that they have lives worth living that that that disease is not
going to define them that they can live full lives that they have worth as a human and
then at the same time we say that we're going to try to eliminate the genetic risk for that
you know what does that say you know we care about you but actually we wish you hadn't
been born I mean that and that you know we're not at a stage where we really have to wrestle
with that other than as a thought experiment but that's we're close to it well depending
on who yeah depending on who you talk to you know so just yeah totally agree and I guess
we are just for accidentally open NIH and that's national super health that there's a whole
branch trying to really address this question very relevant but I recall another effort
from NIH which is more of a repairing the gene or genes so there are a lot of money goes
into our field which is basically say this is a situation and it's a chart is born but
can be really reestablished in normal regulation or whatever situation and now just a couple
of weeks to people of you know the new technology where you can actually get in to sell again
it's just a cell level we don't have the brain level but some yeah now some can do it
and a single gene and you can actually repair it you can eliminate the physical or or or
molecule problem and basically you it's very similar to to repairing an enzyme defect for
example with a virus where you would have a child with an enzyme defect and it's pretty
technically speaking is relatively simple because it's just an enzyme which is everywhere
so you make make a white blood cell and this white blood cell be produced now and you exchange
the deficient cells to their new the gene therapy so that's a similar concept except
that you go to the brain cell or brain region and then you basically re-establish the normal
situation it's it's a fiction and it's just laboratory things but it's certainly in the lab it's in
a one-genent can be done and it's just five years ago that was the first of four years ago so there
are new things happening yeah and we just need a larger I'm not only new things but we need a
scale up from one it's always with one gene and then we have to have hundred genes simultaneously so
it's going a little slow obviously well some degree of the repair of genes the technology is there now
it's not only a mutation can repair you can reap this so-called epigenetic what I refer which is
you know which is more complex you can repair that as well but the issue is in terms of mental
illness is to first determine what genes we have talked about sugar yeah 100 dreams a small fact
you can't be fixing those genes it's not going to make any difference but the whole idea is science
that you have these hundreds of tracks of research and some people working with it and suddenly
everything is just converge and that's the hope so they scale up the technology that they bring
and we don't have access to the brain so we need new technology to get to the brain so when
everything converges maybe a hundred years from now then then this is this is where you say maybe
that was a birth to invest this money but otherwise we wouldn't be there and that's the hope but I
think that was a hope in care sir the thing is though that our we do need to help our patients now
and you know sure it isn't sexy but there is a lot in systems of care that we in psychiatry
used to do a lot with the whole asylum movement the whole beginning of the the profession of
psychiatry in the United States was based on systems of care this idea that we build the
silums to take care of people to restore them to sanity and and so we have similar problems to
what Dorothy the Dix was complaining about a hundred and seventy years ago we have people in the jails
people in the streets people who are suffering who don't have family looking after them and in
Michigan we are reinventing the idea that we need to take a look at state hospitals our
Republican governors over succeeding decades closed most of our state hospitals and now all
of a sudden we have to have a conversation about maybe reopening some reopening new new kinds of
new systems of care and working on ways of taking care of people because gene therapy isn't
available in our lifetime and it's hard to talk about that it's hard to say we need bricks and
mortar we don't just need two different things so we have to talk about yeah I mean I'm not saying
that you know the money should come from there I mean this is more a political issue actually what
you're saying but for the patient the next 20 years neuroscience is probably not going to
touch the problem at the social it's like you know probably be with all the astrophysics is
not necessarily in our lifetime but we still pay or fund astrophysics or going to move or
probably we won't be there in the next few years but still in some respects that's how humanity
and then technology develops just to segue into something that might be a little more positive so
even though I think that neuroscience is going to take 20 years there are certain things that and
it just happens by Kirk Winston it's happening in my department but I put it in a Cornell we have
figured one of the investigators at Cornell who's a psychiatrist has figured it out a way to use
neuroimaging to subtype depression into four categories by the connectome and he is able to
do it granted it's only one study of 1200 patients but he's able to basically get to do it with 90%
specificity and sensitivity so he has the shot of actually possibly getting the first biomarker
for a psychiatric disorder what subtypes where did the subtypes come from so what he did was he
got 600 patients with major depression and then and for so of control made match controls got
their resting state scans which I described theirs and basically through machine learning
slash artificial intelligence asked the computer to tell them is there do these people fall into
different subtypes do the brain connectomes look different from the controls and then the computer
gave what they call a classifier sort of like yes here's a template where this this is the template
for depression number one two three four then he took another set of samples of of 300 new people
with depression or not depression or schizophrenia and this classifier could separate out people with
schizophrenia versus depression with a hundred ninety nine percent precision and so so these are
these are different subtypes and I'm just doesn't have no they're not phonological subs no these were
the computer was not taught DSM so the computer was agnostic to it it was just looking at it essentially
and each subtype has a slightly different abnormality in connectivity with the prefrontal cortex or
first of all he can he confirmed that the prefrontal cortex is probably very important for major
depression and they all have slightly different what they don't look different clinically is the
point right I guess that was they really don't look that different clinically miraculously
subtypes actually fall into anhedonic anxious they actually do really amazingly do and it was not
taught the computer was not taught this and so that felt that's life yeah so that essentially
they naturally which makes sense that if you're anhedonic then the hub that's involved in the reward
circuitry is probably going to be the one that's broken while the one that's that where you're sort
of more anxious is going to be probably more prefrontal cortical because of the anxiety
circuits related there so it fell out naturally and now we're going but what is so remarkable is
that so there's another form of treatment called trans-magnetics stimulation which is
which we had wild enthusiasm ten years ago but has shown to be only effective for 40%
than mild for mild to moderate depression what he found was was that only one subtype responded
optimally to TMS so now the new clinical trial he's running is to do a that was a retrospective
study that he did now he's doing a prospective study to see whether or not he can subtype them
ahead of time then give them TMS and basically see whether or not that this is actually going
to hold up but you can sort of now see how you can use this not obviously we say psychiatrists
and psychologists and social workers we can diagnose pretty well but what this can tell you is is
that what he noticed was was that after the people who responded to TMS their connect home
changed to normal so basically you now have not only a diagnostic tool but something that could
probably tell you whether or not the treatments you've had will possibly effective or not effective
in changing at least one sort of non at least some objective measure and stuff but the future
would be at least only in Cornell the media other than you would get your brain scanned
in the outpatient clinic if you come in for depression and then basically then then different
treatments would be tailored to that it sounds very but human one brain scan will tell you this
yes so basically because he got the computer to come up with what they call it a computational
classifier so then the classifier will then sort of sort it out and just say this you fit into
biotype one two three or four and and so then and and if you put in someone who has schizophrenia
they go you don't fit into any of these biotypes you know you do not you're not depressed so he's
now trying to develop the schizophrenic biotype and the bipolar disorder biotype but for now he
started with depression so but you but the reason why this was possible was because so many people
country and and we're doing resting state scans so he didn't have to scan 1200 people he got people's
data from 1200 people from 1200 subjects from and then just use the computer to basically do
the analysis I think this is probably what's going to happen and that's why it's still important to
do all these studies because who knew that this 10 minute resting state scan was going to be so
important for this type of work I think you know and some ideas that we could be basically be able
to tailor things but it is really quite remarkable even to me it's hard to wrap my mind around the
fact that the brains has an intrinsic connectivity that can be picked up in 10 minutes it's an
fire an MRI machine essentially that's been around for 50 years essentially technology was always
there you know what he only what he did is he used just like he just put the pieces together
and he was able to do it so but replicates psychiatry is full of 50 years of starting to
DSTF tests that look like they're going to be great so two replications are now being written up
for the replication spittifier type things so people from other universities not us really that's
for depression not for any other depression that'd be pretty damn good if you have that
yeah we're very we'll see what happens but what's really nice is is that and and I the thing that
I got from it was then we've we've we've also begun or he and begun doing
anxiety disorders because that's the disorder and the people with anxiety disorders fall into
that but again as office the brain did not read DSM and truly gonna be these gonna
and they're not the sort of
problems are probably going to be very different for each
sorry I can assure you that I hope it replicates too but that's enough the mystic notes so we can
stop the open if you have a question you want
to
have
facts and look at various fields of science over the years and how many years it took for
half the things before the truth to be no more true so I'm wondering if you should
you how many years will take care for what you think is true now if you're not true yeah I'm not
gonna predict the future but I will tell you a funny story about yeah I found a book that was written
from the American College of Pharmacology
and in I think 1965 they wrote this book called
Psychopharmacology in the year 2000 where they were predicting it's gonna
and they were
drugs that people have
helping them
work happy and help them that weren't happy that because we weren't going to solve the food problems but
velocity was the answer to everything was gonna cure outcome it was gonna cure
and then two years after this book was
in the United
take long
right well what I was gonna say we're back we're back to hallucinogens now we're back to
we're not getting it have they not banned it maybe over the 30 years we'd actually have
to
that was a big mistake
that's going to be true and not true yeah like that
that's the way paper that you can laugh at when it's
it's
funny the other you know
your head of nature he was writing a paper by the RDoC project the people so RDoC project was
an attempt to toss out the DSM approach on immunology and
the tree base the idea is we're going to discover the the circuits of the brain
and then we're going to build up you know this huge
uh all these studies we're going to explore treatments went out in the limit said in 15 years
will happen it was so off and the thing to me is the full
it's predicting something in 15 years because those are
these are all you can't ever so you're right I mean assume a lot of what we now is going to be
thank you doctor Lee the end you mentioned a lot of
two different
in a rest brain from a typical brain look these are in huge these are in patients
patients um and it's made me wonder what what is a healthy brain
someone that doesn't meet any criteria for any DSM disorder but are there people who don't
know
you know it's sort of a circular argument but so I think what I think we don't have a really good
idea of what brain is it's just what we call a brain so a brain
besting codified as we have an idea of what the healthy mind is
that the analyst to figure that out
thank you for the
my question is with some question about which way the funding should go
what will be um the field what's the
patients and patients
what goals and what values should guide institution uh what values should
guide medicine and administration what's the future of pakari grants
no questions
so
so pakari grants are supposed to be so there's been a
whatever various new things then we'll
to the community
that seem to look what really
center but they're too complicated or something to be implemented and so
the
supposed to be something where you take a treatment and
grant is to actually dominate it's for example I think the types of
grant
really
into behavioral therapy that has been validated
institution can you
to the queen's the queen's clinic and have trained the people there
and then rally around
lots of money isn't being poured into these human
how
are
sorry
treatments
we would have to say uh that the bigger question is is that we actually
don't just to sort of segue we actually don't have the workforce
liver met to the treatment percent of 20 percent of our population
how that workforce sure I'm not actually sure I would say that
no I think what
the rationale for the
grants has been mainly due to other treatment
more sophisticated behavioral treatments have been able to be implemented
and but it's probably because they don't have enough providers that can
deliver it somewhat
I think
to pick up a thread that two threads of Dr. Mike
one of them about about prevention and the allocation
uh
about being
going to I'm going to echo that also
uh given how we started off with the um
progress with the genetic research
um
given that we spent most of the time talking about that
that this means
so what what does that mean so I will offer a an interpretation
considering where we are
and that and that and that there's an enormous cultural almost delusion of the
Nile of um of the source of most
technology which which Dr. Michael's mentioned which has something to do with
early development early development early attachment traumatic uh dramatic
abandonment early childhood even even we know data from moving to another country
the the the
and mental illness and yet there's no money um
being provided for that kind of research so I suggest we take all of the money
and
for
my
then we may
as far as
um so now
wasn't being brought
just
the second
the
neuroscience research
uh
I think you mentioned
expectation
the
to get back
that's random
in
I think
part of the
is getting rid of stigma I think we're getting rid of stigma okay
this is if they were broken brains we we've just added another type
of
a person
then he did at case conferences okay
the conferences had less details about
interests are
that is a strong
information
which is a war farm kind of far farm a go genetic testing and getting history
several comments
um our call for uh I'll start with the last one I think the psychological psychodynamic
broadly in favor of talking to patients listening to them and getting to know them
in fine texture and detail which you feel a member of I suspect from what you said I think
that community has failed to demonstrate value added from the information it collects
for the majority of psychiatric patients so although we may not like it the fact is that
if you want to be cost effective the first thing you do is make a dss
then use the standard treatment for that diagnosis and wait eight weeks a third of your
patients will be better and there's no point in finding out how they felt about their mother
it's irrelevant to the outcome of the intervention if your focus is on the outcome of the intervention
you'd focus your subtle nuanced history taking and relationship development on the group of
patients who need it and might profit from it but the community doesn't like doing that
and it has an almost ethical quality it's un it's not humanistic no orthopedic surgeon
worries about being humanistic before setting a colleagues fracture but psychiatrists do sometimes
or conversely they don't because they're tired of those that do and they're arguing with them
so your dss diagnosis begin to in many psychiatrists hands substitute the person is sitting next to
you on the bus it's an unsolved problem it's a major problem in psychiatric education so that
if you travel around the country and you make rounds and things like that you find a fair
number of young psychiatrists are very happy if they can document a dssm5 diagnostic
uh conclusion even if they're not the biggest idea who it is they're talking about
on the other hand the the research problem not resolved is when does it make a difference
and very importantly when does it not make a difference
even more provocative i think the lack of engagement
in the future of the proper diagnosis sometimes people being in analysis i don't know about
even doing it properly sometimes well what i would agree with it i think too often i think
you can't do uh not i you know i i created a structured interview for research and i see people
do horrible jobs because they don't ask the right you know get below the surface i mean it's not a
checklist and nobody who's ever worked on the dssm has ever claimed otherwise however because
it looks so simple people there's a human nature here to do the simple quick thing and the dssm you
could argue is one of the worst things that happened because it's a left psychiatrist to do what our
colleagues and the rest of medicines it was just trying to do the quicker thing like getting a
bunch of blood tests and not talking to the patient so it's facilitated that it's had a plus i think
it's treatment and people have responded better but there's a huge cost and i agree about the
psychiatric education it's up to psychiatric education to to go against that tendency for people to
want a cookbook approach and tell them over and over again that is you're not going to get good
results now unfortunately it'd be nice if there were studies that could actually show for sure
check actually in uh alpham it's hard for me to believe that you're right it'd be
somebody could do some kind of god people who
got my gift with the out the
what why do you don't
who's going to fund that you're right i'd be great things to do
there's also an idiotic in the profession
you're patient in depth that it's almost
a virtue rather than efficiency or efficacy right and that's a weak argument in a competitive world
no you're right you see how we've gotten where we are and i'd be great if we can undo that with
data if you had thought like the head of some federal finance health finance
and said well we need to do this then they would ask well just show me why we should invest
billions in this direction rather than in this direction maybe that study a series of
well we may be going backwards and having to do that retrospectively with the current generation
of kids we're raising now so we're raising an entire generation of consumers of mental health
care who think that all they have to do is sit there and somebody will do it they will do a checklist
they'll get a diagnosis they'll get a pill then
they roll in that it's something that they again are it's our failure to treat rather than their
failure to engage so i just had a patient in the hospital a 19 year old student and we get a lot
of university students that umm on the inpatient unit and she she had depression i don't know what
that means for this teenager but she'd been on every drug i could name she'd gotten ECT
she had never engaged with therapy because as far as she was concerned that was effort that she
didn't want to put into and and we were done she was still depressed she was not bothering to go to
serve and you know she needed to actually put some work in and she didn't want to hear that she
wanted the magic the magic pill or you know raising its generation of consumers of mental health care
to not take a role in their own recovery and i i worry about that
i'm pleased that we've positioned the position and we still have
to submit from the beginning the sociologic
the
my question
I that statement have any of you um been studying
abilities now there's anxiety anxiety may be identified as
a good state if it's no guided correctly
the person is facing something in society that is not right
yeah
again he is a symptom not necessarily it's a state it's not bad i mean we all know
you know if you have a test to and you don't have enough anxiety to study for you you're
gonna fail it's anxiety or adaptive parts of being human being you can't live with that exactly
perhaps even
and
deal with illness in that context but
when you have these symptoms coupled with some disability that's causing
it somehow impacts ability to function what you need
ships work you know that these symptoms are being severe enough
always been
in normal
grieving for one year after the loss of loved one every day in pre-op
they agree right with that person say it so there's always a point where you figure out when these
symptoms are when you know that's when they become educated
it's
by case basis it can be very do but it's a bullet theory
let's let's
my name is
I am interested
I have a suggestion to me and I would like to have an answer to it
David
the man who can
obsessive compulsory disorder my question
a statement here is that in the review of the book that I have Adam argues
he is in favor of a more complex
I suggest from my category I'll approach
time mental illness which the category
approach driven by the DSM thank you I'm gonna
I was the driver when the preparation the
approach the whole one of the
I don't know what was just to move it
anyone in the knows that the categorical approach is a fiction there's no hard boundary between
any you know mild depression
life
not so medicine the rest of medicine is categorical and dementia people's
a you have category so this tension between measuring and recognizing that there has to be
a point where you go from a measurement to a category
the DSM it's been people reified I think these boundaries in the book
handed down from something not the high
and and somehow they have some meaning to really shouldn't have so I've always here as a
lifelong
you know it's a thing with it so we're struggling with what happens to the
cat and how they become real
clinicians to practice because you wouldn't know
time to give medicine right now if you have five out of nine symptoms of depression
and you all the clinical trials would use that definition you could say well if my
patient version of depression the one that was in the trial I don't know their
probability of responding to this treatment is because that's what the study
should be in the
not enough for an illness
boundaries are yes that you have to that's why it says at the front of the book
but
go into training and see patients to be able to get the feel
what they are
but
is they opened the door up to continuous revisions they realized that it was
or to see years we're going to redo the whole book now they said that you know
one of the reasons they did that it's very difficult to roll it in the electronic world
the belief is you
but now there's actually a committee set up and anyone outside can make proposals now if you
make a proposal you have to have the data to back it up but
the other thing with
the system it's great in theory and you know very critical of
the
have had issues
and this
does something have it or not criteria but the dimensions are incredibly
sort of a lot of
want to put a
controlled on
here you don't but
systems that were created by a second
so we have their own professional state in all
so complicated that I can imagine anybody actually
use these factor analyses with you know 20 different domains and if you're high in this
it's like it's only on
yeah yeah
it's incredibly complex so it it's any more
real it's not
it's one set of problems
thank you
issue which
is
some serves in general
dimensional approaches
observe information
categorical approaches discard
information when you reduce multiple
dimensions and
up
willing to spend a lot of time
clinician
they have
so then you might guess
20 diagnoses and certainly not much
and there's an argument DSM is a
free purpose
it says the first sentence of the introduction
but the authors of DSM are largely not
they're largely invested in primary loyl
well
of the disorders lots of data but the
dimensions are most complex so
the committee that was supposed to solve the problem came up with the
dimensional system then the parent can
worried about it and extra committees were brought in to review it
and decide about it and we ended up with both of you lose it
if somebody was in treatment that was correlated with the dimensions
dimensions would suddenly become very very popular
yeah i agree with that
thank you
thank you very much for participating in this
it's been very good to hear everybody's
I just when you guys were referring to the
issue that as
the separation that occurred at the turn of the century
with Freud versus Josper you know
don't really
I
in the proper way I think that there was a group of people
that were mainly in psychiatrists dealing with the population
which was you know history
in the individual whereas Josper's and the German
philosophical psychiatrist were looking at people who were much
more profoundly dysfunctional they were
in
and
of
Josper's and his treaties had
the
meat
and the biological psychiatrist have seen some kind of biological basis
for
whereas
the outpatient psychiatrist predominantly were
what is that that
or that
but continued for a century
and in complete
it's pretty clear that the first
predominant
based psychiatrist
was introduced
then
it was
a
biological markers were
a silent
a patient
biggest
as if they are
you know
discipline these are
a
event and that's
one of the leading misunderstandings
because what's happened is that
you know 100 genes
about the brain is a
psychiatry from a lot of the
disciplines that deal with the brain
which is much more linear
and I mean of course they've expanded
because at one point they were
pointing out because they could find a lesion
and they thought they were all going to be
part of
which was initially known for community
and that
that represents
a hierarchical level
that has its own code so
answers
that becomes misleading it's too linear for the majority of
psychics
that are based on genetics usually it's in the
why there hasn't been more
literature that has been able to prove is because
of course linear mechanisms are much much
easier to so now we start
to understand that those people
may not know the world is
what is making them feel
when they take those
can you come to a closure because they have people waiting we have to stop
but
about online
that's why you
that's why you can't prove water
those are the most important things
that make life worth living
those are the things that are of the mind and even
the information
when he said you know it was the father of information
it's not really about information that he proved it was just
a statistic
of data
I think you made your point
Hi
as a data person myself I wanted to offer up
the results from a literature review out of the University of Colorado Denver
School of Medicine they looked
at analysis of all the published studies up until 2012
on antidepressant use versus the use of psychodynamic psychotherapy
and what they found was that the effect size
and there were 74 studies on the use of antidepressants alone was
0.3 which means about three standard deviations between the control group and the
intervention group that received antidepressants and when they
looked at studies where they had control groups versus patients that
had received psychodynamics that could be the average effect
understanding
it seems that there's something about establishing a
science or a relationship with the system on expressing feelings
things are established in the treatment patients
Cancer, or myocardial infarction, or tuberculosis, or dentistry, or dentistry, right?
We've been horrified. That's important.
There are different treatments. There are several types of psychotherapy
cognitive behavior therapies very popular. Dynamic therapy is the beloved of
dynamically oriented psychiatrists, pharmacotherapy.
All the treatments seem to have
a order of magnitude similar effect to mild to moderate depression.
One reading is that with severe depression, the pharmacotherapy
shows an advantage but even more striking, you don't even mention it,
the most effective treatment for severe depression is electroconvulsive
therapy. There's a huge amount of data on that. It's not even in your
survey. But again, more important
I think the average
range of depression is your well-depressed
cover or your main need treatment and then you get better and then you're well again.
That's not the natural history of depression. The majority of depressed
patients have a long term usually lifelong predisposition
or vulnerability to depression and they have more than one
episode and therefore an important goal of the treatment is to modify
that vulnerability and the likelihood of subsequent episodes.
We've been dramatically affected in that with bipolar disease
but that's a small amount of total depression. It's not
quite clear how effective we are
long term.
That if you continue the treatment indefinitely, it continues to work
but no patient continues treatment indefinitely.
Pathologic transfer to their therapist
so we have a problem you want me to end.
We have a problem.
A blind though is...
that the drugs are effective. Take the drugs first. In fact
the best drugs we have help about one third
of the patients who take them. That's not widely recognized.
Partly because the pharmaceutical industry doesn't
advertise it that way. They'll tell you two-thirds of the
patients who take the drugs get better which is true but
with a placebo, one-third of the
logic of efficacy, our best pharmacological treatments
affects one-third of the people who take the treatment.
The same might be true over psychotherapy in terms of
treating depression. If you look on your face you don't like that idea.
I'm trying to know the multiple studies on the use of psychothermology
versus psychotherapy for some to come blind.
As my understanding, I have not seen any literature with psychothermology
but more on the better outcomes that I've done.
I'm looking for R&D, the education program.
I'll be quick. I'm interested to know what the panelists think about the future.
Oh, for psychiatric treatment by hallucinogenics, specifically
psilocybin and chemin.
Interested to know what the state of the situation is now
and what the prognosis is.
I'm interested to know what the state of
the situation is now and what the
prognosis is for future research and
application. It's still pretty early.
I think that studies are not. So certainly the ketamine story,
ketamine is legal to give and easier to study.
As with most things, it's got a little height in the beginning but as more studies are being done
it's clearly solid evidence that people respond to ketamine
and people who are treating resistant to depression and don't respond to anything else
sometimes respond to ketamine. The problem with ketamine of course is it requires continuous
treatment. And we don't know how often we can do this.
There's a signal there that has been now established.
It takes it will be better for one week but that's about as far as we know.
As far as the rest of the psychedelics go, again there's a signal there as well.
This is a sad thing because of what happened in the 60s and the overreaction to
the misuse of psychedelics. These things have been out of the hands of
the patients for 40-50 years. Now luckily it's coming back in and the
studies are now coming in more and more. The clinical trials for all kinds of
you know, originally cancer patients who were terminal because
only people who could be given the meds, they were allowed and they got very good results
and it's now they're trying for more and more application than the
future of psychedelic treatment is
very promising. But the problem is we don't want to start telling people they should go
and buy mushrooms on the street and start taking it because there's so much that's
unknown dosing and these things have bad effects even the studies
that you still aside in there are certain things that are complicated.
What is the placebo?
That's a problem because you're right. People know I think I have
something that has effects.
I think we'll stop after this.
There were two areas that were brought up. One was between medicine and psychiatry
you know somatic medicine doctors and psychiatrists
and the other congress was this between
medicine and psychiatry.
The other book was from my generation the way that patients is better
than the other patients.
But it seems to me that there's kind of been an irony in the course of my
career as a psychiatrist where I watched medicine people
very interested in narrative. So now with Columbia you can get a master's degree in
medicine and the medical school courses.
That's psychiatry.
We have to be abdicated with great skills in the sense and it's funny to me
that we're not the ones teaching narrative medicine to the generation of
medical students.
Almost universal myth
that's untrue and is interesting.
Of course it was not a psychiatrist. Freud was a neurologist
who treated patients who ended up with
the rest of the story. But the psychiatry
grows out of general medicine. Neurology
wasn't a specialty. Freud was seeing his patient
outpatient with physical symptoms.
The history
of the sciences into its moving away
from medicine and away from psychiatry.
But in fact, my view on the
political interview skills and patient recognition are most
with not
with collided patients.
Who are supposed to learn the
or used to be supposed to learn these things. Although the inpatient seriously
mentally on population.
Skittling or disease.
Are probably the least
people
and people. They're much more important.
Physically ill
or
not mentally ill
but they
are
all stuff on an inpatient.
Deafs, you know.
Hospital.
He's not taking his meds anymore
after him.
So there's a
story. And it's funny at University of Michigan
reinvented a medical humanities program.
Because we say, yeah,
our stuff, we need to
do the same thing.
I'm gonna
and I'm gonna afford your medical student applying for psychiatry.
So very interesting to talk. And I really thank you all for being here today.
And when I visited the future and understanding all the neuroscience we're talking about
immunology and more target therapies, nanobots, hallucinogens,
all the neuro stimulation. Before I'm hearing from
this is the future of psychiatry. It sounds more like reallocating resources, delivering care.
Is my future of psychiatrists, are we going to see more of the acceleration of kind of the fancy new therapies,
modalities? Or should we really be advocating for spending money where it's going to be
both impactful things like housing or the early challenge
of vengeance?
I'll take a shot at this. So in five years after you finish your residency,
you will only see the most ill patients.
And then at some point, so that most of the other mild
to moderate will hopefully be taken care of by primary care or some other.
You will at some point realize that the treatment that your
armamentarium you have is limited. Then you will go, I heard this talk about
psilocybin. I got to do something for my patients.
This is why I think there's such a great interest because we have a limited
repertoire of what we can offer are very very ill patients.
And we have a
lot of work to do.