Displaced and the other when I announce your name you could raise your hand Lisa to benedec
Bury Hassan
Athena Viscuzzi
Mars Vogel
Beverly Zabriski who is?
Helix Center executive committee member organized this wonderful program and we're very grateful to her
Also Simon dang is on his way and will be joining the discussion as soon as he arrives
So without further ado
Well we were talking
before this about
the effect of people's stories on each other and I guess
You're the one that's done the research on this so maybe if you could start us off with how you think that relates to this topic
So we
Basically what we're doing in my lab we look in how people communicate
So I'm an old scientist at Princeton University and my lab we're looking now
a
Storyteller
convey his ideas
To the audience, so basically we're scanning the brain of the listeners
Why they listen to me speaking for example and my brain while I'm speaking to you
And basically
What we see that in good communication
The brain of the listeners become coupled to the brain of the speaker and
And the stronger the similarities between my brain patterns now and your brain patterns
Mean that we managed to communicate and you can really understand me
Most likely it's not happening now, right?
You see on that
You need to get used to my accent. We need to develop a common ground. We need to
have common ideas of what we talking about and then it will emerge at the end of the conversation hopefully and
And I think that especially in these days we see more and more that it's very easy to interrupt
communication it's very easy not to be coupled to the other
anything
When good communication happening is like a magic
I thought I will eventually become coupled and I think the question in these days
how can we can really improve communication and
In
Increase the similarities in our responses and serve background and certain understanding of the topics
We are talking about instead of dividing and biking because it's very easy for the listeners to be decoupled and
Not to want to be engaged in communication
So since we're talking we're in a climate, let's say where people are being othered a lot, yes
What are those conditions that we need to create so that people can listen to each other I
Think that the two really important things for communication to happen
I think first we need to develop
similar
joint language like if you were talking about different aspect and have different beliefs and
and
Filters by which we perceive reality
It's very easy to be decoupled. So for example
when I was
reading the news yesterday is
In the attack on the media I got really scared by
trying to say that
For example, journalists are the enemy of the people because that means that one of our basic
Knowledge and way to create a society now is
undermined and
If we don't know what is the fact and what are the tools will be very difficult to establish this coming down and
It will be very easy to divide us more and more and anything that basically
We're living in a water to become more and more fragmented
And I think there are some forces that like it
That can gain power from this fragmented reality and that's something we need to fight against
We're very much a story
We did not exhibit the stories
These are
How these is third-person stories these aren't these aren't stories of our educators
But the goal is to create a sense that this is that the experience of others is very much like the experience of immigrants
And very much like the experience of visitors who don't identify naturally with the immigration experience
We don't have that sense of whether we're connected at that sort of a granular level for us
It's it's it's very superficial
Are people saying to us things like yes, my grandparents experience the same thing or are they saying things to us which they are increasingly
Today I don't have to listen to that crap anymore. There's been a change
And we can tell our story we own our own stories and we don't have to connect our stories and stories of other people
It would be wonderful to be able to to see the kinds of connections that you
That you study and and what it is that facilitates would facilitate our ability to make connections more real
So you were talking about the exhibit that doctors without borders did earlier this this year about
So that's the organization I work for
I'm highlighting our experiences with refugees all over the world and the whole point of that was that in telling the stories and
Making people more than telling the stories but actually making people kind of go through a simulation of that experience
that that's
It's impossible not to be moved. I guess, you know, I think we come from I come from a place where
it's
Stories are moving, you know, and we encourage forms where people can tell their stories because that's what's going to shift
People's minds, but I guess what you're saying is kind of challenging not necessarily. There have to be some conditions. Yeah, I think that
There's something really interesting about storytelling and it's way more effective way of communication than anything else if
If a doctor will come and we tell you that you have a cancer and we start to detail all the facts
To be very difficult for you to process
But if you will talk with someone that went through this
To the therapy and will tell you his own personal experiences
suddenly will get information
So I think in storytelling, it's a way for us to communicate
the way more effectively because
You know, we all humans we all suffer we all have families we all have friends
We we went to the world
So it's very easy to connect when you have this like very basic common ground to use for
When you go and and really become very abstract
and then it's more difficult for people to be coupling in
in the understand the situation
Well, I think that's the premise of having
the work that you're doing
retelling stories from history and then also in the kind of presentations where we were having I
guess all
when when we're trying to
Talk about the displaced and raise empathy for them and
services and funding hopefully
We do rely on story. I think that's kind of the idea. We do rely on stories
But I think what you're I think we're all increasingly
Just talk
You said you need a common language in order to hear somebody else's story, and I think we're all
increasingly siloed
And just listening to the people who speak our language, you know, I mean in terms of
Yeah, I mean, you know and that there would be words
Like if if somebody's telling me his story
Was an illegal immigrant
That's it. I've stopped listening, you know, because I don't
In my language, there's no such thing. There's no illegal immigrants
So we speak a different language so finished look you know my empathy
And
Some guards, right and in your intuition is absolutely right. This is exactly what do we see basically
I can we did an experiment that was a very simple experiment. It was like listening to
50-minute story by JD Salinger. So basically everyone listening to the same story
the story was about
a husband that lost track of his wife in a party and
He calling his best friend in the middle of the night asking did you see my wife?
It's a very simple story
For half of the audience we say that the wife even affair and is with the friend at this
actual moment and for the other group we said
that the husband is lunatic and
And really we have a very iraqi man way
And it's like one sentence was enough
to make the audience
Understand the story in a very different way
It and it was so strong that we can look on the brain of each listener of Intel
You believe that the wife even of her or you believe that the husband is lunatic and
If you think that one sentence
Can filter your reality
Right and think about what happening if you listen to Fox News
424 hours a day or you read the New York time
Then for the same news event that you exposed to you have very different filters
And as you were saying this filters going to change everything
And if I was saying that if we want to have the same filters on reality
we
It's more challenging to communicate and
There is something good about it because you want
The different opinions coming to so you don't want everyone to have the exact same or something about the reality
And but also you want some common ground then the question how to balance it
It's something that we don't really know how to do and it's always the same thing
And then there's quite a difference is you've already raised
Between telling someone else's story that is your story because you're engaging it and then telling your story
which is much of I
Believe what you have done is that you have told your own story
She when we talk about
From the experience of a person's that happened to leave in it
It is something that cannot be
Tall to somebody who have no clue
What it means for instance
To be in a situation knowing that
What tomorrow would be like
To be in a situation
Whether they're going to be tomorrow or not to be in a situation where
Somebody will be in charge of your
life
yourself
Somebody will be giving you a margin order that
You have to be left right or you shouldn't be there
but
In 21st century
For me looking back
The darkness and sadness
Demonization and helpless and this is what
The displaced person or refugees or immigrants
Is the same thing just different names a different circumstances at the time
in 21st century
For me myself when I look at the suffering of the others knowing that I've been there
But I'm not longer there
I'm now a different person
who
is in a position to
Talk about a sufferings of the other persons who
Don't know how to say now
who cannot I
I
Won't be and I don't want this and I don't want this
and this is what I so I
Always ask myself
Why?
any persons
At the moment in 21st century should go through what I went through
maybe 40 years ago
At the time when the
We the world's talking about the
the
global
economy global environment
What about the global humanity?
Where we have to sometime to look
at the time when we have a technology that
We know
What is happening in South Africa within 24 hours?
Which was not like that 50 years ago 40 years ago
Why
a person have to fuck up in
In a tree and climb in a boat risky
a journey
Without knowing what would happen in the middle of the oceans
But they decided so
These are the things that they the the rules should be addressing what make that persons be so desperate
That
To leave the place where he or she was born the place where any person is proud
To call it home because the place where he was born
Sometimes cannot replace even that how bad it is
And then even the the metals of the the sense of where you what was born
It's good because
God created you to be in that place
God didn't create a you to be in heaven
Creating you to be in that place. So this is the miss that
We in the world are not discussing
To address the issue
What makes a person so desperate?
to risk
his life or her life
Seeing
immigrants
Washing out by the oceans and after the drown
Seeing
People risking their life to be shot at
To go to rather side so I think there is something fundamental that
We in the world that we are in especially we in a better world where we are today
We have to look into it
if there is a problem sin
the home where I come from I
think the solutions
should be
Can we address it?
Can we find a solution to that problem so that?
Simon will not risk his life
for a journey with our knowing
What will be ahead of that? I think that's the
That discuss it if you want to do that
So I'm thinking about Simon is the way that you
Believe that people are inextricably tied to their homes, you know and are fundamentally identified to whole
Sorry, I lost my
the way that people are
Fundamentally tied to their homes and
the particular problems that refugees have
When they are essentially homeless and stateless
and
Also the responsibilities then that governments have to create
or not create a sense of home in those kind of interstitial moments when people are traveling and
Morris I was wondering, you know at the Tenement Museum given your own research on home
how
People form those neighborhoods organically we're talking about that downstairs
as Americans
We assume that movement is natural we assume that people are created
with
Opportunities to go somewhere else where an end stage at least for the moment of
That process but in most of the world it's very much like the the world that Simon speaks to people
Didn't expect to move they moved only under the most desperate
Circumstances so we tell the stories of people who for whom there was a differential the lower east side
The streets were not paved with gold as the the language of of some of American history has it
These were extraordinarily difficult circumstances
People encountered struggle they were strangers. They weren't they weren't the victims of terror in the place to which they came
In many cases they were victimized by terror in the places they left
They came because there was marginally more opportunity and significantly more
Safety the question then was how do you reconstruct something? How do you make a community when you're there?
not because of of something that you had always dreamt of doing but
Something that that was forced a choice that was forced on you because of conditions in the place you came from
I mean, I I think of this personally what would I be at this age still? I don't know living in Poland
if if
My parents hadn't gone to Siberia and wound up
wound up here I
Don't know that if as an American I think oh, I can think of nothing worse than spending my life in Poland
But so there there is a there are positive outcomes
But we assume those positive outcomes and yet what we need to do is realize just what the difficult the difficulties are
of that movement
how
How
undesired that movement is in almost all cases
so so came from
look from the story why
the borders were more open on the faulty is it because
The situation in the state was after the depression there was a need for new power
To come in and so they opened the borders a slight remote. It wasn't like they clear up and right because now we see that
the borders are closing more and more
But I think the economic situation of the people around
Actually is better than what was on the 40s. I titled now the process. Why we closed the borders?
In this particular moment in time in history
We we have more resources to give we closed them for the first time in the 1920s
In the laws of 1921 in 1924
established a racial system
That determined who could enter this country and cut immigration back from a million a year to
150,000 a year
Favourying people of superior racial backgrounds Northern Europeans Western Europeans
cutting out altogether Asians
cutting out altogether Africans and restricting to a handful Eastern and Southern Europeans so
Eastern Europeans polls and Russian poll Russian Jews and Polish Jews had been entering at 300,000 a year
They were cut back to 5,000 story the Holocaust is the story of the 1924 Johnson Redact
Past in this country
After the war there's a slight opening
not because as
And by the way then the key to those 1920 laws or that the United States was experiencing great
prosperity in the
1920s it was one of our really great periods, but an awful lot of people in America
Thought they were losing their country's identity. They were
Agriculture collapsed essentially as a source of employment
Small towns gave way and people whose lives were built up in
In their identities were tied to rural America or small town America
To what we would today call red state America
Thought that they were losing the future and so they cut off anything that threatened to continue change in
1945 when the horror of the death camps became unavoidable
President Truman wanted to allow
In refugees to enter the country
Congress wouldn't go along it believed that the same conditions that had prevailed in the 20s
Still obtained Truman had signed an executive order that allowed literally a handful a couple of thousand survivors of the camps
Into the United States
Without congressional authorization in 48 they signed
Congress passed the first refugee act that wound up allowing about 200,000
European refugees and and
That included about 80,000 Jews actually more Ukrainians came in under that law
It's an irony there
Then Jewish survivors we didn't change our laws till 1965
In the city of the as part of the civil rights movement and now we're at another one of those moments probably with great prosperity
And yet with people who who are losing
There there it's like the 20s in a lot of ways people who are losing their sense of the nation
Belonging to them and wanting to go back to a pre-civil rights America
wanting to go back to a white America indeed to a white protest in America and
That's where we are where we are and how it has been and some people would argue that there's a
fundamental change in the economy not the
Superficials of of prosperity or lack of prosperity
It's economics and identity
So if you take this another three of
Lucky the 20s in 1920s then we should be really worried because we all know what happening in the 30s and the 40s
What what happened was the same thing that's happening in the 30s and 40s in Europe
Yeah seems to be happening again
Yeah in in Europe right the irony for us is that usually after an election in
some
Emerging part of the world the American president calls up the new dictator and says will will be your will
Collaborate with you as long as you respect
for a rule of law and human rights and this time after our election was on
Hala Merkel of all people who called Donald Trump to offer the same
collaboration going forward if the United States respected human rights and rule of law
There there's also such a difference between waves of immigration when there is some choice involved and
the homo T for forced from home and that was the exhibit of
Doctors without borders that forced from home and you've worked in many different kinds of refugee camps in different countries
Yeah, when you were talking every my worked in Maban County in South Sudan and
the
Near the shilok people
And
You were I thought I heard you say how people
Downplay that experience of being wrenched from your homeland how it really is
You know a loss a death a grief, you know to be
forced from home like you say but that there's the loss of the of the
What you were saying you're God given
Homeland, you know
Now you know other people have used that idea
anyway
But it was I think that's true that people really you know
We when we think of trauma even we think of well, it's somebody died or you you witnessed this
But just the loss of homeland just the loss of of of of common language
You know of but not just the the tongue but the
Markers, you know
Is so
It's something you need to recover from you know that it's this loss and I was working
With a very small group of people from
Sudan who would take it were in a refugee camp in South Sudan and they had no
Language and they had no word in their language for depression and so I was trying to explain
What's depression and we were trying out different words and?
the
educated people in that spoke Arabic and then their native language and
And then so we're going back between the few languages trying to figure out
You know what is depression?
You know when people are crying and they can't get over it and they're staring out the window and they can't function
And they said oh you mean when you're missing your village
You know and so that became our word for depression like missing your village
You know that it's that fundamental, you know that it's a it's a
It's a mental illness to to be wrenched from home, you know, I always remember that
and
You know talking to I
Was
Talking to a young man from Central America the other day
Who had to flee his father was murdered by gangs, you know and the
You know his father was murdered all these horrible things happened, but the biggest component of the grief was
The the future that he had anticipated in his own place his own God
Yes in place, you know
And that he was never going to have that again and that one person with a gun could take that away from him the rest of his life
You know I
really think we
estimate that I mean the idea that people are crawling over our you know borders to take our jobs or some
Thing like that
But you know then I think in this goes back to the story telling then
Can it really be only people who've experienced this who understand are there?
You know like when you tell the story of the 1920s immigration laws I
Wasn't there, but I'm having that experience right now. I can understand your story right of how the
in prosperity xenophobia
Arises
So I didn't have I have you know, how do we create these?
environments where the language where people can understand people who have not been rinsed from their home can
Understand the severity of that and and you know or people who have not been oppressed can understand
what that really means and how wrong it is and
Hopefully, you know so that people who are oppressing
Can understand what they are doing and stop doing it
But that that presumes empathy
And it can't be presumed
Yeah, I will go to my grave presuming
They can't take that away from me
Home is such an elemental concept
But even if we haven't been driven from our home or nation
Or the people whose language that we share that idea of leaving home is
Something that we can all that we've all encountered even if it's just that struggle. Let's say to leave home and
I was telling you that we I was recently in Greece at a refugee camp and
One of the camps it was a Syrian camp
And it had just opened about two years ago and the people who had the military who organized the camp
Basically just organized people numerically and they gave them their
boxes they call them isoboxes to live in based on whatever number that they happen to be assigned when they entered
So all of the mostly Syrian families were there and they were just organized
numerically, but then over the space of one summer they reorganized themselves
according to
communities or tribal affiliations or whatever
kinds of smaller cultures
They wanted to affiliate with and I think that that was a really powerful experience
The amount of agency that any one person has
When they are in refugee camp was remarkable to me
You know the idea of being able to leave your box and where would you go?
You needed to have an appointment at another box or you need to be you know
You need to have an appointment with the medical staff where you need to be going to a class
But people didn't just walk around and wonder what they might do for the afternoon
I mean this idea of what it means to be home or what it means to be at work
Or what we currently call a third space right that place that we hang out with our people
You know this is something that's really missing in a camp and it was it was somewhat remarkable to me that the people would
Organize the camp. I mean certainly for reasons of efficiency, which are completely understandable
You know that they would just organize people numerically, but it was also
Wonderful to see the agency that people took
Upon themselves to reorganize and to see how that was allowed for you know that shift once there
We've had that in this country with the resettlement the refugee resettlement program has put people
You know the long here and this and everybody has reconfigured themselves
You know that there was a study like within five years everybody had
Migrated to find their own people and create the little Italy's in the Chinatowns and the the things that that people
need I also saw that in South Sudan where there was a
Society that was organized around shakes and so they all moved themselves around and we would call the different parts of the
camp according to the
the shay who you know I'm going to
Shake so and so's part. I'm going to the according to the clans the whole camp had been renamed as opposed to ABC
According to
But even among economic migrants who are much more fortunately situated in a city like New York
You've got dozens of hometown societies organized by Mexican villages. You've got these hometown associations
organized by Chinese regions and and communities
and
if you go back in time you'll have in the on the Lower East Side
the Lonsman Shaftan people who came from some god forsaken village in Ukraine and
Banded together with others of that same background because there's something of home
That that was that significant to their identity to who they were to really empower them to help make their way in this very strange world
You see
There is a word which we learned people like me that it said nothing like home
And come down to
Why you replace home to your refugees can
This is a refugee scale there have to be
something
Undescribables that took home away and make you a displaced persons
and
Nobody within this audience
Can describe it
Be a refugee more than a person's who was from home and become a refugee
for instance
We all know about their slavery you read from the books how bad it is
demonizations and but
If you tell me to explain to you
You will be in tears
different from what you read in the book because
there are certain things that a
Person have to withhold it within inside you cannot throw it out
Nobody should be a refugee
What should be a displaced persons?
That's my
opinions and
If that's the case why we have a
Flow millions and millions of refugees again at the time when we talk about
Globalizations and so on and we have the beautiful organization here talk about the issues
Which they supposed to be responsible about the UN
We sometimes make me to be disappointed
Of the UN how it move away from the principles of the university declaration of the human rights
When you have and you mentioned in southern students
Where at the moment with speaking we have about
four millions
southern Sudanese
our refugees
Question is why?
Yes
southern Sudan has been from refugees to the refugees
Since the time of independent of sedans in 1965
The war has been going on and on and off and on and so on in other words
From the refugees to the refugees to the refugees
Even those those who find better like me
There is nothing to replace home
I remember when I went back to
southern Sudan
The place where there is nothing absolutely nothing there is no running water. There is toilet. There is no nothing absolutely, you know it
But I feel
something joy
I feel like even that I didn't eat for a day
There is no hunger because I feel full
Of home
It is not compared to my daughter, which was born here if I took her over there
There's no connections. She will be like I'm going home
Which is where he's supposed to be so
the point I'm trying to make I
think we
have to
have
a commons of
Humanity in us
Where we have to look at?
The problem what make people become refugees
Sometimes it is very complicated
To explain to the person who was not but to me for instance if people of southern Sudan
Become refugees then there is somebody is responsible
The father of the house of southern Sudan is responsible
It is in my house if my kids running around then who is going to be blamed
It have to be me as a father
Somebody have to say and say we have to hold these call these person and explain to us
like
this
Father why his kids are running around
making thing difficult for the others and
That's it, you know, I feel very strongly that
the solutions to any
Crisis where
vis-a-vis
Immigrants and refugees is it's not to bring them into your house
The solution have to be home
Because bringing it to your house is not a solution at all
The question if if it is a solution, how many you are willing to take?
Because yes, there is
Go to East and Asia there are maybe a hundred a million the one to come in your house
Go to Africa. There's another hundred million go to Europe go to
Anyway in the world if your place is a better place for these problems
How many you willing to take?
And that's why I feel very strongly always
Where the refugees came from
We have to address it what made them to be a refuge now the world talk about the refugees of Syria. Yes, I
Personally half as a lasset
He's responsible if he's responsible, how can we let him?
replace destroyed life of millions, and he is one person's
And then now we have a crisis the problem blaming I was why you're not taking 10 and why you're not taking 20 and why you're not taking 30
Why we don't even take one man out and let people stay in where God given right?
Do you think that there's a difference and this is to the whole group
Between those who feel they have to leave their homeland because of famine or drought or
Some uncontrollable nature aspect versus a
power dynamic versus a totalitarian
Submission aspect because I I would imagine that the way the psyche processes that is quite different
It's one thing to be you know upset
I mean we know that the river is drying comes back to us, but it's a different thing
Then let's saying someone from another
cult within your own religion or a tribe within your own country push you
for survival and I wonder
Have there been studies of the different kinds of trauma in that regard?
Did you see anything different from the Afghans and the Syrians for instance and
So I guess I'm struck because how the psyche processes it is
very different from how the UN and
International law codifies it right so at the camps that I was at the Syrian refugees were given
very different
resources and treatment then at another camp where the Iraqis and Afghans were
because
the Afghans and
Iraqis were not going to be eligible for
refugee status because they weren't considered to have fled as war time
refugees whereas the Syrians
Were going to be entitled for refugee status therefore their children got to go to Greek schools
They lived in very different kinds of circumstances in terms of the psyche
I think that they did understand that they had a different status
Which was one that was more prospective
You know they were able to look toward their future and see a different place
I mean to your point Simon the Iraqis and the Afghans knew that ultimately
I think they were going to have to go back home and in a different way than you mean it
I think which is that going back home is a kind of healing return. They didn't see it that way
Because it wasn't going to be that way for them
So I think that that's a real difference in how people are treated as refugees
You know those conditions under which they left. Yeah, I totally agree that the differences are
artificial differences that we impose all
displacement is because of inequality
It's all
All a power dynamic
People who came
You know
My grandparents came because there was less there and more here
That's a power dynamic. It was unfair. Who's wrong?
You know, it's all because of injustice and then we compound it by making
Categories, I think you know when we treat people with trauma, I mean to me
And I'm not a researcher so I just make this stuff up
You know, but the big difference is the level of helplessness that was involved right and that a traumatic
You know, which is why sexual violence is so difficult to get over because it's it you've lost control over what comes into your own body
right it's just
So the the level of
disruption and and
so if I have been
Raised knowing that the world is unjust my whole life and then I'm going to have to make decisions based on that injustice and do the best
I can I
might be less traumatized
when I
move
to to save my
So then if I grew up thinking
There is maybe some you know that there is justice in order in the world and then I
violently find out that there isn't and have to flee in the middle of the night
however, I would say that all of this is
power dynamics and that
we have a world of globalization and
All it does is give us more information about how unequal it is, you know that now any kid
in
Wherever me and mark can be on his Facebook seeing what other people have that he doesn't have you know
That that's what globalization has given us and not read distribution
Distribution do you think the way?
Your topic and say you have the power now to change dynamic is there even a solution to that
Yes, I mean, I think you know, I think we're always
Trying I mean, I think humanity has always tried to evolve situations of greater justice and greater distribution
You would just not going to interrupt anyone. No, no, please just it, but I would challenge them
Yeah, I don't think that that's hardwired into us by the way, and I say that without evidence except as a historian
Yeah
Because Simon was saying we should let everyone go back
But the conflict brought people away from me and
And we were saying that people want to protect what they have so why should I give more
Texts more money from what I'm earning lose my income for other people that's coming I
Want to protect it so so the
This feeling of honor I've
Two meanings right and I think it's the source of the conflict
First it's like it's like really
pure feeling of this is where I belong and
The other is this is mine and not yours, right?
So it's also create a boundary between one and another
and this is why people if you take serious for example, it's not like an
Asset that is in power it's a minority the alloy that controlled the majority of the Sunic and
They know that if they will lose
The Sunic without their majority going to
Pinance them so it's fight of their life
and it's also their own and
and
And the question because we cannot fix it from the outside
And then we cannot open the borders for everyone that want to come
In this dynamic I think we a bit stuck I as liberal as we do not know how to fix it and
as conservative they don't know how to fix it then and
Sometimes I'm feeling that
We don't really discuss
the complexity of the situation and
And we go to the place that is our comfort zone we believe everyone are equal for example that
Something that we can operate with but we don't know how to make it a pen I don't know how to fix it I
Think there is something she mentioned about when she passed all of us
but the kind of refugees and immigrants because
There are too so many layers when it comes to
Immigrants or those who the refugees there are those who want to go to choose for the better life
there are those who
false
to become
displaced persons and this is the real refugees in my opinion and
And come down to what I said before
about why a person have to be refugees
What is the problems and if we?
Genuineing I'm not talking about we talk about the the global rule that which is today
Focus and invest in
in solutions
of the crisis of very refugees to
diagnose why they become people become refugees I
Things will be better than investing in
Sending the refugees things and so on and so on and so on it will be less cheaper by
If saw the students refugees are four millions and the father of that saw the student in the problems
And and we focus on that person
Why he became a problem and identify and address this and solve these things I think we will save ourself
You know time and energy and resources
of debating one another and a qi you know taking and why
You refuse into text for instance
It my opinion is
the world should have to look and
invest in
Solving the problem what met the refugees as refugees
I guess what you're saying is who is this for who's the world who is the world the United do nothing nations
Because
Based on it is this true. That's why we keep you know going because we are not they are there because all the
The country the nations where the problem come they sit where and they sit in one place, which is the UN
Let's take two examples listen to him in Iraq
It was governed by the tactic the capital right Saddam Hussein the US went in
To cover the country replace it with like a democratic
government and the country collapsed
I don't think something good came of the Iraq war. Maybe Isis came out of it. Hey take Syria
Obama was about to attack Syria and
At the end he decided to back off and not to put military ground on Syria, right?
And then the lesson came into Syria are they fixing it? Who will fix Syria?
I will fix the luck it's
As you think it's like the people in the place
Need to fix their country and if and if they cannot
Because the power dynamic and I agree everything is about power dynamics is too complicated
It's very difficult from the outside to fix it
and and and now we really stuck in in in the crisis and
And because everything is connected. It's one thing
Syria on you like it coming out to Europe and I would say in Europe and
exchanging the US and we are all part of this dynamic because it's a global world in the centers everything is connected and
It's a very serious
Problem that we don't know how to fix
And we have for a long time
To go back to barbers question about
Is there a difference between people leaving for one circumstance or another?
Obviously people who leave because their lives are at risk are one end of a continuum and
People who leave because there's some differential that they think that life could be better
Somewhere else are at the other end, but people have been leaving for both of those reasons
Leading places for a very long time whether it's the idiot sons of English aristocrats who realize there was nothing for them
If they stayed in England in the in the early 17th century and wound up
Populating the American or leading the American south or whether it was people whose whose
livelihoods disappeared as Europe industrialized in the late 19th century
Whether it's people who fled a flood of war in none of those power
Embalances has anyone figured out how to stabilize
Sending societies different as the dynamic involved in the sending was I don't want anyone to think that
Leaving England because you're a cavalier as opposed to a Puritan is the same as as leaving Syria
Because your life is in imminent danger
Well, yeah, I mean maybe this is going too far off track, but one thing I've always been
perplexed by is
the desire to colonize
right like that's like
Because we're always dealing with people who are fleeing
You know like who don't want to leave home because they're fleeing or then we talk
You know, so that's a refugee and an immigrant is somebody who thinks there's something better on the other side
I mean, what's a colonizer like that's really sick
Which is how this country started like it like what's that that you leave your home to go take somebody else's?
How does that fit into this?
Sorry, I'm like way off, but you know when I go to these places. I I really it really puzzles me
Like why do people want to take other people's homes?
Instead of improving their own because that's what colonialism is answering your own question your question was
Why don't we find a way to improve societies where they are and the answer is we haven't
And we haven't for a very long time
Colonization is one element to that one aspect of it
And I think that is that this the
The argument should be focused on and that's why I said before there is nothing like home
For instance, and I seen the works of doctors without borders
In many places in the south of Sudan even before the peace agreement between the north and the south
I always take a risk to go to into the war zones
And
sometimes
We have to carry the patience
for the whole day and
Reach to the where the deltas without borderized station I in the midnight and
I remember I was in northern by the south which is not enough and I
and
The child and a mom
They just felt six and you know something had to be done all day and we have two doctors with us
but there's no medicines and
According to them if we find a medicine these people will
Will survive if we are not going to find a medicine then within 48 hours they
So we have to walk
for
nine hours
To reach where the doctors without border so in my opinion
The investments of the argument should be finding a solution
And wish that the doctors without borders and instead of they because they like their life sometimes are in dangerous
You know it. I don't need to tell you how many
your workers
in in in my band was kills
in in in in because the
The environment is hostile environments
So the solution have to be invested in finding a solution where they is and the doctor without border instead of risking
They have to go there and train a person. Okay, and instead of you relying on
Tradition medicines which probably you know there are people in my band are lying
They're on medicine because there is no other way to find
Doctors, so this is where the focus in my opinion should be today
in a state of
taking
Four million Syrian refugees whom are now need to get our who already refugees to take them somewhere
To my opinion. That's not a solution to take four million in southern Sudanese who are now refugees in their own country
Is not a solution we have in Uganda one and a half million southern Sudanese
They're living in in in life
I don't want to describe it
There is no dignity by
Being a dispersed person in a place which is not your own
For you to survive you have to do ABC
And you just figured out what do I mean by ABC to survive?
But if we find a solution to their home believe it or not I would write there
Be in my village you mentioned before and
Figured out how would I survive whether I want to go to the river in Nile to get a fish?
in instead of be in an hostile environment where
There is no dignity of my child
There is no sense of human of home I become homeless and helpless
So I think that's this that's what we in the world have to be addressing
And I'm just you know who am I to to to to to tell the world
There are so many different levels to address here and it seems to me though that it's
Also really important to address the ethical practice of how we respond to people in need
Even while maybe the primary
Response needs to be to fix the situation because there are always going to be people in need on the sidewalk
Right in front of this building that are displaced and that are homeless
So the question becomes I think how do we ethically respond?
You know we don't have any behavioral
A con economist on the panel who could explain game theory and why we take from other people
You know like they have to have something and we want it so we take it and it would be maybe
Interesting to have somebody like that on this panel
But how do we how do we respond ethically with the few resources that we have?
and I continue to you know to
Reflect as I hear you talk about the primacy of home and how that may change for any of us depending upon where
We've been raised. I mean in Queens where I'm from I
Don't feel a really powerful affiliation with Queens as if I'd be ripped out of my home
If you know to like God and then God thank you
So, you know what is it about certain circumstances that evoke that really powerful
Elemental affiliation where if you did not live there then you're homeless
You know that's a really powerful thing to say and what are the
various conditions that shift for people
You know that makes some people have that primary affiliation and others not
But is it really the case that it's not if if we will take you and
Departure out of the US and
Africa what you feel displaced not from Queens to Brooklyn
Yeah, I would feel yeah if I had to move to Staten Island
I think
Really displaced
Yeah, so who are your people right? That's always the question is how how do you constitute a community of people around you?
You know you're asking what kinds of resources are available actually pointing to how few resources there are
It's really how few resources we make available because resources are
in in the case of homes for those seeking better lives
They're nearly
There's there are so many that they're uncountable
We we had from Simon the numbers of refugees
4 million here 4 million there those are large numbers until you realize that this country alone
Between 1865 and 1914 took in 25 million people that's a big and got nowhere near full
Nowhere near full
So the resources are there what's missing is the empathy the will the willingness to
Not so much share
Because with one mindset we realize that we are enriched by movement
we've we've talked about people who are displaced and and
moving and
Seeking something we can shift that to the society that
societies that in the past have welcomed them and
Part of our argument that the tenement museum and all history is an argument by the way science is not I understand
that you free but part of our argument is that almost anything we could point to in terms of this country's
Prosperity its culture its dynamism
Literally its health is the result of immigration and
To cut ourselves off from that now you don't need to repaul Krugman or David Brooks, though I do
To to to hear the argument pulled out of the literature that if we do this we do
ourselves
Really to economic not just lack of growth, but ultimately in significance and boredom and well that too. Yeah
People like us are blessed to be given an
opportunity
And we cannot take this for granted and that's why some of us we
Felt that being here is a place
but at the same time we have to stay and
Look after those who are not
Fortunate to get what we get and we become the voice of those who have no voice
We speak on people who have cannot speak for themselves for instance one time I have
About 300,000 southern Sudanese
flee from Egypt after they was attacked by the police in a gift since that
In front of the UN in Cairo
Because what happened was that there was being considered as refugees without knowing where they're gonna go and then when southern Sudan's
Peace was being signed between the north and the south all the issue of the refuge through their name already there they
Nobody talk about it because nobody sure what would be the future of southern Sudan is going to be a piece within or
Independence or separate to countries
So they want to know and then they went and you know
peacefully camps in front of the UN in Cairo and then
The UN call on this Egyptian security
We're almost 100 and something people were skills
So they they they felt that they are not welcome in
Egypt and then some of them takes a risky journey to a crossing the border from Egypt all the way to Israel and
The numbers at that time but 28 people who went there
We got information there are southern Sudanese being detained because they are carrying the Sudanese passport saying that you cannot
You can go anywhere, but you cannot go to?
Bela daradu the enemy country that's Israel to them
So Israelis of course there was very concerned
People coming without knowing then they're coming from and a country which is hostile to them
So they want to know who are they and so on
I have to get involved some there because they cannot reach to the levels of the government to
To to tell they the the the the Israeli that these are not your enemy. These are people who just
Run for their life. They run from southern Sudan
They end up in Egypt assuming that there is safety there they're being attacked in Egypt and that's why they came here
They are not even threat to you
Because if you ask them that do you have a problem with Israel?
They're gonna say no, that's why they came here. So
I'm begging you let them give them a chance
Yes, that peace agreement until
Six years from now
We'll southern Sudan probably will become independence even nobody believe me then so I have to be loving on their
on their behalf and we end up with
30,000
southern Sudanese
People from the north people from the arforean and the issue of refugees in Israel become a crisis at the same time
But I have maintained my position with them that these are people
Who are not seeking to be here?
Believe it or not
One sudden Sudan become independent all these people are going to go back
Because to me as I said before there is nothing like home and you cannot replace home because
Running away from where you was born is not a solution
Then who is going to remain there?
If that's the case then let find any place where there are problems in the world and take everybody out of there
And then they're going to be a crisis where we putting them to so
Eventually they was given a chance of opportunity and so on and then southern Sudan to come independence
And all these are refugees who happened from southern Sudan all of them are back in southern Sudan
Even though very unfortunately
We didn't respect what happened in southern Sudan today should have happened
So come to the to the to the argument of refugees
the solution always have to be home and
We have to address why a person have to go. Yes, if there is a way where we can give him because we are human being
Sometimes even we
Hear when somebody begging for something you always if you have you feel some kind of humanity
We give even the law say that you don't do that
But I'm a human being my conscious telling me that I have to do that and that's even why people like me was given
Opportunity in this country and that's why people like me should not take that opportunity
And then look for my own affairs and instead of looking for the affairs of the others
I think Simon there's a piece underneath that that you're really addressing
Though which is a sense of choice. I mean some people would choose to leave
Some people would choose to go back
but the most profound sense of displacement is when you don't feel you have choice and
I mean I probably would be among those
Would flee as I did from Rochester, New York, you know, and
Others would certainly want to go homes
But the issue is that that sense of autonomy and that's what gets taken away in terms of
the displacement the refugee
Situation it is absolutely and if you look at that those who was given a choice
The majority will then will prefer to go home if there's a my place will be a place where I will
For instance, and I will speak for myself as an American sitting with this suit
What for bend me not to go back to saw the students and in my village and make that place a place to look like United States
If there is environment safety and peace and security in that place and
That's why we have to focus on what make people to become a refugee because those who flee of the conflicts
Their numbers are you compare to those who flee with with a choice of
Immigrant or better life
Those who have been driven by when I talk about millions in southern Sudan
These are people who did a choose
Compared to somebody who want to okay. I want to go to Brussels for instance
But these two four millions if you ask them where a Brussels data have no idea
So we leave the issue of me immigrant those who want to leave for individuals
Who want to take a risk a gambling to?
to explore the world
but a human being should not be
a
Refugees well, I think we're talking about the difference between choice and force that and the power dynamic as you were saying
I mean you're a you you chose to you chose to move to a country different from the country of your birth
so you're talking you come from a
Perspective that is different than this
Yeah, this is why I'm not a few three I because someone is right. I wasn't forced out. It's a very different
It was your choice it was my
I will never say that I'm in the future. I mean that would be like email to say
so I had options in my country and I had options over and I choose to come and explode them and
I'm following my dreams and the society give me opportunity to follow my dreams
I have only to be thankful. I cannot do and that is not a crisis. That's not the crisis
Refugees who might be in this place. Yeah
I have a question I want us to get into before we wrap up and ask for questions
Were you surprised by the outpouring of support in this country?
for
Organizations that deal with refugees and human rights
ACLU
International Rescue Committee doctors at that borders when they were threatened I
I one has the sense that people found that they really had a value in the acceptance and
Facilitating of others and that that but it took a crisis it took a challenge
Before that really came out. Could you could you address that?
Morris sure I think that what you're speaking to is that
What has for a long time been the dominant American narrative the story we tell ourselves about who we are and where we come from and
probably a majority of Americans believe that the immigrant story is their story and a
Conscious
denial of that narrative threatens their sense of who they are and there and really their their
Deepest values the question is how long that can be maintained. It's it's it's not just a matter of being able to
Mobilize people or or have them write checks. There's a political system out there that doesn't necessarily respond to the majority or
responds to a
majority that's constructed and
reconstructed and is
There are powers that play here that threaten that narrative
So where we are right now at least when it comes to the stories we tell ourselves
To storytelling and empathy at that level. We're in a good place
What our feet what my fear is will we be in that good place?
Five years from now a generation from now
That's what's scary. I was
joking to my wife who's sitting behind me earlier today that while there we're being part we are rightfully paranoid
about what's going on today as
Opposed to the 60s, which is the last time I recall
This level of oh my god. They're out to get us this time the FBI and the CIA on our side
Who would have thought?
Oh
Yeah, I just think of the power of visual storytelling in the media in in terms of how it I
Think galvanized a response for people. I think about that now famous
image news image of the little boy in Aleppo sitting in the back of an ambulance and
And how so many people saw in that little boy
children and
vulnerable children and and trauma you know for once a face of what trauma looked like you know to just see that boy
So disconnected from whatever was in front of him and it really
Galvanized people as as well as I think the image that had come out in the news of maybe a few months before of
The little child who drowned on lispost right and how that got people speaking in a way that we weren't quite speaking before
And have you have you seen an outpouring of more attention?
Um, yeah, I mean we're all raking in the cash. Yeah, but I mean there um, you
Know even this nation of immigrants thing is a story because the history is its
a
Country that colonized and other people and then imported a lot of people to involuntary slavery to build a country. That's
That's this what this country is. Yeah, okay
And then some people immigrated after all of that, you know
Um, so even that's a story and the fact that we can see the face of trauma in that little Syrian boy, but we can't see it
When a child is shot by the police in our or by a vigilante, you know in our own communities
Um, so it's
It's always difficult as much as I'm I will go to my grave being an optimist
They are never gonna take that away from me, you know because I really believe that's the last thing
You know, I've been rereading Victor Frankle a lot. You know, I really um, they can't have that, you know, um
but um
Where am I going with it, you know that it's
It's that these are illusory victories, I guess, and that we still need the big victory, you know the one
And who is the we that's going to drive? I don't know
That's going to redistribute everything
Equitably and sustainably and
Make it snow in February again and
Um
I don't know but um so so
You know not to be cynical but just to be accepting of the fact that there's always
a lot of things going on at once and so that the
um outpouring of goodwill towards refugees and immigrants is um, I
I
Is a lot due to compassion and a lot due to self-preservation that I I
I want to be sure that we are not this guy, you know, I want to be sure
I um went to the woman's march with a sign saying
white women we need to do better
Right because 50 and 53 percent of white women voted for trump
And white women would say to me really
But not me I didn't
And to me that's our country, you know, so I want to be at this march to be sure that that's not me
You know, but what
What are we doing to change the conditions that create these things?
It's just really what you're saying, you know, what are we doing to create the to change the conditions that create displacement
What are we doing to to change the conditions that created this
Hopefully very temporary regime that we're facing and so so is this outpouring of
of
funding and goodwill
Really changing the the conditions and I don't want to down I think it's great
You know, I don't want to say I don't want to be cynical about that because
Maybe this is what's going to get
Everybody thinking and and willing to mobilize on a whole new level
um
You know, I I
I
You know
Have seen that in my life, you know, gay people can get married in this country now. I mean
In my lifetime, you said you people thought you were crazy to say that south Sudan would be an independent country
I mean we have seen things that were
unthinkable, you know, I mean we
You know, I think we we forget thing and we forget like when HIV hit this city what was going on? I mean that that felt like
You know an unimaginable
Um and and the reactions and the othering talk about othering right. I mean the the pariah, you know, and
These things change they do go for the better and you know, um
and so I just
This this is part of going towards
The better, but it's not it. I guess, you know that the outpouring is just a little part of it. I guess I don't
Yeah, well to be more inclusive here in the room. Um, I would like to ask anyone who would
Of course, and you know
For what this country has given to me and I seen it's given to the others in the world
I still believe that the generosity that come from america
Will steal there and I'm very optimistic
Based on what I
Have seen that american has given to the others
To the point that you mentioned even today we have in a book where
American can bring in the settlement program 250,000 a year
There is no side things in any other countries that we have
you know
Numbers which is being fixed
Uh, you go to england. They don't have that thing you go to german. You go to anywhere
But in america there is even sometime go beyond that so I'm really uh, remain better optimist of american in generosity
And and and and we have that's why we're talking about that. We should not
Try as in a country or immigrants. We should not take things for granted. Let's look
After others who have no voice and let be their voice
Okay, thank you very much
So, um, if anyone would like to ask a question
I'm going to keep this constructed to questions not not statements
And I have to apologize in advance if I have to cut off anybody, but i'm going to if I need to
So
Please would you begin for us?
Yes, um
I'm probably i'm not allowed to say this but I really want to make the moderator feel a little better
Only about 12 percent of white women voted for donald trump
You know if you go back only 50 percent of the population voted
25 percent of the population voted for trump another 25
Maybe half the women now the question thank you all so much, but I do have a quick question
Thank you for allowing me to say that. I really want her to feel better. Yeah
the um
No, I want to feel better. I want to do better
Do you think
And you're so you each have so much wisdom. Do you think that?
That we as americans have become so in your to to suffering
To displacement to violence to trauma that that has a very
Serious consequences on the way we respond to it and if the answer is yes
What if anything are we or can we do about?
indifference towards trauma violence
I'll defer
I'm supposed to be the moderator, but i'm going to put my two cents in here. No, no, no. I don't mind
Tupperay. I don't have that kind of complex, but
um
I think the capacity to feel shame
Has been extremely important. I think the outpouring of support has come from a feeling of shame
and a feeling of shame of what goes on within our own culture
That we really have to allow ourselves to feel it is an impetus and a stimulus, but i'd like to hear
americans
through philanthropy
Probably give only tens of billions of dollars a year to deal specifically with
Those issues the issues of those who are underserved
The issues of those who are in some ways unfortunate that's not matched anywhere in the world
I would not make the case that we're that it's the best way or that it's effective totally effective
But if you're talking about people's feelings
That somehow there is something unjust out there and they ought to address it
And offer a lot of people in this country address it through their pocketbooks
There is a feeling that something dark happened and I think we feel it and we are afraid of it now from the same
And we all I think this is there is a lot of fear and most of us came today to talk about it
And I think it's only the beginning because it's
It happened a few months only two months ago
Even less I
So I think when at the beginning, I think it's not going to change quickly
I think it's going to be way darker than it is now
So we all wore it and we all think how to change and
I think we need to act as you are doing basically
You're going out and trying to change and someone trying to change and
Only by
We tend to be active with in a way and
Expecting that it would be a long process
Maybe we will win at the end
You did mention, you know
There's always
A homeless person in front of us, you know outside the like
We can all start there like today, you know
Like you don't have to send a hundred dollars to doctors without borders
You can give a dollar to that person and I really believe
You know, that's
You know
That's what we're doing to
Whatever you called it, you know if we've been in your to suffering like
Let's make sure let's they can't do that to us like they can't
You know, we will defend our right to give a dollar to somebody who may not deserve it
You know, they can't have that
Sorry
You should really make me set up
We're comparing
Americans attitudes towards immigration in the 1920s versus now
Is the issue more
Not so much the relative wealth of a country, but the amount of inequality in the country
I've read that
Well, any cause a major problem now and it hasn't been this bad since the 1920s. So maybe that's the common thread
It I would say yes inequalities in issue, but the displacement is the larger issue
People by the 1920s who had
Spent their lives and assumed that their futures would be in small towns in New Hampshire
Or in farms on the Great Plains
That had been ripped from them by economic change by
The transformation the industrialization of agriculture by the rise of industry
In the same way today. This isn't this is Joseph Stiglets's argument. This is their so
People today
Who are?
Industrial workers or coal miners and those are the the constituencies we've heard most about in the last year
Those folks have seen their world disappear
Their world is being displaced by Silicon Valley and all the best and the brightest coming in on h1b visas and disrupting everything
All right, that's that's the similarity. It's it's uh, I don't think it's poverty and
Much as I don't like inequality
I don't think it's inequality either and by the way the 20s happened 10 years after the United States began to seriously
Address the question of inequality to the progressive income tax and any number of other
Literally progressive measures like laws against child labor. So the 20s were a good time if you're looking at the
the trajectory towards social justice much better than now
I think there's been a lot of science psychological studies that claim that
Your relative well-being is not as important as how you compare other people in that in terms of their total happiness
If everyone's poor
Doesn't bother people as much as when you're poor and you see other people very wealthy
And yet the people who most loudly speak against inheritance taxes are people with nothing
So a lot
I would like to believe that logic matters
I've
You know, I've got a PhD and demonstrated I could keep that keep a consistent thought through 300 pages of text
Uh, I don't think it does
I don't think if we if we tell them that it's their health insurance that they'll lose they won't do that
They'll do that anyway
So that's another issue why Americans vote against their own interest
I want to address something Athena said
That you believe very deeply that there is an innate empathy
The people who do you believe that the concept of the other is also innate? It's been certainly through every civilization we know every time we know
um
Mm-hmm. What do you think of that? Yeah, maybe they go together. I don't know that's yeah. Yeah
Unfortunately, um
Yeah
It's still shocking
The you know and and how it meant I mean south to then is shocking how
the
People can slaughter each other after having fought so long for their
Freedom from another entity that was slaughtering it's it's shocking. It's it's shocking
um
I don't know if you've read
Maybe I'm going off on a tangent here, but Sebastian younger's uh latest thing about
Um
Yeah, tribe. Yeah, but that that um
Um, oh no, it wasn't in that I was reading something else. Anyway, that's really interesting stuff in there about how
the actually the
Symptoms of PTSD are more from the the loss of connection than from the actual thing that happened to us
And I see that in my work a lot my current work which is working with
uh
expatriates when they come home from very difficult situations and
There's definitely a correlation between those who are still connected to a
A base and those who have lost that connection from working all over the world so much that
Totally I subscribe to that, but no, I was reading something else on combat by this
um
Bill clays piece in the times no his um
vessel band or it's no it's anyway a guy who writes military stuff and um
saying
And he's talking about resili- preparing warriors for resilience blah blah blah, but he's saying that there's um
uh
There is a taboo in all cultures against a human killing a human
You know
Yeah, yeah that guy. What's his name?
Yeah him. Yeah, yeah, yeah
Um
Right, that's like that was a really that was soldiers on this on purpose and they
They don't actually
That's one aspect right but then and then that the trauma of killing somebody is not just a trauma
It's a taboo trauma, you know what I mean? Like it's it's just so wrong
So
Where am I going with this? I don't know where I'm going with this
I'm saying they're boasted maybe you're right that they're both innate and that their flip sides of the same coin maybe
I'm not sure that I know that they're both innate and that the only way that you can overcome that taboo is to other
The only way that you can overcome your natural empathy. Okay. Now it's making sense
Yes, we're hardwired for empathy. I don't know. He's the hardwired guy. Don't ask me. I make all this up
That you know our natural inclination is empathy and and and love and unicorns
And the only way to do it is to is is is to
Other somebody and make them less than human and that's what you see all over the world in these conflicts where people
Just make somebody less and and I think that's why I've been going
Back so much to reading
When I started working with riff
Refugees reading
Literature from the Holocaust, you know, how can people think this of each other? How does this work in their heads?
It's the oppressors that fascinate me, you know, like how does that happen?
Then Yuri from your work
So, you know, so I'm coming from a dynamical system perspective and not from innate
Perspective so I would say the following it up
And I can connect it easily to the other cost and I'll go up in in in Israel and
being so and by like
second generation and first generation survivors and
There was was the question. How did German could be so evil?
Right. How can they not to operate the camps and any two? It's like it's not human, right?
And again
Realization that
Each human being and it doesn't include each one in the room, okay?
No one is excluded from that
every divine aspect and a dark aspect
And it's all a matter of dynamic of the play between them
and
and sometimes
The best can come from human and sometimes the worst can come from the same human
and and being in difficult situation and I was in combat situation. I saw
dark things coming from people that I loved and I was really surprised by it
and
This is human and I think it's a matter of times and context
I can remember even there was like
out
black out in Manhattan for three days
from 23rd below
And my friend that was living there was saying that
after two days of people become kind something become more nasty even in
this very rich Manhattan Island, right? So it's two about all of us and
And as humans what we need we need to strive to bring the best in ourself even in dark times
And and that's what we need to do and I think
We need to find a way to to improve the dynamics even when it's spiraling down and start to get pretty
dark
You have to come and
I think you have to come up and get in line here
Thank you. Did you want to say any and do you want to come down?
It's better. Yeah
Okay
I'm from South Sudan and we go back and forth
My person is
How could you let a government could be such an other countries
Because we talk about this this place and refugees so
Displaced people they do not choose to lick their homes
Right now I have my own family my my sister and 16 other kids they ran off
So basically if they don't run it are they gonna be killed or otherwise
So how could we stop a detector government from doing that to each people?
Is there a way either the UN or the US because South Sudan didn't come
independently that the US fight
And everybody in other american helped us to be free
And I believe
Whatever they are doing to each other is absolutely wrong
And I remember earlier someone mentioned about certain things he don't want to touch or he don't want to it's dehumanizing
We are talking about children getting raped women getting raped
And not only that couple of days ago they announced that South Sudan is
Is stopping basically the whole country is stopping to death that family
So
This is
It's like getting out of control. So how can we intervene at the US or the UN
To stop this from getting out of control like completely
I
Prepare you guys check it first and then uh, no, I'm not I don't know the the political solution. I you know
Yeah, okay, okay
Political power about humanitarian because if people are fleeing or they're hungry the whole country is stopping
Should we do anything or you know to help them at at least like humanitarian
Assistant, yeah, I mean the only thing that's happening in South Sudan is humanitarian assistant
There's no government functioning that I know of I don't know maybe
Yeah, actually, yeah, what my sister here
saying it is
What she's asking it is the question
being asked by
the four million that I talked about before
uh, that question is being asked by
280 000
Uh, those whom are under the united nations protections
And you know them even in jubah in jungula in apanil
Since 2013
They are in the capital, but they cannot get out
But because of the security of the president
Will execute them even to the point that the security are just around there in jubah the capitals
Uh, there was something terrible happened
Uh to those who came out
Including the angios who went there to work and help them
They will be attacked by the bodyguard or the president
uh, american citizens humanitarian with rapes
Uh, in that in the capitals
And nothing being said by the u.s. So the question she asking it is a genuine question
Uh, southern Sudan didn't fall from the sky and become a nation in one night
It went through the united state congress
a united state senate the president of united states
that
Put a bill called sudan peace act to stop the war between the north and the south
And which that the president and his follows and we're talking about all parties by the way
There was nothing happened for the two party to come together
To to vote as one block
Except in the case of sudan peace act
Where that the issue that the slavery have to be stopped
The war the longest war in the in the world have to be stopped between the north and the south
And based on that seeing everything being signed by the president become law
Uh, you had yet to have an obligation to assist
Billions of dollars to the people of sudan's
Humanities and others follow because when american take the lead
Other would follow and then there was given a chance because there was a debate whether
The the the the referendum should be delayed or not
I personally I went walk barefoot in all the offices of the elected official in the congress
And in the senate to deliver to them address them one each individual
If you if you delay these referendum then there's a
The the bomb will go up because southern Sudanese then you're telling them that
Then you remain go back to the miserable situation so the war will go back against so the southern Sudan was given a chance
Independent was a referendum was conducted in sousadisto understand the defendant through american help
After we did that help that we give them millions of billions of dollars
People who doesn't know how to balance the books
Without accountability without even somebody to follow what this money being used for for the first time to have a nations
Uh come out when we depend on with wealth in their hands oil money
In the in the hands of individual who doesn't have an account that was fighting war and so the president offers become a place where
You become rich in one night
Where millions are being stolen every day in the office of the president by his relative and so on and so on
For god sake if you guys are aware of it
four billion dollars
Was distributed by the president to his cabinet
Because he's taking a big chunk about of that and then later on he turned around to tell them that bring the money back
And then now we have joj kuni
I leading this investigation of recovering this much that I'm going to be covered
All we need in southern Sudan today is to recover
The life of a child who is dying now
And then since the world came out last week that there is a femme in southern Sudan they talk about 20 people a day
die in our hunger and it steals uh we're still talking with the man who is in charge who who replaced them the man who brought the catastrophe on southern Sudan and this is where uh my sister is questioned combat
In my opinion if there is a way we have to reach out towards entrance
The united states have more obligations to rescue southern Sudan in the situation where they are in today
Based on what they did what they showed them as I
When when these peace agreement was not being signed between the two parties. I have to go on hanguage five or 45 days
I want to die and she was with me by the way
Until the president of bama realized that I don't want him to die in front of me
And then he went to add this peace was signed but the president of southern Sudan rejected it
He said and I quote this peace agreement. It is not a grand or if he's not a bible
I'm signing but I'm not going to implement it and nobody even hold him responsible
to me
That person the president of southern Sudan by the name salva keel mayardit
Have to be whole accountables of a half a million southern Sudan who paris in four years
Half a million of four million summa now displaced
At kids are being rep on a daily basis rep in southern Sudan become
You know it
Ever but talk about it
Then why we don't have one would I correct
To say to this man enough is enough simply because of the dollar we give you that's the question why why don't we have
Why don't we hold them accountable? Well, there was a problems with my cousins
The president of the united said brok obama
You know the policy of not don't rock the boats
uh lead to
This situation because southern Sudan if as I told them I told him the president of the united state
southern Sudan is an american baby
And that's why I went on a honger's life to tell him that the baby you brought to the world
He died before our own hands and we don't want to hear that story
I think again it goes to the story. This was a great success
We got south Sudan free from the horrible Islamic people and walk away in Sudan and hanas
Very sad
Yeah, no and it's absolutely
Thank you for asking that question very important
That was incredible and
Several times during the session people said why did it happen now you just gave this exemplary
Explanation that's incredible. You know, I don't think many of us knew that but I'm wondering and this kind of goes to the other
When we look at the other then we can do things
And we've always looked at Russia as the other and when south america went all the trouble there
That was that was the other and even today it's the other and we don't necessarily
Well, I'd like to know what what you think of that and that
Because I think we do have the UN as you suggested
And then the gentleman there said that it's never going to improve
I guess until we have another on another solar system
You know, they will behave
But anyway
As uh, steve bannan
Says the other day other
Uh that we're not part of a global community. There is
We are part of a nation that defines itself
As every nation does in opposition to every other nation
Uh
For us for americans for a long time that other was ideological
It was hard to have a racial basis for our nationality
Because the united states was separating itself from britain
And there was an awful lot of overlap there if you used race
So we emphasized those things that we learned about in third grade
Religious freedom
What was it political democracy?
Social opportunity they weren't quite real
But they made us different from britain. They were real enough
Over time
We've used those or at times when we've become a little bit more insecure
We've reverted to race
Uh, we shifted to race over the course of the 19th and early 20th century
Afterworld where too we went back to ideology
As you pointed out the Russians were extraordinarily important to us
When they were the soviet union
They were the they were the communist world
The enslaved world and we were the free world
Free world included. Oh, I don't know
Franco spain it included lots of things that maybe weren't quite free
But weren't in the soviet sphere
Then the soviets did something horrific
They evaporated in
We woke up one day with no other
after 25 years of a civil embracing a civil rights view of who we were
toward racial equality
toward economic opportunity
toward I don't know a culture built intolerance
toward accepting one million immigrants a year
That's what the 1965 law as amended is about without racial basis
We still do that by the way
But it's in those other areas that we've then begun to shift back to race
George hw bush now the sainted
One of the great presidents of the 20th century got elected by running ads about willy horton
Remember a black convict in massachusetts
So we moved we have been moving for the last 20 years
Increasingly toward a racial definition of who we are and that's what we
Because that's all of us as a nation embraced at the polls a scant
Form of is a bit only three months
Let's get three months or so three and a half months, but who's counting a goal a racial definition of nationhood
Don't get me off on race
No, we're back we have we
Right now what we have is great back
What we the people who've lost their jobs in the coal mines the people who've lost their jobs in the industrial plants
That that is that's it's a group that it wants to make america white and great and racially based again
Um, so thank you. I'm alif and aviary. I really enjoyed the diversity of perspectives of the panel
Um, i'm going to try to make a question out of the comment
I just had a really quick comment, but i'm going to now that i'm rocking the mic try to transform it into a question
Um, so I wanted to say a quick element about i know you talked a lot about
um aspects of empathy and the
The one comment that i'm trying to transform has to do with when
um
You look at a lot of the cadre of empathy studies they really
demarcate the capacity for
um
Empathy breakdown really tends to be around um
different social identity categories when you know, there's the in-group kind of outgroup and that tends to be
What we are hardwired for is the identification for um, you know, whatever I identify as my
kind of in-group
However, my community is defined or my social identity categories are defined and then whoever I other which is my outgroup
And that tends to be the ways in which empathy is the quickest and the fastest to breakdown
So that generally is like, whether it is nation states or nationalities or cultural identity categories or races
And that is the- i'm getting into my question. Yeah, and that is generally that was my comment is around
Ethnocultural empathy and so I think it's really um,
Misopportunity whenever we're talking about empathy to not talk about the specificity of
Ethnocultural empathy because that tends to be where empathy tends to be the hardest and tends to be where
It breaks down so that we do get the outcome of war and the missed capacity to see somebody as not our equal or as
um, not even deserving of our time attention and love or capacity for
um, compassion
So it's around differing social identity categories where we have the hardest to
identify with another person so with that
um, my question now is
Uh, when you guys were all talking as a panel
You said americans are very very generous with our capacity for giving funds. So
uh, you raised the idea that when
Recently we are
You know giving and uh donating a lot toward
um new
Well cherries recently and uh with seeing pictures and um connecting a lot with refugee
um
Individuals and not so much with you know the black lives matter movement and a lot of other
Social justice activities that we really need to kind of garner but not feeling a lot of connection with so how do you see there being a capacity
for
other social groups for us to connect to
And having more empathy
with
different social identity categories. How do you see these connections being able to be made across different groups as it's
Kind of maybe garnering from our pockets to actual people. How do you see more connections being able to be made?
How do you see emotional connections being able to be made and more connections across different categories being garnered?
How do you think that can be done?
So Yuri do you want to keep that on? Okay. Yeah, I can tie
Thank you
I think again, it's it's the story that we tell and
finding a common ground
So
You know
We can all be very empathetic and we cannot be very close and see the other and it's in group and out group
It's the right term so very
Because you know sometimes as we were saying we go out in Manhattan and see people on the street living and we don't see them at all
But we're going to denote
Money for people that are starving in Syria, right? So and now you ask why
You don't know so do not to the armlets but in front of you
So it's we can all have this we all have this like two sides, right?
We can be open to some and we can close to other and and if we want to amplify something we need to create
To change the boundaries and they discuss and that's the only way to do it. So
If now is the focus or is on something then this organization will get the money, right?
If the focus will be on I think the other organization will get the money and
And now we need to decide as a group
giving delimited the sources and giving our nature for in-group versus out group
How do we define our group? Oh, yeah, are we Americans? Are we
global citizens? Are we
from Queens? I mean we can we can have many different entities, right? Are we liberal? Are we conservative?
Are we reading the New York Times? I mean we can divide it and
and it's
Up of us now in this moment of crisis to define the way in which we can
Build a common ground that can move us forward to where we want to be in 20 years and if we will fail
Other people will do it for us like Steve Bannon
There really I have a question I guess for both
Alison and Uri are you saying that it's a rhetorical problem then that
How we language who the other is is dynamic and one can actually be strategic?
I don't think it's rhetorical. It's the rhetorical sound like it's world with no accent
I don't mean it now. We're just talking about language and I think
Worlds are accent. I mean you do think with words
I don't think that if you speak you do something and you can really change the reality and I think what we see now
For the moment the attack on the media that
It's an act it's deliberate act to change something in the strikes of the society
And if they will succeed
They will gain power for many years to give them a lot of power. It's a very smart move
It's not
a crazy guy that's talking this
It's not it's not a crazy guy. It's simply know what he's doing. It's a very smart move
And and now that you see the move
you want to react and people reacting and now there's
It's not a rhetorical world. It's it's a real world
but
The concept and there are some sense and how we move forward for me and that's
That's what's happening now. I think
I think what you're really pointing out is that it's as if within all of us
There's the fight between affinity and empathy
And we're seeing a clustering around groups of affinities
But I would like to thank this affinity group those of you who have come and stayed with us through this
And the wonderful speakers and presenters
Very much appreciate the really wonderful level of discussion and your good energy for being here today. So thank you. Thank you. Thank you
I