Coming.
I guess you know we're the amygdalaids and we play music about mind and brain and mental disorders.
So it's fitting that we're in this particular place tonight.
And the program is we're going to play a few songs and play about 45 minutes, 50 minutes or so.
But before each sort of suite of songs, which would be one or two songs together on a particular topic,
I'll just give you a brief kind of background about the intellectual background of the topic,
the historical kind of place that the ideas come from, that the song is sort of based upon.
And we're going to start off with a couple of songs about one of the deep problems in psychology, philosophy,
neuroscience, psychiatry, all of the things that we know and care about, which is the mind-body problem.
And you know this goes back to the ancient Greeks.
We have ideas from the article at Delphi, for example, that the article said know thyself and a couple of millennia later,
Descartes tried to solve this problem by concluding that the only thing he could know was himself with certainty.
But you know this becomes, with Freud this becomes more questionable because then we have some issues about how much of what we are is conscious and how much is unconscious.
So a couple of themes will be explored tonight through the music is consciousness and unconsciousness and the automaticity of certain aspects of who we are.
And we're going to start with a couple of songs that are more in the area of consciousness,
in particular with the first one is sort of a tribute to Descartes and he goes like this.
I think so I am, I feel so I must be, sometimes I don't know, but it is to be me, I see your eyes,
and they're staring at me, they're sharp as knives, oh what do we see, you can't see, you can't see inside of me,
inside of me there's a blade only I can be.
My soul has passion, it's trying to feel, searching for desire, nothing is real, my will is weak, it's not very free,
nothing to get hung about, oh that's just the deal, you can't see inside of me, inside of me, that's a place only I can be,
you can't see inside of me, inside of me that's a place only I can be.
I think so I am, I feel so I must be, sometimes I don't know, it's to be me,
I think so I am, I feel so I must be, sometimes I don't know, but it is to be me, you can't see, you can't see inside of me,
inside of me there's a blade only I can be, it only I can't be only I can beson
All right, thank you very much.
Tyler, you'd say something for a minute while I switch guitars.
Well, about the mind-body problem.
Yes, what's the next song, Joe?
I forgot.
Mind-over matter.
Oh, mind-over matter.
So, yeah, yeah, we have to, well, of course, in culture, we think we have a lot of control
over matter, and we do in a certain sort of way.
But there's always a longing for more and more transcendence, and so we think of ourselves
as immaterial beings as the same times that were materially embodied.
And so this next song is a little bit about the, that kind of conflict between the material
and the immaterial.
Yeah, and it's about the, you know, the longing that you can have for someone who's not here
and sort of delude yourself into thinking you can overcome space and time and bring
that person together with you.
Mind-over matter.
There's something I'm trying to do.
I guess it's only physics that keeps me apart from you.
Mind-over matter.
Something I'm trying to do.
Break down space and time.
Be together with you.
I'm trying to will you here.
Mind you wherever you are.
Locate your body or soul.
Pull you in from afar.
Are you still in my time?
Have you slipped away?
Have you gone forward to back living in another day?
Where am I to be?
Different continent around the sea.
In the air, flying free.
In a place, heavenly.
No mound of space or time can keep you from being mine.
I'm trying to keep you from being mine.
Mind-over matter.
There's something I'm trying to do.
I guess it's only physics that keeps me apart from you.
Mind-over matter.
Something I'm trying to do.
Break down space and time.
Be together with you.
Thank you.
Now we're going to switch gears to the unconscious mind.
We're going to do a couple of songs about how we aren't always quite aware of what's driving our behavior.
There's a lot of stuff deep below the surface.
The mind is below the tip of the iceberg.
This is a song by Tyler called the automatic mind.
The song is about the way the mind travels by itself on its own journey.
You can not have any particular stimulus.
You could be meditating in one of the main lessons.
The first insight is about meditation.
This is an ongoing meditation for me.
The song is called the automatic mind.
I still have to write beyond the automatic mind one of these years.
Right now it's the automatic mind.
It's got an interesting base part here.
When you get there you'll write the song.
Beyond.
I get there.
Okay.
Welcome to the automatic mind.
The door is open to remembered time.
Images are conjured like a dream.
Guiding actions on the waking screen.
Even though I realize it's still I feel so blind.
As I think about and can't live without the automatic mind.
We live in the automatic mind.
Introspection opens in her eyes.
It seems advanced yet hardly in control.
Illusion of the will is comfort cold.
Even though I realize it's still I feel so blind.
As I think about and can't live without the automatic mind.
Walk.
Talk.
Drink.
Think.
So
You
I realize it's still I feel so blind as I think about and can't live without automatic mind
All right, so let me just take that opportunity to introduce Tyler Tyler as a
Professor of Environmental Sciences and biology at NYU and he works on
Atmospheric and issues and carbon and things like that anything else you want to add about that?
That's good Joe. Okay
Daniela Schiller is a
Assistant professor at Mount Sinai. She's a cognitive neuroscientist and she studies
recovery from fear and processes in the brain that
Allow people to get over fears through various ways anything else
And she's also an award-winning storyteller for the moth organization and other places
Amanda Thorpe is a world-famous international
musician
She hails from Derby, England Darby, I guess it's a doggy
And we're very fortunate to have her with us and although she's not technically a scientist
She does have a background in neuropsychology from University College London. So we count her as a part of the team
Okay, and under the lamp, but she's a fabulous musician with a separate solo career all together
With a bunch of CDs you can find her online at demandathorp.com, right?
Okay, I'm Joe LaDue and I'm a professor of neuroscience at NYU and now we're gonna do a song called
My Mind's up
So my mind's eye is another one about the the way the mind plays tricks on us and does things that
We don't always know too much about and if I can remember where this thing goes this time we're being good shit
Okay, so take it away
I can't think
If you look into my mind's eye
You would see the way that I cry
Deep inside in my mind's eye
We had love it was good
You are there you understood
Everything
Yes, everything
You can't always trust what you think you know can't trust what you believe
Sometimes your mind just puts on a show
It's simply disease
My mind's eye you were mine my mind's eye was fine
If you look into my mind's eye
You would see the way that I cry
Deep inside in my mind's eye
You can't always trust what you think you know can't trust what you believe
Sometimes your mind just puts on a show it's simply disease
You
My mind's eye you were mine my mind's I was blind
My mind's I was blind
Oh, yeah, my mind's I was blind
Thank you
Okay
Yeah, map your mind so we have automatic mind and my mind's eyes like part of the the problems with our
psyches and
But there's also a lot of joy being a human being as well
Which I hope we're all smiling about every minute of the day. So this is actually some of our favorite song. It's by Joe
It's called map of your mind. Okay, here we go
Made a map of your mind I've charted my course
I'm sailing deep inside
Got the winds of force got the heat of your heart keep you from the cold
Got the currents of will take me to your soul
I'm on a journey
Out of God
It's a boy
Had I knew I
And excursion
Of the inside
It's a trip fuel by fire
Made a map of your mind I charted my course
Tailing deep inside I've got the winds of force got the heat of your heart
Keep me from the cold got the currents of will
Take me to your soul
I'm just hoping I'll say it will be true
That they'll take me straight to you
Let the winds blow from the sweet
Joe and I land
My minds will meet
Got the heat of your heart
Keep me from the cold
Got the currents of will
Take me to your soul
Made a map of your mind
To your soul
All right, thank you
Now we have a song called Trace, which is something that people here have studied
Of traces of memories, how they leave permanent records in the neurons and now the DNA and the neurotransmitters
From having the memory, it's really there
So it's a connection between our daily lives and the discoveries about the neurological systems of our brains
The song is called Trace
We're moving now into the memory part of the show, so we do a couple songs about memory
You left a trace in my memory
A permanent place in my synoptics
Say the time feels all pain
The time can't erase your place in my brain
Days and nights they were so fine
Months and years, maybe sublime
Time stood still, while it flew on by
Time ended when you said goodbye
You left a trace in my memory
A permanent place in my synoptics
Say the time feels all pain
Time can't erase your place in my brain
Time can't erase your place in my memory
You're a dominant trace, you won't erase your a dominant trace
You won't erase your a dominant trace, you won't erase your a dominant trace
You'll never be a ray
Okay, thank you
For those who are sort of neuroscience aficionados
That song was written over a dinner with Richard Morris and Yadine Doudai
Which Richard challenged me to write a song about Yadine's theory of the dominant trace
Just in case you know what that means
The next song is back to the other guitar, it's glue
This is another song about memory
It's about glue and the way that emotions can glue together your memories and make them stronger
You probably noticed that most of our neuroscience songs are love songs
That's the way we kind of tell the story of the brain
We got us this on
We can go behind you
Turn that off for a second
Shisha's a good scientist
I saw you leaving, you saw me too
You smiled at me, that's what you do
I tried to follow, but you were gone
Now I'm waiting, sitting home alone
Keep thinking about your smile and eyes
Can't believe your words were lies
You made me happy, so very glad
I can't forget those times we had
There must be something in my brain
There must be something in my veins
That keeps my memories stuck on you
I saw you go, I didn't know
But you'd be there in the week or so
It's so hard to realize in that
I wasn't really aware you're right
I dream about you, most every night
I dream you're there, everything's alright
I keep hoping, my dreams will come true
But I'll wake up, right next to you
There must be something in my brain
There must be something in my veins
There must be some crime over
That keeps my memories stuck on you
I keep thinking about your smile and eyes
Can't believe your words were lies
You made me happy, so very glad
I can't forget those times we had
There must be something in my brain
There must be something in my veins
There must be some crime over
That keeps my memories stuck on you
Alright now, so we've done memory and the mind body problem
The unconscious, and now returning to fear
We'll do a couple songs about that
We'll play a couple more songs
When the night is dark
I lose my fear
Never shed a tear, then the daylight comes
It scares me away, the daylight comes
And I have to fake
When the night is dark
Night is dark
I feel so free
When the night is dark
I feel the peace, then the daylight comes
It scares me away, the daylight comes
It scares me away
Night is dark
When the night is dark
I come alive
I begin to thrive
When the daylight comes
It scares me away, the daylight comes
The daylight comes
When the night comes
When the daylight comes
It scares me away
When the night is dark
I begin to thrive
We're going to close things out here with a song
That ends where we started, it's called the mind body problem
And we're going to just solve that problem right here now
Alright, ready for a little blues
I've got a mind body problem
I don't know what to do
I've got a problem
My body won't you sew
My mind says no
You said you'd always love me
To me it'd be true
You said you'd love me
Well now you're gone
I'm sad and blue
Well now you're back
You want me again
Now you're back
If I relent
I lose in the end
I've got a mind body problem
I don't know what to do
I've got a problem
My body won't you sew
My mind says no
I don't know what to do
I even tried religion
Get over you
To get over you
My body's not you sew
Oh, oh, oh
I've got a mind
I can't get over
Oh, oh, oh, oh
I'm going insane
I've got a mind body problem
I don't know what to do
I've got a problem
My body won't you sew
My mind says no
I'm going insane