Good afternoon. We are ready for this afternoon's panel, which will be on classical and Renaissance art
essentially. We have several participants. The first one we already heard this morning,
Georges D. Ubermann, who is a philosopher and art historian and he teaches at the Echol
de Zoudde to the South Social, is the author of several books, just to mention a few images
in spite of all, for photographs from Auschwitz confronting images, questioning the ends of
certain history of art. And this is just a sampler. You have more in the description.
The next member of this panel is Thomas Dacosta Kaufmann. And Dr. Kaufmann is Frederick Markman,
professor of art and archaeology at Princeton University. He's authored several books also
and again the list is in the leaflet, but I can just mention a couple, Archimbaldo, visual jokes,
natural history and still life paintings, painterly enlightenment, the art of France, Anton Malbert.
The next member of the panel is Francois Quivizier. And he is actually curator of digital resources
and librarian and researcher at the Warburg Institute in London. And we owe to him the nice
iconography that we have for the current workshop. He has written recently a book on the sensory world
of Italian Renaissance art. The other member of the panel is Dorothea Rockburn. She's an artist
who works with both industrial and natural materials, paintings and she cuts, draws, falls and calculates
to create complex works of art built upon mathematical foundations. She has been, she has had several
exhibits and actually currently she has an exhibit at the MoMA until January 20th on drawing which makes
itself. And the last member of the panel is Christopher Wood who is a professor at Yale since 1992.
He is currently visiting professor in the German department of NYU. He has taught as a visiting scholar
at different universities and he's author of several books including Albrecht R. Dolfer and the
Origins of Landscape, Forgery, Replica, Fiction, Temporalities of German Renaissance Art among other
books. So I just have another announcement to make that actually Ed mentioned. There is here as a
participant to the workshop Eric Breitbart and he has actually made a documentary on Abi Warburg
entitled Abi Warburg Archives of Memory. It lasts I think 27 minutes if I to be precise and so those
of you are interested in watching it we could actually have it after the round table have a look at this
documentary so I actually think it's a good idea to stay on for another half hour. So have the panel
and I don't know who will start. Ed, are you on the back of the ceremony? I can stand by asking
what I can ask you. Perhaps, well I'm listening to this this morning someone told me that not much
has been spoken about Warburg but really about what he opened and his method and when I open my
computer now I see hundreds and thousands of images and the problem is how to make sense of these images.
So really my first question would be to Jor did you bear man what is the relevance of Warburg to
the current practice of iconography because indeed in this time Warburg was accumulating his collection
for his own purpose. Now we can log into an image database like art store to take a very obvious
example which has 1.5 million images and it's really a sign of the internet this kind of overwhelming
quantity of images which increasingly demand for most scholars an ability to make sense of that
mass of data. So Jor maybe you like to start by pointing out what would be the kind of relevance
of Warburg's method to the current state of the practice of looking at images.
It's a big question. Let us say first that in the beloved Warburg Institute there are two
two things. One is the photo library which is very big and the other is Nemozinian class.
You spoke about hundreds of thousands of images and in the Nemozinian class there is only
1000 image so to speak. Therefore I think that the question of databases the hundreds of millions
of billions of images you are dealing with as a librarian as an archivist is one thing. The other
thing is to make a night-class. I mean there is a crucial and conceptual difference between
an archive and atlas. Archive is a tool. Atlas is a work. It's a decision. It's an act of
interpretation and I would say that I am more interested I use thanks to you and other. I use
archives but my aim my work is directed towards atlas. That is to say to make a decision
to make a montage an editing a proper editing to make sense with the relation of two images three
four fourteen one thousand why not more but this is a complete difference very big difference that
to organize an archive a database and to make a night-class. Absolutely so the question really
is how to make an atlas out of that proliferation of images. What kind of
methods for instance this morning there was a discussion about aesthetic art etc if you look
at the way 16th century people look at images they don't think of art if you look for instance
at records of iconoclasm people attack images in general whether they're on their painting
whether they're on liturgical utensile etc so I was wondering whether precisely that proliferation
of images that accessibility force us to think outside these categories of aesthetic experience
and think rather in terms of of response to two images. You want to say something?
On that?
What is the question? What is the question? What do you do when you're trying to make a point
about the Renaissance and instead of I think you know 100 small reproduction you have 10,000
images when you're looking for mercury instead of I think you know six photocopies and three
books do you have? How does the quantity affect the art non-art distinction? It seemed to me that
in the 19th century with a much smaller database and this was what George was saying,
Varbour and many others he wasn't the only one we're perfectly capable of a distinguish between
works that have been or let's say images that have been institutionalized as art works and functioned
within some kind of art system and those that weren't so are you suggesting somehow that it's
the quantity of images today that's available that blurs the distinction? Or perhaps that calls
for different approaches to two images. For instance if I search for mercury in the Varbour
guy demographic data I won't only find images by femme spencers. I would find mercury in the
view of beer mugs and stuff. If you search on Google you might do better. Yeah possibly but what I mean
is that with these instruments you can see images in a far broader context than you could earlier
and perhaps think more in terms of responses to images than in the kind of rather basic symbology
that is implicit in the iconographic method. Fucu said to know is to cut. So I didn't answer
exactly your questions because your question was what do you do now which by the way is not
a round table about renaissance it's about now but why not? Okay now I can just speak of an
experience I did. I organized an exhibition at Reina Sofia Museum about atlases of images.
So for my own stake I did on my own personal scanner 20,000 scans and of course the exhibition
was cut in this. It was a choice but what is interesting is the choice. It's not my archive
which is 20,000 images is today nothing but this is important this is it is the choice.
You're making a natural class rather than a straightforward paper and perhaps that would
be an approach. Well I just want to pick up on what you said because I want to ask a more general
question. This idea of knowing is cutting which is related I think to what you were saying about
Ponce de Tuaveres, some idea like that. Well and I think it picks up from what I heard what David
was suggesting about how interest in Warburg had changed and you know if one thinks as Christopher
said quite well that this was an esoteric interest. Warburg was very esoteric and now as you put quite
nicely it's become exoteric and why we're all here hearing about this person when in a way you
would have had to have been a kind of fair dank. Kind of. A fair danker as the Germans say or the
Austrian say that you in order to as you were I mean you were interested in this and Warburg
as 30 years ago but not everybody was and unless you had been at the Warburg Institute or thought
about the history of the classical tradition this would not have had the kind of broad resonance
that does. Now you gave a good explanation about why this you know why this particular person cuts
across many fields and why there are many ideas but why my question is even related to going to
talk about now why independent of Renaissance or classical whatever we're supposed to be talking
about directly here does this have four four panels that could have many more I mean why why is
Warburg suddenly resonating as it just that he's been translated into this lecture or is there more
to it I don't know if it's a huge question yeah maybe we could could could I yeah I'm sorry to go
head but I'm yes try to frame the an answer in terms of the Renaissance actually because I mean
it does seem to me that it's significant in the late 19th century and he's not alone in this regard
he's he's following in Warburg's path but that he's framing the self-understanding of modernity
Warburg is attempting to frame the self-understanding of modernity in terms of the Renaissance and
the question here that I'm trying to put forward is what what was his theory of history what did he
think the role of modernity was and there's an there's an alternative to framing the modern
experience or let's say dating the initiation of the modern experience to the Renaissance and that's
and that's focusing on romanticism that was the that was the alternative that's the absent in
Warburg he was he was not a romantic thinker he and this is related I think to his unwillingness
to engage with the problem of the subject subjectivity it's romanticism right I'm talking about the
heart of German romanticism 1800 that puts the subject right at the center and proposes the subject
as the kind of you know irreplaceable foundation for for for private and collective experience and
he's rejecting that and instead re-embracing an older theory of history which proposes that it's
the dialogue with the past with the ancient past an anguished dialogue with the ancient past which
essentially guides our path and he sees I think and Pernofsky and Cassieur and others who followed
him agree with this they see the period from the Quattro cento to 1800 so let's say the 15th century
to the 18th century as essentially a kind of well this was a kind of a period without significant
internal development it was it was a period when the humanistic project kind of found its bearings
maintained its bearings and then it was disrupted again by romanticism and it's that disruption that
he's contesting he's he's trying to re-establish against I would say that the all the currents of
his time re-establish the the the what we now call the early modern period as as the matrix let's
say of so what I would want to ask even those who framed the conference is what is what aspects of
Varborg's concept of modernity and modern experience are presumably being found attractive again
well if I can give perhaps immediate reaction in my view one of the interesting things of
Varborg is its use of neuroscience and when I when I studied the 16th century I found looking at
art you have to look at how the brain works and if you start to look at the 16th century discourse
on the brain that's essentially Aristotle and it's it's kind of naive and anachronistic to
to think that because this thought very startle you have to read Aristotle to understand their
their thinking so at least from my point of view what Varborg would point towards is to use to
take the responsibility of the present and to understand the brain function in a certain way
and then to look out for manifestation of this functioning outside the realm of science which
in the 16th century doesn't really encompass as much brain activity as neuroscience does I mean
you can see that at the very very obvious basic level if you open a university manual for doctors
the concept of five sensors has stopped existing for a long time so you have to think perhaps in
terms of of postural sensors of a hallucetron etc etc so what I find is that it really opens
art history or the history of images to the full function of the brain and the brain has
produced producing or productive of culture I mean from my point of view that that would be the
most interesting interesting side perhaps it could be also said that it's remarkable how
there is a kind of mirror between the object and the method I mean many of great art historians
were reborn as art historian because they studied Renaissance
so you really defined your own practice as an art historian finding in a Renaissance
which is so rich so a new way of damage of course and it's this correspondence between the object
you study and the process as a as a researcher think historian is also in the study of images
what Vabberg said mostly about images is that they were
subject to processes of van derungen migrations like a stamp it's wonderful a stamp because it's an
image which can go from a country with the enemy country crossing the border you can write to your
friend from Germany to Italy during the first world war this is the magic of images and it involved
the thinking of images as possibility of crossing the borders it's the reason I was interested in
this topic I agree with you about the importance of the notion of von derungen and I would say
to answer your question about the modernity here that is certainly something in which Warburg was
responding to his own time I mean not only posted stamps but also the other metaphors I mean just
like we're reusing these metaphors of territoriality which of course just territoriality crossing
borders the border guards this kind of thing but also he does write about he pays attention to
submarines and airplanes and he refers to tapestries as the vehicles or the well Farsawiga which could
be cars automobiles by which images images pass from one place to another so it's not only
the that images wander it's also the the vehicles or the means by which or the media and as we say
now by which they wander including prints and so he talks about the importance of prints and also
so-called decorative arts I mean small objects which were passed and which also carry images on them
so there's something about that which is very modern in that sense or would point to the notion
of modernity being also the invention of newer media or newer vehicles for the transmission
of images not just that they are transmitted or that they exist or that there's some psychic
reason why they're picked up but how they are and that would be I mean that is one reason why it
would be of interest you know to be I mean where one goes from that rather than recognize ah you
already thought about these things of course it goes back to what I you know to the question
that I was asking initially which is why you know why is he now of interest and why wasn't he of
interest because with all of this the history of the classical tradition and one thing that one
must say and that you would be very well aware as you mentioned Shastel and all the rest that the
history of when talks about the Renaissance that the history of the classical tradition and his
interest in it was something that was passed on and was regarded as important but all of these
other kinds of notions of how one would develop a broader conception not only in terms of opening
up to other disciplines opening up to neuroscience or whatever it might be but thinking about notions
of the Renaissance or cultural transmission as being something that was broader than in one place
broader than Italy than Florence's was something that was you could almost say or you were to
experience it suppressed in France or whatever so I mean that so that's interesting that that
comes back so maybe as a model it's important and certainly the modernity I don't know if Christopher
agrees with this or not it's part of that aspect of things and that's something that's also just
makes him a person in the 20th century at least as late 19th as opposed to for the early 19th
except that today it would be hard to find voices among his more progressive adherents
who still consider the engagement with antiquity to be the fundamental so there's a sense of there's
been a translation involved there's been a translation involved right that that that that
vobber didn't think anything in the middle ages you know he said it again and again he said that
they were you know he had it would would now be unacceptable he had it would now be an unacceptable
view of the middle ages namely that it was a period of kind of obscurantism you know limitation
spiritual blindness that was waiting its emancipation he speaks openly in those terms and the renaissance
for him was a heroic liberation of the human will Cassieira will pick up on this later remember
this is completely I mean it's relatively new it's I mean the term renaissance was coined only by
Michlé you know only you know less than 20 years really about 10 years before voborg was born
okay before then no one talked about the renaissance and then bork arts you know just a few years
after that produces his book this interest it launches the concept of the renaissance which by now is a
is a cliche so voborg it still feels fresh I think in the late 1880s to go to Florence and to identify
the quadricento as the matrix of the modern of the modern experience but that had to do with this
relationship to antiquity right and then as George was saying eloquently how it's striking how art
history as a discipline has allowed itself to be guided by the project of the renaissance itself
Panoschi said this explicitly he just said that's what it means to be a historian is to
is to inhabit two time frames at once and to and to and then to have them doubled so that when he
says the humanists already the the humanists in reviving antiquity already already predicting
panoschi who then studies the renaissance which so this is kind of recursive process this kind of
infinite regress where by each generation identifies a revivalist moment in a previous generation so
forth on and on backwards and this this sense of a kind of specular notion of history always
reflecting itself repeating itself maybe this is close to your transversals this I mean you know
this is this is this is voborg's renaissance to what extent is that still alive today I would say
that the voborg literature is split you know on the whole it's split between those who for whom
voborg the anachronist the survivalist the voborg the teller of ghost stories and so forth is still
the fundamental one and those who think that it's about neuroscience so to that extent I see this
panel as potentially a kind of space of um I don't know what resistance is too strong but
let's say a pause in the what seems to be the overall agenda of the conference but maybe I'm
wrong about that but one thing that you don't really bring up is that the renaissance artists
themselves were involved in antiquity they were involved in breeding ancient writings there was a
sort of a flow from ancient Greece to Italy it was kind of underground at that time but it was big
and it shows up in this greeny chapel the the jatto small corner or small figures in the corner that
are black and white or figures from antiquity and so on absolutely yeah
I apologize because I was late this morning so I missed some of the discussions but I had a
fascinating lunch with my friends of a genebra and one thing I can say is
something we as art historians we share with sacroanellists is both
the fact that for a psychoanalyst an image is not here or there it passes through
the second thing is about the uses of past past is not somewhere past is depends on the use we have
of the past so in um it's interesting that the renaissance is precisely a period in which two
models of the uses of the past were developed one is the nationalist one so to speak Vasari
Renaissance equals Tuscany that's all then there is the alternative the movement van der
ungen the work of Thomas for example so it's about the uses of the past some weeks ago I was in
Athens in Greece I went to the musical musical museum there was a bowl of eight century
before Christ with a beautiful swastika okay it's a motif it's linked to the motif we call Greek
okay now what happens I went out of the museum and I was able to observe the work of I don't know
in English L'ob d'Oré this nadzi party which is extremely efficient now in Greece and which uses
the swastika and the Greek motif and the swastika as a nationalist
discourse and I met some poets or filmmakers very very modern who use the past in a completely
different way so this is a question of use value it's not a question of uh uh renaissance is not
the renaissance is exactly what we do with this no it's very simple because I believe
Barbara thought that the past bore down on us that the past uh yeah governed us in a way we were
not there were limits on our freedom to use yeah but uh vabog is not the gods we can also read
Valter Benier along with vabog and make something which works too you agree I agree I don't
know the last I think Barbara gets god but I mean around here he's got a little bit uh certainly not god in London but one aspect that has that has been it tends to be referred in this premise as an art historian but I believe he defined himself as what he called a psycho historian or historian of the psychology of humanity so would you would you see that one aspect of art history would be precisely to diagnose the tensions of
humanity as recorded by by images of course I mean that's why I'm not sure whether the historical
sense is well developed in in the disciplines of the body I was fascinated by the fact that in the
before the second world war there is a kind of constellation of thinkers namely Kal Einstein
a bit barborg Valter Benier me so who plays the image at the center of the question of history
or even time at the same moment they placed the question of time at the center of the notion of
image just before the second world war what happened before after it's quite different but I am extremely
impressed that at this moment there was a kind of urgent emergency to think images through time and
to think time through images no but don't you think that the in order for the image to become a time traveler in the way
barborg describes it and you describe it doesn't the image have to be desycollegized it has to it has to
leave the body essentially it has to be externalized and and and become a formula so that it can move
freely right and to that extent it makes it a historical instrument but it also puts it beyond
the reach of the of the sciences of the body it seems to me therefore the interest to to look to
have a look to psychoanalysis I mean metastatic psychology as a way of desycologize the the the
structures of the yeah yeah psychoanalysis is a human eudic that's of course that's of course but
you speak of science you are laughing oh yeah as an artist this is simply not how it works
you know it's overly intellectualized it's a it's intellectual certainly being an artist as an
intellectual pursuit and historical pursuit it's also visceral and sexual and you're not
you're not talking about the juices you're like refining it into language and I'm missing
you know the guts of it because barborg wasn't interested in art he was interested in images
and in history but art for him had no meaning he never spoke about it I didn't know that no in fact
every time he always did it disparagingly he said oh that's that's that's that's aesthetics that's
for you s-thetes I'm interested in images and I'm interested in time and and and the past and so
forth if you're speaking about images though and the quetricental how can you separate art from images
doesn't exist he did he separated images from art he said I'm going to look at these as images
and whether they're works of art or or or or material culture that doesn't interest me the the
initial the initial question that is asked is a historical question but it's the answer given
is a psychological one and that may also affect the making of things in other words looking at
things abstractly he would say well what is the reason for the development of this style which is
he said that's what he says this station is and the psychology of the style why is there a change
not that there is a change which we could recognize by looking at images or looking not involved in
the process of making but looking to sequence of images saying this is different from that we see
the nymph here and there and then he looks and knows the nymph being there and he gives an explanation
which is and then that leads that can lead into other directions it doesn't necessarily so it's
not as a whether it's art or not it's it's the phenomenon that he's still trying to describe
which he's which is responding of course perhaps to a particular moment which described as being
style if you go something else with your doing but renaissance art i mean yes culturally but
i mean there are only there is only art to take images from and if you look if you spend any time
in seano or sec or uh florants you cannot help but observe how the work is made because they layered
pigment and with time sometimes some pigment has peeled off and some has come through it you know
a green has come through a white or whatever and all of that there's something about the making of
the work which the actual making makes the image the image isn't there before the making you're
completely right but that's not what vardard believed he wasn't interested in fabrication and he wasn't
interested in creativity it does contemporary art historian who inherit from the past what what to
do with with this would be the the question and if if i may just make quick observation you mentioned
sciences of the body i think referring to neuroscience the little i've read of neuroscientific literature
i find it very exciting because it's a literature that points out what the orientals knew very well
long before the 20th century and what the west knew before they came out that is body and mind
they're they're not two different entities they're constantly interconnected but i could name objects
of me of of study which are neither body nor mind namely texts or images they're not body or mind
they're external and i would propose that that's those are the entities that i deal with
not mind not mind's or body but it depends what you call psychology usually there is a big
distinction between uh wirthing and verbal from a formalist i cannot i think and i look at uh
andreopinote who knows very well these things that the difference is not so big i mean when
wirthing speaks about psychology it's not at all a question of ego what time my my choices what i
love my feelings no not at all it's fundamental it's a kind of anthropological psychology
it was the reason i i was recalling the meter psychology the Freudian one so this is very important
to make the distinction and just an quick answer to your question to your difference between
the intellectuals and the creative or i don't know i would say that verbo was as everybody it was
not only verbal verbo did very well he was working all the day and he was transforming things he was
constructing something a library writing organization of images making the work of art yes at the end
at the end one of the greatest painters of the 20th century Gerhard Hichter took the the the model
from verbo to make his own atlas so there is no no even better even better
of course he knows i agree i mean there is no there is a consistency
which begins in the 20th moholynaji did atlases lokorbusier did atlases everybody
so all the members are meant that it's true no it's not a question no no i don't mean maps
atlas the kind of professional like a death by thing in in in verbal atlas there is a temporary to start
very important thing i mean that is never about text the text be important because it brings to mind
it brings to our kind of body and mind something otherwise the text is so many and the images for
for vowels and by all is in the absence of collective in the absence of religion don't forget that he
was because i already mentioned by our friend from los angeles he was in a simulated family that
kept Judaism at home he refused to participate in it i must say that i was also very good friend of his
niece of her in the battle in Rome for four years and i know this detail is very intimately
and his attempt to his fantasy was to reconstruct the co-activity human justice correct to cultural
cultivated way and he believed in you simply you can say naively then by coming to town with the
longest possible path you can reconstruct the co-act form for human life in the absence of religion
in the absence of collective identity with which you could identify it that for me there was no
co-activity got any further and that is the grand purpose of this art history very different
fundamentally different from both are very very great you're right you better be on psychology
of style so thank you for if i appreciate your comments and i consider that the discussion has
been stimulating enough and you've been stimulated by it but what i would prefer is you wait until
the round table finishes their discussion and then we open for comments and questions otherwise if
everybody start jumping in we'll have a problem i also wanted to just remind you that this is about
classical and renaissance art i wanted to come back to one thing that you were saying yes that is
that is if and indeed i can't recall the exact places where he was taking things from but if
if we were to go with him to with warberg to florants we would have not only been looking at you know
the parucio bardi chapels of the cajada we would also be going to the bargello but not to look at
the paintings in the bargello but at the door knockers and the locks and that kind of thing and the
and the and the those are you bring up my very point yeah now as an artist you know um i didn't
grow up in america i grew up in um i i grew back in montreal and life was as much uh juicier in a
certain way the butter was real the bread was real my family they talked about what they had eaten
yesterday what they were going to eat today and what they would eat tomorrow and it was very it had a
reality to it a real reality and when i'm in italy or an aspect of france as well i can sense the
same thing that they were they were the images they're making are a living they're part of their life
and of course there's a journals of pran tormel talk the way my family talked exactly and uh and
they're very concerned with of a food is medicine in the way that to eat healthily was to live longer
and um i think it's very important to talk about this in relation to the images
i also speaking a little bit out of turd i i think that rickter when he built his
complex of buildings was i think we should stick to the renaissance and well i did but it is i'm
talking about warberg you know i think it it was a warberg associated the buildings that people
the same idea as the library
i mean we you were mentioning a verbose notion of the renaissance which is quite outdated now
or not not followed by by current scholarship and indeed if you if you study the renaissance
you realize that so many texts written in the middle ages were still published were still active
if you look at the at the reception of classical art one way of looking at the ways in which
renaissance artists receive classical classical artists to look at the demand of religious
art which the amount increasing realism increasing physical presence to convey the image of a suffering
god etc so basically what is what does remain of our work stuff and the renaissance for the present
for the present um i live in paris and so in paris now there is a wonderful
exhibition about renaissance which comes from Florence so here there is everything i love
donatello it's wonderful really wonderful um kind of uh focus is done about
the model of roman republic in a 15th century uh florantin renaissance and it is shown through
some manuscripts and uh okay good perfect yeah at the end there is the so-called nicolo daudzano
now attributed to deziderio de cetinho and not donatello
i mentioned that nowhere in the very big catalogue in the discourse of curators nowhere
there is a mention to what verbogin produced in 1902 namely the famous boate the ex-voto's
of la santissima anunceta which were a kind of artisanal religious vulgar
kitch oful in deziderio of madam tussos but it was it was an hyper realism the kind of which
um Alessandro Baronqui spoke about about the realism of the first renaissance uh already in 14th
century so verbog introduced the fact that confronting the actual images which you can see in museums
which were kept through the curatorial work of of viserie and the museum etc so you have
masterpieces but all these objects ex-voto's were destroyed in 17th century and the
the the the big work of verbog was to interpret the actual objects which are masterpieces along with
vulgar objects which all disappeared this is a masterpiece of anthropology but now in a big
exhibition on renaissance there is no mention of this despite the fact that to understand the
nickele of the odes anor you need these ex-voto which themselves are linked to the famous roman
republican model of the imaginess so there is something which does not work today these
exhibitions are just the entertainment industry they have nothing to do with uh yes but sexuality
but okay you're just making a comment i just make a because but there is a very big catalog of
specialies and so on but this is a critical point i would say but why verbog today but to speak
again about the ex-voto's you know there's another part of the exhibition which i saw in
Florence which also involves making but also this question of transmission of images not only the
images where they're repeated a memorable room in which there are all the terracadas and casts
so that um suggesting how uh and very interesting also from point of view of art and making things
how the same image is repeated x number of times and then i think it's something that you definitely
um you know we're much more conscious of that as a result perhaps of a long tradition but again
not not going back to this whole why this was done in the first place however uh seeing
seeing the renaissance as warberg might have done that is to say for the transmission of images
in a different way in terms of materiality in terms of making which is what you might have
been interested in which you uh as Christopher says wasn't uh so uh was so concerned concerned
with the question of um making things i mean actually going back to your point that is also of
course how we are much different i mean you know now than than then uh one thing i quite right
about uh making objects in the past sculpture painting whatever took a long time you know you
had to grind your pigments still does well you well particularly if you had to grind your pigments
and you had to find your pigments and you had to find your pigments and you had to find your
pigments and you had to mix them with the medium etc and you had to prime your canvas and all that
or if you have to make paper and making paper and preparing paper and making the drawing
implements or whatever that's why drawing old drawings are small they couldn't make big paper
well paper is valuable too yeah but uh so i mean there's all all of that which is also
uh an experience that we don't have although he would have had it and been more related to it
that's the the shocking thing now of course is uh as we're aware is the older crafts have gone
or the number of places that are gone so that it's increasingly difficult even to repair objects
not just talking with somebody who is a store there and very few places that even exist in the
place like Florence where you know you where if you remember what it was like in the past where you
know you can wear furniture is made where a frame was repaired or can be made relatively speaking
to what you know one over experience a hundred years ago or 150 years ago it's so interesting
in my studio when I hire assistants it used to be that they knew how to stretch canvas and
jesso and now they know how to make websites things just to elaborate on what you're saying
but when I started wandering around Florence was uh the first time was in 66 and a lot of the old
Florence was still there there was a place where you could buy pigment ground pigment and it
didn't it burned down in about 1974 but for a long time I bought pigments there and and
there were there was a wonderful color I mean this isn't a side of Renaissance color
called capuchin yellow which is really pink which was made by the capuchin monks it's just an
incredible material but when I started wandering around I did I actually did a mural that's in
um a bun fresco that's in um main and it's based on the virtues of good government
and so I was studying sienna up and down and spending a lot of time there and I was interested
in the fact that the bank of the sienna was the first bank in Europe and that that tradition had
actually in a certain way come from Egypt via Greece I mean that's the I'm making a lot of shortcuts
to Italy when when the Medici brought the Greeks over to teach the Italians how to paint because
they had lost that skill through invasions and uh all of that I find you know that that whole legacy
uh what happened in Egypt and how it went to Greece and how was brought to Florence and how those
images that we all adore came about that way if I made I think that's an extremely important
comment and coupled with with with with with Thomas remarks about uh transmission and uh and
George on the transversals and the traveling images and so forth we're probably all arrived at a sense
today of a kind of permanent multiplex flow of ideas and images that knit culture together and
therefore we would probably I would think be willing to relativize the epochal significance of the
Renaissance it is to say uh maybe be unwilling to join VAR board in his celebration of the Renaissance
as a as as a fundamental emancipation right because the ex-vodos after all continue straight through
from antiquity straight through the Middle Ages to the Renaissance the forms that you were referring
to travel straight through they're constantly being imported and transmitted and translated and so
forth so then why privilege the Renaissance as he did and that would be that would be the question
I would ask again I mean who who's willing to allow that um perception of an elective affinity
that the Renaissance felt with antiquity classical antiquity you want us to talk about the classical
and I think we should because um who's willing to let that elective affinity between the Renaissance
that is to say European modernity and classical antiquity be a guiding principle and use a rhetoric
of emancipation liberation and so forth though human will human freedom and so forth it seems
very important because not everybody's willing to give up on the idea of human freedom psychoanalysis
is about freedom it seems to me well I'd like to sort of dive in uh I think that the idea of the
Renaissance is is an art historians idea actually I think what artists were living was a continuum
from Egypt through Greece to through Rome through classical Rome
yeah I'm reading a book forever which is because it's very hard to read
calm it's about drawing and it's about a different kind of perspective
than Renaissance perspective and so clearly there was a whole different field of perspective going on
before three point perspective and afterwards so and this is coming from Egypt Greece Renaissance
so I think you know the idea that you know these bunch of English men suddenly discovered the
Renaissance you know is because probably England was really dull and you know and here's this juicy
painting going on and especially when you I mean the whole idea of calling the Mannerous Mannerous
as as Nied Remark and sort of like the Big Bang kind remark is you know they were shocked by the
homosexuality in in Mannerous painting which you know is a very English thing to be shocked at since
there was a high frequency of homosexuality in England well there's something highly
suspect about the whole late 19th century cult of the Renaissance centered in Florence and you
know you might ask what is the isn't it significant that Varbog is an intellectual gravitate towards
Florence in the 1890s and not Paris right Paris is was the center of the intellectual world for
for any for any intellectual and and and Varbog is Paris ophobic right instead it's Florence where
he's in the meteor of Walter Pader Berenson he wasn't friends with Berenson but and many many
others who are all taking refuge from modernity basically taking refuge from technological modernity
taking refuge from the vulgarity of America taking refuge from also German romanticism I believe
so there's a triple threat there I'm talking about Henry James and Sargent and all the rest of it
so the rest they invented the Renaissance yeah but I don't think artists thought about that
you know I think you know they were living art and living I mean artists no matter where they
they're using videotapes they're involved in art history and they know what's going on and they're
you know absorbing it some are more knowledgeable than others but it's always it's always a threat
through everything perhaps there's one problem with Renaissance artists when you read the artistic
literature of the Renaissance is that they never talk about making and they really conceal the
aspect of making and technique from from the literature that they produce but Leonardo is never
published is not published until the late 17th century and these are his personal notes if you
look at the published literature it's about invention disposition by subject by Alberti by
Paul Opino by a lot of the literature he's talking about perspective he's talking about perspective
but that's an intellectual thing that's automatic that's optics perspective and in fact what what
strikes me in that discussion one of the contribution of our works precisely in perspective was optics
Renaissance is also connected but it is connected to optics if you read the beginning of the La
Pittura Alberti explained the visual rays as something optic that goes from the eye and it's based on
but anyway that's an academic discussion what I just would like to emphasize is that it seems
that the verbal doesn't take for granted the message of Renaissance artists who are responsible for
that distinction between so-called decorative art and fine arts and precisely that that's one of the
use of a verbal to take the image as a matter of well if neither as a body nor as a mind but I'm
not quite sure as what but certainly at something that travels across media and that should be studied
through its traveling across media it recalls me a discussion about the the question why
the Natello didn't have a foundry studio of its own a gibberti had the Natello no so you can
interpret it and especially the one of the most the Natello's masterpiece the Judith
is made by various studios of foundry bronze how do you say found so you can interpret in
two different manners you can say the Natello is now a Renaissance artist in this sense he is an
intellectual so he does not touch the bronze foundry the material and he lives he conceived and
the artisans are his assistants and he's the intellectual artist why not it's it's a good
interpretation but insufficient the other interpretation to complete this one is to say
he was so interested in the material because if you look at the Judith the face is completely
classic classic but there is a mold there is elements of gothic there is elements of hyperrealism
there in the same sculpture so he needed various ways to deal with the material
so this is wonderful this is the Renaissance for me and by the way has to do with money then
just as it is now is it the person with their own money had their own money money money money
and money in space i mean because if you think about money in space yeah money money in space
because you think about what was happening in the in the 16th century some people had foundries
in their own studio and others and the ship not and money is not a sufficient explanation no money
okay but if you look at the Natellos in general it's not by chance that in the diacrony the
differences of style you find the same in the single Judith so it's not only a question of money
oh money money can i say something about the classical i don't know whether this how
you know how this will strike you but how would it change things if i made the proposition and
and you agreed with this the viborgh scholars agreed with this that viborgh didn't actually
know much about classical antiquity that his classical antiquity for him was a known a known
quantity a fixed quantity he knew what every cultivated person knows i'm not sure he knew much
more about classical antiquity than say Freud did and it would i think would be instructive to
compare their images of antiquity that essentially his he was able to construct the system of
world's psychohistory of art that he did because antiquity remained a stable quantity he didn't
go too deeply into it he used only cliched images i would say that for vabor classic art classic was
the contrary that classic was for vincalmon for vincalmon classic was a norm a normatability
for vabor classic meant a way of instability classic means instability for him
this is the instability of greek tragic for vaborgh i i a mistake oh sorry sorry for vaborgh
it's instability so um once away once again it's about what do you do with the past
it's not about a news better i agree with you it for him classic is is kind of matrix it's a matrix
if i may just bring there's another element of metric which is in the classification of the
library and it begins with primitive art and then it's followed by pre-story card and then
classical art so there's this sense that primitive art even if it's something made in australia in
the 19th century should be put in a section before the historical section which are arranged
chronologically rather than alphabetically yes you you you're saying that this is the
doctrine of survival like the british folklorists right whom he was very influenced by that that
modern folkloric customs in rural england counted as archaic art archaic customs right yeah yeah
it might not be correct but that's certainly a starting point right that makes a classification
of knowledge so it right indeed that's right and yet that that notion is overlaid upon a in fact
a rather conventional bourgeois conception of what classical art was which included all the
the agitated and tragic features yeah but they're also in vinkleman's canon i mean the you know the
lachlan is he for for for vibor right it's right in the 1905 duress he ends it by talking about the
lachlan and the main ads and the and and all of these figures they're they're all in vinkleman's
canon it's not as if he's expanding the canon of ancient art he's just flipping through
illustrated books about ancient art and picking the images he likes which happens to be the
agitated ones but but there is a very thorough so to speak reception of antiquity in the 19th
century if you look at flobere salambo and the temptation of centantony it's not at all a calm
and our monious antiquity on the contrary it's a delirium for emotion color violence blood i mean
everything in donatello it is like in flobere it is completely chaotic this is the point i
like to throw a little bit of a wrench into what you're saying uh that's my role here
uh i think the way in which museums to this day categorize so-called primitive art
is they don't quite know what to do with it and since you know we are the white imperialists
right and we know everything right why are these funny yellow people black people
red people making work that you can recognize as art i mean the metropolitan is put together
that way and it sounds like the warburg museum was put together that way too i mean there's no
sense of equality between different kinds of people none well we're already as concerned that's
there there's a point that touches on to the whole problem of an also an older idea of anthropology
which may be one of the reasons of course why warburg has regained some interest because it's
supposedly owns onto anthropology as uh we're becoming increasingly sensitive the notion that
the others are those who don't have history that's uh you know they do have history of course
some of course of course of course of course but what i'm saying is that that older
anthropological idea that ethnology or ethnography was a study of other peoples because those people
showed us what we were like when we were in the past and therefore history has stopped in those
parts of the world where supposedly uh progress has not come and others who don't have machines
or whatever it might be but it's always artists that would pick up so-called primitive art like
pakaso and and treat it as contemporary art and i i wonder if that's another actually a sort of a
problem behind some of the assumptions of warburg's work you know i think so going to going to New
Mexico and so forth but and and and actually brings up a question i wanted to ask to this group
because one of the ways in which why would have answered is the question of why warburg's of
generally of interest but i'll bring it back to the renaissance question and relate it to what we
were talking about a minute ago is uh that as you said he's nomencl it's been said that his
writing is enigmatic you could say that it was vatic that it's a prophetic and so it's like
banyam and you can read a lot into it you can read what you want but um i wonder if there aren't
some other things that can be said about that about why this is um attractive now that is to say
war uh yeah um and uh um if uh there is uh this kind of uh tension that is to say the idea of how
there's an underlying presence which is always there and something else uh in terms of the renaissance
too the assumption and what does it mean therefore uh what when we have a dual kind of meaning this
relates to both of the things that we've been talking about warburg says on the one hand
whether they say Athens and uh Oribi always won uh and then but at the same time using Athens
perhaps in another way he says uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh uh
Athens once once to be conquered again back from Alexandria again and again i mean what does Athens
mean in both of these instances the same yeah it just means low logos yeah reason as
a star astra asta so um so and now is andry is a
is a meta-linear is not right but it used to it used to be Jerusalem but he switched it to
Alexandria to orientalize in a non-Jewish way yeah um but uh we're thinking of Oribi also being
what is always present underneath why why does it want to be why does it what do you how do you
interpret the vial the vola the the wanting why and how does that relate to the renaissance in
some sense that's that will to freedom that what wants to be reconquered from uh Alexandria wants
to be delivered from the clutches of the oriental uh bottle you know somaticism and drives and
some work right i mean and that's still how he's i mean we didn't even talk about that but that's
still how he saw the in i mean the renaissance for for him was this you know this uh this this
connection across time back to you know back to uh back to logos overcoming whether we're medieval
demons as well not perhaps it is also the fact that uh it is strange in vabo that when he speaks
about uh archaism primit archaism greek archa it's never greek archaic art it's always
alexandrin i i mean elenistice period always the laocoon style the peregamon you know so it's not
a cake at all for a history on the point of view of the history of greek art but for him this is the
so alexandrin alexandrin should mean something with this kind of no i think his point is the classical
yes i think his point is the classical greek art alexandrinized itself and sort of allowed itself to be
contaminated by the oriental and that's what unleashed all these kind of baroque passions
which then needed to be tamed by by the renaissance which received them and corrected them
thank you
vaboque chose the renaissance as his focus his trap point or maybe the renaissance chose
vaboque um to speak to chris's point precisely because it was the period in which the oscillation
both the temporal and spatial oscillation between what he called the phobic legacy
and the mathematical resulted most clearly in batonin heights in in in this prudencia this
moment in which um a kind of clear-eyed wisdom could exist and therefore the classical ideal
was revivified but the renaissance has the double or the meta value that
it revivifies that classical ideal once removed and then you put vaboque as twice removed and so
he is able to as it were see himself reflected in that renaissance doubling
which raises the question of where we are now right one step further removed
which wing which which factions among the vaboque um literature are participating in that
specular regression regressive process in which are abandoning it and setting up other beachheads
occupying other beachheads i would be in the neuroscience well i don't want to do it
no i think it's more complicated than that certainly the neuro i would say the neuro biological
i mean i don't want to label it so much but this kind of it that aspect of interest in vaboque
is not interested in these questions of history that's all i was saying at the beginning and it
except in so far as the memory is the place where it's way unique
or other places too that's the place that person appears to me
mm-hmm maybe
first of all a quick comment to as your your um
reference to psychology which is i completely agree a very ambiguous word if you use it
referring to authors like very flin whose prolegomena to a psychology of architecture
uh work characterized as psychology without psyche because they are very symmetological and this is
true for many authors of the ein film theories as well he'll the brand fish authors very well
known to to vaboque um my question refers to your very dense paper of this morning
um and particularly on the notion of symptom which is crucial and central to the paper and to
the whole of your reflection and particularly to the polarity opening closing because if i think
of the notion of symptom as used in ordinary language but also in the discourse of the medical
discourse in therapy perhaps even in psychotherapy and in psychoanalytical discourse
symptom is referred to one manifestation of the body fever for example that can have different
causes so the in the medical semiotics you see something an image of the body the rush the red
the high temperature and you have to close the perspective because you have many i.t.i. many
causes and you need to close the perspective the optics until you have found the cause that
determines that symptom on the contrary if i understand well your position and your hermeneutics of the
symptom leaning on vaboque it seems to me that the use of symptom here is here is rather the opposite
it's not closing the perspective closing it on a single meaning because if we take a patos former
it is symptomatic but it is a bodily posture the nymph the manad that can be inversed and
transformed into a christian makdalene like in bertol vudijovani or the serpent that can be
a sign of pathology of evil and a sign of therapy a far macon so in this second perspective that
seems to me yours and verbal perspective symptom and perhaps even froy's perspective symptom is
not closing to a single cause but rather opening up the image to its possible multiple meanings
you know that it is a big question of course i began on this problem
um long ago studying and confronting charco's notion of symptoms and froy's one
it seems to me that the difference between them one could be said positivist and the other
okay for a new way of you find the same in art history the exactly the same
I love the essay by ginsburg about the the clues the indexical but he does not recognize
this battlefield so perhaps i invent a battlefield or if i am wrong or he does not recognize there is
a fundamental difference um you have fever the doctor comes and says uh influencer okay when
you have the name you have the solution because there are some medicine for influencer
you are in front of painting from the
the some collection in parma your name is morality and you say it's i don't know lon franco okay
the name means the solution symptom is an enigma and the name is a solution you have a series of
portraits and through a big graphic analysis you say he is loreann so the image is he is the son
the first son etc this is a kind of interpretative way
uh linked to this first interpretation of what is the symptom the second is of course in my mind
influenced by psychoanalysis i would say if you i am not an analizan but i'm sure that if you go
to a psychoanalysis and one day you say it's mama mami it's not the end of the interpretive
process perhaps it's the beginning and so is art history when you recognize a name an attribution
a signification iconography it's not the end it's the beginning this is my view and i think
there is a big struggle today without even which is not named as such between the symptom in the
first sense so to speak closing and the opening one the most delusian so to speak most rheismatic if you
want
isn't that implicit in your notion of transversal that is metonymic
completely much like delusian fall which may be a single thing but it opens up
absolutely absolutely yeah i'm glad you just opened up a bridge which i wanted to speak about
i'm i'm kind of the devil in between i'm a painter and an art historian and when i was very young
i studied with i guess varbergian influence art historians like the toenai and vittkover
and panofsky was there and oscar christella i wasn't ready for all of them but what i want to say
it opened up a world for me because it formed a kind of armature or a bridge to inter inter
disciplinary worlds because here i suddenly saw the renaissance as an integrated culture where
we got literature and philosophy and all the different disciplines came together and it it
performed amazing kind of mystery for me of how to delve how to get into the intercesses of all
these fields and find a transmission of culture a kernel of culture i never took it literally
and of course we all criticized gombrick for calling primitive art and later it became tribal art
and of course there was a lot of christianists and a lot of problems with with um
um with what we call tribal art today an archaic art but it gave me a sense of how can culture be
contained it's contained in the word but it can also be contained in images so though it's not
the way painters will often discuss a painting it had it gave it another dimension and that
dimension um should be opened up that dimension of a transmission of a total culture um there are
um there are some painters today that attempt that uh unselylm kefer maybe kentridge a few who
attempt to kind of cultural transmission through imagery uh or as or just what we're talking about
now association so that there are there's no such thing as a closed image it's infinite in it
it's historical line lineage and we can go back and forth so it has in it to me speaking also of
bothlyn who was fascinating and i fascinating because he gave words for um for the beginning
of exploring a painting open and closed forms of course he said baroque renous a contrast at
everything we don't have to contrast it as simply but it is an interesting way of perceiving uh is
there such thing as a more closed culture and a more open culture or ways of talking about things
so i think this tradition is very important uh as again as a vessel for culture and shouldn't be
the dichotomy of artists and art historians and scholars should be opened up in a much freer way
and speaking well oh that's that's enough
i i i don't um object to the basic uh statesman by panofsky that art history is a humanistic
discipline i don't object to this uh this article by panofsky and artist uh scientist genius it's
the title artist savagini yes it was about the humanism as de cluison mo how do you say
what is the compartment? the compartment so the in the age of renaissance we have a new kind of
interdisciplinarity so to speak this is wonderful okay uh i am uh i was born to so to speak in the
stricturalist french school at this time uh it was useful to say the humanism is over
i don't agree with this i agree with a very much revolutionary french writer whose name is
josh batai who said that we need a more he says it's a quotation we need a more complete humanism
and he meant we need a humanism which includes the ineshive mo how do you say
incompleteness what is to say of course we need the hypothesis of the unconscious that's all
you know that's all can i just add i mean i very much appreciate what you said because you've
been introduced a term which has been absent from our panel it should have been here and that's
the concept of a cultural cultural history or kulturvissenshaft is the germans called it a
total study of culture which within which varburg loom is very large and it's an ongoing process
and subject today of much debate about what would be an updating of this of this project that you
so well described and experienced the only objection i would have and it's a little bit parallel to
to josh and i would invoke not batai batai de gur who said of the humanists in his letter on
humanism he said the problem with humanism is that its conception of man is not elevated enough
it's this parallel he and batai were contemporaries and a parallel concept of the of the incompleteness
of the project and to that extent i would object the only objection i would have is to the very
concept of culture because the concept of culture it seems to me presupposes already an ideal of
how it should turn out but the culture in fact is something we haven't achieved and we'll probably
never achieve culture is some kind of this total connectedness so i don't i don't think that works
of art can transmit a culture or that they can in any way kind of deliver a culture to us they are
simply attempts or steps towards some kind of project called culture
i meant a historical evolution development by the word
the positivity of things that have existed right
okay okay but the word is in the in high degrees debate with casser and in barberges involved here
because remember varborg is you know casser's close to varborg and identifies his project with
varborg in high degrees debate with casser that's what it comes down to whether culture is is
something we can start with or whether we need to end with it but that wasn't necessarily the
line that one had to take because they were also close to boas here close to close to boas boas here
the anthropology here i mean in new york and that would that would have been another
lie i mean culture is the way you would have heard us and understood here in new york and uh as
you know the other side of the anthropology is being developed which also then enters into the
frang anthropology and so forth so it's uh it doesn't have to be the line you're describing as
as in which shall we say the mandarin view of five inch class
happy yeah just just a short comment um many elements that came from this uh afternoon very
interesting discussion i think point uh or brother to put it slightly differently convince me even
more why we still need fraud and perhaps why we need more varborg in a way i think in
the present moment what is really of the incredible importance uh is uh to focus on images
their power their pervasive presence in our life i i take this to be even more important than
their supposed aesthetic quality because and uh there is a trend which keeps going on
so to speak the more or less explicit tendency to sterilize images to reassert the necessity to
have a subject and an object to externalize images so that we can contemplate uh uh for
hand then so to speak but uh the problem is they are simultaneously very much through hand then
and this through hand the night of images speaks in my opinion also from the very narrow peeping
hole that our level of description allows that of neuroscience they uh put us into question uh so
they are not just the external object or contemplation but they look at us so there is a
charismatic relationship between the image and the beholder and to make full sense of that i think
uh we need uh approaches uh like that of a fraud and and varborg they specifically focus on this
aspect that that needs to be more and more uh at the center of uh of our reflection now i think
and what do you think about phenomenology i mean for the but what's about uh merlot pointi
uh which i'm very fond of the late merlot pointi visible and invisible and particularly um i see
there is uh more and more people are are looking back to merlot pointi um in film theory for example
in this country there are people like vidian subject uh that since maybe 20 years with carnal
thought has brought back phenomenology and particularly merlot pointi in the debate of uh of film theory
uh the publication of his notes for the course uh the collage difference uh the word of expression
and i don't remember exactly the the english title uh that has been recently published
marocarbonne for example in lion is working uh and uh this is perfect for also for for guiding our
approach uh to our relationship to images so i think this uh reversibility of the relationship
between the image and the beholder is something that uh can be inspired by by barber approach beside
uh as i said uh phenomenology so and i i'm i'm pretty much convinced that the debate on on images
will be more and more uh uh focusing on this aspect also because of the real volatile nature of an
aesthetic definition of an image uh as an artistic one everybody seems to be aware of that nowadays
thank you can i say something just uh a small point reacting to your discourse
um if we take seriously the lesson of the phenomenological lesson uh through i mean even
beansbanker which tells merlot pointi lacco we must say that the the relation the visual relation
is complexified when lacan said you are looked by i am looked by you
uh the the the the the the the visual relation the the gaze is also something which is not only
frontal it's a complexification of our our work and i mean when we study a work of art
especially for example or renaissance one we are extremely interested in what happened
in the space what space the cell the the the palazzo what happened of course the painting here
the tapestry but what happened there what was the specialty uh to look at is not only to look at one
point i think do you agree yes in fact that that makes a very nice foundation for an art history
which we normally artists are intent to try to find out who did what for who mapped our march
and when but then the next step is then with all this what is looking at us but that certainly
doesn't exclude finding out the you know contract documents it's fundamental to reconstitute
that's still that is looking at us and that is not of course yeah what are the conditions
in which it were made and what was happening of course um i mean in terms of all kinds of things
that could be said or not about indeed about as we were talking earlier about the speed in which
something was made in other words of people are traipsing through the space where you're trying
to work all the time that's going to slow you down or if there's all kinds of other work going on
and what's happening if they're putting indoors or windows where you're trying to paint your
wall and that's happening for one reason or another or they're trying to conduct services in the very
place where you're working and so forth so all of that kind of thing is also related which is also
some things that we don't necessarily talk about but in a way uh the things that were opened in a
sense by warberg in terms of some of the aspects of cultural history and the other sense of what
goes on in it what goes on in the space uh yeah it's interesting it goes back to images so i was
just thinking about the other aspects of things it may be because we do have just to go back to
dr kiwije's so initial comments it may be because we do have this instrumentarium of uh imagery that's
so great that we talk about images rather than actually objects because the artifacts or what
whether they're art or not what we always you know what artifacts are the pro are what makes
culture i mean culture consists of artifacts now there i guess there could be visual artifacts too
but you know there's still there's still things that are man-made and that's it's
whether or not that's going to change the discussion that is to say that you have images which do not
exist in a in a materials in a material way and warberg could i don't think warberg envisioned that
he was still talking about prince carrying the image or whatever and the photograph carrying the
image but yeah i'd like to say a little bit about what you're saying about gays something that
interests me very much about the Italian Renaissance art in churches uh is that the way
to go into contemporary art the way french artists made paintings still lives and so on
in the 19th century you you go right into the picture plane but with Renaissance art you do not
the work is hung high and it looks at you the different gaze
okay and i'm sorry
my name is saffron hula saffron i'm a professor of architecture at columbia university and they
uh i have run with my students workshop on how to design redesign the bob institute
as part of columbia imagining that at the time when the institute had to move from Berlin to
london it didn't move to london perhaps we now realize that that london perhaps was not the best
choice considering the fact that the university is prepared to disperse the library just threatening
it's still threatening it's still threatening so we decided to design a place for the bob institute
at columbia and so we looked at many aspects of the physical aspect of storing images
and even in the half i know i now know that it takes two cubic meters as a physical form
to store it and the fact that historically there was a connection with columbia because
when bob was on his way to visit new mexico he spent some time with bars bars was a
anthropologist from Berlin who started the first department of anthropology in american
universities and bars invited bobwood to come and speak at columbia accepted
bobwood in the meantime which i and therefore couldn't have and this led me directly to the
question of consolgia i think it's still be confusing for everybody including yourself
probably to mention lacan in the same branch because like what nobody would call a concon
from the other hand i think that they they for my point of view a
pathological chance it would be much better to understand
bobwood in technological challenge than any other challenge precisely there isn't even
a kind of solid background today because he was in contact with ludic bingsbanger as we know
ludic bingsbanger treated him over many years and ludic bingsbanger after all was the first
psychiatrist who takes technology on board reading both whose words aim honey and so that
should have meant quite a lot and it seems to me up to this moment that this has not yet
filtered through and perhaps that's one of the reasons didn't feel that through is
uh the authority of uh grombick because grombick famously wrote as the director of
the bob institute he wrote a book on uh vahu in which he more or less dismissed him as a serious
artist of uh grombick was totally committed to prepare the point of view and from prepare the
prepare point of view none of the thesis of a bobwood made sense about all empathy didn't make sense
and couldn't stand a kind empirical verification not at the time of but of of gromb by now we have
to be a new audience that basically this is a little bit more appealing to the basis not to me I mean I
wrote the thesis of a body uh a body and embodiment from a logical point of view in 1972 which meant
that I had a good basis to approach art from an equal point of view and I was responsible for art
in in the studio for the work of school art at the time that was um you know obstetric for some
on the other hand don't it I dislike you in the application I like you very much but I think I
like I like it because it's you and because it's bound to a kind of rich intellectual of the last
10 years you see the problem of culture as nature or in point art is the balance between the external
in term when the Germans in Berlin built an instant museum and thought that by collecting great
object of art artifacts from the high point of Greek culture they could guarantee their own culture
and tradition obviously they make a big mistake because they believe the possession of these things
is in itself guaranteed for some kind to in fact I made this joke when it was recently
uh restored they instantly said they would chip it with the English architect was responsible
for the French which is a masterpiece but I said to him you see the program of this museum was to
safeguard certain quantization obviously the structure of it is approved of an historical fact that it
did not have to safeguard any culture any visualization the state of crime tried to have a collection
of so-called anti-culture right it's a considerable collection it turned out that it wasn't a different
whole state what does it tell us it tells us that it doesn't matter that's what it tells us because
for him this object that were fake and obviously he never died to distinguish between me treated
them as authentic works but he didn't matter he didn't matter just it doesn't matter how you write
go without you in the famous book that the handwriting of garbou was unwritten it would not be said
so Edgar Wayne in the famous league in anonymous or you in the theater at the time you know you
could write the news anonymously and Edgar Wayne wrote interesting on one hand you claim you can
read barbou and writing on the other hand you claim that he's included so either is claimed
in confide with that so i think the secret of barbou is precisely can be understood best
infineargica terms in serelian terms in which according to which the photos cannot the image
is residual is only like letters are not important in themselves as the Chinese say
when you want to fish a fish you make a nice road and a nice something at the end of the
thread to capture the fish but once you cut the fish the road and all the rest of no interest
i just can answer about paris i mean lacquer okay
okay can i answer to the just about if you think the recourse to lacquer is confusing
perhaps it's because you think that paris is a territory but paris is like new york it's a
place of cost-popolitism i want to recall that the french so so called french thought french
stretch regularism i want to recall that michael fuckel began his work translating carefully
Ludwig bizvanger i want to recall that lacquer uh dedicated a lot of time to translate martin
heidegger and Freud of course and there are there were many connections especially between lacquer
and bizvanger because as you know bizvanger died in the 60s i think in the even in the 70s perhaps
i don't remember but a great psychoanalyst french one whose name is pia fredida who is not
translated into english i guess was precisely the man who was able to go between between lacquer
and bizvanger fredida was the assistant and bizvanger at kreutlingen so there is no isolation of lacquer
and parisianism there is a link between uh profound link between uh french philosophy french
structuralism and german psychiatric
i want to make a distinction between the phandology of melopontic is incompatible with the phandology
of heidegger heidegger was in principle and he says so you know in contrast is a is a
turning turning upside down huster yeah but for t is much more in the huster egan
yeah but contrast contrast is dialogue that is in the way for example we contrast but we dialogue
i think the two of you should fight this after the meeting we set aside a room for you to do this
two quick and really efficient points for your response um following on the idea of uh students
designing uh warberg library at columbia long before that in 1933 even as all the books and
artifacts were being packed up there was a very real possibility and i invite you to imagine
if that had happened where we would be right now at 17 east eightieth street the paul warberg
house was offered as the home of the ab warberg library paul warberg died in early 1932 um he
was my great grandfather his brother ab had died in 1929 i think but 33 they're packing up the
library where can it go london was originally seen simply as a safe harbor phillics warberg
another brother put up half a million dollars 1933 dollars to finance this library and it was
going to happen and the state department put sand in the gears the state department memo exists
saying there was a fear that it could stir anti-semitism in new york if this german library had come here
so i am i'm so it stayed in london where it where it was parked so i invite you to imagine
the warberg library here in new york cross-pollinating with the analytic community that was arriving
all through the thirties assisted in part by ab warberg's niece patina warberg who was once
someone who walked the halls of the new york cycle analytic what would the warberg library
have been like and what would his influence have been like without gombrick annihilating
the legacy of ab warberg in and undercutting him in that fascinating way um the other
point to consider and i'm anticipating tomorrow obviously but i find it curious that we could talk
talk about in such a fascinating way ab warberg's relationship to history and his sense of the past
bearing down on us when you consider that his flight into madness that precipitated this day
uh at bellview in the treatment by bens vanger was in fact his sense in his intersection of
psychosis and brilliance that by delving into antiquities he had stirred these angry spirits
and started world war one he felt responsible uh among other mad thoughts but he specifically
thought that it had to do with his delving into the past so would welcome response
it's i want to return but perhaps it is a program for tomorrow for the next year
uh to the question of the torio galese uh it is important because we are here in the
psychoanalytic new york psychoanalytic society and institute and i think the question was
very central why we need fraud why we need verbog and between these two fields of research
it is an intersection and for me the intersection today was really the question of unconscious
what is the place of unconscious in the process of creation and in the process of interpretation
of the creative work unconscious and drive we can say unconscious in memory it is the question
of the trace and the relation to the time which is very central in our discussion a lesson about
time and survival apre coup afterwards i don't know exactly how to translate always apre coup
and the question of drive is also patos formal and the question of gaze in the division between gaze
and eye it is important in lack of phenomenology like on this question with meadow point three about
the question of the opposition between gaze and eye and i think it is in this distinction that we
have the resistance to the image it's really central we were discussing together a few minutes ago
what is what are the reasons of the resistance today to the image we are in the civilization
of images a lot of images the violence of images but in fact we are in a moment where it is very
difficult to think to images i propose for perhaps tomorrow that we discuss time and gaze
in relation to perhaps the history of personal history of barborg also in his own relation to
bin sanger okay so we will stop here and we will show the documenting
just a second before before the film comes it's been a