I have the pleasure to present you, George L. Ebermann.
I don't know exactly how I will do that.
I saw that in the program of Hans-Wakie-Wiege,
it was your book in the middle of the program
in an excellent position, the surviving image.
I don't know exactly how to say in English about Nachlebahn.
It's an excellent book of George L. Ebermann,
which is not yet translated in English, perhaps no.
We are waiting for that because it is an important book
about Abi-Barbog and this unnamed science,
which include and extended beyond the limit
of different sciences.
And I think we are in the same dispositive
at Nachlebahn created the same frame of thinking.
We are with history, philosophy, anthropology,
ethnology, perhaps metrology, psychology, and also biology,
looking for another science which is beyond the limit
of these different sciences.
And I think it is the experience that we will do
during these two days.
And the purpose of our own table is to revisit
the important concept of Abi-Barbog, like Nachlebahn,
Patos Formal, Memosin, and it is important
to have now a discussion with you.
And you have to use the podium.
Thank you very much, Francois.
I'm so happy to be posted.
How is the type of knowledge inaugurated
by Warbog useful as today, useful for us today?
Shouldn't we say simply that it is useful
for opening the territory of that major science,
this royal science has to use the vocabulary of gildolos
and phillics gateri from their essay
on the cartography of knowledge, mil plato?
That is history as such.
Notice, opening can be understood in two senses at least.
To open is to enlarge, but it's also to wound.
Now, this is not the same thing for the science of history,
which is my interlocutor here.
To accept its opening to images under the angle of enlargement
as it is under the angle of perforation.
To enlarge its domain to images means
to accept certainly new objects, but it is also
to capture them, to enclose them,
under a common administration that pre-exists them.
This is to envisage interdisciplinarity
from the perspective of territorial relations,
so that opening itself to images reduces, more or less,
reduces the extending of its empire,
its authority over new landscapes and objects.
Totally different is the opening that wounds perforate
traverses the territory that hosts the operation.
This opening alone possesses a critical dimension,
dimension, I think, an extraterritorial capacity
to cross the frontiers, to create
unsuspected paths and to modify the plane of consistency
of the territory traversed.
The work of Vabog has long been recognized
for its capacity to enlarge the territory of the historian
and also art history.
But it seems more difficult today, even as yesterday,
to recognize its capacity to wound,
to critique this territory itself.
It is not by chance that the importance
of this critical aspect of Vabog's work has been recognized
before everyone else by historians of art who were careful
to construct their arguments philosophically,
like at Garvinte in the 30s, and by philosophers who are aware
of cultural history as, for instance,
Georgiou Agamben, because your quotation of the La Chienza
sensea no me is an expression taken by Georgiou Agamben
from the art historian Robert Clam.
This meant that we are in this discipline, like in a battlefield,
a field of battle.
It's a perpetual replenaging into the game of clashing theories
where certain objects are studied against others
in order that certain models of historicity are meaning,
and meaning, excuse me, are made to emerge against others.
It is thus that confronting the iconographic sign
that Erwin Panowski enlarged into an iconological symbol,
a Vabog will in advance,
construct the hypothesis of a regime of images
based on a paradoxical economy, a visual, a temporal,
a signifying economy of what I would call,
and here in this house, it's significant, the symptom,
that third at the same time was elaborating into
illuminating new shocking theory.
It's impossible for me to go into the details here,
concerning the complexity of these epistemologic debates.
Perhaps it will be enough to recall certain lines of divisions.
There where Panowski was thinking of the symbol.
By way of the logical development of a theme,
as was shown, for instance, in his brilliant deduction
of the iconography of Dürer's Melancholy
as deriving from ancient and medieval premises
synthesized for the occasion,
Vabog was exposing figurative symptoms
through the paradoxical not the deuxion,
eruption of a memory of unconscious movement.
That entered into conflict with the common sense
given of a shared culture.
In short, when the symbol unites,
the symptom divides.
There where the symbol brings into accord
in a common cultural territory,
the symptom mobilizes a disturbing transversal
across that territory.
There where the symbol is handed down by a tradition,
for instance, humanism, the symptom
migrates and perforates the traditional evidence
of common sense by what I call an
anachronistic accident, for instance,
the unexpected eruption of a Arab astrologer
at the heart of a cycle of Renaissance frescoes.
There where the symbol speaks of a conformity
of images and of discourses, the symptoms reveals
as many of their differences,
their failures to communicate,
their conflicts, their incommensorabilities.
There where the world of symbols
appear in the coherence of its unity,
that of symptoms puts into play
an unexpected diversity of montage, montages,
heterogeneity.
There where the symbol includes us
in the encompassing world of a great
cultural infrastructure where everyone
needs to recognize, the symptom brings to the surface,
as though pulling it up from below,
perforating elements that, in their local space,
booby traps, such an identification.
Therefore, the symbol cementizes
the present from a prolonged past,
the symptom de cementizes the present
from an instance of forgetting that
explodes as a repetition,
nachthaglicate, return of the repressed, etc.
One should understand that
it's the entire psychic, temporal, and visual economy
which finds itself here, divided,
in this way between the encompassing territory of symbols
and the traversing movements of the
critical movements of symptoms.
One example, will perfectly, I suppose,
illustrate this economy.
We could even think of it as a kind of a lagerie.
It is Abi-Vabo's gradiva.
The name of her is NINFA.
Singled out by Vabo in Florence during the period
between 1888 and 1893
when he was preparing his thesis
on the mythological paintings of Botticelli.
Vabo was attempting to make an archaeology
of the first Italian Renaissance
based on a new object that was first assigned
to representation and then generalized
to all forms of cultural life,
symbolic lives, therefore.
This object, that object, was the
living motion for which
Befobaticelli, Donatello, for example,
Montenier II, especially Donatello,
went in search of models from
paradoxically living motion,
but the models were found on the sides
of Roman sarcophagi, death,
where they found impassioned poses
of lamentations, but also erotic
pursuits, dramatic scenes of war, etc.
What fascinated Vabo as he stood
in front of Botticelli's paintings,
or similarly reading the poem of Politiano,
the theoretical press question of Alberti, etc.
was thus, I quote,
the remarkable attempt to delineate
transitory movement, basing his research
on such a common evidence,
therefore I repeat, symbolic form.
Vabo wanted to focalize his gaze
on a figure-out, a particularity,
which in the art of Renaissance Florence
repeated itself from place to place,
never finding itself thematized as such,
but breaking the surface and insisting
like a symptomatic form,
modifying in-depth the economy of images.
Whether they were employed as
corporal resemblances,
perspectival constructions,
likeness of Vabo,
Alberti's Historia.
Thus, this symptomatic form
modifies the representation of motion,
for example, of a character who walks or runs
transversely to the supplement
of two fundamental processes,
firstly, as a question of a displacement
of intensity, which marks itself
notably in an unexpected contrast
between the sculptural impenetrability
of Venus in Botticelli,
and the impassioned dance of the
bevectors by Vek, the accessory in movement,
unbound hair, draperies,
the wind.
The second process, fundamental,
is insufferable from the first.
Here, it's a matter of something that one could name
an eccentric,
transversal symptomatic forces at play,
and of their capacity to sweep the representation
like a breath of air,
be it a breeze or a high wind,
to sweep the space where it's superviness,
where it passes, where it occurs
in French,
passé, and ilse passqué,
que chor.
A lot of troubling things outside of the center
of Renaissance paintings,
as for instance, in the primavera.
Look at the right, the right border.
Zéfir is fecundating the nymph Clarisse,
and the latter already vomiting her children
in the form of a bracelet of flowers
escaping from her mouth.
One must define these weird scenes
as transversal,
since they modify from one border to the other,
the totality of the image is affected by those motions,
be it on this chromatic level,
but photographs of the verbal thesis,
so the chromatic level is,
I'm sorry, it's not here,
the level of the dynamism of forms
or of their significance, of course, finally.
It is equally necessary to qualify them as eccentric
in so far as especially their emerged,
most often along the borders of the painting,
and metaphorically they denote what Verbo wanted to call
the external cause of the image,
external cause of which he sought to theorize
the psychic tenor from the side of Fantasia
and dream images, images of memory,
images of desire at the same time,
images tied to passion, that is to say,
to a regime situated below that of consciousness,
just as a wind is eccentric by definition,
to the place it sweeps, of course,
the id to the ego that is upset,
and the symptom to the symbolic world
where we have taken our bearings and habits
so to the ninja that figure in movement
who seems in Renaissance images
to have emerged from the backstage
and come to modify the total economy of the representation
in making something impassioned,
something of the memory of the desire,
which passes here.
Verbo recognized innumerable instances,
but it's a leaf, leaf, peep, peep,
in turic, manteña, Leonardo, perugino,
rafero, et cetera, et cetera,
but when they, looking at the border
of one of Girlandaio's frescoes
in the Santa Maria novella in Florence,
he discovered something like the contestants of this phenomenon,
and yet it was only a serving girl,
modest, humble, carrying a plate of fruit on her head.
But it was a photograph of this gracious figure
that came to be carefully framed and glued
on the cover of a new notebook from 1900,
entitled, Ninfa Fiorentina.
The manuscript presents us with a collection of fragments
for what Verbo envisioned as his noon-fenn project.
At first, it takes the form of a friendly correspondence
between the historian and the linguist Andrei Yales.
On the question of Girlandaio's female figure
that we see enter, so to speak,
from the right handboarder of the fresco,
which is depicting the birth of Saint John the Baptist
in the Tona Boni Chapel in Santa Maria novella.
There's no doubt that Yales, in his text,
has already integrated all the aesthetic
and theoretical observations contained
in the preceding analysis of Verbo
on the representation of living motion.
Thus, what Verbo had revealed under the iconographic angle
of the erotic pursuit, Zeffi, Chlorix, Apollo Daphne,
Yales had maliciously displaced as a virtual play
between the spectator himself and the Ninfa,
like the le Porcivir,
which so's it grace in the works of Girlandaio.
In the manuscript, there is this phrase by Yales,
Chéchilapham, mine Lieber.
He wrote this in order to make clear
that it's a matter of desire,
like an inadmissible symptom
in the midst of the religious sin depicted
in the Tona Boni Chapel.
He evokes the ethereal grace of her steps,
making of her a cosy pagan goddess,
a practically extraterrestrial, he says,
creature, just as the air seems equally animated,
just for her, this is a close space,
with a local wind that swells her antique dress,
swells her antique dress, in short.
This young Ninfa seems to be something like a phantom
of feminine grace, who traverses the scene
with her light footsteps,
and almost high aerial creature,
an apparition that even provokes in Yales
a sentiment of imma-repressible unheimly,
something between a nightmare and a tale for children, he says.
So new questions present themselves,
questions that Váburgi was really asking himself,
this question especially,
where have I already seen
her, which is very psycho-analytical, of course.
This was a wave of Váburg to dialogue not only with Yales
but with himself, through the most radical prism
of his conceptual scheme,
namely that of Naftleben,
as the symptomatic model of the temporality of images.
Not only did Gerlandaio not respect
the dogmatic iconography of the religious order
that owned the church, but he even in accordance
with Tarnabroni instructions, probably,
sprinkling that figure of the Ninfa,
all over the place, which soon provoked
the anger of Savonarola, by the way.
This is presentation of the Virgin in the same channel.
You see these two charming children
who emerged from the two borders of the Marriag of the Virgin,
here on their female dancers,
traversing the nomination of John the Baptist,
of course, Salome,
in the operation of the angel to the Carriers.
There is a representation in Barriagliaef
and also this angel, a young, effeminate,
winged man, clothed, alantica.
And in the ultraviolet massacre of the innocence,
there are some quasi-menads transformed into furies,
avatars of media.
Finally, there is this young woman
who is a wonderful young woman,
carrying fruits as in the birth of John the Baptist,
and she emerges in Grisail, like a phantom,
from the background, the background of the visitation.
We are thus put confronted with a truly figurative strategy,
a strategy of nomadic apparitions,
eruptions, interruptions.
Ninfas do appear here and there
as this symptomatic figure coming from who knows where.
Again, antiquity surely, but which one?
Under what name?
The nymph, graciously,
opens the symbolic conventions of the space
which she traverses and modifies
with the kind of perverse innocence, if I may say so.
In reality, two territorial logics
are attacked, critic,
that is to say, put into crisis by this nomadic figure.
The first territory is that of church itself,
in its role as a sacred place,
and also in its role as a community of believers,
values, taboos, of course.
From this point of view,
it's almost indecent in such a context
to see the emergence of a figure as clearly sensual as this,
on whose drapery accentuates the contours
at the anterior level of the arms,
the thighs, the breasts,
with that gravity-defying body
from the bare feet to the denser's pace.
Doesn't the Atlantic address by itself
impose already an image of a pagan goddess or nymph
in this scene consecrated to the chaste,
precursor of Christ?
The second territory that is attacked
and perturbed by the emergence of the nympha
is none other than the solemn bourgeois one
of the Tonaboni family, the church, the family.
George O'Vazari has well described the birth of St. John the Baptist
as a scene of a kind directly referring
to the rights of maternity in Quattrochante Florence.
He says there is a beautiful woman
who carries following the Florentine custom,
fruits and flasks of wine from the country.
We can see then,
with this precise example, how far the cycle of Géralandayo,
in spite of his religious iconography,
is inscribed with the lay cymbals of the Florentine bourgeoisie,
whom Christian Clapiers-Yubeyer has dedicated
a wonderful and tropical study,
and of whom Joseph Schmidt has analyzed the issues
in work on the Tonaboni chapel itself.
In the symbolic economy, I say symbolic,
of the birth of St. John the Baptist,
the younger who emerges from the right-hand side
of the image is thus only a simple servant.
According to a long-established custom in Florence,
she carries from the country, from Villa,
outside to Palazzo in the city.
Fresh fruits and wine, which will give force
to the mother, lying in bed after the birth
within the walls of her Palazzo.
But the symptomatic economy of the Ninefa
appears when we discover in that very conformity
the critical effect resulting from differences
that are incarnated by the young serving girl in her stride.
We observe, for instance, how much she differs
from the other serving girl, the one who, in the background
of the scene, carries also the same flasks
to her mistress, and we catch ourselves,
imagining that the two figures are perhaps
two versions, two fashions, to see the same serving girl.
Why not? Just an hypothesis.
The effect of strangeness is found in any case,
doubled. On one side, the young serving girl
with no name. In the economy of the portraits,
the young lady in the center, she has a name,
a prosopography, artistry, history of portraits,
okay, names.
This serving girl with no name in the economy of the portraits,
which are besides those
of the great family, sorry.
And the young lady has also two servants,
with her. On the other side,
the young serving girl comes from
elsewhere, from another
symbolic space, from another time,
the past epoch of paganism,
and another time than that of the bourgeois ceremony,
the now of Florentine customs, or the
evangelical event, the past of sacred history.
They are all means, these are
all means, to denote the extraterritorial
ity, the eccentric and perturbin,
and in short, what I would call critical character of the
NINFA. Why does this figure travel not only the figurative
production of the Renaissance, but as well, the entire
body of Abba Vabo's work? Because
she crystallizes, and up to a point
of view, and she realizes, just like
Graziva for Fjöd, a goodly portion
of his theoretical choices, his objects of interpretation,
and his models of historicity. We are hardly surprised
that a panel of Mne Mosine atlas has been
dedicated to her. The NINFA,
the idea of the idealandios, a legurized first,
naphleben, the survival, the afterlife, constructed
by Abba Vabo as a model of temporality, necessary to understand the
economy of a recollection of images
that was reducible neither to the
idealistic principles of the imitation of the engines,
nor to the positivistic recourse to an iconographic
tradition. NINFA, consequently,
offers us the complexity of a trans- iconographic
and trans-historical model in the context
of a representation that refers to the classics.
The NINFA is still only
an adequate sitation. Iconographic
sign, perfectly consistent with the symbolic universe
that stages it. Classics,
Roman, Greek. But in a context of
Christian representation as
the case here in the nerve center of the largest
Dominican church in Florence, with
the, it's the same in the case of St. Mary Magdalene
being represented at the foot of the cross
with the features of a minute, a hair
unbound, stripped of clothing, violent,
such as with unbound hair, violent, and
stripped of clothings, which is how Donatello,
or here, Bertoldo de Giovanni, present her, for instance.
Therefore, the NINFA becomes a critical
sitation. It's a sitation, but a critical one. She makes
something surface as a counter motif, an unconscious
of representation. In short, it's a symptom.
It's a fleeting, fossil, traversing figurative space
like an accident or an unbidded phantom.
Moreover, the NINFA incarnates and allegorizes
the economy of that Patos formel
that Abba Abbivarborg tried to describe
the lateral transmissions and the missing links
in the long du dure of occidental art.
It's not simply a matter of opposing static representation
of medieval to the living motion in Renaissance,
but it's also necessary to understand the phenomena of
intensification of movement. This problem is crucial
in which Italian art from Polayolo to Michelangelo
experimented with all the possibilities.
In the fresco of Guillen Dio, the NINFA opposes
her dynamism against the immobility of
all the other figures, but she's not satisfied
with merely working graciously
as everything converges in intensifying her motion.
The position of her body, her left foot
is slightly lifted up, the robes streaming in the wind
and therefore enlarging her gesture
and propagating it around her.
We rediscover here a characteristic of Renaissance visual culture
the importance of which has been shown,
of course, by Michael Betsendall and also Charon Fermour.
That is the strictly choreographic fashion of envisioning
the human gesture in representation.
There is no doubt besides that the recognition of these
processes of intensification responded in
Vábog's work with a theoretical awareness of
intensified forms in the total epistemic
of his own time, aesthetic of intensity
Nietzsche,
and the passion of attitudes Charon Fert.
Let's also recall that Vábog in order to
explicate the patos formel in terms of
superlatives of the language of gestures
Utilizai utilized as an
anthropological argument the analogy with
this famous separation function,
in the Indo-European languages studied by the linguist
Herman Ostov, doesn't
the intensification of bonus
into malia and the intensification of malia
into optimus, so three different radicals
suppose a change in the linguistic route
therefore the graceful serving girl
with the light footstep who is an expectedly
invited into the iconography of John the Baptist
would thus be fundamentally
deracinate, a strange woman,
a stranger, an extraterritorial
no green card
anthropologically speaking
the serving girls anonymity
reminds us of one of Abbivabog's first intuition
when reading the work of Edward B. Tyler
concerning the survival observed in Mexico around
1860, he understood that the
survival only appeared contrary to the assumed
traditions as transversal symptoms, phenomena
where unfit to use Tyler's own
expression unfit, that is to say
in adapted, obsolete and congruced, ephemeral
and acronistic, thus in 1895
and 6, when Abbivog visited
the Indians of New Mexico, he would be interested
in impersonal rituals and
anonymous persons, stubborn symptoms like that
Pueblo woman on the right,
that he photographed at the moment that she promptly
regained the back hole of her quarters, fleeing
the eye of the black chamber of the camera or
fleeing the reach of the accidental
logos. The figures and the paradigm of the
human being that helps us finally to better understand
where the history of images must find
its efficacious end to appear
and act as a knowledge that is a repeat against
transversal to those disciplines
constituted in the social sciences
the question is in you for me, the
neurology,
the psychology, but in the social sciences
according to the limits of more or less
defined territories, in photographing himself
a lady, peasant lady
in Setignano here.
Vabog made evident the temporal
transversality of his
concept of Naftleben, setting an image
of a gold star.
Between coins of antiquity and representations of
media, he also made evident the social
transversality of his notion of Patos Formel, but
chiefly he made evident the critical
and finally in the last plates of
Naemozune, political dimension of this transversal
especially when he spoke about Geistus
politics, for example, which remain inherent of all
his analysis, which remain agonistic, generally
as they were to the point of madness
with the devastation of the First World War
to, in general, the tragedy of western culture
which is an expression he used as well as
Georzimel, for example. Perhaps we should
read the Vabogian transversals today in the light of
Michel Foucault's writing in which eccentric
transversals fall under the term heterotopias
all of Gildolous and Felix Guattari,
I come back to Dulous because we learn in
a thousand plateau this, which is a major
point that nomadic knowledge
nomadic knowledges, however
dismissively they are ranked, however
light are the footsteps, can act
in spite of everything like a real what
Dulous
says is a machine of war against
the territorial instrument of
Royal Sciences, so to speak, always
monasté, monast, by their self-sufficient
Thank you.