Helixcenter.org or thehelixcenter.org where you can view the roundtable and it's an entirety and we encourage you to let us know what you think
Helix Center Facebook page or write us at the helixcenter at gmail.com
So we're following up on our inquiry into beginnings by posing complementary questions about endings
Why are we curious about endings whether it's that of the cosmos our own?
Can we discover something about each other's curiosity about endings?
How might conceptualizations of the end of consciousness life civilization and the universe at large inform one another?
So I'd like to introduce our guests today
Starting here James Berger is senior lecturer in American Studies in English at Yale University
He received his BA from Columbia University
His MA from Teachers College Columbia University and his PhD from the University of Virginia
His interests include 20th and 21st century American literature
Literary theory disability studies neuroscience and literature and apocalyptic literature and film the latter including
Apocalypticism and the notion of the post-apocalyptic and exploring the limits of language the relations between language and non-language
The status of discursive objects imagined is somehow whether through global catastrophe
Personal impairment or religious or ethical imperative outside the bounds of discourse
Dr. Berger is the author of multiple scholarly articles and his books include after the end representations of post-apocalypse
Next to him is Paul J Steinhardt the Albert Einstein professor in science and director of the Princeton Center for theoretical science at Princeton University
Where he is also on the faculty of both the Department of physics and the Department of astrophysical sciences
He received his BA in physics from Caltech and his MA and PhD both in physics from Harvard University
The author of over 200 refereed articles five patents three technical books numerous popular articles and the co-author of the
2007 endless universe the Big Bang and Beyond a popular book on contemporary theories of cosmology
Professor Steinhardt's research spans problems in particle physics
Astrophysics cosmology and condensed matter physics with Neil Turock at Cambridge University
He proposed the cyclic model a radical alternative to Big Bang inflationary cosmology in which the evolution of the universe is periodic
And the key events shaping the large-scale structure of the universe occur before the Big Bang
Next is William Cole Brenner associate professor of English at Bart Elon University
He received his BA from Columbia College his MA from University College Oxford and his PhD from Columbia University
He is written in major scholarly journals in literature history theology psychoanalysis and cultural criticism on Jewish topics in commentary as or
JQR and AJS review tradition and many other Jewish publications and the Washington Post column letter from Israel
Professor Cole Brenner is also the author of the 2008 book Milton's Worrying Angels a study of critical engagements and
the 2011 open-minded Torah of irony fundamentalism and love
Michael Rapino is professor biology with the Earth and Environmental Sciences program at New York University
And his research consultant at NASA Goddard Institute for Space Studies. He received his BA from Hunter College of the City University of New York and his PhD in
Geological Sciences from Columbia University a highly regarded teacher at NYU professor and Pinos research led to his proposal of the Shiva hypothesis a
general theory integrating Astrophysics planetary geology and the environment and the history of life to account for Earth's periodic
Extinctions his research also investigates the role of volcanic eruptions and extinctions
Bioguochemical cycles and global climate over a range of timescales
So our round table will go for about an hour and a half followed by time for questions and discussion from the audience
So let's begin the end
Why are we curious about endings?
Well, drop you want to say something about the lack of microphone for bill. Oh, yes that
Dr. Cole Brenner in observing the Sabbath
You know cannot wear an amplifying microphone today, so he will speak
That was good
Okay
Well, I'll start I guess my background is in is in the geological sciences and
There has been a paradox shift in the geological sciences over the past couple of decades and then that's away from the old idea of
a change
Gradually all the time very slowly over very long periods of geological time to a new vision
which is much more apocalyptic which suggests that there are
individual catastrophes which are happening periodically to the earth and those catastrophes are causing mass extinctions of life and
As far as the history of life is concerned you talk about endings
More than 99% of the species that have ever existed on the earth are extinct. So in terms of species
Extinction is the name of the game. They last for a few million years
Then either they evolve to something else or else they become extinct with no issue
I mean, I'll fall up. I mean, I'm interested that this is about endings and a couple of weeks ago was beginning
As a literary critic I think of Elliot's term or phrase the end is where we start from
In the beginnings and ends or is related one to another
I'm just very interested on being in a panel first of all then a literary critic
But I'm interested in the way you think about catastrophe and
Paradimorship to think about ways in which
The languages of the sciences also use plotting as a device
I saw an advertisement on television for a new movie called something extinction
Extinction is thematized
A narrative sense
And I'm wondering for both of you kind of it from a scientific point of view how much
narrative or storytelling or plotting
Is something that gets it's obviously not foregrounded to the same extent that it would be from the agenda, but I'm wondering how much that is a live issue
That's my curiosity
Well the old idea of the
gradualistic change in the earth sciences comes out of
Lyle-Jaws-Lyle his book principles of geology back in 1831 and Lyle saw
geological happenings as being
gradual and
being
connected and so there was a story there the gradual history of the earth and
And he didn't believe in evolution at the time
So life was somehow put into this picture and it was for many years
Geology when you were a student technology 101 you would talk this the same the present is the key to the past
In other words things that are happening at the present time geological processes if you extrapolate those over a long time periods
Even very gradual slow change like erosion by rivers add up into a big
result like the the grand canyon and that was part of Lyle's view of the
naturalness the gradual
The gradualism nature, but this was the way God set things up and
There was an order to this the order that was in God's mind when he created the universe
I was gonna say something akin to what you mark
Which is that the one of the reasons why we're interested in the end of
The universe or
So the cosmologist we're talking about the universe
Is because it gives us a lot of information about how it began and the stages of evolution in between
They're all tied together
And so the debates that we're having about what's going to happen next in the universe
are all tightly related to
What set up the conditions that led to the conditions we observe today and
Those are in turn tied very closely to how
The evolution of the universe is tied to the fundamental laws of physics and what those laws tell us about conditions
At the very beginning or at the big bang or maybe even before the big bang
Yeah, I suppose right about one difference you can point to between the way that the English teachers and scientists
I think we
in our thinking about narrative place the human subject kind of the center of it and
We know that for one thing we ourselves are finite
So the question of ending has to do with the question of finitude in general
and
Narrative
Contributes to that there's a great line in Don de Lilla. Don de Lill is novel all plots lead toward death
So there's that perspective as you're thinking plots. There's going to be an ending to the plot at the same time
You have the example of shehara zal which plot
extends like as long as you can tell the story
You can extend you can put off fine to
There's a couple of movies I always I don't I just want me to think abstractly about this
You know that I think in terms of movies there's a 1991 vin vendors movie called until the end of the world
In which after a lot of kind of weird misadventures they end up in Australia at the end of the world and adjust at that moment
and
A nuclear satellite falls down creates this electromagnetic disruption all around the world or at least in Australia
And so every and they think they're so isolated. They think the world has in fact ended
At which point the plot of the movie completely shifts and there's this amazing invention which someone has developed in order to
Get capture the neurochemical event of vision for one of the characters blind mothers
His mother is blind so she is able to see images again
But they also has this other purpose which is to they discover they can see their own dreams
They can basically videotape their own dreams and so they get this
Insight into this experience of what you might call in psychoanalytic terms primary process complete
Unmediation complete absence the eradication of mediations this extraordinarily
Sophisticated medium for eliminating mediation and what happens is they become addicted to their dreams
That's all that's all they want to do and so that becomes in the sense the apocalypse that's the revelation is this revelation of
complete interiority and
complete
Removal from any symbolic world any social symbolic world and I think it's some degree
That's also what apocalyptic thinking is a yearning for I mean here. We are these symbolic
We're so we're so you know involvement our symbolic communications our relationships to ourselves. He'd be mediated
What is there that's direct? What is there that's unmediated? How do you get to sort of the thing itself?
And some level what apocalyptic thinking allows you to do is to find some place in
In fiction in imagination where that takes place. I think a lot of apocalyptic narratives have to do with the
bashing of this symbolic edifice so that you have people who somehow are
absolutely
There without a symbolic overlays
But that's yeah, I don't know that's that's infection
For them
Your suggestion
The kind of pre-modern
Manifestations of apocalyptic thinking which is just the way everyone thought that is thinking that that history has to tell us
There's an echetym towards which history is ended and the way in which that sense of an ending
infuses the president
Meaning
There's not any beginning in an end that sense of an ending takes
Chronometric time literary pre-chromo may use this distinction
Kind of waiting
Tomorrow tomorrow tomorrow that lack of mediation things happen
But an end
And promoting this degree term chiris. I guess it means the fullness of time
That end towards which one is tending not only forms the end of history
But also infuses the president you spoke before about the president being the key to the past and I think in some sense
Models of time, I mean maybe Adam folks might put it like this. Tell me what you think about why I'll tell you what you believe
Because conceptions of time
Is there an end towards which we're tending or is there not really
And I'm wondering in a kind of scientific or post modern or post-apocalyptic world
How
Does the echetym does this or in your inner is to tell you terms is the notion of life as a pop
He's a either cosmological time as a plot beginning the end and
the way that might
interact
With the subject thinking of his own life or all life as a plot with beginning middle and end is that still something?
That's viable
Or an opposed to apocalyptic age
Born an age given over to scientific stories and narratives for those really
That sense yeah, I think that's a
Science of just to add one one thing to that
In the sense of endings that you're talking about in the commode
People talking about the end the way one conceives the end is what gives meaning to the present
But I'm but I think in the scientific way of thinking in the cosmological way of thinking I can't imagine how that would be
actually
Take place whether sort of the meaning of social and personal life
would have anything to do with the way one conceives of
The act be the ending the universe as hypothesized scientifically
Yeah, I think I think we're talking about
humanity and of humanity for example if there's one kind of apocalypse we think about the earth another kind of apocalypse and
Then the universe
Which is which is a different?
Different kind of end we could talk about for the universe
I think one thing that's happened in cosmology in the in just the last few decades has been a tremendous
Opening up of the possibilities of even what we mean by universe
Which colors the question of what do you mean by the end the end of what what are you interested in?
So of course we're interested in humans and the earth but in terms of the universe
Are we interested in the part of the universe we observe?
Because up until recently we had the notion that we observe all that there is but the current view is that what we observe is a
Tiny infinite testimal patch of what is out there and that what we observe may or may not be typical of what is out there
Now we may be interested in this patch because it is all we see and can ever hope to see
I mean the laws of physics prohibit us from seeing regions that are beyond a certain that are stretching far enough fast enough from us
and for that for that region we can talk about and
We can imagine two kinds of ends at least two kinds of ends one in which it
Crunches into something like a black hole in which time and space lose their meaning
and another one which is where
Time and sense some sense lasts forever, but not in a meaningful sense
The universe expands into more and more vacuum and there's more and more vacuables and empty and continues that way forever
This this patch of space we observe
In either of those circumstances there may be interesting events creation events in fact occurring in other parts of the universe
where new regions are being created new patches are being created and for all and and
Many plausible circumstances this would this process would continue eternally forever and there would be no end to the entire process
Although there may be ends to the regions which are of greatest interest to us
so I've just given you a few examples of some of the
wider variety of possibilities that have been opened up and motivated by recent ideas and in cosmology
It's to give you a taste
I know a few years ago. It was a lot simpler story
the universe began in the Big Bang and
Through cause and effect the scientists could trace the history of the universe from the time of the Big Bang to the present
And the idea then was that either the universe was going to expand forever
Or if the galaxies were massive enough the gravity would pull it all back in again
But things have changed since then things have become much right complex
So first of all in terms of the future going to the future we've discovered there's an entity in the universe
Which we knew in principle could be there, but we didn't realize was actually there which is what we called dark energy
So most forms of matter that were there all the forms of matter that we're familiar with
Gravitationally attract each other in fact most of us learned in school that gravity always attracts
It's not actually true gravity attracts for certain forms of matter and energy, but not for others
There's a form there are forms of matter and energy which would actually cause us repulsion
We've known about it since 1917, but you probably didn't hear about in school because no one believed it it actually
Was an important component of the real universe?
Well, we've known from we now know from recent measurements in the last decade that
73% of the universe is this stuff and
once it takes so it's already taken over the universe in terms of being the dominant form energy in the universe and
It's causing therefore the expansion of the universe to accelerate at the present time speed up rather than slow down
so it's actually promoting the expansion rather than resisting it and
if this continues then what will happen over time is
More and more of the matter that we see in the universe today the galaxies and stars will begin to disappear from view because of this expansion
every region of the universe will begin to approach empty space and
This will be a kind of M and which is like you know TSL it's whimper in which you simply
You know slowly decay into an emptier and more deadly universe for this patch of the universe
And that's a possible that's a possible end to the universe
The point of view is that this dark energy is unstable and will eventually decay and then it will lead to a new crunch bang and
And and the process will begin again even in this patch of the universe
So you have all these things periodic and it could even repeat periodic
So this is the idea behind a possible return of the idea of a kind of cyclical universe
So I'm saying there are other patches that we're just living in a patch. Well, what's what is almost certain?
Is that what we observe as a tiny patch of a much larger space that we're not that when we look at the farthest distances?
we can see
those are not the edge of space that there's simply the edge of what we can see because
The oldest light we can observe is 13.7 billion years old
It's only had a chance to travel 13.7 billion light years
That's as far as we can see but that doesn't say that there isn't plenty of space out
It's not a boundary at all. It's our person
It's our it's in fact we call it our horizon because it's essentially a limit to our vision of what we can see so how do you know that is something beyond them?
Well, we can already see hints of it when we look at radiation from the
comes from the oldest radiation we observe in the universe gives us a
Is radiation that comes from a time when the universe cool to the point that the first atoms were forming in the universe?
So let's go back a bit if you extrapolate back in the time the universe was more and more contracted and more and more
Heated up as you contracts a gas and heats up you go back far enough in time was hot enough to boil atoms into their
fundamental constituents
So now around that time which was when around 13.4 billion years ago 13.7 billion years ago
The atoms first atoms formed the universe became transparent
Radiation began to stream freely through the universe and we collected today to get a picture of what the distribution of matter and radiation
what looks like at that time and
What it shows us is an extremely uniform distribution of matter and radiation that even gives us some vision of
how
smooth
If you hadn't even is able to show us that there isn't an edge that this isn't the edge that there has to be something
Beyond the light to give us a kind of smooth
Boundary to what we're seeing so that already extends us a short distance
And most of our theories to explain that degree of homogeneity tell us that actually what we observe is
a much tinier
tiny patch of a much smoother region of space it must be much larger than what we observe and
And in many versions of these many of these theories that this is one of many
Infinitely many patches that would have formed over time and would continue to form over time. So very
Pushing us way beyond what we can actually observe
It's a doctor how much time do we have?
This is when we need albie singers pediatricians reassurance that Brooklyn's not expanding right
Yeah, I think Brooklyn's okay
How much to tongue we have
Well the universe is a habitable place me say that is could be quite long, you know, I mean
I mean as long as our Sun exists, you know, so another five billion years or so
And our galaxy in this scenario would be habitable
Until such point that there might have been a crunch or something like that if that were to occur then
so
estimates would range from anywhere from
tens of billions of years to
In definite I mean I just I can't help but latch onto the wedding I don't mind
I just wonder what what are the effects of these kinds of cosmological
perspective speculations horizons
What is that what is the effect of that on subjects?
I mean we have different we have models of time
beginnings and middles and Jim and I were talking before
the
Modernist the persistence of the modernist emphasis on enemies
We didn't pursue it because there is a certain kind of post modern
That we're posting
And signed in seems the cosmological visions of the universe reinforce those models
But is there a persistence of a sense of an ending?
That that renders the present meaning
I mean the post modern abandoned that kind of ending
leaves a kind of tomorrow and tomorrow and tomorrow and
I'm just wondering is there
In the world that we live have we given up those endings
psychically of subjects we structure our lives as class
The psycholamilists ask their their their
They're patients to think of their their lives and narrative terms
I think in some place here I'm speaking out of my discipline
The Freud speaks of a past present future in terms of it ego and super evil and the sense in which
Not a non-repressive version of the super evil that the vision of this of the future
The idealized vision of the future will help me reconstitute
My desire is my drives allowed them to speak in a certain my past
so I can believe any more meaningful present
And again, I'm wondering about
the seeming
Facticity of a universe that is one among many
billion year scheme and
Our own
thrusts or drive
For me
I think meaning comes that's why I started to begin about plots and stories
meaning comes through stories and plots
The story that you gave us is first of multifaceted
the 17th century
which notes
The speculation that many many were the first kind of science fiction and it was very unsettling for those who lived in a kind of
universe where there was the divine plot the divine sentence would be getting
Wonder post science
This kind of cosmology
Where does the subject?
How does this subject mean?
How does the subject plot?
We exist on one planet
out of probably many many habitable planets in the in the in the galaxy and
We're the product of
four billion years of evolution and
So if you look at it from the cosmic context at least here on this habitable planet evolution the origin of life started here
Evolution produced more and more complex kinds of life and we are the most
Intelligent at least for the time being form of life on the planet and so we have that narrative
It was the course that I teach at NYU you have the narrative of
Looking back from this special place which is human consciousness and looking back at the history of the universe
It all seems like it's leading someplace, but then that's just a way of looking at it
Really doesn't mean anything because evolution is very very contingent
Because mileage I'd even make that point more strongly the discovery of dark energy
I think shatters this kind of vision that many people had of just what you described the universe itself as
Evolving from simple to more and more complex
If there were not this dark energy if we only had ordinary modern radiation the idea that we had be up until a decade or so
Then what we then the prediction would have been that
The universe does become more and more complex more and more structure forms more and more galaxies form more and more planets form
But that story is now shattered something recently recently on cosmic scale has happened dark energy has taken over the universe
Now the expansion of the universe is accelerating that prevents the formation of any further structure in the universe the largest structures
we see in the universe today or the
Late will be the last to form and now what the universe will be doing is reverting to well
We'll be turning into an emptier and emptier universe
And this has happened so this is this is shattering from several points of view
It means there's something special at this particular juncture in time in cosmology
We live at a juncture in time in cosmology on the one hand
There's enough matter in the universe that we can see galaxies and stars and planets out there
So we can see that where the past came from we can also see that there's dark energy in the universe
So we can see where we're headed if you if we had lived
Let's say six billion years ago
We could see the matter where we couldn't see the dark energy if we in the future will be able to see the dark energy
It'll be hard to see the matter so we live at a very special point in time
This shatters the notion of evolution is some sort of steady process in which every moment is in some sense as good as any other moment
There's really something special about this juncture in cosmology and we don't understand why it's just a fact of nature
We have to live with what nature hands us whether we like the answer or not
It's a special because we're here is the anthropic principle kind of working here. We're in we're there because we're there
If we were early we wouldn't be here if we were late we wouldn't be here
So we so so we could have so there could well be species that evolved earlier
We've evolved you know really relatively could have evolution could have occurred faster suppose it
four billion years ago
Ascension beings evolved in the universe. They would have a lot of trouble seeing that the fact that there was this dark energy
because
The ratio of dark energy to matter changes over time so back then that dark energy would have been a relatively small percentage
Now it's kind of intermediate
We see there's a significant fraction of matter and a significant significant fraction of dark energy in the future
It becomes more and more dark energy, but you know it could have been could be that life evolves in our galaxy
Let's say a hundred billion years from now
They will have a lot of trouble seeing it. There was a lot of matter once in the universe
They'll think they just they just lived in one little island galaxy
They won't see the billions of galaxies
We see and they'll see almost everything being dark energy and they'll have a lot of trouble reconstructing
How they got to where they were right?
It'll be very confusing cosmologists would be in trouble cosmologists
Get involved at that time for the first time at that time will be a lot of trouble
They will have a lot of trouble reconstructing their history just like cosmologists that you know
We're born at four billion years ago
We have a lot of trouble figuring out that the future was going to be one dominated by dark energy
So this is shattering to our traditional ideas and I don't think I mean to me it's something that's a
It's a profound important scientifically what it means, but in terms of what it means in terms of our human reaction to it
I don't think we've even begun to absorb it yet
I don't think the message has gotten out that our view of the world of the universe has changed in such a profound way and
Okay, what are we to make of it? Yeah, I can't think of
Human cultural imaginative examples that that in any way
Take take in these these scientific findings
The closest I can come as Blake
See say William Blake that you know sensing that that what we see as the surface of reality is somehow just
not really the case and you have to burst these doors of perception and
And our whole very terminologies are skewed. We need a new set of names to
Talk about what human existence physical and spiritual are the other person
I think that's some maybe sensitive of trying to negotiate speak a little louder
The other person is a block in their name the South African woman writer
No, no the other one
Doris last thing yeah, exactly as you know
This whole series of kind of science fiction could nostic science fiction
texts in in which all kinds of interesting things happen with time Philip Dick
I guess would be another example of someone who's making that attempt, but generally are you know
most of us are thinking in terms of of human the time frames of human history and
the various historical political
social economic
problems
Which which faces at the moment so in the sense each I think each generation and each writer within each generation
generation
And not just writers but just just people
Sort of choose the ending that fits their immediate concern
So that's a in the late 19th century when H G Wells was writing, you know, you can see in the book like the
the time machine, you know, you know, exactly what the kind of prevalent social anxieties there are which are
anxieties that evolution in which way evolution is going and
anxieties that's class
So you have sort of Darwin and and Marx there at the center of those things of those apocalyptic anxieties
So that the anxiety the vision of the end of the world are
extrapolations of ideas of Marx and ideas of Darwin plus of course then
You know, there's the bifurcation of the social club. There's a specie accorded to social class
But at the end of that book if you remember
Then actually he even brings in the cosmological view you have the sense that everything is gone except these completely non-human
Creatures and the Sun is
Is this giant thing that's expanding and about to you know encompass the earth or something?
and in a relatively
Trivia or at least weird contemporary example. I've been actually been watching this TV show the doomsday preppers
What is the doomsday preppers about it's basically a home improvement show? How do you build perfect bunker?
You know, you know Ted and Edie
You know believe that the world's magnetic poles are going to shift in the next five years and therefore they need an underground bunker
They need to stop, you know, how are they best going to do it and they consult experts and they you know build whatever they have
They build
But what are they really worried about me? We're worried about the social chaos that will instill a lot of them
I mean, that's a lot of people they're worried about the social chaos that will ensue from some
Catastrophic breakdown of of whatever it may be and these people are always not in cities
There is never doomsday prepper in New York City because if you are one you're not gonna be here
You're gonna move somewhere else but don't you think some of this and you
Bringing in psychoanalysis
Some of this has just to do with reactions to mortality and various ways of trying to deny
Mortality the preppers maybe the preppers are basically worried about black people pouring out of cities and invading the suburbs
I mean the racial subtext of this show is unbelievable
So
You can direct about anxiety in different ways you can express it to different things
But if they end with you ending then it has to have something to do with mortality
You mentioned
Psychoanalysis and meaning their different ways psychoanalysis looks at meaning one way you look at meaning is
When you have a person in analysis you try to understand
What is the meaning of their behavior? What is the meaning of their interaction with others? What is their meaning and their?
The meaning of their fantasies about themselves and others
But then when you're talking about meaning of life that's something that develops over time
I don't think an 18 year old who really cares much about the meaning of life
He cares about getting a nice car and a nice girlfriend and so on
The older you get the more the issue of meaning of life and achievements and what you've done and what your
Kids are doing becomes more central
So and that again has to do with mortality is the idea that things are not going to last forever
So you may as well feel like you had some kind of
Good or impact or something that you did in this world
and
This came up last time and it's come keeps coming up to my mind and I've asked the number of
cosmologists and physicists
And I don't really get an answer and the question I have which I think Rob put under the rubric or
Mark no rest put under the rubric of curiosity is why are we interested in the stuff you're talking about?
I mean that you know you're talking about billions of years
I maybe have 10 more years of life. Why do I care what's gonna happen?
What happened billions of years before I was even around?
And why do I care about what's gonna happen?
15 years 20 years 30 years from now maybe for my kids, but after that there is no
But yet we have these tremendous I personally have
curiosity and interest in
The kind of work that you do
And there has to be something in humans that makes us want to keep understanding this
Even to a degree that which seems almost not understandable that this black energy expands or doesn't expand or whatever else it does
Well because well first of all hopefully it does become understandable we
First discover things they at first they're confusing but you've come they begin to become familiar as you deal with them more and more
Um, why are we interested? Well, I think we're all curious to know where we came from where we're going and why things are the way they are
and
So the question of the future
Is not just a question about the future. It's a question about what forms of energy can exist in the universe
how what kinds of effects
What are the interactions between matter energy and gravity because
Not only does that affect the future, but it affects every stage of the universe including the president and what's even happening in this room
So if I want to know for example, you know
Why the atoms in our bodies are stable? I ultimately have to understand something about the most microscopic
components
of matter
Which are the key components of matter that existed at the very beginning of the universe
If there was a beginning at the very beginning of the universe when the universe was quite young they were universe was boiled into those constituents and how they interacted
Is what eventually determined how you ended up with atoms and molecules planets and earths and humans?
and that's also related to what's going to happen in the future and
You want to study every stage of this
I mean the goal is to is to figure out this puzzle of why things are the way they are and you use every hint available to you
Which includes thinking about the past future present
recent past and
Another way to look at it which is that
If there was no end
There wouldn't be really an interest in end
So it must be that to some degree our own mortality is what
Encouraging us or what's pushing us
So when you say well everybody's interested in where it began where it is and where it's going
Yes, that is true, but why is it so?
Why be interested so?
Psychoanalysts have theories about why it's that we become interested in our beginnings and in our endings, but
The fact that we all are aware
That there is a final danger
Which is mortality and that we are
Biologically designed to always avoid danger
We are constantly avoiding anxiety
We are constantly avoiding danger and we have the signal of anxiety which tells us there's danger. Don't go there. Don't go there. Don't go there
so that anxiety
Must have something to do with the kind of
Things we need to find out because we feel as if
You know fantasies that the more we know the safer we are
Don't remember yeah
Which
Conceptions of my ideal self will allow me to give meaning to my past and therefore my presence
And I think the question that you're implicitly asking or raising is really the theological question
And we know that Freud's sense of religion was one of a kind of false consolation
and
Adam Phillips writes about the kind of magical narratives
of the universe, charming oneself with visions of the future
and through those charming narratives
those fantasies of benevolent future a future that gives meaning
of rendering the present meaningful
Phillips says it's really avoiding our helplessness our fundamental
So humanity is defined by their helplessness and we use these narratives of the future of a comforting future significant end to avoid that
And I'm wondering
We haven't spoken about apocalypse and we've spoken about endings
There's also messiness which functions in the same kind of way
And I'm wondering to the extent I find Phillips so interesting because he's skeptical about everything
And he'll write one book where he undermines one set of terms
And the next book he will write will undermine the terms that he used to undermine the previous terms
The one thing that he shows no skepticism about is this a critique of just this kind of theological thinking
Meaning theology
Coming from this Freudian matrix, and I'm gonna know not everybody embraces this
And the low wall the clearer exceptions to serve extent
But theology becomes the one thing about which one and the endings that it passes
Becomes the one thing about which there is endless and only skepticism
And even your comments add I think indicate that you know we get old and we have worried
And we sense danger
And we get sentimental and we create narratives about the future
I'm wondering if that's an exhaustive account
I mean obviously
This kind of transcends the disciplinary conversation where does theology fit in or does it does it not
Is there a generous view of theology from a psychoanalytic point of view from a scientific point of view
Is it something we just tolerate or presume might exist in one of those patches someplace else
Is it an embarrassing question to
I think it's implied in any idea of meaning
I mean feel if implying an actual god
As being part of the picture. I mean it's it's a world
You know their worldviews
For some reason your your voice is not going to be adjusted
I don't know okay. All right, I don't I want to sort of talk
Yeah, it's hard to talk about I mean there's plenty of people who who haven't an
apocalyptic messianic view of the world the left behind series has sold an enormous number of books the christian apocalyptic
perspective
But
Yeah, but I assume when you're talking about theology you're not you know that doesn't exhaust the question
I mean, I don't know next year in Jerusalem. I don't think I'm going to be there
Who knows?
Sure, I'm not I also I don't think we should be rebuilding the temple or anything along those lines
So yeah, I'm yeah, it is it's not an embarrassing question
But it's certainly a difficult question because I think some sort of ultimate sense of where we are and where we're going is
Is implied in all the literary cases that I'm looking at
It may or may not be involved in the minds of scientists who are thinking and he said I mean proof myself
Just in my lazy way. I think that if the universe is going to drift off forever as you described in one scenario
bad
If the universe is going to recoil back on itself and begin again that to me would be a hopeful possibility and so that I suppose is
Well, I'm just gonna science point of view the galaxy is full of planets
and some of those must be Earth like planets just by the
statistics and on some of those earth like planets there could be
Evolution of life would go on and it would produce intelligent beings
and so to do a lot of
Astronomers and planetary scientists the galaxy is probably full of
Symbolizations intelligence civilizations possibly trying to contact each other over the vast distances of space
So we're just one world in a many many world situation
Chris the case that the distances are so vast that communication is
Pretty hopeless possibility. No, Chris MP said last week two weeks ago
Your colleague Chris MP said two weeks ago and I don't know if you agree with it or not
He said within the next hundred years. We will have people going to some other habitable
planet
And when they go there they will continue to live there they will change because they'll be on another planet
But he saw that within completely within realm of possibility humans would go elsewhere humans will go out there
But I think he means planets within our solar system like Mars
I don't think you meant that's a little bit different than contacting the planets that Mike's talking about which would be
Probably a habitable planet where there already exists intelligent life would be probably much farther out
We could receive if we were sending right but having a conversation. I think that's what he was. He wasn't done but Mars
We can't travel very far into the
Space because this distances are so vast and our rockets only go so fast
Well, he was saying in the next hundred years. That's a pretty
I think it underestimates the dangers of space. I mean we I mean just thinking about going to Mars
One of the already there was a
Dangers of going that distance, but what you're talking about which is sort of the Star Wars stars track kind of vision
To develop a tremendous technology. I don't think it's a hundred years. I
But I wanted to ask a question because I don't know the answer to this is so so in
A lot of discussion we're having about theology and cosmology acts like one
It
Presumes that the interest in theology is cosmological and my impression is that's a more modern
Addition to theology theology was really designed about everyday life and decisions we make about our relationship between ourselves and
God and and how we should behave and was
Never you know, it was never intended as a serious competition with what we would call science nowadays as as creating a
Cosmological model that's something we impose even posed on it
Maybe the last thousand years or so or something like that fairly recently
I mean compared to when the religions were compared to when the religions were created
And there was the creators of those religions
Cosmology was not foremost on their mind
Behavior was an ethics was on their mind survival
Have a frame of reference now I was thinking
And they said before that tell me what you believe
Tell me what you think about it at the time and I'll tell you what you believe
Paradise lost in certain senses and education in temporality
The first five lines in the poem
And with the one greater man restore us
It begins with mortality death all our world
The human condition helplessness
It's idea of being lost
And then this
Ended to one greater man restores that is Jesus Christ figure who's going to come to being history
I think in many interesting things about what you said, I think this
The relationship and this is why people coming back to it. There's a relationship between cosmology and ethics
There's a relationship between cosmology and how we know the world. There's a relationship in the day-to-day
And
So so crucial to milk it
and other figures
In the Christian world, Dante, even classical world the importance of ending is in your style
everything tends in esstylosis
trilogy
everything tends towards an ending
And in the very beginning of the plot one can already feel the end of the plot
And I think there is again that strong relationship
Between ending and ethics
I mean, we just tend I think naturally to look at these messianic frames overly simplistic
Milton
gives the light of that because in a way he shows the skeptical
We're not religious moment in the heart in the heart of the religious experience
The reason people keep on reading Milton is because he's a theological skeptic
Which is a paradox
Because I think he he accommodates
Ed sense of we want to know what the ending is
But he doesn't give into simplistic renderings of what that would be
Okay, so let me be more specific about my question. There's okay now. I was being vague
I was going to so let me say specifically Christianity
I think imposes constraints on cosmology because you can't have the idea of original sin and emisiah
Unless that sets up that sets up a time frame of a rigid time frame of beginning
There's something before and there's got to be something at the end
if you think it push that away for a bit then
Then the idea that might be
And you can see that such a concept really runs into trouble when you think about a universe
Which has different patches which are being created at different times and what is original?
What does it mean to say something? What does this whole story even mean in that context?
Sort of loses its meaning in that context entirely whereas it doesn't lose its meaning in other theological context
So I think I think to some degree the problem
It may be specific with the with a christian theology as opposed to other theologies
I would say judio christian in the 17th century one sees this tension the card of hops begin to
sense binoza begin to undermine
theology
And create a whole different set of disciplinary hierarchies and which signs is at the top then of course there's just a disjunction
And then and theology comes artifice. That's why I keep on coming back and taught
I'm very interested in the way in which both of you
Even as you're presenting us and I'm sorry. I'm to be a human here presenting as a picture of facts are reliant upon metaphors
ships
catastrophe
dark
Energy
Which I think comes from her as laws dark maddens of the transformation dark mils dark matter
So it seems to me that there's always a narrative renderer
of
The objective scientific world in which you do obviously the realm of theology and
Literature the artifice is foreground
but I understand
The discomfort you would have with those all of the versions of cosmology
And how they don't they don't gel
And I wonder whether one modern
transformation of theological thinking is utopian thinking
Which also fell into disrepute and disuse
And the sense I think came more that
This way of life that we're in which is capitalism which is global capital
It's simply going to continue and continue the history and you know the end of history scenario
That this is what's before us more and more consumer goods perhaps increased prosperity around the globe
Perhaps not but at the end at any rate no alternative and I think it's that sensibility that has spawned
the just absolute plethora of
violently ending
Narratives which characterized the last 50 years
um
You know just so many apocalyptic you know the apocalyptic imagination
I think is very much in response to this sense of
The end of historical progression and this sense of sort of what seems to be a lot of stuff happening all the time everywhere
Is really just a kind of complex form of stasis
um
And so the even utopso theological thinking yes, it's
Who needs it but even utopian thinking is going it's
A lot of I'm not sure where the origin of this statement is but um, it's easier to imagine the end of the world than the end of capitalism
I think it's it seems to be the case
There are so many ways to imagine the end of the world and all of them seem dedicated to just wiping out this
crop
That seems to be the contemporary world out of which and to which there seems to be no alternative
So the challenge to sort of locate an alternative is
And you know when I think that's one of the reasons that say the occupied movement became
Such a powerful you know popular and powerful phenomenon at least in that moment that it was whether it will be again
I don't know but it's certainly wise for a while and because it seemed to be well
Right, right there is some other way of thinking about addressing the social problems that face us in this country and globally
For ways which are not apocalyptic or which are well or which are but at any rate some some other some other way of thinking
Which is what the utopian imagination is trying to do and which was as I say kind of discredited
For some time
But
It may know is it a form of theology
Yeah, I think you can make a document in the in the evolutionary picture in history life and of the
Science I said that the old idea from lael was the president is the key
The past study what's going on now?
You can figure out what went on in the past the new model. This has been replaced is the past
Is the key to the future
So study the way what has happened in the past if it if it did happen it can happen
Right and then those things will repeat themselves
Into the future and also with with Darwinism Darwin had this very capitalistic mode right of competition between species
And extinctions were caused by what species winning the competition. That's all changed now
The picture now is that species go along for a long period of time pretty much
Stable and then something bad happens and lots of species become extinct some catastrophe
And then the aftermath of that extinction life radiates into lots of new forms
Mammals didn't out-compete the dinosaurs
They just managed to survive the catastrophe 65 million years ago
And they radiated into all the forms of mammals that we see today popular in the earth
So it's been a change and I say it
What did with the social darlinist do with this?
There's no rule for social darlinist. Yeah
I think something that's been implicit in much of what's said is kind of the reverse engineering of
what you call were
Communicating about
how
The
dominance of dark energy would kind of shatter our self-conceptions the reverse engineering of that being and you know
You've all been kind of touching upon this
How are self-conceptions
Shape and influence how
You as scientists
theorize and how you recognize things for what they are what about the
Self-conceptions
that influence that that's that kind of gets at the bridging of the two cultures that you were kind of
Negotiating down in the green room. I wonder what thoughts you have about
I think about that as a theorist as to whether or not we've thought about all the possible
kinds of theories one can have of the universe
Historically most theories of the universe fall into one of three categories
The created universe which is created and then evolves and just goes forward in time
I've been becoming more and more complex with time
the static universe universe. It's always the same
and the
cyclical type universe and
I think we understand
Where those come from in terms of our human experience they you know
cyclicity occurs and in certain things in the daily cycle and the seasonal cycle we understand that and a
Stasis we understand we look out the stars and they seem to be static so they they have an apparent stasis
Although we now know there there's not a real stasis there, but that's where that would have come from
And the idea of the created universe that's birth. That's that's that's that's part of our human experience as well
And when we talk about the end that's kind of you know, that's like our death
So the question is is okay. So most models of cosmology
You could put into one of those categories and you can ask the question
Is that all the possible theories there are or is that just us humans trying to impose our you know
Are we just so influenced by our humanity that that's the only kinds of theories we can come up with and one of the interesting things about recent theories is that
Many of them don't quite so simply categorize and so
That's interesting. I don't know. We don't know whether or not they're true or not
But I think that's an interesting development that we're breaking out of those those traditional moles
I don't know, you know in some sense, you know
You know evolution is also undergoing a change in terms of
Being more complex not not being a simple store a simple story, but being
I mean you were even simplifying it the way you were describing it, but some sort of combination of you know slow evolution and
Traffic evolution and just things are more complex than any simple narrative
Tell us who
Slow evolution taking place and then you have these
Apocalypse
Catastrophe right so one of the things that science has forced us to do is to come to grips with whether our narratives make sense
So you keep pushing your narrative and saying okay if this narrative is true then
I would guess the following would be true and then you look to see if that's true and when it's not
You're forced to correct your narrative and that's I mean that's the discovery of the scientific method
That was the grand discovery that you take the scientific method and you add the human brain to it and really something miraculous happens
Suddenly new information is created out of at a much greater rate than we were able to create any other time
The other period up till the present
Exactly why that come works that way
I don't know. I think it really requires both the humanity and the scientific method to work the humanity to be
imaginative to come up with stories to come up with guesses
and
Huge jumps huge leaps and then the scientific method to check that to put that in check and say okay
That's a good guess and that's a bad guess and somehow that works together in some magical way that has led to
A tremendous amount of tremendous run of progress over the last several hundred years
The scientific method I'm not trying to understand what you're saying
The scientific method is something that exists outside of us that we
Yeah, so I mean we discovered like the monolith and oh it was discovered
Yeah, the idea that you empirically test your ideas that that you don't just tell your story and because it's a good story
I mean that's this we were talking about theology theologies are really good stories
Which have a lot of appeal to them and and there's some good lessons to be learned from them
But then you want to you know, but you know, is that story true or is that story true?
You know well well theology
You may be not answer the question but for you know why stars form
We can either different stories you could think of right but you need back and so the human imagination allows you to leap and think of many possible stories
and then
You impose on that the scientific method with many different
You know, I have to find objective ways of demonstrating to you that that idea is right and that idea is wrong
Objective in the sense that you know people in different parts of the world with different backgrounds can all agree on
You know, I'll make those observations and come to the same conclusions
That was an invented idea and you know invented in the Renaissance
It was not an idea that was there historically beforehand and it led to a tremendous run of several hundred years up to the present time
of
You know the rate of which new information has come to us is just you know, just just exponentially increased since that time
Maybe there's a better invention a better something better than the scientific method for
Increasing the rate at which we gain information. We haven't discovered it yet
I don't know but the moment this is our best invention that does just sound to me as a literary
I'm using the death of the topic in there is the scientific method is the mirage
Yeah, I don't know if this free of science to talk about it, but obviously any all pre-modern societies have had some form of trial and error
You made
Stone, you know implements you figured out ways to do it. It wasn't a formalized scientific method
But it was an empiric it was a form of empiricism, I think so but but but as you
But something happened in the whatever 16th 17th century some convergence. I would think of political economic
social
Thinking such that this idea of standardization of repeatability
a
Different goals. I mean, I guess I would question the sense that oh, you know
Just for no particular reason somebody thought of this great way of doing inquiry
I think the results of it. I think or as you said
but but the origins of it maybe that was discussed two weeks ago, but
the origins of it I
Think they would be more other social ideological economic questions that were
played
You know when wanted to be able to do things one wanted to be able to explore the world
wanted to be able to create products and markets developing so I just at least that's that's just
the mindset that I can disagree with and it's a good and don't disagree those were
that was part of the
spirit of the time I mean and
Yeah, so being being successful and meant being able to succeed in a marketplace
Was different than being successful because I say I was the king or something like that. So so
it led to more competition of
products and a competition of ideas and
Knowledge is power and so suddenly it was possible to be powerful without being let's say aristocratic by having knowledge
And I think that that's I'm not a story. And so my guess would be that would be part of the
Forces that are at work that led to what I think is clearly an invention because certainly the way knowledge was gathered
You know say before Galileo Newton is quite different than the way it was gathered since Galileo Newton and the amount of progress has been made there in every
Area of science is just
There's no comparison
I mean
Sensors of endings and ways of knowing
We know
No
Well, so for example
You know there are different idea we have this is a question
So so
Maybe the way to respond to that is to say to make it a scientifically meaningful issue it had better have some empirical consequences
So in some sense being a scientist you restrict yourself to a domain of questions
Our domain of issues which have empirical consequences if they not you're welcome to think about them
But they're outside the domain of science
Different different different consequences
Different cosmology is electrical is known and the culture that he represents in competition with this conian Hobbesian universe which is I mean Hobbes really comes armed with bacon and anticipated in a society and he comes to destroy Don Shakespeare and Milton these are not legitimately known
They are
How are you through what Hobbes will call and reject as metaphor and contradiction? It's also an extremely resonant question here
How does this kind of empirical mouth Jim talk before about primary process about dreams?
What happens to those primary process insights those insights that are not
reducible to secondary process in how does the psychoanalyst
Intertwan this miraculous narrative and I'm not I'm not doubting
Not only mining that was narrative I also trying to understand
the
Consequences of that cosmology grounded as it is an object of fire reality
With other cosmologies which allow for other kinds of known
And that's a literary historical interest of mine
The beginnings and Milton and the one in the beginning of a kind of murder anybody's also the end
And Hobbes of course is just amounts of it before just the death of this other kind of culture
And the death of a kind knowing which is based upon metaphor or which is based upon paradox
It seems so much of what would go on in this building would have to do with that other kind of not
So maybe it's worth saying that in cosmology
So although cosmology is in some sense one of the oldest sciences in terms of people thinking about it in terms of being an empirical
Science, it's one of the newest
so
Up until 1920 we weren't even able to see and recognize there were galaxies beyond our own and
We've gathered more data in the last ten years about the nearby
Intermediate and most distant observable parts of the universe which correspond to the present
Intermediate and past distant past of the universe that we just didn't have before so
From a scientific point of view you can just take the data from the last ten years and throw against that all the concepts of cosmology
That have been developed by humans throughout human history and almost all of them are inconsistent with those observations with the exception of two I can name
Two ideas, which is a pretty amazing statement just based on a decades worth of data. So that's so
Where does science come into it?
Well if you insist on the scientific methodology that your cosmology should make sense with it
You know with an objective observation, which is what sciences do then then you can sort through these different ideas and say okay
That was a great idea a very imaginative idea, but that idea is
Not our universe and okay, and this one is even though it may not have been the one you would have chosen
So that's all I can offer
I think so but you may not always be happy with the outcome
So so maybe
There are further comments from the round type we could open it up to questions from the audience
Please you know state your name and
The
Sessions for weekly there on Monday and she said that the world was going to end on Friday
And then the next session when she came out on Monday
I asked you how she felt about the situation. She said no, it's going to it's gonna end on Friday
This went on for months
Reason I mentioned is that I think the a couple like the apocalyptic and sort of dramatic sense of ending
Make have a basis in a stereotypical unconscious
Part of our minds where it's it's it's sort of boilerplate. It's stereotypical
It doesn't come it doesn't seem to be based on anything. It's delusional and
That it just is sort of there
Had my therapy focused on
Relieving her of the problem that the world was going to end up it would have gotten nowhere and probably actually would have gotten worse
And any psychotic medication actually did reduce that over a period of time and she got to the point where she said
I just don't think about it
the other issue was
that the problem with anxiety with this lady was was her marrow
And I thought oh, it's symbolic
see if the world's gonna with what that means to her is
My marriage is is gonna break up and that will be the end of the world for me
It really wasn't any connection at all in fact the marriage wasn't breaking up in fact
We did make some progress with the marital therapy and she did fairly well, so it's just a
Sort of a word of caution. I guess is to
is that in the in the unconscious with the stereotype of unconscious we have I
Asked I worked in a prison for what I asked inmates to write down to draw me the devil
It was amazing similarity I had 12 drawings people that didn't know each other and we're not comparing notes a
rodent like figure big teeth
big eyes big ears tail pitchfork
so on
This is a stereotypical unconscious
It and I'm afraid it it fuels things like
Alcoholics and so on that it just keeps keeps that going that we just keep in mind that maybe part of our whole structure
of our mind that is is more stereotypical than actually symbolic or actually
Thing I want to ask is
for
You in particular is would you consider?
There that there might be an eternal universe, but there also might be a local big bang
universe that we live in that's not eternal
is
and is there
Do we perhaps perceive that?
intuitively and is there something having to do with envy?
Are we because we're so finite envious of the eternal that may be out there, and so we try to
go through elaborate situations
In our instance the reason so on to make believe that
Our life is eternal, you know, it's not the universe have those are we envious of the cosmos?
I can't address an interesting question the last one I can't answer it, but to answer your your your scientific question
Which is can you is it possible to have the universe which is eternal on on average?
There are parts that are always existing and being in new creations taking place and parts which are ending in one way or another
ending by
Catastrophically or ending by this sort of petering out. Yes, that is the picture that is if you were going to guess that if you were
Gonna describe the prevalent picture it bunk cosmologist. That would be the prevalent picture among cosmologists at present
The physics the science seems to allow for that possibility
And it seems by but allows for it. I mean it makes predictions about the part of the universe that we observe that so far
I've been verified
So it doesn't allow us to see out there to check it
But there are other inferences of such theories that we can't that do make implications to what we should observe about
The radiation from the early universe and the distribution of galaxies that so far work and so right now that idea seems to be
working well
I would just add
that ancient cosmologist from the Tomlittic Rambi's to Augusta
Assume the time is created thing
That there is something beyond time and eternity
But I also would just add speculations about eternity
Dovetail with what I keep on coming back to the speculation about the divine
And the non-impirically objectifiable
I think that was the question of the science
Is there something beyond the empirically objectifiable?
And that becomes not a question
I think only for scientists
about here the scientific answer
That becomes a conversation where philosophers
and maybe your words also
Ernest Imbradley the new school
I have the impression that we were really talking about two different times
One the cultural time in which theology is subsumed
All theology not just your day but Christian or whatnot
In which literature is subsumed from Doris Lesson to Milton and whatnot
Psychiatry
And what I was lacking in this conversation was the fact of a self-awareness
That we are all talking in a box that we are Western oriented
We have not included other boxes which would still be boxes
So that's really I don't want us to believe that we are the horses mouth
That's why I was very important to mention this
But if I use a term myth that we all every culture needs a myth
To deal with death not just with ending but with death
And sometimes their death can lead into rebirth
So there is no ending
And I thought maybe we should also keep that in mind
And then the last one question I really have is
A question addressed to the cosmologists and the astrophysicists
Whether astrophysics isn't again a myth
A contemporary myth that is totally dependent on the instruments that are available
The instruments chasing the big bang or whatever
And of course you can say that the instruments themselves are already the outcome of the direction
In which you want to go with your research
But I wonder again whether this is not inside a box which is our box today
I think that is a very important thing
Well, let's see, so
You have a number of interesting comments that I'm trying to decide which one to begin with
I do think that
I tried to make the point that I think science is a human invented method
Which combines our ability to imagine and make myths
And make stories and make narratives with
Objectivity in the sense of the instruments and ways in which we can make prescriptions
I can write something down and say you do this observation
I predict you will observe the following
You will go do it and you will actually observe it
Which is an interesting truth
Which turns out to have a lot of practical value that we can do that
As opposed to other stories which may be less practical
Maybe very appealing but maybe less practical
But I mean you can call, I'm not sure the words have connotations
So when you say is science a kind of mythology
Which involves instruments and mathematics and objects
And you can use the word myth
But I think it somehow deserves a different word
And so I'll use the word science
But I think you're saying that there's a difference between calling science a mythology
And science arising from the same human capacities that myth-making entail
Doesn't mean that science is a myth
I think we've extended our imagination
And that's the point I was trying to make
I think a scientific methodology extends us beyond our imagination
To be able to distinguish different stories
Which are of practical interest
Like I want to know if there's going to be a solar eclipse in Japan today
Which there is
The fact that I can predict that is based on observations
And then you can go off and check with the Japanese
Call your friends in Japan and say yeah sure enough
A solar eclipse there is different than other myths I could make up
Of why there are solar eclipse
Which would not give me that power to predict
So I think of science as just a way we've learned to make our imaginations more powerful
To be able to predict and explain things in ways that now allow us to say
What's going to happen next?
Give us better control over our lives, our health, all the things that technology brings us
Those are real things that science has brought us
Which make it different than myth making
Yeah, absolutely
I think the mythological or ideological consequences are that the idea of predictability becomes a kind of fetish
If a discipline does not lead toward predictive consequences then it's devalued
I think that is maybe what Ernst was talking about
And that's certainly something that occurs to me
For example the very prominent pseudoscience of economics
You're not allowed
It seems to me it's predictive assertions seem to be completely
Inattic, please
And yet there's an ideological fixation on this discipline
Such that the smartest guys in the room are the economists
Because they can do these amazing things with numbers
And they have this whole apparatus
And so the scientific instrument has now been appropriated by a field
Which really has nothing to do with science as you described
So there is a mythology of science
Actual scientists I didn't think are part of it in the whole
But there is a myth that comes from it
Well it's an attempt to
I mean, okay we've discovered this method that works for certain kinds of questions
It works really well for explaining why this table is as solid as it is
And the same methodology doesn't work so well for economics
And so science is limited
As I said it's an invention and like any invention
Like the Blackberry, it works well for some things but not for other things
And how do we...
It works so powerful
And when it works it works really powerfully
Right, and we've seen that
And so we... Okay, so it's natural to say
Well could we apply it to answer this question or that other question
And sometimes you can and sometimes you can't
And so you try and do it in a part of human efforts to try to gain knowledge
I have a more narrow technical question
You and they were Michael Sattice
A more narrow technical question for Dr. Stonghart
Is it thought that the amount of dark energy is increasing
And if so why how does it come back?
Okay, so it's a simple question
You guys a simple question, so
Yes it is increasing in terms of a total amount of dark energy
But there's two things going on at the same time
The river is expanding and as it expands
Energy spreads out, it becomes more dilute
But different forms of energy become dilute at different rates
Matter just spreads out the more you make if you double the volume
It's density decreases by a factor of two
Radiation decreases at a faster rate because as it spreads out
It also... the photons redshift so they actually lose energy faster
Dark energy is the energy that loses its energy either not at all
It's density not at all or at the slowest
So over time it eventually takes over because everything else stays loose and it doesn't
Another thing that's happening is when you're stretching the universe
You're creating more space and that space has energy in it
So there's therefore more energy, total of energy is growing
And where is that coming from? Well it's coming from gravity
So one thing that's not... we should have all learned in elementary school
I even find my advanced graduate students don't quite appreciate it
Gravity is the one form of one force from which you can draw an infinite amount of energy
And this is an example of it
An expanding universe filled with dark energy keeps stretching
Creating new space filled with dark energy
So the total dark energy grows, the gravitational energy decreases
But gravitational energy is a kind of bottomless pit
So you can just keep doing that forever
And that's what the laws of physics tell us can happen
And could be happening, that could be happening
That's one possibility for the long term future of the universe
That's all that happens, there's more and more dark energy less and less of everything else
Go ahead
There's gentleman Daniel
My name is Ernie Heller and I'm just passing through like the rest of us in life
I have to go to my question
It's been a great, I really mean a great post-doc over discussion
But I would like you to focus for a couple of minutes on the starkest notion of one's end
That's one's personal death, one's demise
I would venture to say that to discuss the topic today
If this were your final hour, would you say things differently would be clarifying, terrifying
Or indifferent?
The silence towards the time sound
Yeah, I think Bill would have been fine with it
Would it be my last hour?
Yeah
Well, in my last hour, I just had one preservation of poetry
And I'm wondering if that gets preserved of these cosmologies
You said, you know, I might not like it, but one of the things I don't like
Or is there, you know, the post-apocalyptic?
Is there post-apocalyptic poetry? I mean, mention less
I mean, Blake, we know that Blake
Literary theory is post-apocalyptic poetry
We know that Blake worried about Newton
Because Newton made poetry possible
Or he thought so
To get away from the intellectual level, what about the emotional level of life
That was a little too good about his hearing
Where is that involved our efforts to try to get to the point of it all?
I don't know, is one's sense of the meaning of life
Dependent on the actual act of dying, the moment of one's death?
I don't know, I think there's meaning in every moment of your life
I don't, I think it's melodramatic to put it in those terms
Of course, when one gets to that point, then you'll get to that point
Somebody suggested to me we should have an undertaker for this round table
So, I don't know, I can't answer that
I'm not sure that to answer the question, it's not what questions you want to answer
But you're asking whether the emotions you have near your moments before death
Are helpful, is that what you're asking?
Are they helpful in addressing these questions?
My guess is they're not helpful in answering these questions
Because you're emotional, you're a little preoccupied with something else
I'm a little bit nervous, I'm a little nervous, I'm a little nervous
I'm a little nervous, I'm a little nervous, I'm a little nervous
Probably irrationally, but I don't know, I don't know
I'm very interested that you try to connect the arts and literature with the sciences
In terms of what's developing in the science and wanting to feel that the arts have to follow suit
Because most often the arts have dealt with certain structural elements
And there's an implication that some of these structural elements you felt were obsolete
For instance, like tension or drama or apocalypse or contradiction or paradox
And it's curious that you're thinking as science develops, we the artists and the writers and the philosophers
Have to change our structure of the very nature of our existence
Because we experience life in one way, and even if our knowledge changes
There's still certain elements in the paradox of living because of the inherent tensions in it
So I found this, why were you so concerned that my goodness?
Actually that seems to be some of the problems that what's happening in the arts today
That they're dissolving and evaporating and receiving almost in fear that certain structures are obsolete
This is just a general comment
And I have one other thing that always interested me, maybe because in philosophy it was mentioned in Chopinhauer
And so about repetition and Heraclitus speaking about you can never step in the same with a river twice
And it seems to me as you're talking that repetition, there is not any longer a concept of repetition in science
But there is some base by which you work that gradually evolves
But is there an underlying structure that keeps changing or do you find there are some elements that are building stones that are there?
If you follow what I'm saying, I mean the Heraclitusian view versus the idea is there such a thing as repetition?
Do we ever repeat anything?
I think the first question, the humanities have been anxious, poets have been anxious as Plato
We've become anxious again in the 17th century with Hobbes
We became more anxious with the development of science
The disciplinary hierarchies have changed, and go to my university in Israel by a lot
And see the size of the Netflixx buildings and the nanotechnology buildings and the old humanities buildings
It's very clear why that anxiety should exist
I'm also just struck by the assertion of the separation between emotional and intellectual
That's us somehow given, and again I think we're our way
to this building, which I think about that time, very strongly and terribly
To think about the role that the poetic functions not only have hops with the rockator of the Buddha
For something which is a nice looking or pretty
But the way primary process functions as a way of knowing
And paradox functions as a way not only of some kind of ephemeral poetic expression, but of which the emotions
And the intellect are somehow more beautiful
I mean that's one of the inheritances of the scientific world view
Is that the emotions have been pushed out, poetry has been pushed to the side
Yeah, I don't think the arts really are necessarily sort of following the sciences
Or trying to sort of keep up with what scientific developments are doing
Except, I don't know, the science that seems to capture people's imaginations
Those recently have seen the neuroscience and the resonant arts and neuroscience
And some of the people who continue thinking about quite a bit
The gap in sort of disciplinary emphases between cosmology
And these kind of enormous wastes of time
These voids of time
So the question is where do we come together?
And I'm thinking about different things, the histories of our disciplines are different
Maybe this is what a line of the raspberries
Maybe there should be an apparent tension, what's wrong with things that aren't resolved
But our tension between what's happening scientifically, what's going on in the arts
There can remain the tension between which creates
And in the populist division of creates a dramatic movement, a dramatic vision within it
Yeah, I don't think there's any problem with different fields, having different methodologies and different approaches
There's different kinds of people, we've all had different childhoods, we had different teachers
In high school, we went different ways, so that's what we did
The question is where do we come together socially and politically?
Or are there questions which we really do think about in common as a mortal being and be citizens?
And I think that's the more important question, I think, that whether our particular academic interests coincide
Well, science is not a robotic process, it's a creative process like in the arts
And so where does the inspiration come from?
Well, the inspiration comes from a very similar human process
Sometimes you might go to an art museum and look at a piece of art, that might inspire you to think of an idea
That turns out to have a scientific meaning, you know, so
That's the purpose of this round table
Or this, yeah, so that's why I'm here, part of the history
We're here, coming to this is because this kind of thing can't inspire unusual discussions
It gets you just thinking a little bit differently and then suddenly on the train home
I may think a lot of problems and view it in a different way and something good happens from it
So that's where the human part of the process comes from
I want to answer your question about repeatability
So, in fact there's a sort of double problem about repeatability
Number one, if you mean by exact repeatability classically before we consider quantum physics
That is statistically, you know, so unlikely is not to be worth considering
But with quantum mechanics it even becomes ill-defined because when you say exact repeatability
It assumes that you have an exact notion of position, time, energy, mass
And in quantum physics those are all now fuzzy objects which only have probabilities, not certainties
So that's the current condition, or a current way of understanding the best we can do in the universe
Or we can say it's approximately repeating, something is approximately repeating in certain average quantities
But exactly repeating would never, would almost lose meaning in the quantum sense
Go ahead
My name is Ken Wade, I'm the artist from downtown
And I'm talking about Dark and Mad
Dark and Mad
Sounds like a very sinister thing
I remember in movies when I was a week of launching the Japanese to morph into an old fanang
The wolf man came out in full, so I know we're affected by stuff out there
So I'm wondering, this is an increasing problem, as you said
Dark energy, yeah, yeah, right
So does this explain everything, or does it have any influence on matters here, like all these terrible storms?
In the recent republic, in primary things, you were acting a little bit easier
I'm just wondering, is there a push-pull thing on this?
So first of all, the term dark energy is not meant to be sinister, it's meant to tell you that it has energy
And that it doesn't emit or absorb light
So it's a fairly boring term, and not my favorite term for it, but that's become the convention
So although there's lots of it, it's extremely thinly spread
So within our solar system, most of the matter in our solar system is not dark
Most of the energy, sorry, in our solar system is not dark energy
It's the matter you know and love, the energy that makes up the humidity, earth, the sun, the planets, and the light
However, space, it's hard to conceive until you've thought about the numbers
And even with the numbers it might help you, but space is enormous compared to the places where you matter is concentrated
And if you imagine that even in those places between galaxies, there's still this thin distribution of dark energy
It adds up to be a huge total, so the total is huge
But within our galaxy, within our solar system, it's so thinly spread that it doesn't have any significant effect
So the fact of this only effect is when you look at the universe in the large
And then when it sums up to be more than all the matter in galaxies and stars
Then it becomes a dominant influence in controlling the stretching of the universe
And because it's gravitation, we also encourage the stretching and causes this acceleration
Whereas the matter is trying to hold itself together, it wins because there's more of it
Because it's so thinly spread, but it's spread out, but it occupies so much space
More than one
Yes, more than one effect than one effect there are elections
My name is Peter Dithy, I'm a psychoanalyst and I'm a nurse and I want to offer the end of life
People at the end of life, and one of the things that I think you mentioned
Stuck me about this gathering and what we're doing here
And it seems to me that it's a lot of what we're doing is intellectualising
Speaking in the abstract and being scientific is a defense against the anxieties
That we all could feel if we took the time about perhaps our own impending death
Whether it is or isn't
My religion, if you like, and it's not really a religion, it's a lifestyle, it's Buddhism
And Buddhists have a way of making impermanence meaningful to us by using it to motivate us maybe
And say, life, life, I'm mortal, my life is infinite
And I must do something meaningful is one of the common prayers if you like, of the Buddhist
And that therefore is motivating
Impermanence is seen all around, and might walk down the street and see a pigeon that's dropped dead overnight
Any one of us could drop dead now or on the way home, and it's having that awareness in our consciousness
That lends to, adds to the quality perhaps of our lives
Because we know that that is there, to ignore it is a defence against feeling that
Thank you
A little rabbit
Yeah, so I
Want to thank the audience's comments and interlocutors and our panelists today, Jim Berger, Paul Steinhardt, Bill Cobrenner
And Michael Rampino for a stimulating discussion
Perhaps I can invoke Winston Churchill's words from 1942 when he said
This is not the end, it's not even the beginning of the end, but perhaps it's the end of the beginning
And please follow us on helixcenter.org for further announcements, for our fall programs
And thank you all for coming
Thank you